Humanism, Pt 1

The gentle sun of January shone on the cold fields outside Hogwarts.

For some of the students it was a study hour, and others had been let out of class. The first-years who’d signed up for it were practising a certain spell, a spell that was most advantageously learned outdoors, beneath the bright sun and a clear blue sky, rather than within the confines of any classroom. Cookies and lemonade were also considered helpful.

The early gestures of the spell were complex and precise; you twitched your wand once, twice, thrice, and four times with small tilts at exactly the right relative angles, you shifted your forefinger and thumb exactly the right distances …

The Ministry thought this meant it was futile to try and teach anyone the spell before their fifth year. There had been a few known cases of younger children learning it, and this had been dismissed as ‘genius’.

It might not have been a very polite way of putting it, but Harry was beginning to see why Professor Quirrell had claimed that the Ministry Committee of Curriculum would have been of greater benefit to wizardkind if they had been used as landfill.

So the gestures were complicated and delicate. That didn’t stop you from learning it when you were eleven. It meant you had to be extra careful and practise each part for a lot longer than usual, that was all.

Most Charms that could only be learned by older students were like that because they required more strength of magic than any young student could muster. But the Patronus Charm wasn’t like that, it wasn’t difficult because it needed too much magic, it was difficult because it took more than mere magic.

It took the warm, happy feelings that you kept close in your heart, the loving memories, a different kind of strength that you didn’t need for ordinary spells.

Harry twitched his wand once, twice, thrice and four times, shifted his fingers exactly the right distances …

‘Good luck at school, Harry. Do you think I bought you enough books?’

‘You can never have enough books … but you certainly tried, it was a really, really, really good try …’

It had brought tears to his eyes, the first time Harry had remembered and tried to put it into the spell.

Harry brought the wand up and around and brandished it, a gesture that didn’t have to be precise, only bold and defiant.

‘Expecto Patronum!’ cried Harry.

Nothing happened.

Not a single flicker of light.

When Harry looked up, Remus Lupin was still studying the wand, a rather troubled look on his faintly scarred face.

Finally Remus shook his head. ‘I’m sorry, Harry,’ the man said quietly. ‘Your wandwork was exactly right.’

And there wasn’t a flicker of light anywhere else, either, because all the other first-years who were supposed to be practising their Patronus Charms had been glancing out of the corners of their eyes at Harry instead.

The tears were threatening to come back into Harry’s eyes, and they weren’t happy tears. Of all the things, of all the things, Harry had never expected this.

There was something horribly humiliating about being informed that you weren’t happy enough.

What did Anthony Goldstein have inside him that Harry didn’t, that made Anthony’s wand shine with that bright light?

Did Anthony love his own father more?

‘What thought were you using to cast it?’ said Remus.

‘My father,’ Harry said, his voice trembling. ‘I asked him to buy me some books before I came to Hogwarts, and he did, and they were expensive, and then he asked me if they were enough –’

Harry didn’t try to explain about the Verres family motto.

‘Take a rest before you try a different thought, Harry,’ said Remus. He gestured toward where some other students were sitting on the ground, looking disappointed or embarrassed or regretful. ‘You won’t be able to cast a Patronus Charm while you’re feeling ashamed of not being grateful enough.’ There was a gentle compassion in Mr Lupin’s voice, and for a moment, Harry felt like hitting something.

Instead Harry turned around, and stalked to where the other failures were sitting. The other students whose wandwork had also been proclaimed perfect, and who were now supposed to be searching for happier thoughts; by the looks of them they weren’t making much progress. There were many robes there trimmed in dark blue, and a handful of red, and one lone Hufflepuff girl who was still crying. The Slytherins hadn’t even bothered showing up, except for Daphne Greengrass and Tracey Davis, who were still trying to get the gestures.

Harry plopped down on the cold dead grass of winter, next to the student whose failure had surprised him the most.

‘So you couldn’t do it either,’ Hermione said. She’d fled the field at first, but she’d come back after that, and you had to look closely at her reddened eyes to see that she’d been crying.

‘I,’ Harry said, ‘I, I’d probably feel a lot worse about that if you hadn’t failed, you’re the nicest, person I know, that I’ve ever met, Hermione, and if you also can’t do it, it means I might still be, be good …’

‘I should have gone to Gryffindor,’ Hermione whispered. She blinked hard a few times, but she didn’t wipe her eyes.

The boy and the girl walked forward together, definitely not holding hands, but each drawing a kind of strength from the other’s presence, something that let them ignore the whispers of their year-mates, as they walked through the hallway approaching the great doors of Hogwarts.

Harry hadn’t been able to cast the Patronus Charm no matter what happy thought he tried. People hadn’t seemed surprised by that, which made it even worse. Hermione hadn’t been able to do it either. People had been very surprised by that, and Harry had seen her starting to get the same sidelong looks as him. The other Ravenclaws who’d failed weren’t getting those looks. But Hermione was the Sunshine General, and her fans were treating it like she’d failed them, somehow, like she’d betrayed a promise she’d never made.

The two of them had gone to the library to research the Patronus Charm, which was Hermione’s way of dealing with distress, as it was sometimes also Harry’s. Study, learn, try to understand why …

The books had confirmed what the Headmaster had told Harry; often, wizards who couldn’t cast the Patronus Charm in practise would be able to do so in the presence of a real Dementor, going from flat failure all the way to a full corporeal Patronus. It defied all logic, the Dementor’s aura of fear ought to make it harder to wield a happy thought; but that was the way it was.

So the two of them were both going to give it one last try, there was no way either of them wouldn’t give it one last try.

It was the day the Dementor came to Hogwarts.

Earlier, Harry had un-Transfigured his father’s rock from where it usually rested on his pinky ring in the form of a tiny diamond, and placed the huge grey stone back into his pouch. Just in case Harry’s magic failed entirely, when he confronted the darkest of all creatures.

Harry had already started to feel pessimistic, and he wasn’t even in front of a Dementor yet.

‘I bet you can do it and I can’t,’ Harry said in a whisper. ‘I bet that’s what happens.’

‘It felt wrong to me,’ Hermione said, her voice even quieter than his. ‘I tried it this morning and I realized. When I was doing the brandish at the end, even before I said the words, it felt wrong.’

Harry didn’t say anything. He’d felt the same thing, right from the start, though it had taken another five attempts using five other happy thoughts before he’d been able to acknowledge it to himself. Every time he tried to brandish his wand, it had felt hollow; the spell he was trying to learn didn’t fit him.

‘It doesn’t mean we’re going to be Dark Wizards,’ said Harry. ‘Lots of people who can’t cast the Patronus Charm aren’t Dark Wizards. Godric Gryffindor wasn’t a Dark Wizard …’

Godric had defeated Dark Lords, fought to protect commoners from Noble Houses and Muggles from wizards. He’d had many fine friends and true, and lost no fewer than half of them in one good cause or another. He’d listened to the screams of the wounded, in the armies he’d raised to defend the innocent; young wizards of courage had rallied to his calls, and he’d buried them afterwards. Until finally, when his wizardry had only just begun to fail him in his old age, he’d brought together the three other most powerful wizards of his era to raise Hogwarts from the bare ground; the one great accomplishment to Godric’s name that wasn’t about war, any kind of war, no matter how just. It was Salazar, and not Godric, who’d taught the first Hogwarts class in Battle Magic. Godric had taught the first Hogwarts class in Herbology, the magics of green growing life.

To his last day he’d never been able to cast the Patronus Charm.

Godric Gryffindor had been a good man, not a happy one.

Harry didn’t believe in angst, he couldn’t stand reading about whiny heroes, he knew a billion other people in the world would have given anything to trade places with him, and …

And on his deathbed, Godric had told Helga (for Salazar had abandoned him, and Rowena passed before) that he didn’t regret any of it, and he was not warning his students not to follow in his footsteps, no one was ever to say he’d told anyone not to follow in his footsteps. If it had been the right thing for him to do, then he wouldn’t tell anyone else to choose wrongly, not even the youngest student in Hogwarts. And yet for those who did follow in his footsteps, he hoped they would remember that Gryffindor had told his House that it was all right for them to be happier than him. That red and gold would be bright warm colours, from now on.

And Helga had promised him, weeping, that when she was Headmistress she would make sure of it.

Whereupon Godric had died, and left no ghost behind him; and Harry had shoved the book back to Hermione and walked away a little, so she wouldn’t see him crying.

You wouldn’t think that a book with an innocent title like ‘The Patronus Charm: Wizards Who Could and Couldn’t’ would be the saddest book Harry had ever read.

Harry …

Harry didn’t want that.

To be in that book.

Harry didn’t want that.

The rest of the school just seemed to think that No Patronus meant Bad Person, plain and simple. Somehow the fact that Godric Gryffindor also hadn’t been able to cast the Patronus Charm seemed not to get repeated. Maybe people didn’t talk about it to respect his last wish, Fred and George probably didn’t know and Harry certainly wasn’t about to tell them. Or maybe the other failures didn’t mention it because it was less shameful, the smaller loss of pride and status, to be thought Dark rather than unhappy.

Harry saw that Hermione, beside him, was blinking hard; and he wondered if she was thinking of Rowena Ravenclaw, who’d also loved books.

‘Okay,’ Harry whispered. ‘Happier thoughts. If you do go to a full corporeal Patronus, what do you think your animal will be?’

‘An otter,’ Hermione said at once.

‘An otter?’ Harry whispered incredulously.

‘Yes, an otter,’ said Hermione. ‘What about yours?’

‘Peregrine falcon,’ Harry said without hesitation. ‘It can dive faster than three hundred kilometres per hour, it’s the fastest living creature there is.’ The peregrine falcon had been Harry’s favourite animal since forever. Harry was determined to become an Animagus some day, just to get that as his form, and fly by the strength of his own wings, and see the land below with sharper eyes … ’But why an otter?’

Hermione smiled, but didn’t say anything.

And the vast doors of Hogwarts swung open.

They walked for a time, the children, over a pathway that led toward the un-forbidden forest, and continued through the forest itself. The Sun was lowering to near the horizon, the shadows long, the sunlight filtered through the bare branches of the winter trees; for it was January, and the first-years the last to learn, that day.

Then the path swerved and took a new direction, and they all saw it in the distance, the clearing in the forest, and the sere winter grounds, yellowing dried grass whitened by a few small remnants of snow.

The human figures still small at that range. The two spots of dim white light from the Aurors’ Patronuses, and the brighter spot of silver light from the Headmaster’s, next to something …

Harry squinted.

Something …

It must have been purely Harry’s imagination, because there shouldn’t have been any way for a Dementor to reach past three corporeal Patronuses, but he thought he could feel a touch of emptiness brushing at his mind, brushing straight at the soft inner centre of himself without any respect for Occlumency barriers.

Personhood Theory

There comes a point in every plot where the victim starts to suspect; and looks back, and sees a trail of events all pointing in a single direction. And when that point comes, Father had explained, the prospect of the loss may seem so unbearable, and admitting themselves tricked may seem so humiliating, that the victim will yet deny the plot, and the game may continue long after.

Father had warned Draco not to do that again.

First, though, he’d let Mr Avery finish eating all of the cookies he’d swindled from Draco, while Draco watched and cried. The whole lovely jar of cookies that Father had given him just a few hours earlier, for Draco had lost all of them to Mr Avery, down to the very last one.

So it was a familiar feeling that Draco had felt in the pit of his stomach, when Gregory told him about The Kiss.

Sometimes you looked back, and saw things …

(In a lightless classroom – you couldn’t quite call it unused any more, since it’d seen weekly use over the last few months – a boy sat enshrouded in a hooded cowl, with an unlighted crystal globe on the desk in front of him. Thinking in silence, thinking in darkness, waiting for an opening door to let in the light.)

Harry had shoved Granger away and said, I told you, no kissing!

Harry would probably say something like, She just did it to annoy me, last time, just like she made me go on that date.

But the verified story was that Granger had been willing to face the Dementor again in order to help Harry; that she had kissed Harry, crying, when he was lost in the depths of Dementation; and that her kiss had brought him back.

That didn’t sound like rivalry, even friendly rivalry.

That sounded like the kind of friendship you usually didn’t see even in plays.

Then why had Harry made his friend climb the icy walls of Hogwarts?

Because that was the sort of thing Harry Potter did to his friends?

Father had told Draco that to fathom a strange plot, one technique was to look at what ended up happening, assume it was the intended result, and ask who benefited.

What had ended up happening as the result of Draco and Granger fighting Harry Potter together … was that Draco had started to feel a lot friendlier toward Granger.

Who benefited from the scion of Malfoy becoming friends with a mudblood witch?

Who benefited, that was famous for exactly that sort of plot?

Who benefited, that could possibly be pulling Harry Potter’s strings?

Dumbledore.

And if that was true then Draco would have to go to Father and tell him everything, no matter what happened after that, Draco couldn’t imagine what would happen after that, it was awful beyond imagining. Which made him want to cling desperately to the last shred of hope that it wasn’t all what it looked like …

… Draco remembered that, too, from Mr Avery’s lesson.

Draco hadn’t planned to confront Harry yet. He was still trying to think of an experimental test, something that Harry wouldn’t just see through and fake. But then Vincent had come with the message that Harry wanted to meet early this week, on Friday instead of Saturday.

And so here Draco was, in a dark classroom, an unlit crystal globe on his desk, waiting.

Minutes passed.

Footsteps approached.

The door made a gentle creak as it swung open into the classroom, revealing Harry Potter dressed in his own hood and cowl; Harry stepped forward into the dark classroom, and the sturdy door closed behind him with a faint click.

Draco tapped the crystal globe, and the classroom lit with bright green light. Green light projected shadows of the desks onto the floor, and glared back at him from the curved chair-backs, photons bouncing off the wood in such fashion that the angle of incidence equalled the angle of reflection.

At least that much of what he’d learned wasn’t likely to be a lie.

Harry had flinched as the light went on, halting for a moment, then resumed his approach. ‘Hello, Draco,’ Harry said quietly, drawing back his hood as he came to Draco’s desk. ‘Thank you for coming, I know it’s not our usual time –’

‘You’re welcome,’ Draco said flatly.

Harry dragged one of the chairs to face Draco across his desk, the legs making a slight screeching sound on the floor. He spun the chair so that it was facing the wrong way, and sat down straddling it, his arms folded across the back of the chair. The boy’s face was pensive, frowning, serious, looking very adult even for Harry Potter.

‘I have an important question to ask you,’ said Harry, ‘but there’s something else I want us to do before that.’

Draco said nothing, feeling a certain weariness. Part of him just wanted it all to be over with already.

‘Tell me, Draco,’ said Harry. ‘Why don’t Muggles ever leave ghosts behind when they die?’

‘Because Muggles don’t have souls, obviously,’ Draco said. He didn’t even realize until after he’d said it that it might contradict Harry’s politics, and then he didn’t care. Besides, it was obvious.

Harry’s face showed no surprise. ‘Before I ask my important question, I want to see if you can learn the Patronus Charm.’

For a moment the sheer nonsequitur stumped Draco. Good old impossible-to-predict-or-understand Harry Potter. There were times when Draco wondered whether Harry was deliberately this disorienting as a tactic.

Then Draco understood, and shoved himself up and away from his desk in a single angry motion. That was it. It was over. ‘Like Dumbledore’s servants,’ he spat.

‘Like Salazar Slytherin,’ Harry said steadily.

Draco almost stumbled over his own feet in the middle of his first stride toward the door.

Slowly, Draco turned back toward Harry.

‘I don’t know where you came up with that,’ said Draco, ‘but it’s wrong, everyone knows the Patronus Charm is a Gryffindor spell –’

‘Salazar Slytherin could cast a corporeal Patronus Charm,’ Harry said. Harry’s hand darted into his robes, brought out a book whose title was written as white on green, and so almost impossible to read in the green light; but it looked old. ‘I discovered that when I was researching the Patronus Charm before. And I found the original reference and checked the book out of the library just in case you didn’t believe me. The author of this book doesn’t think there’s anything unusual about Salazar being able to cast a Patronus, either; the belief that Slytherins can’t do that must be recent. And as a further historical note, though I don’t have the book with me, Godric Gryffindor never could.’

After the first six times Draco had tried calling Harry’s bluff, on six successively more ridiculous occasions, he’d realized that Harry just didn’t lie about what was written in books. Still, when Harry’s hands opened the book and laid it out to the place of a bookmark, Draco leaned over and studied the place where Harry’s finger pointed.

Then the fires of Ravenclaw fell upon the darkness that had cloaked the left wing of Lord Foul’s army, breaking it, and it was revealed that the Lord Gryffindor had spoken true; the fear they all had felt was not natural in its source, but coming from thrice a dozen Dementors, who had been promised the souls of the defeated. At once the Lady Hufflepuff and Lord Slytherin brought forth their Patronuses, a vast angry badger and a bright silver serpent, and the defenders lifted their heads as the shadow passed from their hearts. And Lady Ravenclaw laughed, remarking that Lord Foul was a great fool, for now his own army would be subject to the fear, but not the defenders of Hogwarts. Yet the Lord Slytherin said, ‘No fool he, that much I know.’ And the Lord Gryffindor beside him studied the battlefield with a frown upon his face …

Draco looked back up. ‘So?’

Harry closed the book and put it into his pouch. ‘Chaos and Sunshine both have soldiers that can cast corporeal Patronus Charms. Corporeal Patronuses can be used to convey messages. If you can’t learn the spell, Dragon Army will be at a severe military disadvantage –’

Draco didn’t care about that right now, and told Harry so. His voice was sharper than it probably should have been.

Harry didn’t blink. ‘Then I’m calling in the favour you owe me from that time I stopped a riot from breaking out, on our first day of broomstick lessons. I’m going to try to teach you the Patronus Charm, and for my favour, I want you to do your honest best to learn and cast it. I trust to the honour of House Malfoy that you will.’

Draco felt that certain weariness again. If Harry had asked at any other time, it would have been a fair return on favour owed, given that it wasn’t actually a Gryffindor spell. But …

‘Why?’ Draco said.

‘To find out whether you can do this thing that Salazar Slytherin could do,’ Harry said evenly. ‘This is an experimental test, and I will not tell you what it means until after you have done it. Will you?’

… It probably was a good idea to discharge that favour on something innocuous, all the more so if it was time to break with Harry Potter. ‘All right.’

Harry drew a wand from his robes, and laid it against the globe. ‘Not really the best colour for learning the Patronus Charm,’ Harry said. ‘Green light the exact shade of the Killing Curse, I mean. But silver is a Slytherin colour too, isn’t it? Dulak.’ The light went out, and Harry whispered the first two phrases of the Continual Light enchantment, recasting that part of it, though neither of them could have cast the whole thing by themselves. Then Harry tapped the globe again, and the room lit with a silver radiance, brilliant but still soft and gentle. Colour returned to the desks and chairs, and to Harry’s slightly sweaty face beneath his shock of black hair.

It took that long for Draco to realize the implication. ‘You saw a Killing Curse cast since the last time we met? When – how –’

‘Cast the Patronus Charm,’ Harry said, looking more serious than ever, ‘and I’ll tell you.’

Draco pressed his hands to his eyes, shutting out the silver light. ‘You know, I really should remember that you’re too weird for any normal plots!’

Within his self-imposed darkness, he heard the sound of Harry snickering.

Harry watched closely as Draco finished his latest run-through of the preliminary gestures, the part of the spell that was difficult to learn; the final brandish and the pronunciation didn’t have to be precise. All three of the last runs had been perfect as far as Harry could see. Harry had also felt an odd impulse to adjust things that Mr Lupin hadn’t said anything about, like the angle of Draco’s elbow or the direction his foot was pointing; it could have been entirely his own imagination, and probably was, but Harry had decided to go with it just in case.

‘All right,’ Harry said quietly. There was a tension in his chest that made it a little hard to speak. ‘Now we don’t have a Dementor here, but that’s all right. We won’t need one. Draco, when your father spoke to me at the train station, he said that you were the one thing in the world that was most precious to him, and he threatened to throw away all his other plans to take vengeance on me, if ever you came to harm.’

‘He … what?’ There was a catch in Draco’s voice, and a strange look on his face. ‘Why are you telling me that?’

‘Why wouldn’t I?’ Harry didn’t let his expression change, though he could guess what Draco was thinking; that Harry had been plotting to separate Draco from his father, and shouldn’t be saying anything that would bring them closer together. ‘There’s always been just one person who matters most to you, and I know exactly what warm and happy thought will let you cast the Patronus Charm. You told it to me at the train station before the first day of school. Once you fell off a broomstick and broke your ribs. It hurt more than anything you’d ever felt, and you thought you were going to die. Pretend that fear is coming from a Dementor, standing in front of you, wearing a tattered black cloak, looking like a dead thing left in water. And then cast the Patronus Charm, and when you brandish the wand to drive the Dementor away, think of how your father held your hand, so that you wouldn’t be afraid; and then think of how much he loves you, and how much you love him, and put it all into your voice when you say Expecto Patronum. For the honour of House Malfoy, and not just because you promised me a favour. Show me you didn’t lie to me that day in the train station when you told me Lucius was a good father. Show me you can do what Salazar Slytherin could do.’

And Harry stepped backward, behind Draco, out of Draco’s field of vision, so that Draco only faced the dusty old teacher’s desk and blackboard at the front of the unused classroom.

Draco cast one look behind him, that strange look still on his face, and then turned away to face forward. Harry saw the exhalation, the inhalation. The wand twitched once, twice, thrice, and four times. Draco’s fingers slid along the wand, exactly the right distances –

Draco lowered his wand.

‘This is too –’ Draco said, ‘I can’t think this right, while you’re watching –’

Harry turned around and started walking toward the door. ‘I’ll come back in a minute,’ Harry said. ‘Just hold to your happy thought, and the Patronus will stay.’

Constrained Cognition, Part 2

In darkness absolute, a boy stood holding his wand to the solid metal wall of Azkaban, essaying a magic that only three other people in the world would have believed possible, and that none save he alone could wield.

Of course a powerful wizard could’ve cut through the wall in seconds, with a gesture and a word.

For an average adult it might have been a matter of a few minutes’ work, and afterwards they would have been winded.

But to accomplish the same end as a first-year Hogwarts student, you had to be efficient.

Luckily – well, not luckily, luck had nothing to do with itconscientiously, Harry had practised Transfiguration for an extra hour every day, to the point where he was ahead of even Hermione in that one class; he’d practised partial Transfiguration to the point where his thoughts had begun taking the true universe for granted, so that it required only slightly more effort to keep its timeless quantum nature in mind, even as he kept a firm mental separation between the concept of Form and the concept of substance.

And the problem with that art having become so routine …

… was that Harry could think about other things while he was doing it.

Somehow his thoughts had managed to not go there, to not confront the obvious, until he was faced with the prospect of really actually doing it in just a few minutes.

What Harry was about to do …

… was dangerous.

Really dangerous.

Someone-might-actually-genuinely-get-killed dangerous.

Facing down twelve Dementors without a Patronus Charm had been scary, but merely scary. Harry could have cast the Patronus Charm, would have cast it as soon as he thought he was in danger of not being able to do so, as soon as he felt his resistance beginning to fail. And even if that hadn’t worked … even so, unless the Dementors had been instructed to Kiss anyone they found, failure shouldn’t have been fatal.

This was different.

The Transfigured Muggle device could explode and kill them.

The interface between the technology and the magic could fail in any number of ways and kill them.

The Aurors could get in a lucky shot.

It was just, well …

Seriously dangerous.

Harry had caught his mind trying to argue itself into believing that it was safe.

And sure, the whole thing could work, but …

But even leaving out that rationalists weren’t ever allowed to argue themselves into things, Harry knew he couldn’t possibly have argued himself into estimating less than a 20% probability of dying.

Lose, said Hufflepuff.

Lose, said the voice of Professor Quirrell in his mind.

Lose, said his mental model of Hermione and Professor McGonagall and Professor Flitwick and Neville Longbottom and, well, basically everyone Harry knew except for Fred and George, who would have gone for it in a hot second.

He should just go find Dumbledore and turn himself in. He should, he really really should, it was the only sane thing to do at this point.

And if it’d been only Harry on the mission, only his own life that’d been at stake, he would have; he surely would have.

The part that was almost causing him to lose his concentration on the partial Transfiguration he was performing, the part that was threatening to open him to the Dementors …

… was Professor Quirrell, still unconscious, still a snake.

If Professor Quirrell went to Azkaban for his part in the escape, he would die. He probably wouldn’t last even a week. He was that sensitive.

It was that simple.

If Harry lost here …

He lost Professor Quirrell.

Even though he’s probably evil, said the Hufflepuff part of him quietly. Even so?

It wasn’t a decision that Harry had made in any conscious way. He just couldn’t do it. Losing was for House points, not people.

If you think your own life is valuable enough that you’re not willing to take on an eighty percent probability of dying in order to protect all the prisoners in Azkaban, his Slytherin side observed, there’s no way you can justify taking a twenty percent risk to your life to save Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell. The maths doesn’t add up, you can’t be assigning consistent utilities over outcomes here.

The logical side of him noted that Slytherin had just won the argument.

Harry kept the Form in his mind, kept on casting the spell. He could always just abort the mission when he was done with the Transfiguration, he didn’t want to lose the effort he’d already invested.

And then Harry thought of something else that suddenly made it very hard to keep the magic going, very hard to keep up his resistance to the Dementors.

What if the portkey doesn’t take us where Professor Quirrell said it did?

It was obvious in retrospect the moment he thought about it.

Even if the planned escape went completely right, even if the Muggle device worked and didn’t explode and didn’t interact badly with the mated magic item, even if the Aurors didn’t get in a lucky shot, even if Harry made it far enough away from Azkaban to use the portkey …

… there might not be a psychiatric healer at the end of it.

That was something Harry had believed when he’d trusted Professor Quirrell, and he’d forgotten to re-evaluate it after Professor Quirrell was no longer to be trusted.

You can’t do this, said Hufflepuff. At this point we’re talking mere stupidity.

Cold seemed to spread through the room, but Harry kept the Transfiguration going, even as his resistance against the Dementors faltered.

I can’t lose Professor Quirrell.

He tried to kill a police officer, said Hufflepuff. You already lost him, in that moment. Bellatrix is probably just what everyone thinks she is. Just take your Cloak back, go find Dumbledore and tell him you were tricked.

No, thought Harry desperately, not without talking to Professor Quirrell, there might be an explanation, I don’t know, maybe he was standing far enough away from my Patronus that the Dementors got to him … I don’t understand, it doesn’t make sense on any hypothesis, why he would do that … I can’t just …

Harry turned his mind away from that chain of thought before it completely broke his resistance to the fear, because he couldn’t think of feeding Professor Quirrell to Dementors while staying resolved against Death, it was a cognitive impossibility.

Your reasoning is artificially impaired, observed the logical part of him calmly, find a way to unimpair it.

All right, let’s just generate alternatives, Harry thought. Not choose, not weigh, certainly not commit … just think about what else I might be able to do besides the original plan.

And Harry went on cutting the hole in the wall. He was using partial Transfiguration on a thin cylindrical shell of metal, two metres in diameter and half a millimetre thick, running all the way through the wall. He was Transfiguring that half-millimetre thickness of metal into motor oil. Motor oil was a liquid and you weren’t to Transfigure liquids because they might evaporate, but he and Bellatrix and the snake all had Bubble-Head Charms. And Harry would cast Finite on the oil immediately after, dispelling his own Transfiguration …

… as soon as the separated and lubricated hunk of metal slid out of the wall and onto the floor of their cell, he’d slanted it so gravity would pull it in, once the Transfiguration was done.

If Harry and Bellatrix didn’t exit on his broomstick through the resulting hole in the wall …

Harry’s brain suggested that he could try to Transfigure a surface cover over the hole in the wall, leaving a space for Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell to hide in, wearing the Cloak, while Harry turned himself in. And Professor Quirrell would eventually wake up, and he and Bellatrix could try to figure out how to exit Azkaban on their own.

It was, first of all, a dumb idea, and second, there would still be a huge hunk of metal on the floor of the cell, which would give it away.

And then Harry’s brain saw the obvious.

Let Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell use the escape route you invented. You stay behind, and turn yourself in.

Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell were the ones whose lives were at stake.

They were gaining, not losing, from taking the risk.

And there was no reason, no sane reason at all, for Harry to go with them.

A calm came over Harry as he thought it, the cold and darkness that had been wavering around the fringes of his mind retreated. Yes, that was it, that was the creative outside-the-box route, that was the hidden third alternative. The falseness of the dilemma was obvious in retrospect. If Harry turned himself in, he didn’t have to turn in Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell. If Bellatrix and Professor Quirrell took a dangerous escape route, Harry didn’t need to go with them.

Harry didn’t even need to face the embarrassment of admitting he’d been tricked, if he ordered Bellatrix to remove the memory. Everyone would just assume he’d been kidnapped, including Harry himself. Admittedly, there was no plausible reason why the Dark Lord would ever ask Bellatrix to do that; but Harry could simply smile and tell Bellatrix she wasn’t allowed to know, and that would be that …

Her Auror team was around three-quarters of the way down Azkaban, as were the other two teams on the other two spirals. Amelia was feeling tenser already, though she was betting on the criminals hiding on the second-to-lowest floor, part of her wished Dumbledore had thought to check that specific floor more carefully and part of her was glad he hadn’t.

And then there was a distant sound, like a tiny tink noise coming from far away. Like a very loud sound coming from the second-to-lowest floor, say.

Amelia looked at Dumbledore before she realized, before she managed to stop herself.

The old wizard shrugged, gave her a small smile, said, ‘Since you asked it, Amelia,’ and went off yet again.

‘Finite Incantatem,’ Harry said to the oil coating the giant chunk of metal on the floor. He hardly heard himself speak, his ears were still ringing from the gigantic thud of the solid metal sliding out of the wall and falling. (He should have put up a Quieting Charm, in retrospect, though that wouldn’t have stopped the noise from spreading through the solid metal floor.) And then Harry said it again, ‘Finite Incantatem’ to the oil coating the two-metre hole in the wall, spreading the effect wide; it was his own magic Harry was cancelling, which made the spell almost effortless. Harry was feeling a bit tired now, but that was the last use of magic he would need. He hadn’t even needed to do it, really, but Harry didn’t want to leave Transfigured liquid lying around, and he didn’t want to betray the secret of partial Transfiguration either.

It seemed very … inviting, that two-metre hole leading to freedom.

The light from outside coming in … wasn’t exactly the Sun shining on his face, but it was brighter than anything in Azkaban’s interior.

Harry was tempted to just go with them, just hop on the broomstick with Bellatrix and the snake. Chances were that they would get out safely. And if they did get out safely, and Harry came along, then he and Professor Quirrell could go back in time and look perfectly innocent, and everything could go back to normal.

If Harry stayed behind and turned himself in … then even if everyone assumed Harry had been a hostage, assumed Harry had lied to Professor McGonagall’s Patronus at wand-point … even if Harry himself got off lightly, well …

It wasn’t likely that the Defence Professor would go on teaching at Hogwarts.

Professor Quirrell would have reached the predestined end of his career, in February of the school year.

And yes, Professor McGonagall would kill Harry, and yes, it would be slow and painful.

But staying behind was the sensible, safe, sane thing to do, and Harry was feeling more relaxed than regretful.

Harry turned to Bellatrix; he opened his mouth to instruct her a final time –

And there was a hiss, a weak hiss, a hiss that sounded slow and confused, and the hiss said,

‘What was … that noise?’

Through the corridor the old wizard strode. He came to a metal door and opened it, already knowing from memory that the cells within were empty.

Seven mighty and discerning incantations the wizard spoke then, before he moved on; it would be little enough exertion in total, with so few cells left to check.

‘Teacher,’ Harry hissed. So many emotions bubbling up in him, all at once. He knew, though he could not see, that the green snake around Bellatrix’s shoulders was slowly lifting its head to look around. ‘Are you … all right, teacher?’

‘Teacher?’ came the weak, confused hiss. ‘Where is this?’

‘Prison,’ Harry hissed, ‘the prison with life-eaters, we were to rescue a woman, you and I. You tried to slay the protector man, I blocked your killing curse, there was a resonance between us … you fell unconscious, I had to defeat the protector man myself … my guardian Charm was dispelled, the life-eaters could tell the protectors that the woman had escaped. There is someone here who can sense my guardian Charm, probably the schoolmaster … so had to dispell my guardian Charm, find different way to hide you and the woman from life-eaters without guardian Charm, learn to protect myself without guardian Charm, scare off life-eaters without guardian Charm, then devise new escape plan for you and the woman, and finally, cut hole in thick metal wall of prison even though I am only first-year student. No time to explain, you must go now. If we never meet again, teacher, then I was glad to know you for a time, even though you are probably evil. It is good to have the chance to say this much: Goodbye.’

And Harry took the broomstick and presented it to Bellatrix, saying simply, ‘Get on.’

He had decided to keep the memories. For one thing, they were important. For another, he and the Defence Professor had started planning this a week ago, and Harry wasn’t about to obliterate the whole last week, or explain to Bellatrix exactly what needed to be Obliviated. Harry could probably fool Veritaserum, and if Dumbledore insisted that Harry drop his Occlumency shields for a deeper examination … well, Harry had acted heroically throughout.

‘Stop!’ said the snake. Its voice was stronger now. ‘Stop, stop, stop! What do you mean, goodbye?’

‘Escape plan is risky,’ said Harry. ‘My life is not at stake, only yours and hers. So I am staying, turning myself in –’

‘No!’ said the snake. The hiss was forceful. ‘Must not! Not permitted!’

Bellatrix mounted the broomstick; Harry could sense (but never see) her head turning to look at him, she said no word. Awaiting him, perhaps, or merely awaiting his orders.

‘No longer trust you,’ Harry said simply. ‘Not since you tried to slay the protector man.’

And the snake hissed, ‘I did not seek to slay the protector man! Are you fool, boy? Slaying him would not make sense, evil or no!’

The Earth ceased to turn on its axis, paused in its orbit around the Sun.

The snake’s hiss was now more furious than anything Harry had ever heard from the human Professor Quirrell. ‘Slay him? Had I sought to slay him he would have been dead within seconds, fool boy, he was no match for me! I sought to subdue, to dominate, force him to drop shields upon his mind, needed to read him, to know who awaited his reply, learn details for memory spell –’

‘You cast killing curse!’

‘Knew he would dodge!’

‘Was his life worth so little? What if he did not dodge?’

‘Would have pushed him out of the way with own magic, fool boy!’

Again the pause in the planet’s spin. Harry hadn’t thought of that.

‘Witless dunce of a plotter,’ hissed the snake, so angrily that the hisses seemed to overlap and slither over each other’s tails, ‘clever imbecile, cunning idiot, fool of an untrained Slytherin, your misplaced mistrust has ruined –’

‘This is not a fair time to argue,’ Harry observed mildly. The surge of relief trying to flood through him was canceled by the increased tension. ‘Since I cannot get angry at you properly, without opening myself to life-eaters. Must rush, someone may have heard noise –’

‘Explain escape plan,’ the snake said imperiously. Swiftly!’

Harry explained. Parseltongue didn’t have words for the Muggle technology, but Harry described the function and Professor Quirrell seemed to understand.

There were a few short hisses, the snakish equivalent of a bark of surprised laughter, and then, snapped commands. ‘Tell woman to look away, cast spell of silence, set guardian Charm outside door. Will transform myself, make few swift improvements to your invention, give woman emergency potion so she can shield us, transform back before you dispell Charm. Plan will be safer, then.’

‘And am I to believe,’ Harry hissed, ‘that healer for woman truly awaits us?’

‘Use sense, boy! Suppose I am evil. To end use of you here is obviously not what I planned. Mission is target of opportunity, invented after saw your guardian Charm, whole affair meant to be unnoticed, hid when left eating-place. Obviously you will see person pretending to be healer on arrival! Go back to eating-place afterwards, original plan carries on undisturbed!’

Harry stared at the invisible snake.

On the one hand, saying it like that made Harry feel rather dumb.

And on the other hand, it wasn’t exactly reassuring.

‘So,’ Harry hissed, ‘what is your plan for me, precisely?’

‘You said no time,’ came the snake’s hiss, ‘but plan is for you to rule country, obviously, even your young noble friend has understood that by now, ask him on return if you wish. Will say no more now, is time to fly, not speak.’

The old wizard reached out toward another metal door, from behind which came a endless dead mutter, ‘I’m not serious, I’m not serious, I’m not serious …’ The red-golden phoenix on his shoulder was already screaming urgently, and the old wizard was already wincing, when –

Another cry pierced the corridor, phoenix-like but not the true phoenix’s call.

The wizard’s head turned, looked at the blazing silver creature on his other shoulder, even as ephemeral and immaterial talons launched the spell-entity into the air.

The false phoenix flew down the corridor.

The old wizard raced off after, legs churning like a spry young man of sixty.

The true phoenix screamed once, twice, and a third time, hovering before the metal door; and then, when it became clear that its master would not return for all its calling, flew reluctantly after.

Professor Quirrell had assumed his true form, this time – Polyjuice only lasted for an hour without re-dosing – and though the Defence Professor was pale, leaning against the metal bars of the nearest cell, his magic was strong enough to seize his wand without a word, even as Bellatrix doffed the Cloak and placed it obediently in Harry’s waiting hand. The sense of doom was building once more, though not in full force, as the Defence Professor’s power returned, the fringes of its vast force clashing with Harry’s slight childish aura.

Harry said aloud the description of his Muggle device, naming it to the observing wizard, and then a Finite from Harry turned all his hard work back into an ice cube. Professor Quirrell could not cast spells on something Harry had Transfigured, for that would be an interaction, however slight, between their magics, but –

Three seconds after, Professor Quirrell was holding his own Transfigured version of the Muggle device. A single barked word and a sweep of his wand, and the residue of glue was gone from the magical item; three more incantations later, the magical and technological were fused together as though into a single thing, and Charms of Unbreakability and flawless function had been cast upon the Muggle device.

(Harry felt a lot better about doing this under adult supervision.)

A potion was thrown to Bellatrix, and Professor Quirrell and Harry both commanded, ‘Drink,’ as though speaking in the same voice. The emaciated woman had already been lifting it to her lips, without waiting; for it was evident to anyone that this snake Animagus was a servant of the Dark Lord, and a powerful and trusted one.

Harry finished pulling the hood of the Cloak of Invisibility over his head.

A brief and terrible magic lashed out from the Defence Professor’s wand, scouring the hole in the wall, scarring the huge chunk of metal that lay in the room’s midst; as Harry had requested, saying that the method he’d used might identify him.

‘Left-hand glove,’ Harry said to his pouch, and drew it forth, and put it on.

A gesture from the Defence Professor made a harness appear upon Bellatrix’s shoulders, and another, smaller cloth device upon her hand, and something like handcuffs on her wrists, even as the woman finished drinking the potion.

A strange, unhealthy colour seemed to come over Bellatrix’s pale face, she straightened, her sunken eyes seemed brighter and far more dangerous …

… small wisps of steam were coming out of her ears …

(Harry decided not to think about that part.)

… and Bellatrix Black laughed, then, sudden mad laughter that rang much too loudly amid the small prison cells of Azkaban.

(Very soon, the Defence Professor had said, Bellatrix would fall unconscious and stay that way for quite awhile, the price of the potion she had taken; but for just a few moments she would regain perhaps a twentieth part of the power she had once wielded.)

The Defence Professor threw his wand toward Bellatrix, and an instant later blurred into a green snake.

An instant after that the Dementors’ fear returned to the room.

Bellatrix flinched only slightly, caught the wand, and gestured without a word; the snake flew up and was inserted into the harness on her back.

Harry said ‘Up!’ to the broomstick.

Bellatrix attached the wand to the holster on her hand.

Harry leaped onto the two-person broomstick in the lead position.

Bellatrix followed behind him, she took the cuff-like devices on her wrists and chained her hands to the grips of the broomstick, even as Harry’s right hand shoved his wand into his pouch.

And the three shot forward through the hole in the wall –

– emerging into the open air, directly above the Dementors’ pit, in the interior of the vast triangular prism that was Azkaban, the blue sky now clearly visible above them, shining down its daylight.

Harry angled the broomstick and began accelerating, upward and toward the centre of the triangular space. His left hand, gloved to prevent direct contact between his skin and something which Professor Quirrell had Transfigured, held the switch of the control on the Muggle device.

Far above them, distant shouts rang out.

All right, you primitive screwheads!

Aurors on fast racing broomsticks angled out of the sky, diving straight down toward them, faint sparks of light already blazing downward as the first shots were fired.

Listen up!

‘Protego Maximus!’ shouted Bellatrix in a mighty, cracked voice, followed by a cackling laugh as a shimmering blue field surrounded them.

You see this?

From the decaying pit in the centre of Azkaban, over a hundred Dementors rose into the air, appearing to some as a great mass of corpses, a flying graveyard; appearing to another as a conglomerate of absences that seemed to form one vast rip in the world as they slid upward.

This …

The voice of an ancient and powerful wizard bellowed a terrible incantation, and a great blast of white-golden fire shot out of the hole in Azkaban’s wall, shapeless for only a moment before it began to form wings.

Is …

And the Aurors activated the Anti-Anti-Gravity Jinx that had been built into the wards of Azkaban, disabling all flying spells whose enchantment had not been cast with the recently changed passphrase.

The lift on Harry’s broom switched off.

Gravity, on the other hand, stayed on.

Their broom’s upward rise slowed, started to decelerate, began the process of turning into a fall.

My …

But the enchantments that kept the broom pointed in a direction and allowed steering, the enchantments that kept the riders attached and somewhat protected them from acceleration, those enchantments were still functioning.

Broomstick!

Harry hit the ignition switch on the General Technics made, model Berserker PFRC, N-class, ammonium perchlorate composite propellant, solid-fuel rocket that had been mated to his Nimbus X200 two-person broomstick.

And there was noise.

TSPE, Aftermaths

She was just starting to close up her books and put away her homework in preparation for sleep, Padma and Mandy stacking up their own books across the table from her, when Harry Potter walked into the Ravenclaw common room; and it was only then that she realized, she hadn’t seen him at all since breakfast.

That realization was rapidly stomped-on by a much more startling one.

There was a golden-red winged creature on Harry’s shoulder, a bright bird of fire.

And Harry looked sad and worn and really tired like the phoenix was the only thing keeping him on his feet, but there was still a warmth about him, if you crossed your eyes you might have thought you were looking at the Headmaster somehow, that was the impression that went through Hermione’s mind even though it didn’t make any sense.

Harry Potter trudged across the Ravenclaw common room, past sofas full of staring girls, past card-game circles of staring boys, heading for her.

In theory she wasn’t talking to Harry Potter yet, his week wasn’t up until tomorrow, but whatever was going on was clearly a whole lot more important than that –

‘Fawkes,’ Harry said, just as she was opening her mouth, ‘that girl over there is Hermione Granger, she’s not talking to me right now because I’m an idiot, but if you want to be on a good person’s shoulder she’s better than me.’

So much exhaustion and hurt in Harry Potter’s voice –

But before she could figure out what to do about it, the phoenix had glided off Harry’s shoulder like a fire creeping up a matchstick on fast-forward, flashing toward her; there was a phoenix flying in front of her and staring at her with eyes of light and flame.

‘Caw?’ asked the phoenix.

Hermione stared at it, feeling like she was facing a question on a test she’d forgotten to study for, the one most important question and she’d gone her whole life without studying for it, she couldn’t find anything to say.

‘I’m –’ she said. ‘I’m only twelve, I haven’t done anything yet –’

The phoenix just glided gently around, rotating around one wing-tip like the being of light and air that it was, and soared back to Harry Potter’s shoulder, where it settled down quite firmly.

‘You silly boy,’ said Padma across from her, looking like she was deciding whether to laugh or grimace, ‘phoenixes aren’t for smart girls who do their homework, they’re for idiots who charge straight at five older Slytherin bullies. There’s a reason why the Gryffindor colours are red and gold, you know.’

There was a lot of friendly laughter in the Ravenclaw common room.

Hermione wasn’t one of the laughing ones.

Neither was Harry.

Harry had put a hand over his face. ‘Tell Hermione I’m sorry,’ he said to Padma, his voice almost fallen to a whisper. ‘Tell her I forgot that phoenixes are animals, they don’t understand time and planning, they don’t understand people who are going to do good things later – I’m not sure they understand really the notion of there being something that a person is, all they see is what people do. Fawkes doesn’t know what twelve means. Tell Hermione I’m sorry – I shouldn’t have – it just all goes wrong, doesn’t it?’

Harry turned to go, the phoenix still on his shoulder, began slowly trudging toward the staircase that led up to his dorm.

And Hermione couldn’t leave it at that, she just couldn’t leave it at that. She didn’t know if it was her competition with Harry or something else. She just couldn’t leave it with the phoenix turning away from her.

She had to –

Her mind keyed a frantic question to the entirety of her excellent memory, found just one thing –

‘I was going to run in front of the Dementor to try and save Harry!’ she shouted a little desperately at the red-golden bird. ‘I mean, I actually did start running and everything! That was stupid and courageous, right?’

With a warbling cry the phoenix launched itself from Harry’s shoulder again, back toward her like a spreading blaze, it circled her three times like she was the centre of an inferno, and for just a moment its wing brushed against her cheek, before the phoenix soared back to Harry.

There was a hush in the Ravenclaw common room.

‘Told you so,’ Harry said aloud, and then he started climbing the stairs up to his bedroom; he seemed to climb very quickly, like he was very light on his feet for some reason, so that in just a moment he and Fawkes were gone.

Hermione held up a trembling hand to her cheek where Fawkes had brushed her with his wing, a spot of warmth lingering there like that one small patch of skin had been very gently set on fire.

She’d answered the question of the phoenix, she supposed, but it felt to her like she’d just barely squeaked by on the test, like she’d got 62 and she could’ve got 104 if she’d tried harder.

If she’d tried at all.

She hadn’t really been trying, when she thought about it.

Just doing her homework –

Who have you saved?

Nightmares, the boy had expected, screams and begging and howling hurricanes of emptiness, the discharge of the horrors being laid down into memory, and in that fashion, perhaps, becoming part of the past.

And the boy knew that the nightmares would come.

The next night, they would come.

The boy dreamed, and in his dreams the world was on fire, Hogwarts was on fire, his home was on fire, the streets of Oxford were on fire, all ablaze with golden flames that shone but did not consume, and all the people walking through the blazing streets were shining with white light brighter than the fire, like they were flames themselves, or stars.

The other first-year boys came to bed, and saw it for themselves, the wonder whose rumour they had already heard, that in his bed Harry Potter lay silent and motionless, a gentle smile on his face, while perched on his pillow a red-golden bird watched over him, with bright wings swept above him like a blanket pulled over his head.

The reckoning had been put off one more night.

Draco straightened his robes, making sure the green trim was straight. He waved his wand over his own head and said a Charm that Father had taught him while other children were still playing in mud, a Charm which ensured that not a single speck of lint or dust would dirty his wizard’s robes.

Draco picked up the mysterious envelope that Father had owled him, and tucked it into his robes. He had already used Incendio and Everto on the mysterious note.

And then he headed off to breakfast, to seat himself on exactly the same tick of the clock where the food appeared, if he could manage it, so that it would seem like all others had been waiting on his appearance to eat. Because when you were the scion of Malfoy you were first in everything, including breakfast, that was why.

Vincent and Gregory were waiting for him outside the door of his private room, up even before he was – though not, of course, dressed quite as sharply.

The Slytherin common room was deserted, anyone who got up this early was heading straight to breakfast anyway.

The dungeon halls were silent but for their own footsteps, empty and echoing.

The Great Hall was a hubbub of alarm despite the relatively few arrivals; some younger children crying, students running back and forth between tables or standing in knots shouting at each other, a red-robed prefect was standing in front of two green-trimmed students and yelling at them and Snape was striding toward the mess –

The noise dimmed a little as people caught sight of Draco, as some of the faces turned to stare at him, and fell quiet.

The food appeared on the tables. No one looked at it.

And Snape spun on his heel, abandoning his target, and headed straight toward Draco.

A knot of fear clutched at Draco’s heart, had something happened to Father – no, surely Father would have told him – whatever was happening, why hadn’t Father told him –

There were bags of fatigue beneath Snape’s eyes, Draco saw as their Head of House came close, the Potions Master had never been a sharp dresser (that was an understatement) but his robes were even dirtier and more disarrayed this morning, spotted with extra grease.

‘You haven’t heard?’ hissed their Head of House as he came close. ‘For pity’s sake, Malfoy, don’t you have a newspaper delivered?’

‘What is it, Profe–’

‘Bellatrix Black was taken from Azkaban!’

‘What?’ said Draco in shock, as Gregory behind him said something he really shouldn’t have and Vincent just gasped.

Snape was gazing at him with narrowed eyes, then nodded abruptly. ‘Lucius told you nothing, then. I see.’ Snape gave a snort, turned away –

‘Professor!’ said Draco. The implications were just starting to dawn on him, his mind spinning frantically. ‘Professor, what should I do – Father didn’t instruct me –’

‘Then I suggest,’ Snape said sneeringly, as he strode away, ‘that you tell them that, Malfoy, as your father intended!’

Draco glanced back at Vincent and Gregory, though he didn’t know why he was bothering, of course they looked even more confused than he did.

And Draco walked forward to the Slytherin table, and sat down at the far end, which was still empty of sitters.

Draco put a sausage omelet on his plate, began eating it with automatic motions.

Bellatrix Black had been taken from Azkaban.

Bellatrix Black had been taken from Azkaban … ?

Draco didn’t know what to make of that, it was as totally unexpected as the Sun going out – well, the Sun would expectedly go out in six billion years but this was as unexpected as the Sun going out tomorrow. Father wouldn’t have done it, Dumbledore wouldn’t have done it, no one should have been able to do it – what did it mean – what use would Bellatrix be to anyone after ten years in Azkaban – even if she got strong again, what use was a powerful sorceress who was completely evil and insane and fanatically devoted to a Dark Lord who wasn’t around any more?

‘Hey,’ said Vincent from where he was sitting next to Draco, ‘I don’t understand, boss, why’d we do that?’

‘We didn’t do it, you dolt!’ snapped Draco. ‘Oh, for Merlin’s sake, if even you think we – didn’t your father ever tell you any stories about Bellatrix Black? She tortured Father once, she tortured your father, she’s tortured everyone, the Dark Lord once told her to Crucio herself and she did it! She didn’t do crazy things to inspire fear and obedience in the populace, she did crazy things because she’s crazy! She’s a bitch is what she is!’

‘Oh, really?’ said an incensed voice from behind Draco.

Draco didn’t look up. Gregory and Vincent would be watching his back.

‘I would’ve thought you’d be happy –’

‘– to hear that a Death Eater had been freed, Malfoy!’

Amycus Carrow had always been one of the other problem people; Father had once told Draco to make sure he was never alone in the same room with Amycus …

Draco turned around and gave Flora and Hestia Carrow his Number Three Sneer, the one that said that he was in a Noble and Most Ancient House and they weren’t and yes, that mattered. Draco said in their general direction, certainly not deigning to address them in particular, ‘There’s Death Eaters and then there’s Death Eaters,’ and then turned back to his food.

There were two furious huffs in unison, and then two pairs of shoes stormed off toward the other end of the Slytherin table.

It was a few minutes later that Millicent Bulstrode ran up to them, visibly out of breath, and said, ‘Mr Malfoy, did you hear?’

‘About Bellatrix Black?’ said Draco. ‘Yeah –’

‘No, about Potter!’

‘What?’

‘Potter was going around with a phoenix on his shoulder last night, looking like he’d been dragged through ten leagues of mud, they say that the phoenix took him to Azkaban to try to stop Bellatrix and he fought a duel with her and they blew up half the fortress!’

‘What?’ said Draco. ‘Oh, there is just no way that –’

Draco stopped.

He’d said that a number of times about Harry Potter and had started to notice a trend.

Millicent ran off to tell someone else.

‘You don’t really think –’ said Gregory.

‘I honestly don’t know any more,’ said Draco.

A few minutes later, after Theodore Nott had sat down across from him and William Rosier had gone to sit with the Carrow twins, Vincent nudged him and said, ‘There.’

Harry Potter had entered the Great Hall.

Draco watched him closely.

There was no alarm on Harry’s face as he saw, no surprise or shock, he just looked …

It was the same distant, self-absorbed look Harry wore when he was trying to figure out the answer to a question Draco couldn’t understand yet.

Draco hastily shoved himself up from the bench of the Slytherin table, saying ‘Stay behind,’ and walked with all decorous speed toward Harry.

Harry seemed to notice his approach just as the other boy was turning toward the Ravenclaw table, and Draco –

– gave Harry one quick look –

– and then walked right past him, straight out of the Great Hall.

It was a minute later that Harry peered around the corner of the small stony nook where Draco had waited, it might not fool everyone but it would create plausible deniability.

‘Quietus,’ said Harry. ‘Draco, what –’

Draco took the envelope out of his robes. ‘I have a message for you from Father.’

‘Huh?’ said Harry, and took the envelope from Draco, and tore it open in a rather careless manner, and drew forth a sheet of parchment and unfolded it and –

Harry gave a sharp intake of breath.

Then Harry looked at Draco.

Then Harry looked back down at the parchment.

There was a pause.

Harry said, ‘Did Lucius tell you to report on my reaction to this?’

Draco paused for a moment, weighing, and then opened his mouth –

‘I see he did,’ said Harry, and Draco cursed himself, he should’ve known better, only it had been hard to decide. ‘What are you going to tell him?’

‘That you were surprised,’ said Draco.

‘Surprised,’ Harry said flatly. ‘Yeah. Good. Tell him that.’

‘What is it?’ said Draco. And then, as he saw Harry looking conflicted, ‘If you’re dealing with Father behind my back –’

And Harry, without a word, gave Draco the paper.

It said:

I know it was you.

‘What the –’

‘I was going to ask you that,’ said Harry. ‘Have you got any idea what’s up with your Dad?’

Draco stared at Harry.

Then Draco said, ‘Did you do it?’

‘What?’ said Harry. ‘What possible reason would I – how would I –’

‘Did you do it, Harry?’

‘No!’ Harry said. ‘Of course not!’

Draco had listened carefully, but he hadn’t detected any hesitation or tremor.

So Draco nodded, and said, ‘I’ve got no idea what Father’s thinking but it can’t, I mean it can’t possibly be good. And, um … people are also saying …’

‘What,’ said Harry warily, ‘are they saying, Draco?’

‘Did a phoenix really take you to Azkaban to try to stop Bellatrix Black from escaping –’

Escalation of Conflicts

Harry walked forward a step, then another step, until a sense of unease began to pervade him, a disquiet in his nerves.

He said nothing, lifted no hand; the pervading sense of unease would say it for him.

From behind the closed door of the office came a whisper, carrying through the door as though no door were present.

‘It is not my office hours,’ said that cold whisper, ‘nor yet the time of our meeting. I take ten Quirrell points from you, and be glad it is not more.’

Harry stayed calm. Going through Azkaban had recalibrated his scale of emotional disturbances; and losing a House point, which had formerly rated five out of ten, now lay somewhere around zero point three. Harry’s voice was likewise level, as he said, ‘You made a testable prediction and it was falsified, Professor. I only wished to note that.’

As Harry turned to go, he heard the door opening behind him, and he swung back around in some surprise.

Professor Quirrell was leaning back in his chair, his head lolling back against its rest, as a parchment floated before him. Both the Defence Professor’s hands rested limply on the desk, as though nerveless. He might have been a corpse, excepting that the ice-blue eyes still moved, back and forth, back and forth.

The parchment vanished, and was replaced by another so quickly it was like the material had only flickered.

Then the lips moved as well. ‘And from this,’ whispered the lips, ‘you infer what, Mr Potter?’

Harry was shaken by the sight, but his voice stayed even as he said, ‘That ordinary people do not always do nothing, and that Hermione Granger is in more danger from Slytherin House than you thought.’

The lips curved, ever so barely. ‘So you think I have failed in my grasp of human nature. But that is hardly the only possibility, boy. Do you see the other?’

Harry furrowed his brows as he stared at the Defence Professor.

‘I tire of this,’ the Defence Professor whispered. ‘You will stand there until you see it for yourself, or else leave.’ As though Harry had stopped existing, the Defence Professor’s eyes looked back to the parchment, once more scanning back and forth.

It was six parchments later that Harry saw it, and said out loud, ‘You think your prediction failed because there was some other factor at work which was not in your model. Some reason why Slytherin House hates Hermione more than you realized. Like when the orbital calculations for Uranus were wrong, and the problem wasn’t in Newton’s Laws, it was that they didn’t know about Neptune –’

The parchment vanished, and was not replaced. The head rose from its lolling position then, facing Harry more directly, and the voice which issued forth was quiet, but not toneless. ‘I think, boy,’ Professor Quirrell said softly, but in something approaching his normal voice, ‘that if all Slytherin House hated her so much, I would have seen it. And yet three formidable fighters of that House did something rather than nothing, at risk and at cost to themselves. What force could have moved them, or willed their motion?’ The icy blue glitter of the Defence Professor’s eyes met Harry’s own gaze. ‘Some hand possessed of influence within Slytherin, perhaps. Then how would that hand have benefited itself by harm done to the girl and her followers?’

‘Um …’ said Harry. ‘It would have to be someone threatened by Hermione somehow, or someone who would get the credit if she was hurt? I don’t know anyone who fits that profile, but then I don’t know much about anyone in Slytherin outside first-year.’ The thought was also coming to Harry that deducing a hidden mastermind from a single mildly-unexpected attack seemed like insufficient evidence to support the prior improbability of the theory; but then it was Professor Quirrell who was doing the deducing …

The Defence Professor was just looking at Harry, eyelids slightly lowered as though in impatience.

‘And yes,’ said Harry, ‘I am sure that Draco Malfoy isn’t behind it.’

A hiss of outward air like a sigh. ‘He is the son of Lucius Malfoy, trained to the most exacting standards. Whatever you have seen of him, even in what seem to be unguarded moments when his mask slips and you trust that you have seen the truth beneath, even that may all be part of the face he chooses to show you.’

Only if Draco successfully cast the Patronus Charm as part of keeping up the act. But Harry didn’t say that, of course; instead he just grinned slightly, and said, ‘So either you’ve really never read Draco’s mind, or that’s just what you want me to think.’

There was a pause. One of the hands turned over, beckoned a finger.

Harry stepped into the room. The door closed behind him.

‘That was not something you should have said aloud in human speech,’ said Professor Quirrell’s soft voice. ‘Legilimency, on Malfoy’s heir? Did Lucius Malfoy learn of it, he would have me assassinated outright.’

‘He would try,’ Harry said. It should have won a crinkle of Professor Quirrell’s eyes, but the Defence Professor’s face was unmoving. ‘But sorry.’

When the Defence Professor spoke again, his voice had once more become a cold whisper. ‘I suppose I could, and pity the assassin.’ His head fell back against the chair, lolled to one side, the eyes no longer meeting Harry’s. ‘But these small games hardly hold my interest as they stand. Add Legilimency, and it ceases to be a game at all.’

Harry hardly knew what to say. He’d seen Professor Quirrell in an angry mood once or twice before, but this seemed emptier, and Harry didn’t know what to say to it. What’s bothering you, Professor Quirrell? he could not ask.

‘What does hold your interest?’ Harry said a few moments later, after he’d worked it out as a safer-seeming strategy for redirecting Professor Quirrell’s attention to positive things. Citing experimental results about keeping a gratitude journal as a strategy for improving life happiness didn’t seem like it would be taken well.

‘I will tell you what does not hold my interest,’ said that icy whisper. ‘Grading Ministry-mandated essays does not hold my interest, Mr Potter. But I have undertaken the position of Defence Professor at Hogwarts, and I will see it through to its end.’ Another parchment appeared in front of Professor Quirrell’s head, and his eyes began to scan it. ‘Reese Belka held a high position in my armies before her folly. I will offer her the chance to stay rather than being expelled, if she tells me exactly of the forces which moved her. And I shall make clear to her what will happen if she lies. I do permit myself to read faces.’

The Defence Professor’s finger pointed past Harry, toward the door.

‘But whether you were wrong about human nature,’ Harry said, ‘or whether there’s some extra force at work in Slytherin House – either way, Hermione Granger is in more danger than you predicted. Last time it was three strong fighters, so what happens after –’

‘She wishes not my help, nor yours,’ said a soft cold voice. ‘I no longer find your concerns so entertaining as I once did, Mr Potter. Go.’

Somehow, even though they were all equals and she definitely wasn’t in charge, it was always Hermione who ended up speaking first in this sort of situation.

The four tables of Hogwarts, the four Houses having breakfast, were glancing over at where they, the eight members of S.P.H.E.W., had gathered off to one side.

Professor Flitwick was also staring sternly at all of them from the Head Table. Hermione wasn’t looking there, but she could feel Professor Flitwick’s gaze on the back of her neck. Literally feel it. It was really creepy.

‘Why’d you tell Tracey you wanted to talk to us, Mr Potter?’ said Hermione, her tone crisp.

‘Professor Quirrell expelled Reese Belka from her army last night,’ Harry Potter said. ‘And from all her other after-school Defence activities. Do any of you see the significance of that? Miss Greengrass? Padma?’

Harry’s eyes swept over them, as Hermione exchanged a puzzled glance with Padma, and Daphne shook her head.

‘Well,’ Harry said quietly, ‘I wouldn’t actually expect you to. But what it means is that you’re in danger, and I don’t know how much danger.’ The boy squared his shoulders, looking straight into Hermione’s eyes. ‘I wasn’t going to say this, but … I just wanted to offer to put you under whatever protection I could give. Make it clear to everyone that anyone who messes with you, is messing with the Boy-Who-Lived.’

‘Harry!’ said Hermione sharply. ‘You know I don’t want –’

‘Some of them are my friends too, Hermione.’ Harry didn’t take his eyes from hers. ‘And it’s their decision, not yours. Padma? You told me that I owed you no debt for what I did, and that’s the sort of thing a friend would say.’

Hermione broke her gaze from Harry, to look at where Padma was shaking her head.

‘Lavender?’ Harry said. ‘You fought well in my army, and I’ll fight for you if you wish it.’

‘Thank you, General!’ Lavender said crisply. ‘I mean Mr Potter. No, though. I’m a heroine and a Gryffindor, and I can fight for myself.’

There was a pause.

‘Parvati?’ Harry said. ‘Susan? Hannah? Daphne? I don’t know any of you so well, but it’s something I would offer anyone who came to ask it of me, I think.’

One by one, the other four girls shook their heads.

Hermione realized what was coming, then, but she didn’t see a single thing she could do about it.

‘And my loyal soldier, Chaotic Tracey?’ said Harry Potter.

‘Really?’ gasped Tracey, oblivious to the stabbing glares that Hermione and every other girl were directing at her. Tracey’s hands flew artfully to her cheeks, though she didn’t actually manage to blush, not that Hermione could see; and her brown eyes were, if not shining, at least opened very wide. ‘You’d do that? For me? I mean – I mean, of course, absolutely, General Chaos –’

And so it was on that very morning that Harry Potter went over to the Gryffindor table, and then the Slytherin table, and told both Houses that anyone who hurt Tracey Davis, regardless of what she was doing at the time, would, quote, learn the true meaning of Chaos, unquote.

It was with considerable restraint that Draco Malfoy managed to prevent himself from slamming his head repeatedly into his plate of toast.

They weren’t exactly scientists, the bullies of Hogwarts.

But even they, Draco knew, were going to want to test it.

The Society for the Promotion of Heroic Equality for Witches hadn’t announced it, it didn’t seem like it would do any good to announce it. But they had all quietly decided (or, in the case of Lavender, been shouted into it by all seven other girls) to take a break from fighting bullies for a while, at least until their Heads of House weren’t looking at them quite so sharply any more, and older students had stopped bumping Hermione into walls.

Daphne had told Millicent that they were taking a break.

And so it was with some puzzlement, a few days later, that Daphne looked at the parchment delivered to her at lunch, drawn in a hand so shaky it was almost unreadable, saying:

2 this afternoon at the top of the stairs going up from the library really important everyone has to be there – Millicent

Daphne looked around, but she couldn’t see Millicent anywhere in the Great Hall.

‘A message from your informant?’ said Hermione, when Daphne told her. ‘That’s odd – I didn’t –’

‘You didn’t what?’ said Daphne, after the Ravenclaw girl had stopped in mid-sentence.

The Sunshine General shook her head and said, ‘Listen, Daphne, I think we need to know where these messages come from before we keep following them. Look at what happened last time, how could anyone have known where those three bullies would be, unless they were in on it?’

‘I can’t say –’ Daphne said. ‘I mean, I can’t say anything, but I know where the messages come from, and I know how anyone can know.’

Hermione gave Daphne a look that, for a moment, made the Ravenclaw girl look scarily like Professor McGonagall.

‘Uh huh,’ said Hermione. ‘And do you know how Susan suddenly turned into Supergirl?’

Daphne shook her head, and said, ‘No, but I think it might be really important that if we get a message saying we should be somewhere, everyone has to be there.’ Daphne hadn’t seen what had happened with Susan, after Daphne had tried to avert the prophecy by keeping Susan away. But she’d been told about it afterwards, and now Daphne was afraid that …

She might have possibly …

Might possibly have Broken Something …

‘Uh huh,’ said Hermione, who was doing the McGonagall Stare again.

Nobody seemed to know where it had started, who had started it. If you’d tried tracing it afterwards, tracked it back word by word and mutter by mutter, you probably would have found it all going in a huge circle.

Peregrine Derrick was tapped on his shoulder as he left Potions that morning.

Jaime Astorga heard a whisper in his ear at lunch.

Robert Jugson III discovered a tiny folded note under his plate.

Carl Sloper overheard two older Gryffindors whispering about it, and they gave him significant glances as they walked past.

Nobody seemed to know where the word began, or who had first spoken it, but it named the place, and it named the time, and it said that the colour would be white.

Cheating

It was Saturday, on the 4th of April, in the year 1992.

Mr and Mrs Davis looked rather nervous, as they sat in a certain special section of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands – though today the cushioned benches did not look upon flying broomsticks, but rather viewed a gigantic square of something like parchment; a great white blankness soon to flicker with windows into grass and soldiers. For now it showed only the reflected dull grey colour of the surrounding overcast skies. (Looking rather stormy, though the weather-wizards had promised that the rain wouldn’t break before nightfall.)

Ordinarily it was the ancient tradition of Hogwarts that mere parents were to Stay Out – for much the same reason that impatient children are told to get out of the kitchen and not meddle in the cook’s affairs. The only reason for a parent-teacher conference was if a teacher felt that a parent wasn’t shaping up properly. It took an exceptional circumstance to make the Hogwarts administration feel that it had to justify itself to you. On any given occasion, generally speaking, the Hogwarts administration was backed up by eight hundred years of distinguished history and you were not.

Thus it had been with some trepidation that Mr and Mrs Davis had insisted on an audience with Deputy Headmistress McGonagall. It was hard to muster a proper sense of indignation when you were confronting the same dignified witch who, twelve years and four months earlier, had given both of you two weeks’ detention after catching you in the act of conceiving Tracey.

On the other hand, Mr and Mrs Davis’ courage had been helped by angrily waving about a copy of The Quibbler whose headline showed, in bright bold text for all the world to see:

Pacts with Potter?
Bones, Davis, Granger
in love rectangle of fear

And so Mr and Mrs Davis had argued their way into the Faculty Box of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands, where they were now ensconced with an excellent view of Professor Quirrell’s enchanted screens, so that the two of them could see for themselves ‘Just what the Fiddly-Snocks has been going on in this school, if you’ll pardon the expression, Deputy Headmistress McGonagall!’

Seated to the left of Mr Davis was another concerned parent, a white-haired man in elegant black robes of unmatchable quality, one Lucius Malfoy, political leader of the strongest faction of the Wizengamot.

To the left of Lord Malfoy, a sneeringly aristocratic man with a scarred face who had been introduced to them as Lord Jugson.

Then an elderly but sharp-eyed fellow named Charles Nott, rumoured to be nearly as wealthy as Lord Malfoy, seated on Lord Jugson’s left.

On the right of Mrs Davis, one would find the comely Lady and yet handsomer Lord of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Greengrass. Young they were as wizards counted age, garbed in grey silken robes set with tiny dark emeralds embroidered into the shape of grass blades. The Lady Greengrass was considered a key swing vote on the Wizengamot, her own mother having retired from the body with surprising speed. Her charming husband, though his family was not noble or wealthy of itself, had taken a seat on the Hogwarts Board of Governors.

To their right, a square-jawed and incredibly tough-looking old witch, who had shaken hands with Mr and Mrs Davis without the slightest hint of condescension. This was Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement.

To Amelia’s right was a oldish woman who had set the fashion scene of magical Britain on its ear by integrating a live vulture into her hat, one Augusta Longbottom. Though she was not addressed as Lady, Madam Longbottom would exercise the full rights of the Longbottom family for so long as their last scion had yet to attain his majority, and she was considered a prominent figure in a minority faction of the Wizengamot.

At the side of Madam Longbottom was seated none other than Chief Warlock Supreme Mugwump Headmaster Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore, legendary defeater of Grindelwald, protector of Britain, rediscoverer of the fabled twelve uses of dragon’s blood, the most powerful wizard in the world &c.

And finally, on the far right, one would find the enigmatic Defence Professor of Hogwarts, Quirinus Quirrell, who was leaning back on the cushioned benches as though resting; seeming entirely and naturally at ease in the rarefied company of a voting quorum of the Hogwarts Board of Governors, which had dropped by on this fine Saturday to learn just what the Fiddly-Snocks had been going on at Hogwarts in general and with Draco Malfoy, Theodore Nott, Daphne Greengrass, Susan Bones, and Neville Longbottom in particular. The name of Harry Potter had also been much discussed.

Oh, and one mustn’t forget Tracey Davis, of course. Director Bones’s eyebrows had climbed in some interest upon hearing the young couple introduced as her parents. Lord Jugson had given them a brief, incredulous stare before dismissing them with a snort. Lucius Malfoy had greeted them politely, his smile containing a hint of grim amusement mixed with pity.

Mr and Mrs Davis, whose last vote on anything of significance had been touching their wands to the name of Minister Fudge, who had all of three hundred Galleons stored in their Gringotts vault, and who respectively worked at selling cauldrons in a Potions shop and enchanting Omnioculars, were pressed up tightly against each other, sitting rigidly erect upon their cushioned benches, and desperately wishing they’d worn nicer robes.

The sky above was a solid mass of cloud dispersed into darker and lighter greys, grim with the promise of future storms; though no lightning flickered as yet, nor distant rumbles of thunder echoed; and only a few threatening droplets had fallen.

To their designated starting place in a certain forest, the Sunshine Regiment marched, though it was really more like a slow walk; you wouldn’t want to tire yourself out before the battle even started, and the breezes of April were annoyingly humid, though cool. Ahead of them, a yellow flame wandered slowly through the air, guiding them according to their pace.

Susan Bones kept throwing worried glances toward the Sunshine General as they marched through the greyly illuminated forest. Professor Snape’s going after Hermione seemed to have really shaken her. Hermione had even missed her Sunshine Regiment Official Planning Meeting, which seemed understandable enough; but when Susan had offered her sympathy afterwards, Hermione had stammered that she’d lost track of time, which wasn’t at all a usual thing for her to say, and the girl had looked exhausted and frightened like she’d just spent three days locked in a bathroom stall with a Dementor. Even now, when all the Sunshine General’s focus should’ve been on the coming battle, the Ravenclaw girl’s gaze was constantly darting in all directions, as though she expected Dark Wizards to jump out of the bushes and sacrifice her.

‘The ban on Muggle artifacts cuts down our options a lot,’ Anthony Goldstein was saying in the dour tones the boy used to denote deliberate pessimism. ‘I had the idea of trying to Transfigure nets to throw on people, but –’

‘No good,’ said Ernie Macmillan. The Hufflepuff boy shook his head, looking even more serious than Anthony. ‘I mean, it’s just like throwing a hex, they’d dodge.’

Anthony nodded. ‘That’s what I figured, too. Do you have any ideas, Seamus?’

The former Chaotic Lieutenant still looked a bit nervous and out-of-place, marching along with his new comrades in the Sunshine Regiment. ‘Sorry,’ said the newly minted Captain Finnigan. ‘I’m more the strategic master type.’

‘I’m the strategic master type,’ said Ron Weasley, sounding put-off.

‘There are three armies,’ the Sunshine General said acerbically, ‘which means we fight two armies at once, which means we need more than one strategist, which means shut up, Ron!’

Ron gave their General a surprised and worried look. ‘Hey,’ the Gryffindor boy said in a calming tone, ‘you shouldn’t let Snape get to you so much –’

‘What do you think we ought to do, General?’ Susan said very loudly and quickly. ‘I mean, we don’t really have a plan at this point.’ Their official planning session had failed amazingly with Hermione gone and both Ron and Anthony thinking they were in charge.

‘Do we really need a plan?’ the Sunshine General said, sounding a little distracted. ‘We’ve got you and me and Lavender and Parvati and Hannah and Daphne and Ron and Ernie and Anthony and Captain Finnigan.’

‘That –’ began Anthony.

‘Sounds like a pretty good strategy,’ Ron said with an approving nod. ‘We’ve got as many strong soldiers now as both other armies put together. Chaos’s only got Potter and Longbottom and Nott left – well, and Zabini too, I suppose –’

‘And Tracey,’ said Hermione.

Several people swallowed nervously.

‘Oh, stop it,’ Susan said sharply. ‘She’s just a battle-hardened member of S.P.H.E.W., that’s all General Sunshine means.’

‘Still,’ Ernie said, turning to look seriously at Susan, ‘I think you’d better go with whatever group fights Chaos, Captain Bones. I know you can’t use your double magical powers except when innocents are in danger, but I mean – just in case Miss Davis does, you know, go out of control and try to eat someone’s soul –’

‘I can handle her,’ Susan told him, keeping her voice reassuring. Admittedly, Susan hadn’t been replaced by a Metamorphmagus at the moment, but then Tracey probably wasn’t Polyjuiced Dumbledore or whoever.

Captain Finnigan intoned in a deep, sort-of-rumbling voice, ‘I find your lack of skepticism disturbing.’ He raised his hand with his thumb and forefinger almost touching, pointed at Ernie.

For some reason Anthony Goldstein seemed to be having a sudden choking fit. ‘What’s that supposed to mean?’ said Ernie.

‘It’s just something General Potter says sometimes,’ said Captain Finnigan. ‘Funny, when you first join the Chaos Legion it all seems crazy, and then after a couple of months you realize that actually everyone who isn’t in the Chaos Legion is crazy –’

‘I said,’ Ron said loudly, ‘it sounds like good strategy. We don’t Transfigure anything, we don’t tire ourselves out, we handle whatever they throw at us, and then we just overrun them.’

‘Okay,’ said Hermione. ‘Let’s do that.’

‘But –’ said Anthony, shooting a glare at Ron. ‘But General, Harry Potter’s got sixteen people left in his army. Dragon and us each have twenty-eight. Harry knows that, he knows he’s got to come up with something incredible –’

‘Like what?’ demanded Hermione, sounding stressed. ‘If we don’t know what he’s planning, we might as well save our magic for doing massed Finites. Like we should’ve done last time!’

Susan touched Hermione gently on the shoulder. ‘General Granger?’ said Susan. ‘I think you should take a break for a bit before the battle.’

She’d been expecting Hermione to argue, but Hermione just nodded and then walked a little faster, pulling away from the Sunshine Regiment Official Officer Group, her eyes still watching the forest, and sometimes the sky.

Susan followed her. It wouldn’t do, having it look like the Sunshine General was being ejected from her own Official Officer Group.

‘Hermione?’ Susan said softly, after they’d walked a bit away. ‘You’ve got to focus. Professor Quirrell’s in charge here, not Snape, and he won’t let anything bad happen to you or anyone.’

‘You’re not helping,’ Hermione said, sounding shaky. ‘You’re not helping at all, Captain Bones.’

The two of them walked faster, circling around some of the other soldiers, inspecting the marching perimeter and glancing at the surrounding trees.

‘Susan?’ Hermione said in a small voice, when they were further away from all the others. ‘Do you think Daphne’s right about Draco Malfoy plotting something?’

‘Yes,’ Susan said at once, not even thinking about it. ‘You can tell, because his name’s got the letters M-A-L-F-O and Y in it.’

Hermione looked around, as if to make sure that nobody was watching, although of course that was a wonderful way to get other people to pay attention to you. ‘Could Malfoy have been behind what Snape did?’

‘Snape could be behind Malfoy,’ Susan said thoughtfully, remembering dinner-table conversations she’d heard at Auntie’s, ‘or Lucius Malfoy could be behind both of them.’ A slight chill went down Susan’s spine as this last thought occurred to her. Suddenly, telling Hermione to just focus on the coming battle seemed a lot less reasonable. ‘Why, did you find some sort of clue about that?’

Hermione shook her head. ‘No,’ the Ravenclaw girl said, in a voice that sounded almost like she was about to cry. ‘I was – just thinking about it myself – that’s all.’

In their designated place in a forest near Hogwarts, the Dragon General and the warriors of Dragon Army waited where their red flame had led them, beneath grey skies.

At Draco’s right side stood Padma Patil, his second-in-command, who had once led all of Dragon Army after Draco had been stunned. At Draco’s back was Vincent, the son of Crabbe, a family which had served the Malfoys into the distance of forgotten memory; the muscular boy was watchful as he was always watchful, whether battle had been declared or no. Further back, Gregory of the Goyles stood waiting beside one of the two broomsticks Dragon Army had been given; if the Goyles had not served the Malfoys so long as the Crabbes, yet they had served no less well.

And at Draco’s left side, now, stood one Dean Thomas of Gryffindor, a mudblood or possible half-blood who knew nothing of his father.

Sending Dean Thomas to Dragon Army had been a quite deliberate move on Harry’s part, Draco was certain. Three other former Chaotics had also been transferred to Dragon Army, and all were watching Draco hawklike to see if he offered the former Lieutenant the slightest insult.

Some might have called it sabotage, but Draco knew better. Harry had also sent Lieutenant Finnigan to the Sunshine Regiment, even though Professor Quirrell’s mandate had only required that Harry give up one Lieutenant. That too had been a deliberate move, making crystal clear to everyone that Harry wasn’t dumping his least-favoured soldiers.

In one sense, it might have been easier for Draco to win the true loyalties of his new soldiers if they’d thought Harry hadn’t wanted them. In another sense … well, it wasn’t easy to put into words. Harry had given him good soldiers with their pride intact, but it was more than that. Harry had showed kindliness toward his soldiers, but it was more than that. It wasn’t just Harry playing fair, it was something that … that you couldn’t help but contrast with the way the game was played in Slytherin House.

So Draco hadn’t offered the slightest insult to Mr Thomas, but brought him straight to his side, subordinate to himself and Padma but no one else. It was a test, Draco had told Mr Thomas and everyone, not a promotion. Mr Thomas would have to show himself worthy of rank within Dragon Army – but he would be given a chance, and the chance would be fair. Mr Thomas had looked surprised at the ceremony of it (the Chaos Legion, from what Draco had heard, didn’t stand on formality) but the Gryffindor boy had stood a little straighter, and nodded.

And then, after Mr Thomas had done well enough in one of Dragon Army’s training sessions, he’d been brought into the strategy session in Dragon Army’s huge military office. And a few minutes into the session, Padma had happened to ask – as though it was a perfectly normal question – whether Mr Thomas had any ideas about how to defeat the Chaos Legion.

The Gryffindor boy had said cheerfully that Harry had predicted that General Malfoy would get one of his soldiers to ask him that, and that Harry had given him the message that General Malfoy should ask himself where his relative advantage lay – what Draco Malfoy could do, or what Dragon Army could do, that the Chaos Legion couldn’t match – and then try to exploit it for all it was worth. Dean Thomas couldn’t think of what that advantage might be, but if he did come up with any ideas for beating Chaos, he’d share them. Harry had ordered him to, after all.

Sigh, Draco had thought, since he couldn’t actually sigh out loud. But it was good advice, and Draco had followed it, sitting at his bedroom desk with quill and parchment listing out everything that might be a relative advantage.

And, almost to Draco’s own surprise, he’d had an idea, a real one. In fact he’d had two.

The hollow bell sounded through the forest, somehow sounding more ominous than ever before. On the instant, the two pilots cried ‘Up!’ and leapt onto their broomsticks, heading into the grey sky.

Mr and Mrs Davis had now slumped slightly against each other, more from sheer muscle exhaustion than from any decrease of tension. Before them, the vast blank white parchment flickered with three great windows, as though holes had been cut through into the forest, showing three armies on the march. Lesser windows showed the six riders upon their broomsticks, and the corner of the parchment showed a view of the entire forest, with glowing dots to indicate armies and scouts.

The window into Sunshine showed General Granger and her Captains marching in the centre of the Sunshine Regiment, protected by Contego screens along with a number of other young witches. The Sunshine Regiment, the Defence Professor had remarked, knew well that it had now acquired a strong advantage in experienced soldiers, and it meant to protect those soldiers from a surprise attack. Aside from that, the Sunshine Soldiers were moving forward at a steady march, conserving their strength.

The soldiers in General Malfoy’s army, at least those with higher Transfiguration scores, were picking up leaves and Transfiguring them into … well, if you looked at Padma Patil, who was almost done with hers, it looked like her leaf was becoming a left-handed glove bearing a dangling strap. (The window had zoomed in to show this.)

Lord Jugson was watching the screen with a flat expression; his voice, when he spoke, seemed to ooze and drip with disdain. ‘What is your son doing, Lucius?’

The foreign-born witch who stood at Draco Malfoy’s right side had finished Transfiguring her glove, and was now bringing it before the Dragon General like a sacrifice.

‘I do not know,’ said Lucius Malfoy, his tone calm though no less aristocratic, ‘but I must trust that he has good reason for doing it.’

All Dragon Army stopped for a moment as Padma slid the glove over her left hand, strapped it in place, and presented it before Draco Malfoy; who also stopped in place, took several deep breaths, raised his wand, executed a precise set of eight movements and bellowed ‘Colloportus!’

The Dragon Warrior raised her gloved hand, flexed it, and gave a small bow to Draco Malfoy, who returned it more shallowly, though the Dragon General was staggering slightly. Padma then returned to her place at Draco’s side, and the Dragons began marching once more.

‘Well,’ remarked Augusta Longbottom. ‘I don’t suppose someone would care to explain?’ Amelia Bones was frowning slightly as she gazed at the screen.

‘For some reason or other,’ said the amused voice of Professor Quirrell, ‘it seems that the scion of Malfoy is able to cast surprisingly strong magic for a first-year student. Due to the purity of his blood, of course. Certainly the good Lord Malfoy would not have openly flouted the underage magic laws by arranging for his son to receive a wand before his acceptance into Hogwarts.’

‘I suggest you be careful in your implications, Quirrell,’ Lucius Malfoy said coldly.

‘Oh, I am,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘A Colloportus cannot be dispelled by Finite Incantatem; it requires an Alohomora of equal strength. Until then, a glove so Charmed will resist lesser material forces, deflect the Sleep Hex and the Stunning Hex. And as neither Mr Potter nor Miss Granger can cast a counter-spell powerful enough, that Charm is invincible upon this battlefield. It is not the original intent of the Charm, nor the intent of whoever taught Mr Malfoy an emergency spell for evading his enemies. But it would seem that Mr Malfoy has been learning creativity.’

Lucius Malfoy had straightened as the Defence Professor spoke; he now sat erect upon his cushioned bench, his head held perceptibly higher than before, and when he spoke it was with quiet pride. ‘He will be the greatest Lord Malfoy that has yet lived.’

‘Faint praise,’ Augusta Longbottom said under her breath; Amelia Bones chuckled, as did Mr Davis for a tiny, fatal fraction of a second before he stopped with a strangled gargle.

‘I quite agree,’ said Professor Quirrell, though it wasn’t clear to whom he spoke. ‘Unfortunately for Mr Malfoy, he is still new to the art of creativity, and so he has committed a classic error of Ravenclaw.’

‘And what might that be?’ said Lucius Malfoy, his voice now turned chill once more.

Professor Quirrell had leaned back in his seat, the pale blue eyes briefly unfocusing as one of the windows shifted its viewpoint within the greater screen, zooming in to show the sweat now on Draco Malfoy’s forehead. ‘It is such a beautiful idea that Mr Malfoy has quite overlooked its pragmatic difficulties.’

‘Would someone care to explain that?’ said Lady Greengrass. ‘Not all of us present are experts at such … affairs.’

Amelia Bones spoke, the old witch’s voice somewhat dry. ‘It will tempt them to try to catch hexes that they would be wiser to simply dodge. The more so, if they have had little practise catching them. And the casting of so many Charms will tire their strongest warrior.’

Professor Quirrell gave the DMLE Director a half-nod of acknowledgement. ‘As you say, Madam Bones. Mr Malfoy is new to the business of having ideas, and so when he has one, he becomes proud of himself for having it. He has not yet had enough ideas to unflinchingly discard those that are beautiful in some aspects and impractical in others; he has not yet acquired confidence in his own ability to think of better ideas as he requires them. What we are seeing here is not Mr Malfoy’s best idea, I fear, but rather his only idea.’

Lord Malfoy simply turned to watch the screens again, as though the Defence Professor had used up his right to exist.

‘But –’ said Lord Greengrass. ‘But what in Merlin’s name is Harry Potter –’

Sixteen remaining soldiers of the Chaos Legion – or fifteen plus Blaise Zabini, rather – marched confidently through the forest, their shoes thudding over the still-dry ground. Their camouflage uniforms blended into the forest even more than usual, all colours washed out by the tints of an overcast day.

Sixteen Chaos Legionnaires, against twenty-eight Dragon Warriors and twenty-eight Sunshine Soldiers.

The common consensus had been that, with odds that bad, it was practically impossible for them to lose. After all, General Chaos was bound to come up with something really spectacular, facing odds like that.

There was something almost nightmarish about how everyone seemed to now expect Harry to pull miracles out of his hat, on demand, any time one was needed. It meant that if you couldn’t do the impossible, you were disappointing your friends and failing to live up to your potential …

Harry hadn’t bothered complaining to Professor Quirrell about too much pressure. Harry’s mental model of the Defence Professor had predicted him looking severely annoyed, saying things along the lines of You are perfectly capable of solving this problem, Mr Potter; did you even try? and then deducting several hundred Quirrell points.

From above, from where two broomsticks watched their march, the high young voice of Tess Walsh cried ‘Friend!’ and after another moment, ‘Gingersnap!’

A handful of seconds later, the soldier who’d code-named herself Gingersnap returned bearing a double handful of acorns, sweating slightly in the cool but humid air from the jog that had taken her to the oak tree Neville had spotted. Gingersnap approached to where Shannon was holding a uniform-shirt with the neck tied off, in lieu of anyone having to Transfigure a bag. When Gingersnap brought her hands forward to try and dump her acorns into the holding-shirt, Chaotic Shannon, giggling, jerked the shirt to the right, then to the left again as Gingersnap made another effort to dump the acorns, until a sharp ‘Miss Friedman!’ from Lieutenant Nott caused Shannon to sigh and hold the shirt still. Gingersnap dumped her acorns into those accumulated, and then headed out for more.

Somewhere in the background, Ellie Knight was singing her very own version of the Chaos Legion’s marching song, and around half the other soldiers were trying to step along with it despite not knowing the tune in advance. Nearby, Nita Berdine, who had a high Transfiguration score, finished creating yet another pair of green sunglasses, and handed them to Adam Beringer, who folded up the sunglasses before tucking them into his uniform pocket. Other soldiers were already wearing their own green sunglasses, despite the cloudy day.

You might guess that there was some sort of incredibly complicated and fascinating explanation behind this, and you would be right.

Two days earlier Harry had been sitting amid his bookcases in the comfy rocking-chair he’d obtained for his trunk’s cavern level, pondering silently in the quiet span between classes and dinnertime, thinking about power.

For sixteen Chaotics to defeat twenty-eight Sunnies and twenty-eight Dragons they would need a force amplifier. There were limits to what you could do with manoeuvre. There had to be a secret weapon and it had to be invincible, or at least moderately unstoppable.

Muggle artifacts were now illegal in Hogwarts’s mock battles, banned by Ministry edict. And the trouble with finding some other clever and unusual spell was that an army twice your own size could brute-force Finite almost anything you tried. The Sunshine Regiment might have missed that tactic with the Transfigured chain mail, but nobody would miss it again now that Professor Quirrell had pointed it out. And Finite Incantatem was a brute-force counter-spell which required at least as much magic as the spell being cancelled … which, if you were severely outnumbered, made it a whole new order of military challenge. The enemy could Finite anything you tried, and still have enough magic left over for shields and volleys of Sleep Hexes.

Unless, somehow, you could invoke potencies beyond the ordinary strength of first-year Hogwarts students, something too powerful for the enemy to Finite.

So Harry had asked Neville if he’d ever heard of any small, safe sacrificial rituals –

And then, after the screaming and the shouting had subsided, after Harry had stopped trying to argue about Unbreakable Vows and just given up the whole thing as impossible from a public relations standpoint, Harry had realized that he hadn’t even needed to go there. They taught you how to invoke potencies far beyond your own strength in ordinary Hogwarts classes.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question.

Defence. Charms. Transfiguration. Potions. History of Magic. Astronomy. Broomstick Flying. Herbology …

‘Foe!’ screamed the voice from above.

It was a good thing that Neville Longbottom hadn’t the tiniest idea that his grandmother was watching; or he would’ve been more self-conscious about screaming scary battlecries at the top of his lungs while casting Luminos every three seconds as he rocketed through a dense forest of trees, hot on the tail of Gregory Goyle.

(‘But –’ Augusta Longbottom said, her expression showing almost as much astonishment as worry. ‘But Neville is afraid of heights!’)

(‘Not all fears last,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the great screen before them with a measuring gaze. ‘Or perhaps he has found courage. It is much the same, in the end.’)

A glimmer of red –

Neville dodged, very nearly into a tree but he did dodge; and then Neville somehow also managed to dodge almost all of the branches before they smacked him in the face.

Now Mr Goyle’s broomstick was pulling further and further away – even though the two of them were riding exactly the same broomstick and Mr Goyle weighed more, somehow Neville was still falling behind. So Neville slowed down, pulled back, angled up out of the forest and began to accelerate back toward where the Chaos Legion still marched.

Twenty seconds later – it hadn’t been a long chase, just an exciting one – Neville was back among his fellow Chaotics, and dismounted his broom to walk on the ground for a little bit.

‘Neville –’ said General Potter. Harry’s voice was a little distant, as he walked carefully and steadily through the forest, his wand still applied to the almost-finished Form of the object he was slowly Transfiguring. Beside him, Blaise Zabini, working a smaller version of the same Transfiguration, looked like a shambling Inferi as he stumbled forward. ‘I told you – Neville – you don’t have to –’

‘Yes, I do,’ said Neville. He looked down at where his fingers grasped the broomstick, and saw that not just his hands, but his whole arms were shaking. But unless anyone else in Chaos had been practising duelling for an hour a day with Mr Diggory, and then practising their aim in private for another hour afterwards, Neville was probably the best shot from a broomstick even after taking into account that he wasn’t a very good flyer.

‘Good show, Neville,’ Theodore said from where he was walking ahead of them all, leading the Chaos Legion forward through the forest while wearing only his under-shirt.

(Augusta Longbottom and Charles Nott exchanged brief astonished glances and then wrenched their gazes away from one another as though stung.)

Neville took a few deep breaths, trying to steady his hands, trying to think; Harry might not be good for deep strategic thinking while he was in the middle of an extended Transfiguration. ‘Lieutenant Nott, do you have any idea why Dragon Army just did that? They lost a broom –’ The Dragons had started the combat with a feint to provide a distraction for Mr Goyle’s approach through the forest; Neville hadn’t realized there were two brooms attacking until almost too late. But the Chaos Legion had got the other pilot. That was why broomsticks usually didn’t attack before armies met, it meant a whole army would concentrate fire on the broomstick. ‘And the Dragons didn’t even get anyone, did they?’

‘Nope!’ Tracey Davis said proudly. She too was now marching by General Potter’s side, her wand gripped low and watchful as her eyes scanned the surrounding forest. ‘I threw up a Prismatic Sphere like a split second before Mr Goyle’s hex got Zabini, and the way Mr Goyle had his other arm stretched out I think he planned to knock down the General, too.’ The Slytherin witch smiled with vicious confidence. ‘Mr Goyle tried a Breaking Drill Hex, but learned to his dismay that his weak magic was no match for my newfound dark powers, hahahaha!’

Some Chaotics laughed with her, but a queasy sensation was starting in Neville’s stomach as he realized how close the Chaos Legion had come to complete disaster. If Mr Goyle had managed to disrupt both Transfigurations –

‘Report!’ snapped the Dragon General, doing his best to conceal the fatigue he felt after casting seventeen Locking Charms, with more yet to come.

Beads of sweat now dotted Gregory’s forehead. ‘The enemy downed Dylan Vaughan,’ Gregory said formally. ‘Harry Potter and Blaise Zabini were each Transfiguring something dark-grey and roundish, I don’t think it was finished but it looked like it would be big and hollow, sort of cauldron-shaped. Zabini’s was smaller than Potter’s. I couldn’t get either of them or disrupt their Transfigurations, Tracey Davis blocked me. Neville Longbottom is on a broomstick and he’s still a terrible flyer but his aim is really good.’

Draco listened, frowning, and then he glanced at Padma and Dean Thomas, who both shook their own heads, indicating that they also couldn’t think of what might be big and grey and shaped like a cauldron.

‘Anything else?’ said Draco. If that was it, they’d lost a broom for nothing –

‘The only other weird thing I saw,’ Gregory said, sounding puzzled, ‘was that some Chaotics were wearing … sort of like goggles?’

Draco thought about this, not noticing that he’d stopped marching or that all of Dragon Army had automatically stopped with him.

‘Was there anything special about the goggles?’ Draco said.

‘Um …’ Gregory said. ‘They were … greenish, maybe?’

‘Okay,’ said Draco. Again without thinking, he began walking once more and his Dragons followed. ‘Here’s our new strategy. We’re only going to send eleven Dragons against the Chaos Legion, not fourteen. That should be enough to beat them, now that we can neutralize their special advantage.’ It was a gamble, but you had to take gambles sometimes, if you wanted to come in first in a three-way battle.

‘You figured out Chaos’s plan, General Malfoy?’ said Mr Thomas with considerable surprise.

‘What are they doing?’ said Padma.

‘I haven’t the faintest idea,’ said Draco, with a smirk of the most refined smugness. ‘We’ll just do the obvious thing.’

Harry, having now finished his cauldron, was carefully scooping acorns into the container while the scouts searched for a nearby source of water that could be used as a liquid base. They’d come across frequent sinkholes and miniature creeks in the forest before, so it ought not to take long. Another scout had brought a straight stick that would serve as a stirrer, so Harry didn’t have to Transfigure one.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

How can I invoke magical powers that ought to be beyond the reach of first-year students?

There was a cautionary tale the Potions Master had told them (with much sneers and laughter to make the stupidity seem low-status instead of daring and romantic) about a second-year witch in Beauxbatons who’d stolen some extremely restricted and expensive ingredients, and tried to brew Polyjuiceso she could borrow the form of another girl for purposes better left unmentioned. Only she’d managed to contaminate the potion with cat hairs, and then instead of seeking a healer immediately, the witch had hidden herself in a bathroom, hoping the effects would just wear off; and when she’d finally been found, it had been too late to reverse the transformation completely, condemning her to a life of despair as a sort of cat-girl hybrid.

Harry hadn’t realized what that meant until the instant of thinking the right question – but what that implied was that a young wizard or witch could do things with Potions-Making that they couldn’t even come close to doing with Charms. Polyjuice was one of the most potent potions known … but what made Polyjuice a N.E.W.T.-level potion, apparently, wasn’t the required age before you had enough magical power; it was how difficult the potion was to brew precisely and what happened to you if you messed up.

Nobody in any army had tried brewing any potions up until then. But Professor Quirrell would let you get away with nearly anything, if it was something you could also have done in a real war. Cheating is technique, the Defence Professor had once lectured them. Or rather, cheating is what the losers call technique, and will be worth extra Quirrell points when executed successfully. In principle, there was nothing unrealistic about Transfiguring a couple of cauldrons and brewing potions out of whatever came to hand, if you had enough time before the armies met.

So Harry had retrieved his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions, and begun looking for a safe but useful potion he could brew in the minutes before the battle started – a potion which would win the battle too fast for counter-spells, or produce spell effects too strong for first-years to Finite.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

What potion can I brew using only components gathered from an ordinary forest?

Every recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions used at least one ingredient from a magical plant or animal. Which was unfortunate, because all the magical plants and animals were in the Forbidden Forest, not the safer and lesser woods where battles were held.

Someone else might have given up at that point.

Harry had turned the pages from one recipe to another, skimming faster and faster in dawning realization, confirming what he had already read and was now seeing for the first time.

Every single Potions recipe seemed to demand at least one magical ingredient, but why should that be true?

Charms required no material components at all; you just said the words and waved your wand. Harry had been thinking about Potions-Making as essentially analogous: instead of your spoken syllables triggering a spell effect for no comprehensible reason, you collected a batch of disgusting ingredients and stirred four times clockwise, and that arbitrarily triggered a spell effect.

In which case, given that most potions used ordinary components like porcupine quills or stewed slugs, you’d expect to see some potions using only ordinary components.

But instead every single recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions demanded at least one component from a magical plant or animal – an ingredient like silk from an Acromantula or petals from a Venus Fire Trap.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

If making a potion is like casting a Charm, why don’t I fall over from exhaustion after brewing a draught as powerful as boil-curing?

The Friday before last, Harry’s double Potions class had brewed potion of boil-curing … although even the most trivial healing Charms, if you tried to cast them with wand and incantation, were at least fourth-year spells. And afterwards, they’d all felt the way they usually felt after Potions class, namely, not magically exhausted to any discernible degree.

Harry had shut his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions with a snap, and rushed down to the Ravenclaw common room. Harry had found a seventh-year Ravenclaw doing his N.E.W.T. potions homework and paid the older boy a Sickle to borrow Moste Potente Potions for five minutes; because Harry hadn’t wanted to run all the way to the library to find confirmation.

After skimming through five recipes in the seventh-year book, Harry had read the sixth recipe, for a potion of fire breathing, which required Ashwinder eggs … and the book warned that the resulting fire could be no hotter than the magical fire which had spawned the Ashwinder which had laid the eggs.

Harry had shouted ‘Eureka!’ right in the middle of the Ravenclaw common room, and been severely rebuked by a nearby prefect, who’d thought Mr Potter was trying to cast a spell. Nobody in the wizarding world knew or cared about some ancient Muggle named Archimedes, nor the ur-physicist’s realization that the water displaced from a bathtub would equal the volume of the object entering the bathtub …

Conservation laws. They’d been the critical insight in more Muggle discoveries than Harry could easily count. In Muggle technology you couldn’t raise a feather one metre off the ground without the power coming from somewhere. If you looked at molten lava spilling from a volcano and asked where the heat came from, a physicist would tell you about radioactive heavy metals in the centre of the Earth’s molten core. If you asked where the energy to power the radioactivity came from, the physicist would point to an era before the Earth had formed, and a primordial supernova in the early days of the galaxy which had baked atomic nuclei heavier than the natural limit, the supernova compressing protons and neutrons into a tight unstable package that yielded back some of the supernova’s energy when it split. A light bulb was fuelled by electricity, fuelled by a nuclear power plant, fuelled by a supernova … You could play the game all the way back to the Big Bang.

Magic did not appear to work like this, to put it mildly. Magic’s attitude toward laws like Conservation of Energy was somewhere between a giant extended middle finger, and a shrug of total indifference. Aguamenti created water out of nothingness, so far as anyone knew; there was no known lake whose water level went down each time. That was a simple fifth-year spell, not considered impressive by wizards, because creating a mere glass of water didn’t seem amazing to them. They didn’t have the wacky notion that mass ought to be conserved, or that creating a gram of mass was somehow equivalent to creating 90,000,000,000,000 joules of energy. There was an upper-year spell Harry had run across whose literal incantation was Arresto Momentum! and when Harry had asked if the momentum went anywhere else he’d just got a puzzled look. Harry had kept an increasingly desperate eye out for some kind of conservation principle in magic, anywhere whatsoever …

… and the whole time it had been right in front of him in every Potions class. Potions-Making didn’t create magic, it preserved magic, that was why every potion needed at least one magical ingredient. And by following instructions like stir four times anticlockwise and once clockwise – Harry had hypothesized – you were doing something like casting a small spell that reshaped the magic in the ingredients. (And unbound the physical form so that ingredients like porcupine quills dissolved smoothly into a drinkable liquid; Harry strongly suspected that a Muggle following exactly the same recipe would end up with nothing but a spiny mess.) That was what Potions-Making really was, the art of transforming existing magical essences. So you were a little tired after Potions class, but not much, because you weren’t empowering the potions yourself, you were just reshaping magic that was already there. And that was why a second-year witch could brew Polyjuice, or at least get close.

Harry had kept scanning through Moste Potente Potions, looking for something that might disprove his shiny new theory. After five minutes he’d flipped the older boy another Sickle (over his protests) and kept going.

The potion of giant strength required a Re’em to trample the mashed Dugbogs you stirred into the potion. It was odd, Harry had realized after a moment, because crushed Dugbogs weren’t strong themselves, they were just … very, very crushed after the Re’em got through with them.

Another recipe said to touch with forged bronze, i.e., grasp a Knut in pliers so you could skim the potion’s surface; and if you dropped the Knut all the way in, the book warned, the potion would instantly superheat and boil over the cauldron.

Harry had stared at the recipes and their warnings, forming a second and stranger hypothesis. Of course it wouldn’t be as simple as Potions-Making using magical potentials imbued in the ingredients, like Muggle cars fuelled by the combustion potential of gasoline. Magic would never be as sensible as that …

And then Harry had gone to Professor Flitwick – since he didn’t want to approach Professor Snape outside of class – and Harry had told Professor Flitwick that he wanted to invent a new potion, and he knew what the ingredients ought to be and what the potion should do, but he didn’t know how to deduce the required stirring pattern –

After Professor Flitwick had stopped screaming in horror and running in little circles, and Professor McGonagall had been called into the ensuing fierce interrogation to promise Harry that in this case it was both acceptable and important for him to reveal his underlying theory, it had developed that Harry had not made an original magical discovery, but rediscovered a law so ancient that nobody knew who had first formulated it:

A potion spends that which is invested in the creation of its ingredients.

The heat of goblin forges that had cast the bronze Knut, the Re’em’s strength that had crushed the Dugbogs, the magical fire that had spawned the Ashwinder: all these potencies could be recalled, unlocked, and restructured by the spell-like process of stirring the ingredients in exact patterns.

(From a Muggle standpoint it was just odd, a deranged version of thermodynamics invented by someone who thought life ought to be fair. From a Muggle standpoint, the heat expended in forging the Knut hadn’t gone into the bronze, the heat had left and dissipated into the environment, becoming permanently less available. Energy was conserved, could be neither created nor destroyed; entropy always increased. But wizards didn’t think that way: from their perspective, if you’d put some amount of work into making a Knut, it stood to reason that you could get exactly the same work back out. Harry had tried to explain why this sounded a bit odd if you’d been raised by Muggles, and Professor McGonagall had asked bemusedly why the Muggle perspective was any better than the wizarding one.)

The fundamental principle of Potions-Making had no name and no standard phrasing, since then you might be tempted to write it down.

And someone who wasn’t wise enough to figure out the principle themselves might read it.

And they would start having all sorts of bright ideas for inventing new Potions.

And then they would be turned into cat-girls.

It had been made very clear to Harry that he wasn’t going to be sharing this particular discovery with Neville, or Hermione either after the next armies’ battle. Harry had tried to say something about Hermione seeming really off lately and this being just the sort of thing that might cheer her up. Professor McGonagall had said flatly that he wasn’t even to think it, and Professor Flitwick had raised his little hands and made a gesture as of snapping a wand in half.

Although the two Professors had been kind enough to suggest that if Mr Potter thought he knew what the potion’s ingredients should be, he might be able to find an already-existing recipe that did the same thing; and Professor Flitwick had mentioned several volumes in the Hogwarts library that might be useful …

The vast parchment-like screen now showed only an aerial view of the forest, from which you could barely make out the camouflaged forms of three armies, split up into two groups each, converging to fight their three-way battle.

The benches of the Quidditch stadium were now rapidly filling up with the more easily bored sort of spectator who only wanted to be there for the final battle and skip out on all the boring points along the way. (If there was anything wrong with Professor Quirrell’s battles, it was widely agreed, it was that his spectacles didn’t last nearly as long as Quidditch matches, once they actually started. To this Professor Quirrell had replied only, Such is realism, and that had been that.)

Within the huge window – it was all one window now, observing from a great height – the vague collections of tiny camouflaged forms grew closer.

Closer.

Almost touching –

The vast white parchment window showed the first touch of battle between Sunshine and Chaos, a screaming mass of running children with smiley-faces upon their breasts, charging forward with Contego shields held high and others shouting ‘Somnium!’ –

Until one of their number shrieked ‘Prismatis!’ in a terrified voice and the entire charge came to a sudden halt before the sparkling wall of force that had appeared in front of them.

Tracey Davis had walked out from behind the trees.

‘That’s right,’ said Tracey, her voice low and grim as she levelled her wand on the barrier. ‘You should fear me. For I am Tracey Davis, the Darke Lady! That’s Darke Lady spelled D-A-R-K-E, with an E!’

(Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement, was sending an inquiring look at Mr and Mrs Davis, both of whom looked like they would have dearly loved to die on the spot.)

Behind the Prismatic Barrier, there was some kind of hushed argument taking place among the Sunshine Soldiers, one of whom in particular seemed to be getting scolded by several of the others.

Then, a moment later, Tracey flinched.

Susan Bones had come to the front of the Sunshine contingent.

(‘Goodness,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘What do you suppose your grand-niece has been learning at Hogwarts?’)

(‘I don’t know,’ Amelia Bones said calmly, ‘but I shall owl her a Chocolate Frog and instructions to learn more of it.’)

The Prismatic Barrier vanished.

The Sunshine Soldiers resumed their charge forward.

Tracey yelled, her voice high with strain, ‘Inflammare!’ and the Sunshine charge came to another sudden halt as a line of fire blazed up between them in the half-dry grass, extending to follow the path of Tracey’s wand as she pointed it; an instant later Susan Bones cried ‘Finite Incantatem!’ and the flames dimmed, brightened, dimmed in the contest of their wills, other soldiers raising their wards to aim at Tracey; and that was when Neville Longbottom plunged shrieking out of the sky.

One of the Dragon Warriors, Raymond Arnold, made a hand-sign, pointing forward and oblique left; and there was a sudden hushed hiss of whispers among the Dragon Army contingent as they all quietly reoriented themselves in the direction of the enemy. The Sunnies knew they were there, of course both armies knew; but somehow, in this moment, they had all become instinctively quiet.

The Dragons crept forward further, and then further, the dull camouflaged forms of the Sunnies beginning to appear among the distant trees, and still nobody spoke, nobody bellowed the call to charge.

Draco was now at the forefront of his soldiers, Vincent behind him and Padma only a shade further back; if the three of them could take the shock of Sunshine’s best, the rest of Dragon Army might stand a chance.

Then Draco saw one Sunnie staring at him from the distance, in the vanguard of her own army; staring at him with a look of fury –

Across the forest battleground, their eyes met.

Draco had only a fraction of a second to wonder, in the back of his mind, what Hermione Granger was so angry about, before the shout went up from both their armies; and they were all running forward to the charge.

The other Chaotics had appeared now from among the trees, some had dropped out of trees, and the battle was in full force now, everyone firing in every direction at anything that looked like an enemy. Plus a number of Sunnies crying ‘Luminos!’ at Neville Longbottom as the Chaos Hufflepuff twisted and rocketed up through the air on courses that could only be described as, indeed, ‘chaotic’ –

And it happened, the way it happened only one time out of twenty in mock aerial combat, that Neville Longbottom’s broomstick glowed bright red beneath his clenched hands.

It should’ve meant that Longbottom was out of the game.

Then, in the Hogwarts stands, among the watching crowds of students, a scream went up –

Combat realism. It was Professor Quirrell’s one master rule. You could get away with anything if it was realistic, and in real life, a soldier didn’t just vanish when their broomstick got hit by a curse.

Neville was falling toward the ground and screaming ‘Chaotic landing!’ and the Chaotics were wrenching their attention away from fights to cast the Hover Charm (and run at the same time so they wouldn’t be sitting ducks), almost everyone else stopping to gape –

And Neville Longbottom slammed into the leaf-laden forest ground, landing on one knee, one foot, and both hands, as though he were kneeling down to be knighted.

Everything stopped. Even Tracey and Susan paused in their duel.

In the stadium, all crowd noises vanished.

There was a universal silence composed of astonishment, concern, and sheer dumbstruck gaping awe, as everyone waited to see what would happen next.

And then Neville Longbottom slowly rose to his feet, and levelled his wand at the Sunshine Soldiers.

Though nobody on the battlefield heard it, a large segment of the stadium audience had begun chanting, in steadily rising notes each time the word was uttered, ‘DOOM DOOM DOOM DOOM DOOM’, because you just couldn’t see that and not think it required musical accompaniment.

‘The crowd is cheering your grandson,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the screen with a measuring look.

‘So they are,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘Some, if I hear correctly, are cheering, Our blood for Neville! Our souls for Neville!’

‘Quite,’ said Amelia, taking a sip from a teacup which had not been there moments earlier. ‘It shows the lad has leadership potential.’

‘These cheers,’ continued Augusta, her voice taking on an even more stunned quality, ‘seem to be coming from the Hufflepuff benches.’

‘It is the House of the loyal, my dear,’ said Amelia.

‘Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore! What in Merlin’s name has been happening in this school?’

Lucius Malfoy was watching the screens with an ironic smile, his fingers tapping at his armrest in no discernible pattern. ‘I do not know what is more frightening, the thought that he has some hidden plan behind all this, or the thought that he does not.’

‘Look!’ cried the Lord of Greengrass. The dapper young man had risen half out of his chair, pointing his finger at the screen. ‘There she goes!’

‘We’ll both take him at once,’ Daphne whispered. She knew that a few fear-filled minutes of real combat experience, a handful of times each week, might not be enough to match Neville’s regular duelling practise with Harry and Cedric Diggory over the same period. ‘He’s too much for one of us, but both of us together – I’ll use my Charm, you just try to stun him –’

Hannah, beside her, nodded, and then they both screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward, the Hover Charms of two supporting Sunshine Soldiers moving them faster and making them light on their feet, Daphne already crying ‘Tonare!’ even as Hannah kept a huge Contego shield moving in front of them, and with a brief extra lift they leapt over the heads of the front screen of soldiers and landed in front of Neville with their hair billowing high around them –

(Photographs were strictly prohibited at all Hogwarts games, but somehow this moment still ended up on the front page of the next day’s Quibbler.)

– and in the same instant, because fighting older bullies had burned away the slightest traces of hesitation, Hannah fired her first Sleep Hex at Neville (she’d started the incantation while she was still in the air) even as Daphne, concentrating more on speed than on force, slashed down with her Ancient Blade at where she thought Neville’s thighs would be after he dodged –

But Neville leapt up, not sideways, leapt up higher than he should’ve been able to go, so that her glowing sword cut only the air beneath his feet. Somehow Daphne realized what it meant, that Neville still had other Chaotics Hovering him, in time for her to raise her Blade up over her head, but Neville fell too fast and when his Blade smashed into hers it was like being hit by a Bludger. It knocked Daphne off her feet and sent her sprawling backward onto the grass, hitting the ground hard on her back. It might have been all over for her, then, if Neville hadn’t landed too hard himself and gone to his knees with a pained gasp. And then before Neville could bring his glowing Blade down, Hannah shouted ‘Somnium!’ and Neville lurched frantically backward – though of course no spell had actually come from Hannah’s wand, the Hufflepuff girl couldn’t really have fired again that fast – which gave Daphne a second to scramble to her feet and get both hands around her wand again –

‘Dear Merlin,’ said Lady Greengrass. Her voice seemed unsteady, the aristocratic poise well-punctured. ‘My daughter is fighting with the Charm of the Most Ancient Blade. In her first year. I never knew she possessed – such extraordinary talent –’

‘Excellent blood,’ Charles Nott said approvingly, causing Augusta to snort.

‘My good Lady,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding grave. ‘Do not wrong your daughter so. That is not mere talent which you see.’ His voice grew a little dryer. ‘Rather, it is what happens when children put their competitive efforts into a game which involves actual spell-casting.’

‘Expelliarmus!’ shouted Draco, trying not to let his voice crack as he simultaneously dodged the blazing red stunbolt that Hermione Granger had fired at him, his muscles twisting with the need to dodge in the wrong direction – she’d pointed to his left, and then with a mysterious twitch fired right –

Hermione dodged the fast-moving duelling hex, and cried with hardly another moment’s pause, ‘Steleus!’, a wide-angle Hex that Draco couldn’t avoid, but he managed to point his wand at his own face and cry ‘Quiescus!’ before the sudden urge to inhale could devolve into a sneezing fit that would’ve ended the battle.

Draco Malfoy was already half-exhausted from all the Locking Charms and Transfigurations earlier, but his confusion was beginning to give way to a sense of his own blood boiling, he didn’t know why Granger was attacking him so angrily all of a sudden, but if she wanted a fight he’d give her one –

(The Dragons and Sunnies weren’t stopping to watch the duel of their Generals, the Dragons were too disciplined to stop and watch and that meant the Sunnies had to go on fighting too; but the gaping audience in the Hogwarts Quidditch stands were being distracted even from Neville and Daphne’s spectacle, shifting their eyes to the duel of two Generals as Malfoy and Granger fired hex after hex and jinx after jinx at each other, casting more rapidly than any other student in their year could have managed, the Dragon General’s trained duelling dance matched by the Sunshine General’s frantic energy, the combat between them beginning to resemble an adult duel as the two most magically powerful first-years resorted to spells more exotic than the usual Sleep Hex.)

– although, Draco was beginning to realize, when he and Harry and Professor Quirrell had dismissed Miss Granger as having as much intent to kill as a bowl of wet grapes, they’d never seen her angry.

Daphne lashed out with her Ancient Blade, again not trying to hit hard but just moving the Blade as fast as possible, at the same time Hannah cried ‘Somnium!’ and Neville leapt back again, but it had been another bluff and Hannah was moving in to fire a real spell almost point-blank –

– and Neville Longbottom did exactly what – he would explain afterwards – Cedric Diggory had trained him to do if he was fighting Bellatrix Black, which was to spin around and kick Hannah really hard in the pit of her stomach.

The Hufflepuff girl made a sad little sound, a gasping cry of pain, as she was knocked off her feet by the hard shoe sinking into her abdomen with the force of Neville’s whole body behind it.

For an instant the battlefield stood still, everything halted except Hannah’s falling form.

Then Neville’s face turned to absolute dismay and he lowered his wand, the Chaotic Lieutenant starting instinctively toward his House-mate as he reached for her with his other hand –

Even as Hannah turned her fall into a roll and came out with her wand raised and shot him.

A fractional second later, Daphne, who hadn’t hesitated either, sank her Most Ancient Blade squarely into Neville’s back, causing the Chaotic Lieutenant’s muscles to jerk convulsively with the stunning magic discharging into him even as Hannah’s Sleep Hex took effect, and then the last scion of Longbottom was sprawled still on the ground with a look of total surprise frozen to his face.

‘Today Mr Longbottom has learned a valuable lesson about his feelings of pity and remorse,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘And chivalry,’ said Amelia, sipping her tea again.

‘Are you all right?’ whispered Daphne, as she stood protectively over where Hannah lay on the ground clutching her stomach. The girl didn’t give anything back in reply except more retching sounds that sounded like Hannah was trying not to throw up while trying not to cry.

Somehow, even though it might not have been good tactics – it would’ve been better if Hannah had been hexed outright, than for other soldiers to be tied up protecting her – a number of Sunnies seemed to be standing in front of Hannah with their wands clutched tightly, staring angrily at the Chaotics. Someone had thrown up a Prismatic barrier between the two groups, Daphne couldn’t see who.

And for some reason the Chaotics didn’t seem to be pressing the attack. Even Tracey had completely dropped the grim look on her face and was shifting her weight nervously from one foot to another, as though she was having trouble remembering which side she was on –

‘Hold!’ shouted a voice. ‘Hold battle!’

There wasn’t much battle going on anyway, but it held.

General Potter, looking every inch the Boy-Who-Lived, strode out from the trees with something large and camouflage-cloth-covered held under one arm.

‘Is Miss Abbott breathing all right?’ General Potter yelled.

Daphne didn’t look back. She didn’t trust that this wasn’t a trap – it was absolutely certain that if the Chaotics took the opportunity to attack, Professor Quirrell would not only rule it legal but also award them extra points afterwards. But Daphne could hear the answer well enough with her ears, it wasn’t like Hannah was trying to breathe quietly, and so she said, ‘Sort of.’

‘She should get out of here and to someone who can use healing Charms,’ Harry said. ‘Just in case that broke something.’

From behind Daphne, a small gasping voice said, ‘I – can – still – fight –’

‘Miss Abbott, don’t –’ Harry said, just as there was the sound from behind Daphne of someone collapsing back to the grass after trying and failing to get to her feet. Everyone winced, but Daphne didn’t turn her back on Harry.

‘Why haven’t the teachers stopped the battle?’ said Susan, her voice angry.

‘I expect it’s because Miss Abbott is in no danger of permanent damage and Professor Quirrell thinks we’re learning valuable lessons,’ Harry said in a hard voice. ‘Look, Miss Abbott, if you go, Tracey will also retire from the battle. You already outnumber us, so that’s a very good deal for your side. Please take it.’

‘Hannah, just go!’ said Daphne. ‘I mean, just say you’re out!’

When Daphne glanced back she saw that Hannah was shaking her head, still curled up in a ball on the grass.

‘Oh, screw this,’ said Harry. ‘Chaotics! The faster we stun them, the faster she’s out of here! We’re going to do this very quickly, even if we take casualties! End truce! Tunafish!’

Daphne’s political hindbrain had only an instant to admire how Harry’s few words had just made the Chaotics the good guys, and then in almost perfect unison, the Chaotics were plunging their hands into the pockets of their uniforms and drawing out green sunglasses in an unfamiliar style. Not like anything you would wear to the beach, more like goggles for advanced Potions –

Then Daphne realized what was about to happen and snapped up her other hand to shield her eyes, just as Harry ripped the cloth off the cauldron.

The fluid that spilled forth as Harry Potter threw the cauldron’s contents into the air was too bright to be seen, too brilliant to be imagined, incandescent like the Sun magnified a dozen times –

(which was exactly what it was)

(the sunlight which had been invested to create the acorns, the bright energy that had fuelled a tree rising up from the bare dirt)

(blazing a searing purple, the colour of the mixed blue and red wavelengths that chlorophyll absorbed)

(with almost none of the green wavelengths that chlorophyll reflected to create the green colour of leaves)

(which was the colour of the Chaos Legion’s sunglasses, made to pass through green wavelengths, blocking red and blue, reducing even the most incandescent purple glare to something bearable)

– the violet light blazed on and on, Daphne tried dropping her arm from her eyes but found that she couldn’t look directly at anything, even the second-hand purple glare was so bright she had to squint; and she had only time to cry one Finite Incantatem, which didn’t work, before a Sleep Hex took her.

What was left of the battle didn’t take very long after that.

‘Now!’ bellowed Blaise Zabini, formerly of Sunshine, now commanding a detachment of Chaos Legionnaires. ‘I mean, Tunafish!’ The Slytherin boy’s hand grasped the cloth shielding the cauldron from the triggering touch of daylight, already beginning to move it aside.

‘Now!’ bellowed Dean Thomas, formerly of Chaos, commanding a consignment of Dragon Warriors. ‘Do whatever they do!’

The Chaotics of Zabini’s detachment plunged their hands into their uniform pockets, and came forth bearing green sunglasses –

– an action almost perfectly mirrored by Dean and the Dragon Warriors, who drew forth green-coloured Potions goggles, and quickly drew the straps over their own heads, even as the Chaotics put on their sunglasses and the violet incandescence blasted forth.

(As General Malfoy had explained, if Mr Goyle reported that the Chaos Legion was wearing green-coloured Potions goggles, you didn’t have to know why to Transfigure some copies.)

‘That’s cheating!’ shrieked Blaise Zabini.

‘That’s technique!’ Dean yelled back. ‘Dragons, charge!’

(‘Pardon me,’ the Lady Greengrass said. ‘Could you stop laughing like that, Mr Quirrell? It’s unnerving.’)

‘Finite their goggles!’ shouted Blaise Zabini, as the two armies ran headlong toward each other through omnipresent eye-searing purple glare. ‘We can still win!’

‘You heard him!’ bellowed Dean. ‘Get their glasses!’

Blaise Zabini’s reply to this wasn’t anything articulate.

That battle went on a lot longer.

‘Stupefy!’ shrieked the Sunshine General.

Draco didn’t dodge, he didn’t counter, he didn’t have enough energy left for either, all he could do was whip his left hand into position and hope –

The red stunbolt dissipated again on Draco’s Colloportused glove, which he’d Transfigured and spell-locked to his hand the same as the rest of Dragon Army. It was all that was saving him now, that shield.

It should have been a time to counter-attack, but Draco could only catch his breath, as the two of them danced backward and forward beneath the trees in the never-ending movements of their duel. Across from him, General Granger was panting hard, the young girl’s face glistening with sweat like dew, her chestnut hair wetted into brown plaits. Her camouflage uniform was stained with damp spots, her shoulders visibly trembling with exhaustion, but her wand was still steel-steady where it stayed level on Draco through all their motion. Her eyes glaring, her cheeks flushed with rage.

So, little girl, why’re you pretending to fight like a grown-up today?

The taunt came to mind, but he didn’t really think he needed Granger any angrier; so instead Draco just said – though he could hear his own voice cracking – ‘Any reason you’re feeling mad at me, Granger?’

The girl was gasping for breath herself, her own voice wobbling as she spoke. ‘I know what you’re up to,’ said Hermione Granger, her voice rising. ‘I know what you and Snape are up to, Malfoy, and I know who’s behind it!’

‘Huh?’ Draco said without even thinking about it.

That only seemed to increase Granger’s fury, and her fingers whitened on the wand she held levelled on him.

And then Draco got it, and it boiled his own blood in his veins. Even she thought he was secretly plotting against her –

‘You too?’ Draco yelled. ‘I helped you, you bucktoothed bint! You, you, you,’ – stuttering past all the Dark curses that came to mind until he found something he could actually cast at her – ‘Densaugeo!’

But Granger flashed and whirled around the Tooth-Lengthening Hex, and then her own wand came around and levelled at almost point-blank range, even as Draco brought up his left hand like a shield, placing the magic-locked glove between himself and whatever she was about to fire, and the Sunshine General’s own voice rose to a shriek audible across the whole battleground –

‘Alohomora!’

Time should have paused.

But it didn’t.

Instead the padlock clicked and fell off the glove.

Just like that.

Just like that.

The screens showed it all very clearly, to the entire watching Hogwarts stadium.

And the bone-dead-silent hush that fell over every bench in every stand said that everyone understood quite clearly what it meant, that the scion of House Malfoy had just had his magic overcome by a Muggleborn.

Hermione Granger didn’t pause in her fight, gave no sign that she even knew what she’d done; instead her foot snapped out in a Muggle-style kick that knocked Draco’s wand cleanly out of his hand, his shocked mind and body moving just a little too slowly. Draco dove after his wand, scrabbling frantically on the ground, but from behind him a girl’s cracking voice said ‘Somnium!’ and Draco Malfoy fell and didn’t rise again.

There was another moment of frozen silence. The Sunshine General was wobbling on her feet, looking like she might faint.

Then the Dragon Warriors screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward to avenge their fallen commander.

Mr and Mrs Davis were shaking as they stood up from the comfortable chairs of the faculty Quidditch box; they couldn’t quite clutch each other while walking, but they held hands tightly, pretending hard to be invisible. If they’d been children young enough for accidental magic they probably would’ve spontaneously Disillusioned themselves.

The elderly Charles Nott said nothing as he stood from his chair. The scarred Lord Jugson said nothing, as he stood from his own chair.

Lucius Malfoy said nothing as he stood.

All three of them turned without pause and strode toward the stairwell of the elevated stands, moving in eerie unison like an Auror trio –

‘Lord Malfoy,’ the Defence Professor said in mild tones. That man was still seated in his own chair, looking upon his parchment-like screens, arms limp at his side, as though for some reason he didn’t feel like moving.

The white-haired man halted just before reaching the exit archway, and the elderly man and the scarred man halted as well, flanking him. Lord Malfoy’s head turned, too slightly to be any form of acknowledgement, but in the Defence Professor’s direction.

‘Your son performed exceptionally well today,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I must confess that I underestimated him. And he has earned his army’s loyalty, as you have witnessed.’ Still very mild, the Defence Professor’s voice. ‘Speaking as your son’s teacher, it is my opinion that he will not benefit if you interfere in his –’

Lord Malfoy and his compatriots vanished down the stairs.

‘A fine try, Quirinus,’ Dumbledore said quietly. The old wizard’s face showed small lines of worry; he hadn’t risen from his own seat either, staring at the parchment screens as though they were still active. ‘Do you think he will listen?’

The Defence Professor’s shoulders twitched in a slight shrug, the only movement they’d shown since the battle ended.

‘Well,’ said the Lady Greengrass, as she rose up and cracked her knuckles, stretching, her husband silent beside her. ‘I must say, that was quite … interesting …’

Amelia Bones had risen from her own cushioned seat without any fuss. ‘Interesting indeed,’ said Director Bones. ‘I do confess, I find myself disturbed by the skill with which those children were fighting one another.’

‘The skill?’ Lord Greengrass said. ‘Their spells didn’t seem all that impressive to me. Except for Daphne’s, of course.’

The old witch did not move her eyes from where she was gazing at the Defence Professor’s balding head. ‘The Stunning Hex is not a first-year spell, Lord Greengrass, but that is not the skill I had in mind. They supported each other with those simple spells, they reacted at speed to surprises …’ The Director of the DMLE paused, as though searching for words that a mere civilian could understand. ‘In the midst of battle,’ she said finally, ‘with spells flying in every direction … those children seemed quite at home.’

‘Indeed, Director Bones,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Some arts are best begun in youth.’

The old witch’s eyes narrowed. ‘You are readying them to become a military force, Professor. To what end?’

‘Now hold on!’ interjected Lord Greengrass. ‘There’s plenty of schools where they teach duelling in first year!’

‘Duelling?’ said the Defence Professor. From behind it wasn’t visible if the pale face was smiling. ‘That is nothing, Lord Greengrass, to what my students have learned. They have learned not to hesitate in the face of ambushes and greater foes. They have learned to adapt when combat conditions change and change again. They have learned to protect their allies, to protect more those who are more valuable, to abandon pieces which cannot be rescued. They have learned that to survive they must follow orders. Some have even learned a little creativity. Oh, no, Lord Greengrass, these wizards will not hide in their manors and wait to be protected, when the next threat comes. They will know that they know how to fight.’

Augusta Longbottom loudly clapped her hands together three times.

We won.

It was the first thing Draco heard when he woke up on the battlefield, Padma telling him how his soldiers had rallied after he fell. How, thanks to the Dragon General’s foresight, Mr Thomas had led his detachment to victory over Chaos. How General Potter had defeated the portion of the Sunshine Regiment that clashed with him. How Mr Thomas’s Dragon Warriors had rejoined the main body of soldiers bearing both their own goggles and the sunglasses of the defeated Chaotics. How, only moments later, General Potter’s remaining contingent had attacked both other armies with a potion that emitted searing purple light. But Dragon had held the numerical advantage over Sunshine and Chaos both, and enough sunglasses for their warriors; and so Padma had managed to lead her inherited army to victory.

From the light in Padma’s eyes and her arrogant smile that would have done proud to a Malfoy, she was expecting congratulations. Draco managed to grit out some form of praise from between his clenched teeth, and couldn’t have said afterwards what it was. The foreign-born witch, it appeared, hadn’t any idea what’d happened, or what it meant.

I lost.

The Dragons trudged back to Hogwarts beneath grey skies, cold droplets landing heavy on Draco’s skin, one by one. While he’d been stunned, it had begun, the long-promised rain finally beginning to fall. There was only one option left to Draco now. A forced move, as Mr Macnair, who’d taught Draco chess, would have termed it. Harry Potter probably wouldn’t like it, if he really was in love with Granger the way everyone said. But the forced move, as Mr Macnair had defined it, was one you needed to make if you wanted the game to continue at all.

It kept on playing in Draco’s mind, over and over again, even as he walked like an automaton through the massive portals of Hogwarts, sent away Vincent and Gregory with two sharp words, and became alone within his private bedroom, sitting on his bed, staring at the wall above his desk. Filling his mind like a Dementor had locked him into the memory.

The padlock on his glove clicking and falling away –

Draco knew, he knew what he’d done wrong. He’d been so tired after casting twenty-seven Locking Charms for all the other Dragon Warriors. Less than a minute wasn’t enough time to recover after each spell. And so he’d just cast Colloportus on his own padlocked glove, just cast the spell, not put in all his strength to bind it stronger than Harry Potter or Hermione Granger could undo.

But nobody was going to believe that, even if it was true. Even in Slytherin, nobody would believe that. It sounded like an excuse, and an excuse was all that anyone would hear.

Granger whirled and spun and screamed ‘Alohomora!’ –

Draco’s mind kept playing it over and over as the resentment built. He’d helped Granger – cooperated with her on banning traitors – held her hand as she’d dangled off the roof – stopped a riot from breaking out around her in the Great Hall – did she have any idea what he’d risked, what he’d probably already lost, what it meant for the heir of House Malfoy to do that for a mudblood –

And now there was only one move left, and the thing about a forced move was that you had to make it, even if it meant getting detention and losing House points. Professor Snape would know and understand, but there were limits (Father had warned him) to what the Potions Master would overlook.

Challenge Granger to a wizard’s duel, in open defiance of Hogwarts regulations. Attack her outright, if she tried to refuse. Defeat her one-on-one, in public, not with clever duelling technique, but by overpowering her magic. Beat her solidly, completely, crush her as utterly as the Dark Lord himself had crushed his enemies. Make it absolutely clear to everyone, so that nobody could possibly doubt, that Draco had just been exhausted from casting the spell so many times. Prove that the Malfoy blood was stronger than any mudblood’s –

Only it’s not, Harry Potter’s voice whispered inside Draco’s mind. It’s easy to forget what’s really true, Draco, once you start trying to win at politics. But in reality there’s only one thing that makes you a wizard, remember?

Draco knew, then, he knew the reason for the disquiet in the back of his mind, as he stared at the blank wall above his desk contemplating his forced move. It should’ve been simple – when you only had one move, the thing to do was make it – but –

Granger whirling, spinning, sweat-dampened hair flying around her, bolts flying from her wand as fast as his own, jinx and counter-jinx, glowing bats flying at his face, and through all of it the look of fury in Granger’s eyes –

There’d been a part of him admiring that, before it had all gone wrong, admiring Granger’s fury and power; a part of him that had exulted in the first real fight he’d ever been in, against …

… an equal opponent.

If he challenged Granger, and lost …

It ought not to be possible, Draco had got his wand two full years before anyone else in his Hogwarts class.

Only there was a reason why they usually didn’t bother giving wands to nine-year-olds. Age counted too, it wasn’t just how long you’d held a wand. Granger’s birthday had been only a few days into the year, when Harry had bought her that pouch. That meant she was twelve now, that she’d been twelve almost since the start of Hogwarts. And the truth was, Draco hadn’t been practising much outside of class, probably not nearly as much as Hermione Granger of Ravenclaw. Draco hadn’t thought he needed any more practise to stay ahead …

And Granger was exhausted too, whispered the Voice of Contrary Evidence inside him. Granger must have been exhausted from all those Stunning Hexes, and even in that state she’d been able to undo his Locking Charm.

And Draco could not afford to challenge Granger publicly, one-on-one with no excuses, and lose.

Draco knew what you were supposed to do in this sort of situation. You were supposed to cheat. But if anyone discovered Draco cheating, it would be disastrous, perfect blackmail material even if it never got out publicly, and any Slytherins watching would know that, they’d be looking …

And then, if you were watching, you would have seen Draco Malfoy get up from his bed, and go to his desk, and take out a sheet of the finest sheepskin parchment, and a pearl-carven inkwell, filled with greenish-silver ink that had been made with true silver and crushed emeralds. From the great trunk at his bed’s foot, the Slytherin drew forth a book bound also in silver and emeralds, entitled The Etiquette of the Houses of Britain. And with a new, clean quill, Draco Malfoy began to write, frequently looking to the book where it lay open as a reference. There was a grim smile on the boy’s face, making the young Malfoy look very much like his father, as he carefully drew each letter as though it were a separate artwork.

From Draco, son of Lucius son of Abraxis Lords of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, son also of Narcissa daughter of Druella Lady of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Black, scion and heir of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy:

To Hermione, the first Granger:

(That form might have been meant to sound polite, long ago when it had been invented; nowadays, after centuries of being used to address mudbloods, it carried a lovely tinge of refined venom.)

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for

Draco paused, carefully moving the quill aside so that it wouldn’t drip. He needed a pretext for this, at least if he wanted to impose the duel’s conditions. The challenged had the choice of terms unless they had insulted a Noble House. He needed to make it look like Granger had insulted him …

What was he thinking? Granger had insulted him.

Draco flipped the book to the page of standard formulae, and found one that seemed appropriate.

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for that I have thrice over helped you and offered you only my goodwill, and in return you falsely accused me of plotting against you,

Draco had to stop and take a breath, forcing down the seething anger; he was starting to genuinely feel the insult now, and he’d just written out the last phrase and underlined it without thinking, like it was an ordinary letter. After a moment’s reflection, he decided to let it stand; it might not be the exact formal phrasing but it had a raw, angry tone that seemed appropriate.

which insult you committed before the eyes of Britain.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by

‘The seventeenth ruling of the thirty-first Wizengamot,’ Draco said aloud without looking, a line delivered in many plays; he sat straighter as he said it, feeling every pulse of the noble blood in his veins.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by the 17th ruling of the 31st Wizengamot, to meet me in wizard’s duel with terms: That we each come alone and in silence, speaking to none before or after,

If the duel went poorly, Draco could just say nothing and leave it at that. And if he did defeat Granger, he would have learned experimentally that he could beat her again in a public challenge. It wasn’t cheating, but it was Science, which was almost as good.

contesting by magic solely, without death or lasting injury,

… where? Draco had been told about a room in Hogwarts that was good for duels, where everything valuable was already protected by wards, and there were no portraits to tattle on you … which one had it been again …

in the trophy room of the Castle of the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry,

And their second and public duel had better be soon, like tomorrow, it would take very little time for his reputation in Slytherin to go irretrievably to sludge. He needed to fight Granger for the first time tonight.

upon midnight’s stroke that shall end this very day.

Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy.

Draco signed the formal parchment, and then drew forth his ordinary and lesser parchment, and his regular ink, for his post scriptum:

If you don’t know how the rules work, Granger, here’s how it is. You insulted a Most Ancient House, and I’ve got the lawful right to challenge. And if you affront the conditions of the duel, like by having Flitwick show up at the trophy room, or even just telling anyone else, my father will take you and your false honor straight to the Wizengamot.

Draco Malfo

On the last letter his quill pressed down on the parchment so viciously that the nib snapped off, creating a streak of ink and a small rip in the parchment, which Draco decided also looked appropriate.

That night at dinnertime, Susan Bones came to Harry Potter and told him that she thought Draco Malfoy was going to carry out his plot against Hermione very soon. She was warning all the members of S.P.H.E.W., and she’d warned Professor Sprout, and she’d warned Professor Flitwick, and she was going to send a letter to her Aunt tonight, and now she was warning Harry Potter, too. Only they couldn’t quite talk about it with Padma – Susan said, looking very serious – because Padma was feeling torn between her loyalty to Hermione and her loyalty to her General.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, who was at this point feeling more frustrated with the entire situation than anything really productive, snapped at her that yes, he knew something had to be done.

After Susan Bones left, Harry looked over at the other end of the Ravenclaw table, where Hermione had sat down away from him or Padma or Anthony or any of her other friends.

But Hermione didn’t look like she was in a mood where somebody going over and bothering her would be taken very well.

Later, looking backward, Harry would think of how, in his SF and fantasy novels, people always made their big, important choices for big, important reasons. Hari Seldon had created his Foundation to rebuild the ashes of the Galactic Empire, not because he would look more important if he could be in charge of his own research group. Raistlin Majere had severed ties with his brother because he wanted to become a god, not because he was incompetent at personal relationships and unwilling to ask for advice on how to do better. Frodo Baggins had taken the Ring because he was a hero who wanted to save Middle-Earth, not because it would’ve been too awkward not to. If anyone ever wrote a true history of the world – not that anyone ever could or would – probably 97% of all the key moments of Fate would turn out to be constructed of lies and tissue paper and trivial little thoughts that somebody could’ve just as easily thought differently.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres looked at Hermione Granger, where she’d sat down at the other end of the table, and felt a sense of reluctance to bother her when she looked like she was already in a bad mood.

So then Harry thought that it probably made more sense to talk to Draco Malfoy first, just so that he could absolutely positively definitely assure Hermione that Draco really wasn’t plotting against her.

And later on after dinner, when Harry went down to the Slytherin basement and was told by Vincent that the boss ain’t to be disturbed … then Harry thought that maybe he should see if Hermione would talk to him right away. That he should just get started on unravelling the whole mess before it ravelled any further. Harry wondered if he might just be procrastinating, if his mind had just found a clever excuse to put off something unenjoyable-but-necessary.

He actually thought that.

And then Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres decided that he’d just talk to Draco Malfoy the next morning instead, after Sunday breakfast, and then talk to Hermione.

Human beings did that sort of thing all the time.

It was Sunday morning, on the 5th of April, 1992, and the simulated sky above the Great Hall of Hogwarts showed great torrents of rain pouring down in such density that the lightning flashes were diminished and scattered into small pulses of white light that sometimes transformed the House tables, paling their faces and making all the students appear briefly to be ghosts.

Harry sat at the Ravenclaw table, wearily eating a waffle, waiting for Draco to make an appearance so that he could get started on sorting this whole thing out. There was a Quibbler being passed around which had somehow ended up with Hannah and Daphne on the front page, but it hadn’t reached his place yet.

A few minutes later Harry finished eating his waffle, and then looked around again to see if Draco had arrived yet for breakfast at the Slytherin table.

It was odd.

Draco Malfoy was almost never late.

Since Harry was looking in the direction of the Slytherin table, he didn’t see Hermione Granger entering through the huge doors of the Great Hall. Thus he was rather startled when he turned back and discovered Hermione sitting down directly beside him at the Ravenclaw table, just as if she hadn’t not-done that for more than a week.

‘Hi, Harry,’ Hermione said, her voice sounding almost exactly normal. She started to put toast on her plate and a selection of healthy fruits and vegetables. ‘How are you?’

‘Within one standard deviation of my own peculiar little average,’ Harry automatically replied. ‘How are you doing? Did you sleep okay?’

There were dark bags under Hermione Granger’s eyes.

‘Why, yes, I’m fine,’ said Hermione Granger.

‘Um,’ Harry said. He took a slice of pie onto his plate (as his brain was occupied with other things, Harry’s hand simply took the tastiest thing within range, without evaluating complex concepts like whether he was ready to eat dessert). ‘Um, Hermione, I’m going to need to talk to you later today, is that okay?’

‘Sure,’ said Hermione. ‘Why wouldn’t it be?’

‘Because –’ Harry said. ‘I mean – you and I haven’t – for the last few days –’

Shut up, suggested an internal part of Harry that seemed to have been recently allocated for governing Hermione-related issues.

Hermione Granger didn’t look like she was paying much attention to him in any case. She just stared down at her plate, and then, after about ten seconds of awkward silence, began to eat her tomato slices, one after another, without pause.

Harry looked away from her and began to eat a slice of pie which, he discovered, had somehow materialized on his plate.

‘So!’ Hermione Granger suddenly said after she’d polished off most of her plate in silence. ‘Anything happening today?’

‘Um …’ Harry said. He looked around frantically, as though to find something-happening that he could use as conversational fodder.

And so Harry was one of the first to see it, and wordlessly point, although the sudden swell of whispers that swept through the Great Hall showed that a number of other people had seen it too.

The distinctive crimson tinge of the robes would have been recognizable anywhere, but it still took Harry’s brain a few moments to place the faces. An Asianish-looking man, solemn, and today looking rather grim. A man with a piercing gaze that swept over the room, his long black hair waving behind him in a ponytail. A man thin and pale and unshaven, with a face so blank that it was like stone. It took Harry a few moment to place the faces, and remember the names, from that long-ago day in January when the Dementor had come to Hogwarts: Komodo, Butnaru, Goryanof.

‘An Auror trio?’ Hermione said in a strange bright voice. ‘Why, I wonder what they’d be doing here.’

Dumbledore was in their company as well, looking as worried as Harry had ever seen him; and after a moment’s pause while the old wizard’s eyes scanned the Great Hall and the students whispering over their breakfasts, he pointed –

– straight at Harry.

‘Oh, now what,’ Harry said under his breath. His inward thoughts were a lot more panicked than that, as he wondered frantically if anyone had connected him to the Azkaban breakout somehow. He looked at the Head Table, trying to make the glance casual, and realized that Professor Quirrell was nowhere to be seen, this morning –

The Aurors swept toward him with swift strides, Auror Goryanof approaching from the other side of the Ravenclaw table as though to block any escape in that direction, Auror Komodo and Auror Butnaru approaching from Harry’s side, the Headmaster following straight on Komodo’s heels.

All conversation everywhere had ground to utter silence.

The Aurors reached Harry’s place at the table, surrounding him from three angles.

‘Yes?’ Harry said, as normally as he could. ‘What is it?’

‘Hermione Granger,’ Auror Komodo said in a toneless voice, ‘you are under arrest for the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.’

The words dropped into Harry’s consciousness and shattered his thoughts into a hundred shards of incredulity, the shock of adrenaline running into so much confusion that –

‘She –’ Harry said. ‘She – she wouldn’t – What?’

The Aurors weren’t paying any attention to him. Komodo spoke again, still in that colourless voice. ‘Mr Malfoy has regained consciousness in St. Mungo’s and named you, Hermione Granger, as his assaulter. He has repeated these accusations under two drops of Veritaserum. The Blood-Cooling Charm you cast upon Mr Malfoy would have killed him if he had not been found and treated, and it must be presumed known to you that this was a fatal curse. I therefore arrest you upon the serious charge of attempted murder and you will be taken into Ministry custody to be interrogated under three drops of Veritaserum –’

‘Are you mad?’ the words burst out of Harry’s mouth, as he shoved himself up from the Ravenclaw table, an instant before Auror Butnaru’s hand clamped down hard upon his shoulder. Harry ignored it. ‘That’s Hermione Granger you’re trying to arrest, the nicest girl in Ravenclaw, she helps Hufflepuffs with their homework, she’d die before she tried to kill anyone –’

Hermione Granger’s face had crumpled. ‘I did it,’ she whispered in a tiny voice. ‘It was me.’

Another huge rock fell on Harry’s thoughts and crushed their fragile order, bursting fragments of comprehension into dust.

Dumbledore’s face seemed to have aged decades over the course of seconds. ‘Why, Miss Granger?’ Dumbledore said, his own voice barely above a whisper. ‘Why would you do such a thing?’

‘I’m,’ Hermione said, ‘I’m, I’m – sorry – I don’t know why I –’ She seemed to collapse in on herself, her voice was formed of nothing but sobs, and the only words that could be made out were, ‘I thought – killed him – sorry –’

And Harry should have said something, should have done something, should have jumped up out of his seat and stunned all three Aurors and then gone on to some incredibly clever next move, but the twice-shattered fragments of his thought processes could yield no output. Butnaru’s hand pushed Harry gently but firmly back into his seat and Harry found himself stuck there like he’d been glued, he tried to grab his wand for a Finite and it wouldn’t come out of his pocket, the three Aurors and Dumbledore escorted Hermione out of the Great Hall amid a rising storm of outcries and the doors began to swing shut behind them – nothing made sense, it was surreal beyond all reckoning, like he’d been transported into an alternate universe, and then Harry’s mind flashed back to another day of confusion and in a moment of desperate inspiration he finally realized what the Weasley twins had done to Rita Skeeter, and his voice rose in a scream, ‘Hermione you didn’t do it you’ve been false-memory-charmed!’

But the doors had already shut.

Minerva couldn’t possibly have stood still, she paced back and forth through the Headmaster’s office, the back of her mind half-expecting Severus or Harry to tell her to shut up and sit down, but neither the Potions Master or the Boy-Who-Lived seemed much concerned with her, both of their gazes focused on Albus Dumbledore where he had emerged from the Floo. There were sounds in the background that nobody heard. Severus seemed as passionless as ever, sitting in a small cushioned chair beside the Headmaster’s desk. The old wizard stood terrible and upright by the still-burning fireplace, robed in black like a starless night, radiating power and dismay. All her own thoughts were of utter confusion and horror. Harry Potter sat on a wooden stool with his fingers gripping the seat, and his eyes were fury and freezing ice.

At 6:33am, Quirinus Quirrell had Flooed St. Mungo’s from his office for immediate pickup of Draco Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had found Mr Malfoy in the trophy room of Hogwarts, on the verge of death from the continuing effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm slowly lowering his body temperature. Professor Quirrell had immediately dispelled the Charm, cast stabilizing spells on Mr Malfoy, and levitated him to his office to Floo him to St. Mungo’s for further treatment. After this, Professor Quirrell had informed the Headmaster, stating the facts briefly before vanishing through the Floo; the Aurors, notified by St. Mungo’s, had demanded his presence for questioning.

The clear intent of the Blood-Cooling Charm had been to kill Draco Malfoy so slowly that the wards of Hogwarts, set to detect sudden injury, would not trigger. Under interrogation, Professor Quirrell had told the Aurors that he had cast several tracking Charms upon Mr Malfoy’s person in January, shortly after Mr Malfoy’s return to Hogwarts from the Christmas holidays. Professor Quirrell had cast tracking Charms because he had learned of a person with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had refused to identify this person. The tracking Charms which Professor Quirrell had cast were triggered by Mr Malfoy’s health falling below an absolute level, rather than by sudden changes, and had therefore alerted Professor Quirrell before Mr Malfoy had died.

Two drops of Veritaserum, sufficient to prevent Mr Malfoy from withholding any meliorating or moderating information in his statements, had shown that Mr Malfoy had – legally under the laws of Noble Houses, illegally under the regulations of Hogwarts – challenged Hermione Granger to a duel. Mr Malfoy had won the duel but had then, as he left, been attacked from behind by Miss Granger with a Stunning Hex. After this Mr Malfoy knew nothing.

Three drops of Veritaserum, requiring her to volunteer all relevant information, had caused Hermione Granger to confess that she had stunned Draco Malfoy from behind, and then, in a fit of anger, cast the Blood-Cooling Charm on him, with the deliberate intention of killing him slowly enough to evade identification from the Hogwarts wards, whose workings she had read about in Hogwarts: A History. She had been horrified at herself upon awakening the next morning, but had not told anyone of what she’d done, believing Draco Malfoy to be already dead – as he certainly would have been after seven hours, had his body’s own magic not been resisting the effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm.

‘Her trial,’ said Albus Dumbledore, ‘is set for tomorrow at noon.’

‘What?’ the word burst out of Harry Potter. The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t rise from his chair, but Minerva saw his fingers whiten where they gripped the wooden seat beneath him. ‘That’s insane! You can’t do a police investigation in one day –’

The Potions Master raised his voice. ‘This is not Muggle Britain, Mr Potter!’ Severus’s face was as expressionless as ever, but the bite in his voice was sharp. ‘The Aurors have an accusation under Veritaserum and a confession under Veritaserum. So far as they are concerned, the investigation is done.’

‘Not quite,’ said Dumbledore, just as Harry seemed ready to explode. ‘I have insisted to Amelia that this matter be given the utmost scrutiny. Unfortunately, as the ill-fated duel was at midnight –’

‘Supposed duel,’ Harry said sharply.

‘As the supposed duel was at midnight – yes, you’re quite right, Harry – it is beyond the range of any Time-Turner –’

‘Also supposedly,’ the Boy-Who-Lived said coldly. ‘And rather suspiciously, since the alleged murder suspect doesn’t know about Time-Turners. I hope that an invisible Auror was immediately sent back in time as far as possible to observe –’

Dumbledore inclined his head. ‘I went myself, Harry, the moment I heard. But by the time I reached the trophy room, Mr Malfoy was already unconscious and Miss Granger had gone –’

‘No,’ said Harry Potter. ‘You reached the trophy room and saw Draco unconscious. That is all you observed, Headmaster. You did not observe Hermione there, or watch her leave. Let us distinguish observation from inference.’ The boy’s head turned to look at her. ‘Imperius, Obliviation, False Memory Charm, Legilimency. Professor McGonagall, am I leaving out any mind-affecting spell that could have made Hermione do this or make her believe she’d done it?’

‘The Confundus Charm,’ she said. And the Dark Arts had never been her study, but she knew – ‘And certain Dark rituals. But none of those could be performed in Hogwarts without alarm.’

The boy nodded, his eyes still directly addressing her. ‘Which of those spells can be detected? Which would the Aurors try to detect?’

‘The Confundus Charm would wear off in a few hours,’ she said, after a moment to gather her thoughts. ‘Miss Granger would remember the Imperius. Obliviation cannot be detected by any known means, but only a Professor could have cast that spell upon a student without alarm from the Hogwarts wards. Legilimency – can only be detected by another Legilimens, I think –’

‘I requested that Miss Granger be examined by the court Legilimens,’ said Dumbledore. ‘The examination showed –’

‘Do we trust him?’ said Harry.

‘Her,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Sophie McJorgenson, whom I remember as an honest student of Ravenclaw, and she is bound by the Unbreakable Vow to tell the truth of what she sees –’

‘Could someone else be Polyjuiced as her?’ Harry Potter interrupted again. ‘What did you observe, Headmaster?’

Albus said heavily, ‘A person who looked like Madam McJorgenson told us that a single Legilimens had lightly touched Miss Granger’s mind some months ago. That is from January, Harry, when I communicated with Miss Granger about the matter of a certain Dementor. That was expected; but what I did not expect was the rest of what Sophie found.’ The old wizard turned to gaze into the Floo fire, letting the orange flames reflect on his face. ‘As you say, Harry, a False Memory Charm is one possibility; they are, when cast perfectly, indistinguishable from true memory –’

‘That doesn’t surprise me,’ Harry interrupted. ‘Studies show that human memories are more or less rewritten every time we remember them –’

‘Harry,’ Minerva said softly, and the boy’s mouth clamped shut.

The old wizard continued. ‘– but a False Memory Charm of such quality requires as much time to create as a true memory. Creating a detailed memory of ten minutes would be ten minutes’ work. And according to the court Legilimens,’ Albus’s face now seemed more tired and lined than before, ‘Miss Granger has been obsessing over Mr Malfoy since the day that Severus … yelled at her. She has been thinking of how Mr Malfoy might be in league with Professor Snape, how he might be planning to harm her and harm Harry – imagining it for hours every day – it would be impossible to create false memories for so much time.’

‘The appearance of insanity …’ Severus murmured softly, as though he were speaking to himself. ‘Could it be natural? No, it is too disastrous to be pure accident; too convenient for someone, I have no doubt. A Muggle drug, perhaps? But that would not be enough – Miss Granger’s madness would have to be guided –’

‘Ah!’ Harry said suddenly. ‘I get it now. The first False Memory Charm was cast on Hermione after Professor Snape yelled at her, and showed, say, Draco and Professor Snape plotting to kill her. Then last night that False Memory was removed by Obliviation, leaving behind the memories of her obsessing about Draco for no apparent reason, at the same time she and Draco were given false memories of the duel.’

Minerva blinked in astonishment. It would have been a thousand years before she thought of that possibility.

The Potions Master was frowning thoughtfully, eyes intent. ‘The reaction to a False Memory Charm is hard to predict in advance, Mr Potter, without Legilimency. The subjects do not always act as expected, when they first remember the false memories. It would have been a risky ploy. But I suppose that is one way Professor Quirrell could have done it.’

‘Professor Quirrell?’ said Harry. ‘What motive does he have to –’

The Potions Master said dryly, ‘The Defence Professor is always a suspect, Mr Potter. You will notice a trend, given time.’

Albus raised up a hand, a silencing gesture, and their heads all turned to look at him. ‘But in this case there is another suspect,’ Albus said quietly. ‘Voldemort.’

That deadliest of unspeakable words seemed to echo around the room, cancelling all the heat from the orange flames of the fireplace.

‘I do not know,’ the old wizard said slowly, ‘I know all too little of the methods of Voldemort’s immortality. He searched out those books before I did, I think. All I could find were ancient tales, scattered across too many volumes for him to remove. But to find truth among many stories is also a wizard’s mastery, and this I have endeavoured to do. There is a human sacrifice, a murder, of that I am certain; committed in coldest blood, the victim dying in horror. And old, old tales of wizards possessed, doing mad deeds, claiming the names of Dark Lords thought defeated; and there is usually a device, of that Dark Lord, which they wield …’ Albus looked at Harry, the ancient eyes searching the younger. ‘I think, Harry – though you will call it only inference – that the act of murder splits the soul. That by ritual of blackest horror, the torn fragment of soul is chained to this world. To a material thing of this world. Which must be, or which then becomes, a device of power.’

Horcrux. The terrible name echoed in Minerva’s mind, though it seemed that – for what reason she did not know – Albus would not speak that word in front of Harry.

‘And therefore,’ the old wizard finished quietly, ‘the remainder of the soul is bound to its chained part, lingering here when its body is destroyed. A sad and painful existence, I think it would be; less than spirit, less than the meanest ghost …’ The old wizard’s eyes were locked on Harry, who gazed back with his eyes narrowed. ‘It would take time for that mutilated soul to regain a mockery of life. That is why we have had our ten-year reprieve, I believe; why Voldemort did not return at once. But in time … that revenant would become capable of rising again.’ The old wizard spoke with grim precision. ‘It is clear, from the stories, that the Dark Lords who return by possessing another’s form, wield lesser magics than they once knew. I do not think Voldemort would be satisfied with that. He would take some other avenue to life. But Voldemort was more Slytherin than Salazar, grasping at every opportunity. He would use his pitiful state, use his power of possession, if he had reason. If he could benefit by another’s … inexplicable fury.’ Albus’s voice had fallen to almost a whisper. ‘That is what I suspect happened to Miss Granger.’

Minerva’s throat was very dry. ‘He’s here,’ she gasped. ‘Here, in Hogwarts –’

And stopped, because the reason Voldemort had come to Hogwarts –

The old wizard glanced at her only briefly, and said, still in that whisper, ‘I am sorry, Minerva, you were right.’

Harry’s voice was edged. ‘Right about what?’

‘Voldemort’s strongest avenue to life,’ Dumbledore said heavily. ‘The most desirable road for him, by which he would rise greater and more terrible than ever before. It is guarded here, within this castle –’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said politely. ‘Are you stupid?’

‘Harry,’ she said, but there was no force in her voice.

‘I mean, maybe you haven’t noticed this, Headmaster Dumbledore, but this castle is full of children –’

‘I had no choice!’ bellowed Dumbledore. The blue eyes were blazing now, beneath the half-moon spectacles. ‘I do not own it, that thing which Voldemort desires. It belongs to another, and is held here by his consent! I asked if it could be kept in the Department of Mysteries. But he would not permit that – he said it must be within the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of the Founders’ protection –’ Dumbledore passed his hand across his forehead. ‘No,’ the old wizard said in a quieter voice. ‘I cannot pass this blame to him. He is right. There is too much power in that thing, too much that men desire. I agreed that the trap should be laid behind the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of my own power.’ The old wizard bowed his head. ‘I knew Voldemort would worm his way here somehow, and planned to trap him. I did not think – I did not dream – that he would tarry in an enemy fortress one minute longer than he must.’

‘But,’ said Severus in some puzzlement, ‘what would the Dark Lord possibly gain by killing Lucius’s only heir?’

‘Point of order,’ Harry Potter said, a hard edge in his voice. ‘The motives of whoever’s behind this are not the primary issue. Our top priority at this point is that an innocent Hogwarts student is in trouble!’

The green eyes locked with the blue, as Albus Dumbledore gazed back at the Boy-Who-Lived –

‘Quite right, Mr Potter,’ Minerva said, she hadn’t even thought about it, the words just seemed to pop out of her lips. ‘Albus, who is watching over Miss Granger now?’

‘Professor Flitwick has gone to her,’ the Headmaster said.

‘She needs a lawyer,’ Harry said. ‘Anyone who just blurts out “I did it” to the police –’

‘Unfortunately,’ Minerva said, her tone taking on some of Professor Dumbledore’s sternness without thinking, ‘I doubt an attorney will be any use to Miss Granger at this point, Mr Potter. She is to face the judgement of the Wizengamot, and they would be exceedingly unlikely to free her on a technicality.’

Harry was looking at her with an utterly incredulous expression, as though suggesting that Hermione Granger didn’t need an attorney was akin to suggesting that she be set on fire.

‘She is correct, Mr Potter,’ Severus said quietly. ‘Few court processes in this country involve solicitors.’

Harry lifted his glasses and rubbed his eyes, briefly. ‘Fine. How do we get Hermione off the hook, exactly? I suppose it’s too much to hope that with all the lawyers gone, the judges understand the concept of “common sense” and “prior probability” well enough to realize that twelve-year-old girls basically never commit cold-blooded murders?’

‘It is the Wizengamot that she faces,’ said Severus. ‘The oldest Noble Houses, and certain other wizards of influence.’ Severus’s face twisted in something approaching his customary sarcasm. ‘As for them showing common sense – you might as well expect them to make you a bacon sandwich, Potter.’

Harry nodded, his mouth set. ‘Exactly what sort of penalty is Hermione facing? Snapped wand and expulsion –’

‘No,’ Severus said. ‘Nothing that light. Are you wilfully misunderstanding, Potter? She is facing the Wizengamot. There is no set penalty. There is only the vote.’

Harry Potter murmured, ‘The rule of law, in complex times, has proved itself deficient; we much prefer the rule of men, it’s vastly more efficient … There’s no constraining legal rules at all, then?’

Light glinted off the old wizard’s half-moon glasses; he spoke carefully, and not without anger. ‘Legally, Harry, we are dealing with a blood debt from Hermione Granger to the House of Malfoy. The Lord of Malfoy proposes a repayment of that debt, and then the Wizengamot votes on his proposal. That is all.’

‘But …’ Harry said slowly. ‘Lucius was Sorted into Slytherin, he’s got to realize that Hermione was just a pawn. Not the one he should actually be angry at. Right?’

‘No, Harry Potter,’ Albus Dumbledore said heavily. ‘That is how you wish Lucius Malfoy would think. Lucius Malfoy himself … will not share your desire that he think that way.’

Harry gazed at the Headmaster, his eyes growing colder, at the same time that Minerva herself had to clamp down harder on her own emotions, stop her pacing and try to breathe. She’d been trying not to think about it, trying to turn her thoughts away from it, but she knew. She’d known since the instant she’d heard. She could see it in Albus’s eyes –

‘Is she facing capital punishment?’ Harry said quietly, and chills went all the way down Minerva’s spine at the undertones of that voice.

‘No!’ Albus said. ‘No, not the Kiss, not Azkaban, not for a first-year in Hogwarts. Our country is not so lost, not yet.’

‘But Lucius Malfoy,’ Severus said tonelessly, ‘certainly will not be satisfied with only snapping her wand.’

‘All right,’ Harry said commandingly. ‘As I see it, we’ve got two essential lines of attack. Line one, find the real culprit. Line two, other leverage over Lucius. Professor Quirrell saved Draco’s life, does that create a blood debt from House Malfoy to him that he could redeem to cancel Hermione’s?’

Minerva blinked in astonishment again.

‘No,’ Dumbledore said. The old wizard shook his head. ‘It was a clever thought – but no, Harry, I’m afraid not. There is an exception when the Wizengamot suspects that the circumstances of a life-debt may have been created deliberately. And the Defence Professor is hardly above suspicion. Thus Lucius would argue.’

Harry nodded once, face set. ‘Headmaster, I know I said I wouldn’t – but under the circumstances – that time Draco cast that torture hex on me, is that debt enough –’

‘No,’ the old wizard said (even as she blurted ‘What?’ and Severus lifted an eyebrow). ‘It would not have been enough, and now it is no debt at all. You are an Occlumens and cannot testify under Veritaserum. Draco Malfoy could be Obliviated of his own memory before he could testify –’ Albus hesitated. ‘Harry … whatever you have done with Draco, you must assume that Lucius Malfoy will soon know of it.’

Harry’s head sank into his hands. ‘He’ll give Draco Veritaserum.’

‘Yes,’ Albus said quietly.

The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t say anything, as he sat with his head in his hands.

The Potions Master looked genuinely shocked. ‘Draco really was trying to help Miss Granger,’ Severus said. ‘You – Potter, you actually –’

‘Turned him?’ Harry said from between his hands. ‘I was about three-quarters done. Taught him the Patronus Charm and everything. I don’t know what will happen now, though.’

‘Voldemort has struck a grave blow against us, this day,’ Albus said. The sound of old wizard’s voice was like the look of the boy with his head in his hands. ‘He has taken two of our pieces, with one … No. I should have seen it earlier. He has taken two of Harry’s pieces with one move. Voldemort has begun his game again, not against myself, but against Harry. Voldemort knows the prophecy, he knows who his last foe shall be. He is not waiting to face Hermione Granger and Draco Malfoy at Harry’s side when they are grown. He is striking at them now.’

‘Maybe it’s You-Know-Who and maybe it isn’t,’ Harry said, his voice sounding a little unsteady. ‘Let’s not narrow down the hypothesis space prematurely.’ Harry took a breath and lowered his hands. ‘The other thing we can try is to nail the real culprit before the trial – or at least find solid evidence that someone else did it.’

‘Mr Potter,’ said Minerva, ‘Professor Quirrell told the Aurors that he knew of someone with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Do you know who he was talking about?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, after a hesitation. ‘But I think I shall conduct that part of my investigation with the Defence Professor – just as I would not have Professor Quirrell in the room while we were discussing how to investigate him.’

‘He suspects me?’ Severus said, then gave a short laugh. ‘Why, of course he does.’

‘My own plan,’ said Harry, ‘is to go and look at the trophy room where the supposed duel took place and see if I can discover anything anomalous. If you can tell the investigating Aurors to let me through –’

‘What investigating Aurors?’ Severus said tonelessly.

Harry Potter took a deep breath, slowly let it out, and then spoke again. ‘In mystery books it usually takes longer than one day to solve a crime, but twenty-four hours is – no, thirty hours is eighteen hundred minutes. And I can think of at least one other important place to look for clues – though it’ll have to be someone who can get into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm. Back when Hermione was fighting bullies, she was finding notes under her pillow each morning, telling her where to go –’

‘Albus …’ ground out Minerva.

‘I did not send them,’ said the old wizard. His white eyebrows had lifted in surprise. ‘I knew nothing of this. You think she was being played, Harry?’

‘It’s a possibility,’ Harry said. ‘More so, because there’s a part of this puzzle that you don’t know about yet.’ Harry’s voice lowered, grew more intense. ‘Headmaster, you already know that I got my father’s invisibility cloak from someone who left a note under my pillow, saying it was an early Christmas present. I think we have to assume that’s the same person who left notes for Hermione –’

‘Harry,’ the old wizard said, and hesitated momentarily. ‘Returning your father’s cloak to you, does not seem to me like the act of a villain –’

‘Listen,’ Harry Potter said urgently. ‘The part you don’t know is that after Bellatrix Black escaped from Azkaban, I found another note under my pillow, signed “Santa Claus”, saying that they’d heard you were shutting me up inside Hogwarts, and that they were giving me an escape route to the Salem Witches’ Institute in America. That note came with a deck of cards, in which the King of Hearts was supposedly a portkey –’

‘Mr Potter!’ cried Professor McGonagall, she hadn’t even thought before she spoke. ‘That could well be a kidnapping attempt! You should have told – ’

‘Yes, Professor, I did the sensible thing,’ the boy said levelly. ‘As adapted to the circumstances, I did the sensible thing. I told Professor Quirrell. And according to Professor Quirrell, that portkey goes to somewhere in London – it’s definitely not strong enough to be an international portkey. Now it’s possible that the person who sent the note is honest, and that the point in London is just a way station.’ The boy reached into his robes and took out a deck of cards, along with a folded paper note. ‘I will trust you not to go in guns blazing – I mean wands blazing – just in case the sender is an ally of mine, if not yours. But if this is a trap, I say we spring it now. And whoever it is, take them alive so we can exhibit them before the Wizengamot, I cannot overemphasize that part.’

Severus rose from his chair, his eyes now intent, and moved toward Harry. ‘I’ll need a hair of yours for Polyjuice, Mr Potter –’

‘Let us not be hasty!’ said Albus. ‘We have not yet examined the notes sent to Miss Granger; there may be no resemblance after all. Severus, would you enter her dorm and see if you can find those?’

Harry Potter’s eyebrows had raised, even as he stood to offer the Potions Master better access to his unruly hair. ‘You think two different people are running around Hogwarts leaving notes beneath pillows?’

Severus gave a brief sardonic laugh, as his hand moved forward and plucked a hair, which soon was being carefully wrapped in silk. ‘Quite possibly. If I have learned anything in my tenure as Head of Slytherin, I have learned what ridiculous messes arise when there is more than one plotter and more than one plan. But Headmaster – I think Mr Potter is correct that I should follow this portkey and see where it leads.’

Albus hesitated, and then nodded reluctantly. ‘I will speak to you before you go, then.’

Even as Harry Potter left the room for his own investigations, Severus spun on his heel and strode swiftly toward the jar of Floo powder, his cloak rising behind him with his speed. ‘I’ll get some raw Polyjuice, add the hair, and go. Headmaster, will you stand by to –’

‘Albus,’ Minerva said, surprised at how steady her own voice was, ‘did you leave those notes under Mr Potter’s pillow?’

Severus’s hand halted an instant before casting Floo powder into the fire.

Dumbledore nodded to her, though the accompanying smile seemed a bit hollow. ‘You know me far too well, my dear.’

‘And I suppose the portkey goes to a friendly home where Mr Potter would be kept safe and sound until you arrived to pick him up and return him to Hogwarts?’ Her voice tight – it was sensible, she could not deny it was sensible, but somehow it seemed a little cruel.

‘It would depend on the circumstances,’ the old wizard said quietly. ‘If Harry had gone so far – I might have let him make good his escape, for a time. Better to know where he was going, and ensure it was somewhere safe, with friends –’

‘And to think,’ said Professor McGonagall, ‘that I had thought to reprimand Mr Potter for not telling us about this important matter! Upbraid him for not having the sense to trust us!’ Her voice had risen in volume. ‘I shall skip that lecture, I suppose!’

Severus was gazing at the Headmaster with narrowed eyes. ‘And the notes to Miss Granger –’

‘The Defence Professor, very likely,’ the old wizard said. ‘Still – that is only a guess.’

‘I shall go and look for them,’ Severus said. ‘And then, I suppose, start looking for You-Know-Who.’ A frown crossed the Potions Master’s face. ‘A task which I haven’t the faintest idea of where to start. Do you know of any magics to find a soul, Headmaster?’

The Divination classroom was lit by the dim red light of a hundred small fires where burned a hundred kinds of incense, so that if you were to ask for one word describing what the room looked like, the answer would be smoke. (Assuming you bothered to look at anything, when your nose was threatening to overload and die.) If your gaze could pierce those dank mists, you would see a tiny, cluttered room in which forty stuffed armchairs, most of them unused, were crammed around a small open space in the centre of the room, where a circular trapdoor waited on your escape.

‘The grim!’ Professor Trelawney said in a quavering voice, as she peered into George Weasley’s teacup. ‘The grim! It is a sign of death! One whom you know, George – someone you know is to die! And soon – yes, it shall be quite soon, I think – unless of course it is later –’

It would have been a good deal scarier, thought Fred and George, if she hadn’t said the same thing to every single other student in their Divination class. They were hardly even thinking about it at this point; all their thoughts were on today’s disaster –

The trapdoor in the floor flew open with a bang that caused Professor Trelawney to shriek and spill George’s tea all over his robes, and then an instant later Dumbledore was whooshing up out of the floor with a bird of fire upon his shoulder.

‘Fred!’ the old wizard said commandingly. His robes were the black of a moonless night, his eyes hard like blue diamonds. ‘George! With me, now!’

There was an collective gasp and by the time Fred and George were climbing down the ladder after the Headmaster, the entire class was already speculating what role they’d played in the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.

The trapdoor had hardly slammed shut above them before all nearby sounds muted and the old wizard spun on them and held out a hand and commanded, ‘Give me the map!’

‘M-map?’ said Fred or George in total shock. They’d never even suspected that Dumbledore suspected. ‘Why, w-we don’t know what you’re –’

‘Hermione Granger is in trouble,’ said the old wizard.

‘The Map is in our dorm,’ George or Fred said immediately. ‘Just give us a few minutes to get it and we’ll –’

The wizard’s arms swept them up as if they were hugging-pillows, there was a piercing cry and a flash of fire and then the three of them were in the third-year Gryffindor boys’ dorm.

A few moments later, Fred and George were handing over the Map to the Headmaster, wincing only slightly at the sacrilege of giving their precious piece of the Hogwarts security system to the person who actually owned it, and the old wizard was frowning at the apparent blankness.

‘You’ve got to say,’ they explained, ‘I solemnly swear that I am up to no good –’

‘I decline to lie,’ said the old wizard. He held the Map high and bellowed, ‘Hear me, Hogwarts! Deligitor prodi!’ An instant later the Headmaster was wearing the Sorting Hat, which looked scarily right upon his head, as though Dumbledore had always been waiting for a patchwork pointed hat to complete his existence.

(Fred and George immediately memorized this phrase, just in case it would work for somebody besides the Headmaster, and began trying to think of pranks that would involve the Sorting Hat.)

The old wizard wasted not a moment before sweeping the Sorting Hat off his head and turning it upside-down – it was hard to tell with the Hat upside-down, but it looked a bit cross at the treatment – and then plunged in his hand and drew out a crystal rod. With this instrument he began tracing rune-like patterns on the Map, muttering strange incantations that sounded not quite like Latin and echoed in their ears in an unusually creepy fashion. In the midst of tracing one rune he looked up at both of them, fixing them with a sharp glare. ‘I will return this to you later, sons of Weasley. Go back to class.’

‘Yes, Headmaster,’ they said, and hesitated. ‘Ah – about Hermione Granger, is she really going to be bound to serve Draco Malfoy forever as his –’

‘Go,’ said the old wizard.

They went.

When he was alone in the room, the old wizard looked down at the map, which had now written upon itself a fine line drawing of the Gryffindor dorms in which they stood, the small handwritten Albus P.W.B. Dumbledore the only name left therein.

The old wizard smoothed the map, bent over it, and whispered, ‘Find Tom Riddle.’

The interrogation room at the Department of Magical Law Enforcement was usually lit by a small orange light, so that the Auror interrogating you would be leaning toward your uncomfortable metal chair with most of their face in shadow, preventing you from reading their expression, even as they read yours.

As soon as Mr Quirrell had entered the room, the small orange light had dimmed and begun flickering like a candle about to be blown out by the wind. The room was now lit by a sourceless ice-coloured glow which illuminated all of Mr Quirrell’s pale skin like alabaster, except, somehow, his eyes, which stayed in darkness.

The Auror on duty outside had surreptitiously tried to dispel this effect four times without the slightest success, despite the fact that Mr Quirrell had politely surrendered his wand upon being detained for interrogation, and had shown no sign of speaking any incantations nor exerting any other power.

‘Quirinus … Quirrell,’ drawled the man now sitting across from where the Defence Professor had waited courteously. The interrogator had tawny hair that swept back like a lion’s mane, with yellowish eyes set into the sternly lined face of a man late in his tenth decade. The man was, at this moment, leafing through a large folder of parchments that he had taken from a black and very solid-looking briefcase after he had limped into the room and sat down, seeming not to look at the face of the man he was interrogating. He had not introduced himself.

After some further leafing through parchments, carried out in silence, the Auror spoke again. ‘Born the 26th of September, 1955, to Quondia Quirrell, of an acknowledged tryst with Lirinus Lumblung …’ intoned the Auror. ‘Sorted into Ravenclaw … O.W.L.s quite good … N.E.W.T.s in Charms, Transfiguration … an Outstanding in Muggle Studies, impressive … Ancient Runes, and ah yes, Defence. An Outstanding in that as well. Went on to become quite the tourist, visiting all sorts of places. Portkey visas for Transylvania, the Forbidden Empire, the City of Endless Night … my my, Texas.’ The man looked up from the portfolio, eyes narrowed. ‘What were you doing there, Mr Quirrell?’

‘Sightseeing, mostly in the Muggle areas,’ the Defence Professor said easily. ‘As you say, I am quite the tourist.’

The man listened to this with a frown, then looked back down, then up again. ‘I also see that you visited Fuyuki City in 1983.’

The Defence Professor lifted an eyebrow in mild puzzlement. ‘What of it?’

‘What did you do in Fuyuki City?’ The question snapped out razor-sharp.

The Defence Professor frowned slightly. ‘Nothing of any account. I visited some better-known sights, some less-known sights, and aside from that, kept to myself.’

‘Really?’ the Auror said softly. ‘I find that reply rather interesting.’

‘How so?’ said the Defence Professor.

‘Because there was no visa listed for Fuyuki City.’ The man slammed the folder shut. ‘You’re not Quirinus Quirrell. Who the hell are you?’

The Potions Master walked quietly into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm, the first-year dorm, a festive place where bronze and blue competed to be the colour of stuffed animals, scarves and dresses, small bits of inexpensive jewellery, and posters of famous people. Hermione Granger’s bed was easy to identify; it was the one that had been attacked by a book monster.

Nobody else seemed to be around, at that time of day, and a number of spells verified this.

The Potions Master searched under Hermione Granger’s pillow, and beneath her bed, and then began going through her trunk, sorting through mentionable and unmentionable items without change of expression, and finally succeeded in drawing forth a set of papers describing places and times where bullies would be found, all of the papers signed only with an elaborate S.

A brief burst of fire later, the papers were gone, and the Potions Master left to report the failure of his mission.

The Defence Professor was sitting calmly with his hands still folded in his lap. ‘If you consult Headmaster Dumbledore,’ said the Defence Professor, ‘you will find that he is well aware of this matter, and that I agreed to teach his Defence class on the explicit condition that no inquiry be made into my –’

In a lightning motion, the interrogator whipped out his wand and spat ‘Polyfluis Reverso!’ at the same time that the Defence Professor sneezed, which somehow caused the mirror-silvered ray to disrupt in a shower of white sparks.

‘Pardon me,’ the Defence Professor said politely.

The smile that the Auror gave had absolutely no mirth in it. ‘So where’s the real Quirinus Quirrell, eh? Under an Imperius in the bottom of a trunk somewhere, while you take a hair now and then for your illegal Polyjuice?’

‘You are making highly questionable assumptions,’ the Defence Professor said with an edged voice. ‘What makes you think I did not steal his body outright using incredibly Dark magic?’

This was followed by a certain pause.

‘I suggest,’ the Auror said, ‘that you take this seriously, Mr Whoever-You-Are.’

‘I’m sorry,’ said the Defence Professor, leaning back in his chair, ‘but I see little reason to humble myself on this particular occasion. What are you going to do, kill me?’

‘I don’t appreciate your humour,’ the Auror said softly.

‘How unfortunate for you, Rufus Scrimgeour,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘You have my deepest sympathy.’ He tilted his head, seeming to study the interrogator; and even within the shadow of the ice-light, the eyes glinted.

Padma stared down at her plate.

‘Hermione wouldn’t just do that!’ yelled Mandy Brocklehurst, who was practically in tears, in fact she was in tears, her voice would have been loud enough to silence the Great Hall if it hadn’t been for all the other students also screaming at each other. ‘I – I bet Malfoy tried to – to do things to her –’

‘Our General would never do that!’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled even louder than Mandy.

‘Of course he would!’ shouted Anthony Goldstein. ‘Malfoy’s the son of a Death Eater!’

Padma stared down at her plate.

Draco was the General of her army.

Hermione was the founder of S.P.H.E.W.

Draco had trusted her to be his second-in-command.

Hermione was her fellow Ravenclaw.

Both of them were her friends, maybe the two best friends she had.

Padma stared down at her plate. She was glad the Sorting Hat hadn’t offered her Hufflepuff. If she’d been Sorted into Hufflepuff it would probably have been much more painful, trying to decide where her divided loyalties lay …

She blinked and realized that her vision had blurred again, and raised a trembling hand to wipe once more at her eyes.

Morag MacDougal snorted so loudly it was audible even amid the pandemonium of lunch, and said in a loud voice, ‘I bet Granger cheated in her battle yesterday, I bet that’s why Malfoy challenged her –’

‘All of you Shut up!’ roared Harry Potter, as he hit the table with his fists so hard that plates rattled all the way along it.

At any other time that would have earned him a Professorial reprimand; this time it just got a few nearby students to look.

‘I’d wanted to eat lunch,’ Harry Potter said, ‘and then get back to investigating, so I wasn’t going to talk. But you’re all being silly, and when the truth comes out you’re going to regret what you said about innocent people. Draco didn’t do anything, Hermione didn’t do anything, they were both False-Memory-Charmed!’ Harry Potter’s voice had been rising on the last words. ‘How is that not BLOODY OBVIOUS?’

‘You think we’ll believe that?’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled right back at him. ‘That’s what everyone says! “I didn’t do it, it was all just a False Memory Charm!” You think we’re stupid?’

And Morag nodded right along with him, with a condescending look.

The look that came over Harry Potter’s face then made Padma flinch.

‘I see,’ Harry Potter said; it wasn’t a shout, so Padma had to strain to hear it. ‘Professor Quirrell isn’t here to explain to me how stupid people are, but I bet this time I can get it on my own. People do something dumb and get caught and are given Veritaserum. Not romantic master criminals, because they wouldn’t get caught, they would have learned Occlumency. Sad, pathetic, incompetent criminals get caught, and confess under Veritaserum, and they’re desperate to stay out of Azkaban so they say they were False-Memory-Charmed. Right? So your brain, by sheer Pavlovian association, links the idea of False Memory Charms to pathetic criminals with unbelievable excuses. You don’t have to consider the specific details, your brain just pattern-matches the hypothesis into a bucket of things you don’t believe, and you’re done. Just like my father thought that magical hypotheses could never be believed, because he’d heard so many stupid people talking about magic. Believing a hypothesis that involves False Memory Charms is low-status.’

‘What are you blithering about?’ said Morag, looking down her nose at the Boy-Who-Lived.

‘You think we’d believe anything you say?’ yelled a slightly older-looking Ravenclaw witch who Padma didn’t recognize. ‘When you turned Granger Dark?’

‘And I’m not going to complain,’ Harry Potter said in an eerily calm voice, ‘about wizards not having any logic and believing the craziest things. Because I said that to Professor Quirrell once, and he just gave me this look and said that if I wasn’t blinded by my upbringing I could think of a hundred more ridiculous things that lots of Muggles believe. What you’re all doing is very human and very normal and doesn’t make you unusually bad people, so I’m not going to complain.’ The Boy-Who-Lived rose up from his bench. ‘I’ll see you all later.’

And Harry Potter walked away from them, walked away from all of them.

‘You’re not thinking he’s right, are you?’ said Su Li from beside her, in a tone which made it clear what she thought.

‘I –’ said Padma. Her words seemed to be caught in her throat, her thoughts seemed to be caught in her head. ‘I – I mean – I –’

If you think hard enough you can do the impossible.

(It had always been an article of faith with Harry. There’d been a time when he’d acknowledged the laws of physics as ultimate limitations, and now he suspected there were no true limits at all.)

If you think fast enough you can sometimes do the impossible quickly …

… sometimes.

Only sometimes.

Not always.

Not reliably.

The Boy-Who-Lived stared around the trophy room, surrounded by awards and cups and plates and shields and statues and medals kept behind thousands, perhaps tens of thousands, of crystal glass displays. For as many centuries as Hogwarts had existed, this room had been accumulating details. A week, a month, maybe even a year, wouldn’t have sufficed to take the examine option on every item in the room. With Professor Flitwick gone, Harry had asked Professor Vector if there was any way to detect damage to the wards around the crystal cases, verify the residue that a real duel should have left behind. Harry had raced through the Hogwarts library looking for spells to tell the difference between old fingerprints and new fingerprints, or to detect lingering exhalations in a room. And all those attempts at playing detective had failed.

There were no clues, none that he was smart enough to find.

Professor Snape had said that the portkey led to an empty house in London, with no sign of anyone or anything else.

Professor Snape hadn’t found any notes in Hermione’s dorm.

Headmaster Dumbledore had said that Voldemort’s spirit was probably hiding out in the Chamber of Secrets where the Hogwarts security system couldn’t find him. Harry had sneaked into the Slytherin dungeons under the Cloak of Invisibility and spent the rest of the afternoon looking through all the obvious places, but he hadn’t found anything snaky that answered back when spoken to. The entrance to the Chamber of Secrets, it seemed, hadn’t been meant to be found in a day.

Harry had talked to all of Hermione’s friends that would still talk to him, and none of them had remembered Hermione saying anything specific about why she’d believed that Draco was plotting against her.

Professor Quirrell hadn’t come back from the Ministry as of dinnertime. The older students seemed to think that this year’s Defence Professor would probably end up being blamed for the incident, and fired for teaching Hogwarts students to be too violent. They’d talked about the Defence Professor as though he were already gone.

Harry had used up all six hours from his Time-Turner, and there were still no clues, and he had to go to sleep now if he wanted to be functional at Hermione’s trial the next day.

The Boy-Who-Destroyed-A-Dementor was standing in the middle of the Hogwarts trophy room, his wand dropped at his feet.

He was crying.

Sometimes you call your brain and it doesn’t answer.

The trial of Hermione Granger started on schedule the next day.

We won.

It was the first thing Draco heard when he woke up on the battlefield, Padma telling him how his soldiers had rallied after he fell. How, thanks to the Dragon General’s foresight, Mr Thomas had led his detachment to victory over Chaos. How General Potter had defeated the portion of the Sunshine Regiment that clashed with him. How Mr Thomas’s Dragon Warriors had rejoined the main body of soldiers bearing both their own goggles and the sunglasses of the defeated Chaotics. How, only moments later, General Potter’s remaining contingent had attacked both other armies with a potion that emitted searing purple light. But Dragon had held the numerical advantage over Sunshine and Chaos both, and enough sunglasses for their warriors; and so Padma had managed to lead her inherited army to victory.

From the light in Padma’s eyes and her arrogant smile that would have done proud to a Malfoy, she was expecting congratulations. Draco managed to grit out some form of praise from between his clenched teeth, and couldn’t have said afterwards what it was. The foreign-born witch, it appeared, hadn’t any idea what’d happened, or what it meant.

I lost.

The Dragons trudged back to Hogwarts beneath grey skies, cold droplets landing heavy on Draco’s skin, one by one. While he’d been stunned, it had begun, the long-promised rain finally beginning to fall. There was only one option left to Draco now. A forced move, as Mr Macnair, who’d taught Draco chess, would have termed it. Harry Potter probably wouldn’t like it, if he really was in love with Granger the way everyone said. But the forced move, as Mr Macnair had defined it, was one you needed to make if you wanted the game to continue at all.

It kept on playing in Draco’s mind, over and over again, even as he walked like an automaton through the massive portals of Hogwarts, sent away Vincent and Gregory with two sharp words, and became alone within his private bedroom, sitting on his bed, staring at the wall above his desk. Filling his mind like a Dementor had locked him into the memory.

The padlock on his glove clicking and falling away –

Draco knew, he knew what he’d done wrong. He’d been so tired after casting twenty-seven Locking Charms for all the other Dragon Warriors. Less than a minute wasn’t enough time to recover after each spell. And so he’d just cast Colloportus on his own padlocked glove, just cast the spell, not put in all his strength to bind it stronger than Harry Potter or Hermione Granger could undo.

But nobody was going to believe that, even if it was true. Even in Slytherin, nobody would believe that. It sounded like an excuse, and an excuse was all that anyone would hear.

Granger whirled and spun and screamed ‘Alohomora!’ –

Draco’s mind kept playing it over and over as the resentment built. He’d helped Granger – cooperated with her on banning traitors – held her hand as she’d dangled off the roof – stopped a riot from breaking out around her in the Great Hall – did she have any idea what he’d risked, what he’d probably already lost, what it meant for the heir of House Malfoy to do that for a mudblood –

And now there was only one move left, and the thing about a forced move was that you had to make it, even if it meant getting detention and losing House points. Professor Snape would know and understand, but there were limits (Father had warned him) to what the Potions Master would overlook.

Challenge Granger to a wizard’s duel, in open defiance of Hogwarts regulations. Attack her outright, if she tried to refuse. Defeat her one-on-one, in public, not with clever duelling technique, but by overpowering her magic. Beat her solidly, completely, crush her as utterly as the Dark Lord himself had crushed his enemies. Make it absolutely clear to everyone, so that nobody could possibly doubt, that Draco had just been exhausted from casting the spell so many times. Prove that the Malfoy blood was stronger than any mudblood’s –

Only it’s not, Harry Potter’s voice whispered inside Draco’s mind. It’s easy to forget what’s really true, Draco, once you start trying to win at politics. But in reality there’s only one thing that makes you a wizard, remember?

Draco knew, then, he knew the reason for the disquiet in the back of his mind, as he stared at the blank wall above his desk contemplating his forced move. It should’ve been simple – when you only had one move, the thing to do was make it – but –

Granger whirling, spinning, sweat-dampened hair flying around her, bolts flying from her wand as fast as his own, jinx and counter-jinx, glowing bats flying at his face, and through all of it the look of fury in Granger’s eyes –

There’d been a part of him admiring that, before it had all gone wrong, admiring Granger’s fury and power; a part of him that had exulted in the first real fight he’d ever been in, against …

… an equal opponent.

If he challenged Granger, and lost …

It ought not to be possible, Draco had got his wand two full years before anyone else in his Hogwarts class.

Only there was a reason why they usually didn’t bother giving wands to nine-year-olds. Age counted too, it wasn’t just how long you’d held a wand. Granger’s birthday had been only a few days into the year, when Harry had bought her that pouch. That meant she was twelve now, that she’d been twelve almost since the start of Hogwarts. And the truth was, Draco hadn’t been practising much outside of class, probably not nearly as much as Hermione Granger of Ravenclaw. Draco hadn’t thought he needed any more practise to stay ahead …

And Granger was exhausted too, whispered the Voice of Contrary Evidence inside him. Granger must have been exhausted from all those Stunning Hexes, and even in that state she’d been able to undo his Locking Charm.

And Draco could not afford to challenge Granger publicly, one-on-one with no excuses, and lose.

Draco knew what you were supposed to do in this sort of situation. You were supposed to cheat. But if anyone discovered Draco cheating, it would be disastrous, perfect blackmail material even if it never got out publicly, and any Slytherins watching would know that, they’d be looking …

And then, if you were watching, you would have seen Draco Malfoy get up from his bed, and go to his desk, and take out a sheet of the finest sheepskin parchment, and a pearl-carven inkwell, filled with greenish-silver ink that had been made with true silver and crushed emeralds. From the great trunk at his bed’s foot, the Slytherin drew forth a book bound also in silver and emeralds, entitled The Etiquette of the Houses of Britain. And with a new, clean quill, Draco Malfoy began to write, frequently looking to the book where it lay open as a reference. There was a grim smile on the boy’s face, making the young Malfoy look very much like his father, as he carefully drew each letter as though it were a separate artwork.

From Draco, son of Lucius son of Abraxis Lords of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, son also of Narcissa daughter of Druella Lady of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Black, scion and heir of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy:

To Hermione, the first Granger:

(That form might have been meant to sound polite, long ago when it had been invented; nowadays, after centuries of being used to address mudbloods, it carried a lovely tinge of refined venom.)

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for

Draco paused, carefully moving the quill aside so that it wouldn’t drip. He needed a pretext for this, at least if he wanted to impose the duel’s conditions. The challenged had the choice of terms unless they had insulted a Noble House. He needed to make it look like Granger had insulted him …

What was he thinking? Granger had insulted him.

Draco flipped the book to the page of standard formulae, and found one that seemed appropriate.

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for that I have thrice over helped you and offered you only my goodwill, and in return you falsely accused me of plotting against you,

Draco had to stop and take a breath, forcing down the seething anger; he was starting to genuinely feel the insult now, and he’d just written out the last phrase and underlined it without thinking, like it was an ordinary letter. After a moment’s reflection, he decided to let it stand; it might not be the exact formal phrasing but it had a raw, angry tone that seemed appropriate.

which insult you committed before the eyes of Britain.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by

‘The seventeenth ruling of the thirty-first Wizengamot,’ Draco said aloud without looking, a line delivered in many plays; he sat straighter as he said it, feeling every pulse of the noble blood in his veins.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by the 17th ruling of the 31st Wizengamot, to meet me in wizard’s duel with terms: That we each come alone and in silence, speaking to none before or after,

If the duel went poorly, Draco could just say nothing and leave it at that. And if he did defeat Granger, he would have learned experimentally that he could beat her again in a public challenge. It wasn’t cheating, but it was Science, which was almost as good.

contesting by magic solely, without death or lasting injury,

… where? Draco had been told about a room in Hogwarts that was good for duels, where everything valuable was already protected by wards, and there were no portraits to tattle on you … which one had it been again …

in the trophy room of the Castle of the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry,

And their second and public duel had better be soon, like tomorrow, it would take very little time for his reputation in Slytherin to go irretrievably to sludge. He needed to fight Granger for the first time tonight.

upon midnight’s stroke that shall end this very day.

Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy.

Draco signed the formal parchment, and then drew forth his ordinary and lesser parchment, and his regular ink, for his post scriptum:

If you don’t know how the rules work, Granger, here’s how it is. You insulted a Most Ancient House, and I’ve got the lawful right to challenge. And if you affront the conditions of the duel, like by having Flitwick show up at the trophy room, or even just telling anyone else, my father will take you and your false honor straight to the Wizengamot.

Draco Malfo

On the last letter his quill pressed down on the parchment so viciously that the nib snapped off, creating a streak of ink and a small rip in the parchment, which Draco decided also looked appropriate.

That night at dinnertime, Susan Bones came to Harry Potter and told him that she thought Draco Malfoy was going to carry out his plot against Hermione very soon. She was warning all the members of S.P.H.E.W., and she’d warned Professor Sprout, and she’d warned Professor Flitwick, and she was going to send a letter to her Aunt tonight, and now she was warning Harry Potter, too. Only they couldn’t quite talk about it with Padma – Susan said, looking very serious – because Padma was feeling torn between her loyalty to Hermione and her loyalty to her General.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, who was at this point feeling more frustrated with the entire situation than anything really productive, snapped at her that yes, he knew something had to be done.

After Susan Bones left, Harry looked over at the other end of the Ravenclaw table, where Hermione had sat down away from him or Padma or Anthony or any of her other friends.

But Hermione didn’t look like she was in a mood where somebody going over and bothering her would be taken very well.

Later, looking backward, Harry would think of how, in his SF and fantasy novels, people always made their big, important choices for big, important reasons. Hari Seldon had created his Foundation to rebuild the ashes of the Galactic Empire, not because he would look more important if he could be in charge of his own research group. Raistlin Majere had severed ties with his brother because he wanted to become a god, not because he was incompetent at personal relationships and unwilling to ask for advice on how to do better. Frodo Baggins had taken the Ring because he was a hero who wanted to save Middle-Earth, not because it would’ve been too awkward not to. If anyone ever wrote a true history of the world – not that anyone ever could or would – probably 97% of all the key moments of Fate would turn out to be constructed of lies and tissue paper and trivial little thoughts that somebody could’ve just as easily thought differently.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres looked at Hermione Granger, where she’d sat down at the other end of the table, and felt a sense of reluctance to bother her when she looked like she was already in a bad mood.

So then Harry thought that it probably made more sense to talk to Draco Malfoy first, just so that he could absolutely positively definitely assure Hermione that Draco really wasn’t plotting against her.

And later on after dinner, when Harry went down to the Slytherin basement and was told by Vincent that the boss ain’t to be disturbed … then Harry thought that maybe he should see if Hermione would talk to him right away. That he should just get started on unravelling the whole mess before it ravelled any further. Harry wondered if he might just be procrastinating, if his mind had just found a clever excuse to put off something unenjoyable-but-necessary.

He actually thought that.

And then Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres decided that he’d just talk to Draco Malfoy the next morning instead, after Sunday breakfast, and then talk to Hermione.

Human beings did that sort of thing all the time.

It was Sunday morning, on the 5th of April, 1992, and the simulated sky above the Great Hall of Hogwarts showed great torrents of rain pouring down in such density that the lightning flashes were diminished and scattered into small pulses of white light that sometimes transformed the House tables, paling their faces and making all the students appear briefly to be ghosts.

Harry sat at the Ravenclaw table, wearily eating a waffle, waiting for Draco to make an appearance so that he could get started on sorting this whole thing out. There was a Quibbler being passed around which had somehow ended up with Hannah and Daphne on the front page, but it hadn’t reached his place yet.

A few minutes later Harry finished eating his waffle, and then looked around again to see if Draco had arrived yet for breakfast at the Slytherin table.

It was odd.

Draco Malfoy was almost never late.

Since Harry was looking in the direction of the Slytherin table, he didn’t see Hermione Granger entering through the huge doors of the Great Hall. Thus he was rather startled when he turned back and discovered Hermione sitting down directly beside him at the Ravenclaw table, just as if she hadn’t not-done that for more than a week.

‘Hi, Harry,’ Hermione said, her voice sounding almost exactly normal. She started to put toast on her plate and a selection of healthy fruits and vegetables. ‘How are you?’

‘Within one standard deviation of my own peculiar little average,’ Harry automatically replied. ‘How are you doing? Did you sleep okay?’

There were dark bags under Hermione Granger’s eyes.

‘Why, yes, I’m fine,’ said Hermione Granger.

‘Um,’ Harry said. He took a slice of pie onto his plate (as his brain was occupied with other things, Harry’s hand simply took the tastiest thing within range, without evaluating complex concepts like whether he was ready to eat dessert). ‘Um, Hermione, I’m going to need to talk to you later today, is that okay?’

‘Sure,’ said Hermione. ‘Why wouldn’t it be?’

‘Because –’ Harry said. ‘I mean – you and I haven’t – for the last few days –’

Shut up, suggested an internal part of Harry that seemed to have been recently allocated for governing Hermione-related issues.

Hermione Granger didn’t look like she was paying much attention to him in any case. She just stared down at her plate, and then, after about ten seconds of awkward silence, began to eat her tomato slices, one after another, without pause.

Harry looked away from her and began to eat a slice of pie which, he discovered, had somehow materialized on his plate.

‘So!’ Hermione Granger suddenly said after she’d polished off most of her plate in silence. ‘Anything happening today?’

‘Um …’ Harry said. He looked around frantically, as though to find something-happening that he could use as conversational fodder.

And so Harry was one of the first to see it, and wordlessly point, although the sudden swell of whispers that swept through the Great Hall showed that a number of other people had seen it too.

The distinctive crimson tinge of the robes would have been recognizable anywhere, but it still took Harry’s brain a few moments to place the faces. An Asianish-looking man, solemn, and today looking rather grim. A man with a piercing gaze that swept over the room, his long black hair waving behind him in a ponytail. A man thin and pale and unshaven, with a face so blank that it was like stone. It took Harry a few moment to place the faces, and remember the names, from that long-ago day in January when the Dementor had come to Hogwarts: Komodo, Butnaru, Goryanof.

‘An Auror trio?’ Hermione said in a strange bright voice. ‘Why, I wonder what they’d be doing here.’

Dumbledore was in their company as well, looking as worried as Harry had ever seen him; and after a moment’s pause while the old wizard’s eyes scanned the Great Hall and the students whispering over their breakfasts, he pointed –

– straight at Harry.

‘Oh, now what,’ Harry said under his breath. His inward thoughts were a lot more panicked than that, as he wondered frantically if anyone had connected him to the Azkaban breakout somehow. He looked at the Head Table, trying to make the glance casual, and realized that Professor Quirrell was nowhere to be seen, this morning –

The Aurors swept toward him with swift strides, Auror Goryanof approaching from the other side of the Ravenclaw table as though to block any escape in that direction, Auror Komodo and Auror Butnaru approaching from Harry’s side, the Headmaster following straight on Komodo’s heels.

All conversation everywhere had ground to utter silence.

The Aurors reached Harry’s place at the table, surrounding him from three angles.

‘Yes?’ Harry said, as normally as he could. ‘What is it?’

‘Hermione Granger,’ Auror Komodo said in a toneless voice, ‘you are under arrest for the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.’

The words dropped into Harry’s consciousness and shattered his thoughts into a hundred shards of incredulity, the shock of adrenaline running into so much confusion that –

‘She –’ Harry said. ‘She – she wouldn’t – What?’

The Aurors weren’t paying any attention to him. Komodo spoke again, still in that colourless voice. ‘Mr Malfoy has regained consciousness in St. Mungo’s and named you, Hermione Granger, as his assaulter. He has repeated these accusations under two drops of Veritaserum. The Blood-Cooling Charm you cast upon Mr Malfoy would have killed him if he had not been found and treated, and it must be presumed known to you that this was a fatal curse. I therefore arrest you upon the serious charge of attempted murder and you will be taken into Ministry custody to be interrogated under three drops of Veritaserum –’

‘Are you mad?’ the words burst out of Harry’s mouth, as he shoved himself up from the Ravenclaw table, an instant before Auror Butnaru’s hand clamped down hard upon his shoulder. Harry ignored it. ‘That’s Hermione Granger you’re trying to arrest, the nicest girl in Ravenclaw, she helps Hufflepuffs with their homework, she’d die before she tried to kill anyone –’

Hermione Granger’s face had crumpled. ‘I did it,’ she whispered in a tiny voice. ‘It was me.’

Another huge rock fell on Harry’s thoughts and crushed their fragile order, bursting fragments of comprehension into dust.

Dumbledore’s face seemed to have aged decades over the course of seconds. ‘Why, Miss Granger?’ Dumbledore said, his own voice barely above a whisper. ‘Why would you do such a thing?’

‘I’m,’ Hermione said, ‘I’m, I’m – sorry – I don’t know why I –’ She seemed to collapse in on herself, her voice was formed of nothing but sobs, and the only words that could be made out were, ‘I thought – killed him – sorry –’

And Harry should have said something, should have done something, should have jumped up out of his seat and stunned all three Aurors and then gone on to some incredibly clever next move, but the twice-shattered fragments of his thought processes could yield no output. Butnaru’s hand pushed Harry gently but firmly back into his seat and Harry found himself stuck there like he’d been glued, he tried to grab his wand for a Finite and it wouldn’t come out of his pocket, the three Aurors and Dumbledore escorted Hermione out of the Great Hall amid a rising storm of outcries and the doors began to swing shut behind them – nothing made sense, it was surreal beyond all reckoning, like he’d been transported into an alternate universe, and then Harry’s mind flashed back to another day of confusion and in a moment of desperate inspiration he finally realized what the Weasley twins had done to Rita Skeeter, and his voice rose in a scream, ‘Hermione you didn’t do it you’ve been false-memory-charmed!’

But the doors had already shut.

Minerva couldn’t possibly have stood still, she paced back and forth through the Headmaster’s office, the back of her mind half-expecting Severus or Harry to tell her to shut up and sit down, but neither the Potions Master or the Boy-Who-Lived seemed much concerned with her, both of their gazes focused on Albus Dumbledore where he had emerged from the Floo. There were sounds in the background that nobody heard. Severus seemed as passionless as ever, sitting in a small cushioned chair beside the Headmaster’s desk. The old wizard stood terrible and upright by the still-burning fireplace, robed in black like a starless night, radiating power and dismay. All her own thoughts were of utter confusion and horror. Harry Potter sat on a wooden stool with his fingers gripping the seat, and his eyes were fury and freezing ice.

At 6:33am, Quirinus Quirrell had Flooed St. Mungo’s from his office for immediate pickup of Draco Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had found Mr Malfoy in the trophy room of Hogwarts, on the verge of death from the continuing effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm slowly lowering his body temperature. Professor Quirrell had immediately dispelled the Charm, cast stabilizing spells on Mr Malfoy, and levitated him to his office to Floo him to St. Mungo’s for further treatment. After this, Professor Quirrell had informed the Headmaster, stating the facts briefly before vanishing through the Floo; the Aurors, notified by St. Mungo’s, had demanded his presence for questioning.

The clear intent of the Blood-Cooling Charm had been to kill Draco Malfoy so slowly that the wards of Hogwarts, set to detect sudden injury, would not trigger. Under interrogation, Professor Quirrell had told the Aurors that he had cast several tracking Charms upon Mr Malfoy’s person in January, shortly after Mr Malfoy’s return to Hogwarts from the Christmas holidays. Professor Quirrell had cast tracking Charms because he had learned of a person with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had refused to identify this person. The tracking Charms which Professor Quirrell had cast were triggered by Mr Malfoy’s health falling below an absolute level, rather than by sudden changes, and had therefore alerted Professor Quirrell before Mr Malfoy had died.

Two drops of Veritaserum, sufficient to prevent Mr Malfoy from withholding any meliorating or moderating information in his statements, had shown that Mr Malfoy had – legally under the laws of Noble Houses, illegally under the regulations of Hogwarts – challenged Hermione Granger to a duel. Mr Malfoy had won the duel but had then, as he left, been attacked from behind by Miss Granger with a Stunning Hex. After this Mr Malfoy knew nothing.

Three drops of Veritaserum, requiring her to volunteer all relevant information, had caused Hermione Granger to confess that she had stunned Draco Malfoy from behind, and then, in a fit of anger, cast the Blood-Cooling Charm on him, with the deliberate intention of killing him slowly enough to evade identification from the Hogwarts wards, whose workings she had read about in Hogwarts: A History. She had been horrified at herself upon awakening the next morning, but had not told anyone of what she’d done, believing Draco Malfoy to be already dead – as he certainly would have been after seven hours, had his body’s own magic not been resisting the effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm.

‘Her trial,’ said Albus Dumbledore, ‘is set for tomorrow at noon.’

‘What?’ the word burst out of Harry Potter. The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t rise from his chair, but Minerva saw his fingers whiten where they gripped the wooden seat beneath him. ‘That’s insane! You can’t do a police investigation in one day –’

The Potions Master raised his voice. ‘This is not Muggle Britain, Mr Potter!’ Severus’s face was as expressionless as ever, but the bite in his voice was sharp. ‘The Aurors have an accusation under Veritaserum and a confession under Veritaserum. So far as they are concerned, the investigation is done.’

‘Not quite,’ said Dumbledore, just as Harry seemed ready to explode. ‘I have insisted to Amelia that this matter be given the utmost scrutiny. Unfortunately, as the ill-fated duel was at midnight –’

‘Supposed duel,’ Harry said sharply.

‘As the supposed duel was at midnight – yes, you’re quite right, Harry – it is beyond the range of any Time-Turner –’

‘Also supposedly,’ the Boy-Who-Lived said coldly. ‘And rather suspiciously, since the alleged murder suspect doesn’t know about Time-Turners. I hope that an invisible Auror was immediately sent back in time as far as possible to observe –’

Dumbledore inclined his head. ‘I went myself, Harry, the moment I heard. But by the time I reached the trophy room, Mr Malfoy was already unconscious and Miss Granger had gone –’

‘No,’ said Harry Potter. ‘You reached the trophy room and saw Draco unconscious. That is all you observed, Headmaster. You did not observe Hermione there, or watch her leave. Let us distinguish observation from inference.’ The boy’s head turned to look at her. ‘Imperius, Obliviation, False Memory Charm, Legilimency. Professor McGonagall, am I leaving out any mind-affecting spell that could have made Hermione do this or make her believe she’d done it?’

‘The Confundus Charm,’ she said. And the Dark Arts had never been her study, but she knew – ‘And certain Dark rituals. But none of those could be performed in Hogwarts without alarm.’

The boy nodded, his eyes still directly addressing her. ‘Which of those spells can be detected? Which would the Aurors try to detect?’

‘The Confundus Charm would wear off in a few hours,’ she said, after a moment to gather her thoughts. ‘Miss Granger would remember the Imperius. Obliviation cannot be detected by any known means, but only a Professor could have cast that spell upon a student without alarm from the Hogwarts wards. Legilimency – can only be detected by another Legilimens, I think –’

‘I requested that Miss Granger be examined by the court Legilimens,’ said Dumbledore. ‘The examination showed –’

‘Do we trust him?’ said Harry.

‘Her,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Sophie McJorgenson, whom I remember as an honest student of Ravenclaw, and she is bound by the Unbreakable Vow to tell the truth of what she sees –’

‘Could someone else be Polyjuiced as her?’ Harry Potter interrupted again. ‘What did you observe, Headmaster?’

Albus said heavily, ‘A person who looked like Madam McJorgenson told us that a single Legilimens had lightly touched Miss Granger’s mind some months ago. That is from January, Harry, when I communicated with Miss Granger about the matter of a certain Dementor. That was expected; but what I did not expect was the rest of what Sophie found.’ The old wizard turned to gaze into the Floo fire, letting the orange flames reflect on his face. ‘As you say, Harry, a False Memory Charm is one possibility; they are, when cast perfectly, indistinguishable from true memory –’

‘That doesn’t surprise me,’ Harry interrupted. ‘Studies show that human memories are more or less rewritten every time we remember them –’

‘Harry,’ Minerva said softly, and the boy’s mouth clamped shut.

The old wizard continued. ‘– but a False Memory Charm of such quality requires as much time to create as a true memory. Creating a detailed memory of ten minutes would be ten minutes’ work. And according to the court Legilimens,’ Albus’s face now seemed more tired and lined than before, ‘Miss Granger has been obsessing over Mr Malfoy since the day that Severus … yelled at her. She has been thinking of how Mr Malfoy might be in league with Professor Snape, how he might be planning to harm her and harm Harry – imagining it for hours every day – it would be impossible to create false memories for so much time.’

‘The appearance of insanity …’ Severus murmured softly, as though he were speaking to himself. ‘Could it be natural? No, it is too disastrous to be pure accident; too convenient for someone, I have no doubt. A Muggle drug, perhaps? But that would not be enough – Miss Granger’s madness would have to be guided –’

‘Ah!’ Harry said suddenly. ‘I get it now. The first False Memory Charm was cast on Hermione after Professor Snape yelled at her, and showed, say, Draco and Professor Snape plotting to kill her. Then last night that False Memory was removed by Obliviation, leaving behind the memories of her obsessing about Draco for no apparent reason, at the same time she and Draco were given false memories of the duel.’

Minerva blinked in astonishment. It would have been a thousand years before she thought of that possibility.

The Potions Master was frowning thoughtfully, eyes intent. ‘The reaction to a False Memory Charm is hard to predict in advance, Mr Potter, without Legilimency. The subjects do not always act as expected, when they first remember the false memories. It would have been a risky ploy. But I suppose that is one way Professor Quirrell could have done it.’

‘Professor Quirrell?’ said Harry. ‘What motive does he have to –’

The Potions Master said dryly, ‘The Defence Professor is always a suspect, Mr Potter. You will notice a trend, given time.’

Albus raised up a hand, a silencing gesture, and their heads all turned to look at him. ‘But in this case there is another suspect,’ Albus said quietly. ‘Voldemort.’

That deadliest of unspeakable words seemed to echo around the room, cancelling all the heat from the orange flames of the fireplace.

‘I do not know,’ the old wizard said slowly, ‘I know all too little of the methods of Voldemort’s immortality. He searched out those books before I did, I think. All I could find were ancient tales, scattered across too many volumes for him to remove. But to find truth among many stories is also a wizard’s mastery, and this I have endeavoured to do. There is a human sacrifice, a murder, of that I am certain; committed in coldest blood, the victim dying in horror. And old, old tales of wizards possessed, doing mad deeds, claiming the names of Dark Lords thought defeated; and there is usually a device, of that Dark Lord, which they wield …’ Albus looked at Harry, the ancient eyes searching the younger. ‘I think, Harry – though you will call it only inference – that the act of murder splits the soul. That by ritual of blackest horror, the torn fragment of soul is chained to this world. To a material thing of this world. Which must be, or which then becomes, a device of power.’

Horcrux. The terrible name echoed in Minerva’s mind, though it seemed that – for what reason she did not know – Albus would not speak that word in front of Harry.

‘And therefore,’ the old wizard finished quietly, ‘the remainder of the soul is bound to its chained part, lingering here when its body is destroyed. A sad and painful existence, I think it would be; less than spirit, less than the meanest ghost …’ The old wizard’s eyes were locked on Harry, who gazed back with his eyes narrowed. ‘It would take time for that mutilated soul to regain a mockery of life. That is why we have had our ten-year reprieve, I believe; why Voldemort did not return at once. But in time … that revenant would become capable of rising again.’ The old wizard spoke with grim precision. ‘It is clear, from the stories, that the Dark Lords who return by possessing another’s form, wield lesser magics than they once knew. I do not think Voldemort would be satisfied with that. He would take some other avenue to life. But Voldemort was more Slytherin than Salazar, grasping at every opportunity. He would use his pitiful state, use his power of possession, if he had reason. If he could benefit by another’s … inexplicable fury.’ Albus’s voice had fallen to almost a whisper. ‘That is what I suspect happened to Miss Granger.’

Minerva’s throat was very dry. ‘He’s here,’ she gasped. ‘Here, in Hogwarts –’

And stopped, because the reason Voldemort had come to Hogwarts –

The old wizard glanced at her only briefly, and said, still in that whisper, ‘I am sorry, Minerva, you were right.’

Harry’s voice was edged. ‘Right about what?’

‘Voldemort’s strongest avenue to life,’ Dumbledore said heavily. ‘The most desirable road for him, by which he would rise greater and more terrible than ever before. It is guarded here, within this castle –’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said politely. ‘Are you stupid?’

‘Harry,’ she said, but there was no force in her voice.

‘I mean, maybe you haven’t noticed this, Headmaster Dumbledore, but this castle is full of children –’

‘I had no choice!’ bellowed Dumbledore. The blue eyes were blazing now, beneath the half-moon spectacles. ‘I do not own it, that thing which Voldemort desires. It belongs to another, and is held here by his consent! I asked if it could be kept in the Department of Mysteries. But he would not permit that – he said it must be within the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of the Founders’ protection –’ Dumbledore passed his hand across his forehead. ‘No,’ the old wizard said in a quieter voice. ‘I cannot pass this blame to him. He is right. There is too much power in that thing, too much that men desire. I agreed that the trap should be laid behind the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of my own power.’ The old wizard bowed his head. ‘I knew Voldemort would worm his way here somehow, and planned to trap him. I did not think – I did not dream – that he would tarry in an enemy fortress one minute longer than he must.’

‘But,’ said Severus in some puzzlement, ‘what would the Dark Lord possibly gain by killing Lucius’s only heir?’

‘Point of order,’ Harry Potter said, a hard edge in his voice. ‘The motives of whoever’s behind this are not the primary issue. Our top priority at this point is that an innocent Hogwarts student is in trouble!’

The green eyes locked with the blue, as Albus Dumbledore gazed back at the Boy-Who-Lived –

‘Quite right, Mr Potter,’ Minerva said, she hadn’t even thought about it, the words just seemed to pop out of her lips. ‘Albus, who is watching over Miss Granger now?’

‘Professor Flitwick has gone to her,’ the Headmaster said.

‘She needs a lawyer,’ Harry said. ‘Anyone who just blurts out “I did it” to the police –’

‘Unfortunately,’ Minerva said, her tone taking on some of Professor Dumbledore’s sternness without thinking, ‘I doubt an attorney will be any use to Miss Granger at this point, Mr Potter. She is to face the judgement of the Wizengamot, and they would be exceedingly unlikely to free her on a technicality.’

Harry was looking at her with an utterly incredulous expression, as though suggesting that Hermione Granger didn’t need an attorney was akin to suggesting that she be set on fire.

‘She is correct, Mr Potter,’ Severus said quietly. ‘Few court processes in this country involve solicitors.’

Harry lifted his glasses and rubbed his eyes, briefly. ‘Fine. How do we get Hermione off the hook, exactly? I suppose it’s too much to hope that with all the lawyers gone, the judges understand the concept of “common sense” and “prior probability” well enough to realize that twelve-year-old girls basically never commit cold-blooded murders?’

‘It is the Wizengamot that she faces,’ said Severus. ‘The oldest Noble Houses, and certain other wizards of influence.’ Severus’s face twisted in something approaching his customary sarcasm. ‘As for them showing common sense – you might as well expect them to make you a bacon sandwich, Potter.’

Harry nodded, his mouth set. ‘Exactly what sort of penalty is Hermione facing? Snapped wand and expulsion –’

‘No,’ Severus said. ‘Nothing that light. Are you wilfully misunderstanding, Potter? She is facing the Wizengamot. There is no set penalty. There is only the vote.’

Harry Potter murmured, ‘The rule of law, in complex times, has proved itself deficient; we much prefer the rule of men, it’s vastly more efficient … There’s no constraining legal rules at all, then?’

Light glinted off the old wizard’s half-moon glasses; he spoke carefully, and not without anger. ‘Legally, Harry, we are dealing with a blood debt from Hermione Granger to the House of Malfoy. The Lord of Malfoy proposes a repayment of that debt, and then the Wizengamot votes on his proposal. That is all.’

‘But …’ Harry said slowly. ‘Lucius was Sorted into Slytherin, he’s got to realize that Hermione was just a pawn. Not the one he should actually be angry at. Right?’

‘No, Harry Potter,’ Albus Dumbledore said heavily. ‘That is how you wish Lucius Malfoy would think. Lucius Malfoy himself … will not share your desire that he think that way.’

Harry gazed at the Headmaster, his eyes growing colder, at the same time that Minerva herself had to clamp down harder on her own emotions, stop her pacing and try to breathe. She’d been trying not to think about it, trying to turn her thoughts away from it, but she knew. She’d known since the instant she’d heard. She could see it in Albus’s eyes –

‘Is she facing capital punishment?’ Harry said quietly, and chills went all the way down Minerva’s spine at the undertones of that voice.

‘No!’ Albus said. ‘No, not the Kiss, not Azkaban, not for a first-year in Hogwarts. Our country is not so lost, not yet.’

‘But Lucius Malfoy,’ Severus said tonelessly, ‘certainly will not be satisfied with only snapping her wand.’

‘All right,’ Harry said commandingly. ‘As I see it, we’ve got two essential lines of attack. Line one, find the real culprit. Line two, other leverage over Lucius. Professor Quirrell saved Draco’s life, does that create a blood debt from House Malfoy to him that he could redeem to cancel Hermione’s?’

Minerva blinked in astonishment again.

‘No,’ Dumbledore said. The old wizard shook his head. ‘It was a clever thought – but no, Harry, I’m afraid not. There is an exception when the Wizengamot suspects that the circumstances of a life-debt may have been created deliberately. And the Defence Professor is hardly above suspicion. Thus Lucius would argue.’

Harry nodded once, face set. ‘Headmaster, I know I said I wouldn’t – but under the circumstances – that time Draco cast that torture hex on me, is that debt enough –’

‘No,’ the old wizard said (even as she blurted ‘What?’ and Severus lifted an eyebrow). ‘It would not have been enough, and now it is no debt at all. You are an Occlumens and cannot testify under Veritaserum. Draco Malfoy could be Obliviated of his own memory before he could testify –’ Albus hesitated. ‘Harry … whatever you have done with Draco, you must assume that Lucius Malfoy will soon know of it.’

Harry’s head sank into his hands. ‘He’ll give Draco Veritaserum.’

‘Yes,’ Albus said quietly.

The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t say anything, as he sat with his head in his hands.

The Potions Master looked genuinely shocked. ‘Draco really was trying to help Miss Granger,’ Severus said. ‘You – Potter, you actually –’

‘Turned him?’ Harry said from between his hands. ‘I was about three-quarters done. Taught him the Patronus Charm and everything. I don’t know what will happen now, though.’

‘Voldemort has struck a grave blow against us, this day,’ Albus said. The sound of old wizard’s voice was like the look of the boy with his head in his hands. ‘He has taken two of our pieces, with one … No. I should have seen it earlier. He has taken two of Harry’s pieces with one move. Voldemort has begun his game again, not against myself, but against Harry. Voldemort knows the prophecy, he knows who his last foe shall be. He is not waiting to face Hermione Granger and Draco Malfoy at Harry’s side when they are grown. He is striking at them now.’

‘Maybe it’s You-Know-Who and maybe it isn’t,’ Harry said, his voice sounding a little unsteady. ‘Let’s not narrow down the hypothesis space prematurely.’ Harry took a breath and lowered his hands. ‘The other thing we can try is to nail the real culprit before the trial – or at least find solid evidence that someone else did it.’

‘Mr Potter,’ said Minerva, ‘Professor Quirrell told the Aurors that he knew of someone with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Do you know who he was talking about?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, after a hesitation. ‘But I think I shall conduct that part of my investigation with the Defence Professor – just as I would not have Professor Quirrell in the room while we were discussing how to investigate him.’

‘He suspects me?’ Severus said, then gave a short laugh. ‘Why, of course he does.’

‘My own plan,’ said Harry, ‘is to go and look at the trophy room where the supposed duel took place and see if I can discover anything anomalous. If you can tell the investigating Aurors to let me through –’

‘What investigating Aurors?’ Severus said tonelessly.

Harry Potter took a deep breath, slowly let it out, and then spoke again. ‘In mystery books it usually takes longer than one day to solve a crime, but twenty-four hours is – no, thirty hours is eighteen hundred minutes. And I can think of at least one other important place to look for clues – though it’ll have to be someone who can get into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm. Back when Hermione was fighting bullies, she was finding notes under her pillow each morning, telling her where to go –’

‘Albus …’ ground out Minerva.

‘I did not send them,’ said the old wizard. His white eyebrows had lifted in surprise. ‘I knew nothing of this. You think she was being played, Harry?’

‘It’s a possibility,’ Harry said. ‘More so, because there’s a part of this puzzle that you don’t know about yet.’ Harry’s voice lowered, grew more intense. ‘Headmaster, you already know that I got my father’s invisibility cloak from someone who left a note under my pillow, saying it was an early Christmas present. I think we have to assume that’s the same person who left notes for Hermione –’

‘Harry,’ the old wizard said, and hesitated momentarily. ‘Returning your father’s cloak to you, does not seem to me like the act of a villain –’

‘Listen,’ Harry Potter said urgently. ‘The part you don’t know is that after Bellatrix Black escaped from Azkaban, I found another note under my pillow, signed “Santa Claus”, saying that they’d heard you were shutting me up inside Hogwarts, and that they were giving me an escape route to the Salem Witches’ Institute in America. That note came with a deck of cards, in which the King of Hearts was supposedly a portkey –’

‘Mr Potter!’ cried Professor McGonagall, she hadn’t even thought before she spoke. ‘That could well be a kidnapping attempt! You should have told – ’

‘Yes, Professor, I did the sensible thing,’ the boy said levelly. ‘As adapted to the circumstances, I did the sensible thing. I told Professor Quirrell. And according to Professor Quirrell, that portkey goes to somewhere in London – it’s definitely not strong enough to be an international portkey. Now it’s possible that the person who sent the note is honest, and that the point in London is just a way station.’ The boy reached into his robes and took out a deck of cards, along with a folded paper note. ‘I will trust you not to go in guns blazing – I mean wands blazing – just in case the sender is an ally of mine, if not yours. But if this is a trap, I say we spring it now. And whoever it is, take them alive so we can exhibit them before the Wizengamot, I cannot overemphasize that part.’

Severus rose from his chair, his eyes now intent, and moved toward Harry. ‘I’ll need a hair of yours for Polyjuice, Mr Potter –’

‘Let us not be hasty!’ said Albus. ‘We have not yet examined the notes sent to Miss Granger; there may be no resemblance after all. Severus, would you enter her dorm and see if you can find those?’

Harry Potter’s eyebrows had raised, even as he stood to offer the Potions Master better access to his unruly hair. ‘You think two different people are running around Hogwarts leaving notes beneath pillows?’

Severus gave a brief sardonic laugh, as his hand moved forward and plucked a hair, which soon was being carefully wrapped in silk. ‘Quite possibly. If I have learned anything in my tenure as Head of Slytherin, I have learned what ridiculous messes arise when there is more than one plotter and more than one plan. But Headmaster – I think Mr Potter is correct that I should follow this portkey and see where it leads.’

Albus hesitated, and then nodded reluctantly. ‘I will speak to you before you go, then.’

Even as Harry Potter left the room for his own investigations, Severus spun on his heel and strode swiftly toward the jar of Floo powder, his cloak rising behind him with his speed. ‘I’ll get some raw Polyjuice, add the hair, and go. Headmaster, will you stand by to –’

‘Albus,’ Minerva said, surprised at how steady her own voice was, ‘did you leave those notes under Mr Potter’s pillow?’

Severus’s hand halted an instant before casting Floo powder into the fire.

Dumbledore nodded to her, though the accompanying smile seemed a bit hollow. ‘You know me far too well, my dear.’

‘And I suppose the portkey goes to a friendly home where Mr Potter would be kept safe and sound until you arrived to pick him up and return him to Hogwarts?’ Her voice tight – it was sensible, she could not deny it was sensible, but somehow it seemed a little cruel.

‘It would depend on the circumstances,’ the old wizard said quietly. ‘If Harry had gone so far – I might have let him make good his escape, for a time. Better to know where he was going, and ensure it was somewhere safe, with friends –’

‘And to think,’ said Professor McGonagall, ‘that I had thought to reprimand Mr Potter for not telling us about this important matter! Upbraid him for not having the sense to trust us!’ Her voice had risen in volume. ‘I shall skip that lecture, I suppose!’

Severus was gazing at the Headmaster with narrowed eyes. ‘And the notes to Miss Granger –’

‘The Defence Professor, very likely,’ the old wizard said. ‘Still – that is only a guess.’

‘I shall go and look for them,’ Severus said. ‘And then, I suppose, start looking for You-Know-Who.’ A frown crossed the Potions Master’s face. ‘A task which I haven’t the faintest idea of where to start. Do you know of any magics to find a soul, Headmaster?’

The Divination classroom was lit by the dim red light of a hundred small fires where burned a hundred kinds of incense, so that if you were to ask for one word describing what the room looked like, the answer would be smoke. (Assuming you bothered to look at anything, when your nose was threatening to overload and die.) If your gaze could pierce those dank mists, you would see a tiny, cluttered room in which forty stuffed armchairs, most of them unused, were crammed around a small open space in the centre of the room, where a circular trapdoor waited on your escape.

‘The grim!’ Professor Trelawney said in a quavering voice, as she peered into George Weasley’s teacup. ‘The grim! It is a sign of death! One whom you know, George – someone you know is to die! And soon – yes, it shall be quite soon, I think – unless of course it is later –’

It would have been a good deal scarier, thought Fred and George, if she hadn’t said the same thing to every single other student in their Divination class. They were hardly even thinking about it at this point; all their thoughts were on today’s disaster –

The trapdoor in the floor flew open with a bang that caused Professor Trelawney to shriek and spill George’s tea all over his robes, and then an instant later Dumbledore was whooshing up out of the floor with a bird of fire upon his shoulder.

‘Fred!’ the old wizard said commandingly. His robes were the black of a moonless night, his eyes hard like blue diamonds. ‘George! With me, now!’

There was an collective gasp and by the time Fred and George were climbing down the ladder after the Headmaster, the entire class was already speculating what role they’d played in the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.

The trapdoor had hardly slammed shut above them before all nearby sounds muted and the old wizard spun on them and held out a hand and commanded, ‘Give me the map!’

‘M-map?’ said Fred or George in total shock. They’d never even suspected that Dumbledore suspected. ‘Why, w-we don’t know what you’re –’

‘Hermione Granger is in trouble,’ said the old wizard.

‘The Map is in our dorm,’ George or Fred said immediately. ‘Just give us a few minutes to get it and we’ll –’

The wizard’s arms swept them up as if they were hugging-pillows, there was a piercing cry and a flash of fire and then the three of them were in the third-year Gryffindor boys’ dorm.

A few moments later, Fred and George were handing over the Map to the Headmaster, wincing only slightly at the sacrilege of giving their precious piece of the Hogwarts security system to the person who actually owned it, and the old wizard was frowning at the apparent blankness.

‘You’ve got to say,’ they explained, ‘I solemnly swear that I am up to no good –’

‘I decline to lie,’ said the old wizard. He held the Map high and bellowed, ‘Hear me, Hogwarts! Deligitor prodi!’ An instant later the Headmaster was wearing the Sorting Hat, which looked scarily right upon his head, as though Dumbledore had always been waiting for a patchwork pointed hat to complete his existence.

(Fred and George immediately memorized this phrase, just in case it would work for somebody besides the Headmaster, and began trying to think of pranks that would involve the Sorting Hat.)

The old wizard wasted not a moment before sweeping the Sorting Hat off his head and turning it upside-down – it was hard to tell with the Hat upside-down, but it looked a bit cross at the treatment – and then plunged in his hand and drew out a crystal rod. With this instrument he began tracing rune-like patterns on the Map, muttering strange incantations that sounded not quite like Latin and echoed in their ears in an unusually creepy fashion. In the midst of tracing one rune he looked up at both of them, fixing them with a sharp glare. ‘I will return this to you later, sons of Weasley. Go back to class.’

‘Yes, Headmaster,’ they said, and hesitated. ‘Ah – about Hermione Granger, is she really going to be bound to serve Draco Malfoy forever as his –’

‘Go,’ said the old wizard.

They went.

When he was alone in the room, the old wizard looked down at the map, which had now written upon itself a fine line drawing of the Gryffindor dorms in which they stood, the small handwritten Albus P.W.B. Dumbledore the only name left therein.

The old wizard smoothed the map, bent over it, and whispered, ‘Find Tom Riddle.’

The interrogation room at the Department of Magical Law Enforcement was usually lit by a small orange light, so that the Auror interrogating you would be leaning toward your uncomfortable metal chair with most of their face in shadow, preventing you from reading their expression, even as they read yours.

As soon as Mr Quirrell had entered the room, the small orange light had dimmed and begun flickering like a candle about to be blown out by the wind. The room was now lit by a sourceless ice-coloured glow which illuminated all of Mr Quirrell’s pale skin like alabaster, except, somehow, his eyes, which stayed in darkness.

The Auror on duty outside had surreptitiously tried to dispel this effect four times without the slightest success, despite the fact that Mr Quirrell had politely surrendered his wand upon being detained for interrogation, and had shown no sign of speaking any incantations nor exerting any other power.

‘Quirinus … Quirrell,’ drawled the man now sitting across from where the Defence Professor had waited courteously. The interrogator had tawny hair that swept back like a lion’s mane, with yellowish eyes set into the sternly lined face of a man late in his tenth decade. The man was, at this moment, leafing through a large folder of parchments that he had taken from a black and very solid-looking briefcase after he had limped into the room and sat down, seeming not to look at the face of the man he was interrogating. He had not introduced himself.

After some further leafing through parchments, carried out in silence, the Auror spoke again. ‘Born the 26th of September, 1955, to Quondia Quirrell, of an acknowledged tryst with Lirinus Lumblung …’ intoned the Auror. ‘Sorted into Ravenclaw … O.W.L.s quite good … N.E.W.T.s in Charms, Transfiguration … an Outstanding in Muggle Studies, impressive … Ancient Runes, and ah yes, Defence. An Outstanding in that as well. Went on to become quite the tourist, visiting all sorts of places. Portkey visas for Transylvania, the Forbidden Empire, the City of Endless Night … my my, Texas.’ The man looked up from the portfolio, eyes narrowed. ‘What were you doing there, Mr Quirrell?’

‘Sightseeing, mostly in the Muggle areas,’ the Defence Professor said easily. ‘As you say, I am quite the tourist.’

The man listened to this with a frown, then looked back down, then up again. ‘I also see that you visited Fuyuki City in 1983.’

The Defence Professor lifted an eyebrow in mild puzzlement. ‘What of it?’

‘What did you do in Fuyuki City?’ The question snapped out razor-sharp.

The Defence Professor frowned slightly. ‘Nothing of any account. I visited some better-known sights, some less-known sights, and aside from that, kept to myself.’

‘Really?’ the Auror said softly. ‘I find that reply rather interesting.’

‘How so?’ said the Defence Professor.

‘Because there was no visa listed for Fuyuki City.’ The man slammed the folder shut. ‘You’re not Quirinus Quirrell. Who the hell are you?’

The Potions Master walked quietly into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm, the first-year dorm, a festive place where bronze and blue competed to be the colour of stuffed animals, scarves and dresses, small bits of inexpensive jewellery, and posters of famous people. Hermione Granger’s bed was easy to identify; it was the one that had been attacked by a book monster.

Nobody else seemed to be around, at that time of day, and a number of spells verified this.

The Potions Master searched under Hermione Granger’s pillow, and beneath her bed, and then began going through her trunk, sorting through mentionable and unmentionable items without change of expression, and finally succeeded in drawing forth a set of papers describing places and times where bullies would be found, all of the papers signed only with an elaborate S.

A brief burst of fire later, the papers were gone, and the Potions Master left to report the failure of his mission.

The Defence Professor was sitting calmly with his hands still folded in his lap. ‘If you consult Headmaster Dumbledore,’ said the Defence Professor, ‘you will find that he is well aware of this matter, and that I agreed to teach his Defence class on the explicit condition that no inquiry be made into my –’

In a lightning motion, the interrogator whipped out his wand and spat ‘Polyfluis Reverso!’ at the same time that the Defence Professor sneezed, which somehow caused the mirror-silvered ray to disrupt in a shower of white sparks.

‘Pardon me,’ the Defence Professor said politely.

The smile that the Auror gave had absolutely no mirth in it. ‘So where’s the real Quirinus Quirrell, eh? Under an Imperius in the bottom of a trunk somewhere, while you take a hair now and then for your illegal Polyjuice?’

‘You are making highly questionable assumptions,’ the Defence Professor said with an edged voice. ‘What makes you think I did not steal his body outright using incredibly Dark magic?’

This was followed by a certain pause.

‘I suggest,’ the Auror said, ‘that you take this seriously, Mr Whoever-You-Are.’

‘I’m sorry,’ said the Defence Professor, leaning back in his chair, ‘but I see little reason to humble myself on this particular occasion. What are you going to do, kill me?’

‘I don’t appreciate your humour,’ the Auror said softly.

‘How unfortunate for you, Rufus Scrimgeour,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘You have my deepest sympathy.’ He tilted his head, seeming to study the interrogator; and even within the shadow of the ice-light, the eyes glinted.

Padma stared down at her plate.

‘Hermione wouldn’t just do that!’ yelled Mandy Brocklehurst, who was practically in tears, in fact she was in tears, her voice would have been loud enough to silence the Great Hall if it hadn’t been for all the other students also screaming at each other. ‘I – I bet Malfoy tried to – to do things to her –’

‘Our General would never do that!’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled even louder than Mandy.

‘Of course he would!’ shouted Anthony Goldstein. ‘Malfoy’s the son of a Death Eater!’

Padma stared down at her plate.

Draco was the General of her army.

Hermione was the founder of S.P.H.E.W.

Draco had trusted her to be his second-in-command.

Hermione was her fellow Ravenclaw.

Both of them were her friends, maybe the two best friends she had.

Padma stared down at her plate. She was glad the Sorting Hat hadn’t offered her Hufflepuff. If she’d been Sorted into Hufflepuff it would probably have been much more painful, trying to decide where her divided loyalties lay …

She blinked and realized that her vision had blurred again, and raised a trembling hand to wipe once more at her eyes.

Morag MacDougal snorted so loudly it was audible even amid the pandemonium of lunch, and said in a loud voice, ‘I bet Granger cheated in her battle yesterday, I bet that’s why Malfoy challenged her –’

‘All of you Shut up!’ roared Harry Potter, as he hit the table with his fists so hard that plates rattled all the way along it.

At any other time that would have earned him a Professorial reprimand; this time it just got a few nearby students to look.

‘I’d wanted to eat lunch,’ Harry Potter said, ‘and then get back to investigating, so I wasn’t going to talk. But you’re all being silly, and when the truth comes out you’re going to regret what you said about innocent people. Draco didn’t do anything, Hermione didn’t do anything, they were both False-Memory-Charmed!’ Harry Potter’s voice had been rising on the last words. ‘How is that not BLOODY OBVIOUS?’

‘You think we’ll believe that?’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled right back at him. ‘That’s what everyone says! “I didn’t do it, it was all just a False Memory Charm!” You think we’re stupid?’

And Morag nodded right along with him, with a condescending look.

The look that came over Harry Potter’s face then made Padma flinch.

‘I see,’ Harry Potter said; it wasn’t a shout, so Padma had to strain to hear it. ‘Professor Quirrell isn’t here to explain to me how stupid people are, but I bet this time I can get it on my own. People do something dumb and get caught and are given Veritaserum. Not romantic master criminals, because they wouldn’t get caught, they would have learned Occlumency. Sad, pathetic, incompetent criminals get caught, and confess under Veritaserum, and they’re desperate to stay out of Azkaban so they say they were False-Memory-Charmed. Right? So your brain, by sheer Pavlovian association, links the idea of False Memory Charms to pathetic criminals with unbelievable excuses. You don’t have to consider the specific details, your brain just pattern-matches the hypothesis into a bucket of things you don’t believe, and you’re done. Just like my father thought that magical hypotheses could never be believed, because he’d heard so many stupid people talking about magic. Believing a hypothesis that involves False Memory Charms is low-status.’

‘What are you blithering about?’ said Morag, looking down her nose at the Boy-Who-Lived.

‘You think we’d believe anything you say?’ yelled a slightly older-looking Ravenclaw witch who Padma didn’t recognize. ‘When you turned Granger Dark?’

‘And I’m not going to complain,’ Harry Potter said in an eerily calm voice, ‘about wizards not having any logic and believing the craziest things. Because I said that to Professor Quirrell once, and he just gave me this look and said that if I wasn’t blinded by my upbringing I could think of a hundred more ridiculous things that lots of Muggles believe. What you’re all doing is very human and very normal and doesn’t make you unusually bad people, so I’m not going to complain.’ The Boy-Who-Lived rose up from his bench. ‘I’ll see you all later.’

And Harry Potter walked away from them, walked away from all of them.

‘You’re not thinking he’s right, are you?’ said Su Li from beside her, in a tone which made it clear what she thought.

‘I –’ said Padma. Her words seemed to be caught in her throat, her thoughts seemed to be caught in her head. ‘I – I mean – I –’

If you think hard enough you can do the impossible.

(It had always been an article of faith with Harry. There’d been a time when he’d acknowledged the laws of physics as ultimate limitations, and now he suspected there were no true limits at all.)

If you think fast enough you can sometimes do the impossible quickly …

… sometimes.

Only sometimes.

Not always.

Not reliably.

The Boy-Who-Lived stared around the trophy room, surrounded by awards and cups and plates and shields and statues and medals kept behind thousands, perhaps tens of thousands, of crystal glass displays. For as many centuries as Hogwarts had existed, this room had been accumulating details. A week, a month, maybe even a year, wouldn’t have sufficed to take the examine option on every item in the room. With Professor Flitwick gone, Harry had asked Professor Vector if there was any way to detect damage to the wards around the crystal cases, verify the residue that a real duel should have left behind. Harry had raced through the Hogwarts library looking for spells to tell the difference between old fingerprints and new fingerprints, or to detect lingering exhalations in a room. And all those attempts at playing detective had failed.

There were no clues, none that he was smart enough to find.

Professor Snape had said that the portkey led to an empty house in London, with no sign of anyone or anything else.

Professor Snape hadn’t found any notes in Hermione’s dorm.

Headmaster Dumbledore had said that Voldemort’s spirit was probably hiding out in the Chamber of Secrets where the Hogwarts security system couldn’t find him. Harry had sneaked into the Slytherin dungeons under the Cloak of Invisibility and spent the rest of the afternoon looking through all the obvious places, but he hadn’t found anything snaky that answered back when spoken to. The entrance to the Chamber of Secrets, it seemed, hadn’t been meant to be found in a day.

Harry had talked to all of Hermione’s friends that would still talk to him, and none of them had remembered Hermione saying anything specific about why she’d believed that Draco was plotting against her.

Professor Quirrell hadn’t come back from the Ministry as of dinnertime. The older students seemed to think that this year’s Defence Professor would probably end up being blamed for the incident, and fired for teaching Hogwarts students to be too violent. They’d talked about the Defence Professor as though he were already gone.

Harry had used up all six hours from his Time-Turner, and there were still no clues, and he had to go to sleep now if he wanted to be functional at Hermione’s trial the next day.

The Boy-Who-Destroyed-A-Dementor was standing in the middle of the Hogwarts trophy room, his wand dropped at his feet.

He was crying.

Sometimes you call your brain and it doesn’t answer.

The trial of Hermione Granger started on schedule the next day.

Cheating

It was Saturday, on the 4th of April, in the year 1992.

Mr and Mrs Davis looked rather nervous, as they sat in a certain special section of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands – though today the cushioned benches did not look upon flying broomsticks, but rather viewed a gigantic square of something like parchment; a great white blankness soon to flicker with windows into grass and soldiers. For now it showed only the reflected dull grey colour of the surrounding overcast skies. (Looking rather stormy, though the weather-wizards had promised that the rain wouldn’t break before nightfall.)

Ordinarily it was the ancient tradition of Hogwarts that mere parents were to Stay Out – for much the same reason that impatient children are told to get out of the kitchen and not meddle in the cook’s affairs. The only reason for a parent-teacher conference was if a teacher felt that a parent wasn’t shaping up properly. It took an exceptional circumstance to make the Hogwarts administration feel that it had to justify itself to you. On any given occasion, generally speaking, the Hogwarts administration was backed up by eight hundred years of distinguished history and you were not.

Thus it had been with some trepidation that Mr and Mrs Davis had insisted on an audience with Deputy Headmistress McGonagall. It was hard to muster a proper sense of indignation when you were confronting the same dignified witch who, twelve years and four months earlier, had given both of you two weeks’ detention after catching you in the act of conceiving Tracey.

On the other hand, Mr and Mrs Davis’ courage had been helped by angrily waving about a copy of The Quibbler whose headline showed, in bright bold text for all the world to see:

Pacts with Potter?
Bones, Davis, Granger
in love rectangle of fear

And so Mr and Mrs Davis had argued their way into the Faculty Box of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands, where they were now ensconced with an excellent view of Professor Quirrell’s enchanted screens, so that the two of them could see for themselves ‘Just what the Fiddly-Snocks has been going on in this school, if you’ll pardon the expression, Deputy Headmistress McGonagall!’

Seated to the left of Mr Davis was another concerned parent, a white-haired man in elegant black robes of unmatchable quality, one Lucius Malfoy, political leader of the strongest faction of the Wizengamot.

To the left of Lord Malfoy, a sneeringly aristocratic man with a scarred face who had been introduced to them as Lord Jugson.

Then an elderly but sharp-eyed fellow named Charles Nott, rumoured to be nearly as wealthy as Lord Malfoy, seated on Lord Jugson’s left.

On the right of Mrs Davis, one would find the comely Lady and yet handsomer Lord of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Greengrass. Young they were as wizards counted age, garbed in grey silken robes set with tiny dark emeralds embroidered into the shape of grass blades. The Lady Greengrass was considered a key swing vote on the Wizengamot, her own mother having retired from the body with surprising speed. Her charming husband, though his family was not noble or wealthy of itself, had taken a seat on the Hogwarts Board of Governors.

To their right, a square-jawed and incredibly tough-looking old witch, who had shaken hands with Mr and Mrs Davis without the slightest hint of condescension. This was Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement.

To Amelia’s right was a oldish woman who had set the fashion scene of magical Britain on its ear by integrating a live vulture into her hat, one Augusta Longbottom. Though she was not addressed as Lady, Madam Longbottom would exercise the full rights of the Longbottom family for so long as their last scion had yet to attain his majority, and she was considered a prominent figure in a minority faction of the Wizengamot.

At the side of Madam Longbottom was seated none other than Chief Warlock Supreme Mugwump Headmaster Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore, legendary defeater of Grindelwald, protector of Britain, rediscoverer of the fabled twelve uses of dragon’s blood, the most powerful wizard in the world &c.

And finally, on the far right, one would find the enigmatic Defence Professor of Hogwarts, Quirinus Quirrell, who was leaning back on the cushioned benches as though resting; seeming entirely and naturally at ease in the rarefied company of a voting quorum of the Hogwarts Board of Governors, which had dropped by on this fine Saturday to learn just what the Fiddly-Snocks had been going on at Hogwarts in general and with Draco Malfoy, Theodore Nott, Daphne Greengrass, Susan Bones, and Neville Longbottom in particular. The name of Harry Potter had also been much discussed.

Oh, and one mustn’t forget Tracey Davis, of course. Director Bones’s eyebrows had climbed in some interest upon hearing the young couple introduced as her parents. Lord Jugson had given them a brief, incredulous stare before dismissing them with a snort. Lucius Malfoy had greeted them politely, his smile containing a hint of grim amusement mixed with pity.

Mr and Mrs Davis, whose last vote on anything of significance had been touching their wands to the name of Minister Fudge, who had all of three hundred Galleons stored in their Gringotts vault, and who respectively worked at selling cauldrons in a Potions shop and enchanting Omnioculars, were pressed up tightly against each other, sitting rigidly erect upon their cushioned benches, and desperately wishing they’d worn nicer robes.

The sky above was a solid mass of cloud dispersed into darker and lighter greys, grim with the promise of future storms; though no lightning flickered as yet, nor distant rumbles of thunder echoed; and only a few threatening droplets had fallen.

To their designated starting place in a certain forest, the Sunshine Regiment marched, though it was really more like a slow walk; you wouldn’t want to tire yourself out before the battle even started, and the breezes of April were annoyingly humid, though cool. Ahead of them, a yellow flame wandered slowly through the air, guiding them according to their pace.

Susan Bones kept throwing worried glances toward the Sunshine General as they marched through the greyly illuminated forest. Professor Snape’s going after Hermione seemed to have really shaken her. Hermione had even missed her Sunshine Regiment Official Planning Meeting, which seemed understandable enough; but when Susan had offered her sympathy afterwards, Hermione had stammered that she’d lost track of time, which wasn’t at all a usual thing for her to say, and the girl had looked exhausted and frightened like she’d just spent three days locked in a bathroom stall with a Dementor. Even now, when all the Sunshine General’s focus should’ve been on the coming battle, the Ravenclaw girl’s gaze was constantly darting in all directions, as though she expected Dark Wizards to jump out of the bushes and sacrifice her.

‘The ban on Muggle artifacts cuts down our options a lot,’ Anthony Goldstein was saying in the dour tones the boy used to denote deliberate pessimism. ‘I had the idea of trying to Transfigure nets to throw on people, but –’

‘No good,’ said Ernie Macmillan. The Hufflepuff boy shook his head, looking even more serious than Anthony. ‘I mean, it’s just like throwing a hex, they’d dodge.’

Anthony nodded. ‘That’s what I figured, too. Do you have any ideas, Seamus?’

The former Chaotic Lieutenant still looked a bit nervous and out-of-place, marching along with his new comrades in the Sunshine Regiment. ‘Sorry,’ said the newly minted Captain Finnigan. ‘I’m more the strategic master type.’

‘I’m the strategic master type,’ said Ron Weasley, sounding put-off.

‘There are three armies,’ the Sunshine General said acerbically, ‘which means we fight two armies at once, which means we need more than one strategist, which means shut up, Ron!’

Ron gave their General a surprised and worried look. ‘Hey,’ the Gryffindor boy said in a calming tone, ‘you shouldn’t let Snape get to you so much –’

‘What do you think we ought to do, General?’ Susan said very loudly and quickly. ‘I mean, we don’t really have a plan at this point.’ Their official planning session had failed amazingly with Hermione gone and both Ron and Anthony thinking they were in charge.

‘Do we really need a plan?’ the Sunshine General said, sounding a little distracted. ‘We’ve got you and me and Lavender and Parvati and Hannah and Daphne and Ron and Ernie and Anthony and Captain Finnigan.’

‘That –’ began Anthony.

‘Sounds like a pretty good strategy,’ Ron said with an approving nod. ‘We’ve got as many strong soldiers now as both other armies put together. Chaos’s only got Potter and Longbottom and Nott left – well, and Zabini too, I suppose –’

‘And Tracey,’ said Hermione.

Several people swallowed nervously.

‘Oh, stop it,’ Susan said sharply. ‘She’s just a battle-hardened member of S.P.H.E.W., that’s all General Sunshine means.’

‘Still,’ Ernie said, turning to look seriously at Susan, ‘I think you’d better go with whatever group fights Chaos, Captain Bones. I know you can’t use your double magical powers except when innocents are in danger, but I mean – just in case Miss Davis does, you know, go out of control and try to eat someone’s soul –’

‘I can handle her,’ Susan told him, keeping her voice reassuring. Admittedly, Susan hadn’t been replaced by a Metamorphmagus at the moment, but then Tracey probably wasn’t Polyjuiced Dumbledore or whoever.

Captain Finnigan intoned in a deep, sort-of-rumbling voice, ‘I find your lack of skepticism disturbing.’ He raised his hand with his thumb and forefinger almost touching, pointed at Ernie.

For some reason Anthony Goldstein seemed to be having a sudden choking fit. ‘What’s that supposed to mean?’ said Ernie.

‘It’s just something General Potter says sometimes,’ said Captain Finnigan. ‘Funny, when you first join the Chaos Legion it all seems crazy, and then after a couple of months you realize that actually everyone who isn’t in the Chaos Legion is crazy –’

‘I said,’ Ron said loudly, ‘it sounds like good strategy. We don’t Transfigure anything, we don’t tire ourselves out, we handle whatever they throw at us, and then we just overrun them.’

‘Okay,’ said Hermione. ‘Let’s do that.’

‘But –’ said Anthony, shooting a glare at Ron. ‘But General, Harry Potter’s got sixteen people left in his army. Dragon and us each have twenty-eight. Harry knows that, he knows he’s got to come up with something incredible –’

‘Like what?’ demanded Hermione, sounding stressed. ‘If we don’t know what he’s planning, we might as well save our magic for doing massed Finites. Like we should’ve done last time!’

Susan touched Hermione gently on the shoulder. ‘General Granger?’ said Susan. ‘I think you should take a break for a bit before the battle.’

She’d been expecting Hermione to argue, but Hermione just nodded and then walked a little faster, pulling away from the Sunshine Regiment Official Officer Group, her eyes still watching the forest, and sometimes the sky.

Susan followed her. It wouldn’t do, having it look like the Sunshine General was being ejected from her own Official Officer Group.

‘Hermione?’ Susan said softly, after they’d walked a bit away. ‘You’ve got to focus. Professor Quirrell’s in charge here, not Snape, and he won’t let anything bad happen to you or anyone.’

‘You’re not helping,’ Hermione said, sounding shaky. ‘You’re not helping at all, Captain Bones.’

The two of them walked faster, circling around some of the other soldiers, inspecting the marching perimeter and glancing at the surrounding trees.

‘Susan?’ Hermione said in a small voice, when they were further away from all the others. ‘Do you think Daphne’s right about Draco Malfoy plotting something?’

‘Yes,’ Susan said at once, not even thinking about it. ‘You can tell, because his name’s got the letters M-A-L-F-O and Y in it.’

Hermione looked around, as if to make sure that nobody was watching, although of course that was a wonderful way to get other people to pay attention to you. ‘Could Malfoy have been behind what Snape did?’

‘Snape could be behind Malfoy,’ Susan said thoughtfully, remembering dinner-table conversations she’d heard at Auntie’s, ‘or Lucius Malfoy could be behind both of them.’ A slight chill went down Susan’s spine as this last thought occurred to her. Suddenly, telling Hermione to just focus on the coming battle seemed a lot less reasonable. ‘Why, did you find some sort of clue about that?’

Hermione shook her head. ‘No,’ the Ravenclaw girl said, in a voice that sounded almost like she was about to cry. ‘I was – just thinking about it myself – that’s all.’

In their designated place in a forest near Hogwarts, the Dragon General and the warriors of Dragon Army waited where their red flame had led them, beneath grey skies.

At Draco’s right side stood Padma Patil, his second-in-command, who had once led all of Dragon Army after Draco had been stunned. At Draco’s back was Vincent, the son of Crabbe, a family which had served the Malfoys into the distance of forgotten memory; the muscular boy was watchful as he was always watchful, whether battle had been declared or no. Further back, Gregory of the Goyles stood waiting beside one of the two broomsticks Dragon Army had been given; if the Goyles had not served the Malfoys so long as the Crabbes, yet they had served no less well.

And at Draco’s left side, now, stood one Dean Thomas of Gryffindor, a mudblood or possible half-blood who knew nothing of his father.

Sending Dean Thomas to Dragon Army had been a quite deliberate move on Harry’s part, Draco was certain. Three other former Chaotics had also been transferred to Dragon Army, and all were watching Draco hawklike to see if he offered the former Lieutenant the slightest insult.

Some might have called it sabotage, but Draco knew better. Harry had also sent Lieutenant Finnigan to the Sunshine Regiment, even though Professor Quirrell’s mandate had only required that Harry give up one Lieutenant. That too had been a deliberate move, making crystal clear to everyone that Harry wasn’t dumping his least-favoured soldiers.

In one sense, it might have been easier for Draco to win the true loyalties of his new soldiers if they’d thought Harry hadn’t wanted them. In another sense … well, it wasn’t easy to put into words. Harry had given him good soldiers with their pride intact, but it was more than that. Harry had showed kindliness toward his soldiers, but it was more than that. It wasn’t just Harry playing fair, it was something that … that you couldn’t help but contrast with the way the game was played in Slytherin House.

So Draco hadn’t offered the slightest insult to Mr Thomas, but brought him straight to his side, subordinate to himself and Padma but no one else. It was a test, Draco had told Mr Thomas and everyone, not a promotion. Mr Thomas would have to show himself worthy of rank within Dragon Army – but he would be given a chance, and the chance would be fair. Mr Thomas had looked surprised at the ceremony of it (the Chaos Legion, from what Draco had heard, didn’t stand on formality) but the Gryffindor boy had stood a little straighter, and nodded.

And then, after Mr Thomas had done well enough in one of Dragon Army’s training sessions, he’d been brought into the strategy session in Dragon Army’s huge military office. And a few minutes into the session, Padma had happened to ask – as though it was a perfectly normal question – whether Mr Thomas had any ideas about how to defeat the Chaos Legion.

The Gryffindor boy had said cheerfully that Harry had predicted that General Malfoy would get one of his soldiers to ask him that, and that Harry had given him the message that General Malfoy should ask himself where his relative advantage lay – what Draco Malfoy could do, or what Dragon Army could do, that the Chaos Legion couldn’t match – and then try to exploit it for all it was worth. Dean Thomas couldn’t think of what that advantage might be, but if he did come up with any ideas for beating Chaos, he’d share them. Harry had ordered him to, after all.

Sigh, Draco had thought, since he couldn’t actually sigh out loud. But it was good advice, and Draco had followed it, sitting at his bedroom desk with quill and parchment listing out everything that might be a relative advantage.

And, almost to Draco’s own surprise, he’d had an idea, a real one. In fact he’d had two.

The hollow bell sounded through the forest, somehow sounding more ominous than ever before. On the instant, the two pilots cried ‘Up!’ and leapt onto their broomsticks, heading into the grey sky.

Mr and Mrs Davis had now slumped slightly against each other, more from sheer muscle exhaustion than from any decrease of tension. Before them, the vast blank white parchment flickered with three great windows, as though holes had been cut through into the forest, showing three armies on the march. Lesser windows showed the six riders upon their broomsticks, and the corner of the parchment showed a view of the entire forest, with glowing dots to indicate armies and scouts.

The window into Sunshine showed General Granger and her Captains marching in the centre of the Sunshine Regiment, protected by Contego screens along with a number of other young witches. The Sunshine Regiment, the Defence Professor had remarked, knew well that it had now acquired a strong advantage in experienced soldiers, and it meant to protect those soldiers from a surprise attack. Aside from that, the Sunshine Soldiers were moving forward at a steady march, conserving their strength.

The soldiers in General Malfoy’s army, at least those with higher Transfiguration scores, were picking up leaves and Transfiguring them into … well, if you looked at Padma Patil, who was almost done with hers, it looked like her leaf was becoming a left-handed glove bearing a dangling strap. (The window had zoomed in to show this.)

Lord Jugson was watching the screen with a flat expression; his voice, when he spoke, seemed to ooze and drip with disdain. ‘What is your son doing, Lucius?’

The foreign-born witch who stood at Draco Malfoy’s right side had finished Transfiguring her glove, and was now bringing it before the Dragon General like a sacrifice.

‘I do not know,’ said Lucius Malfoy, his tone calm though no less aristocratic, ‘but I must trust that he has good reason for doing it.’

All Dragon Army stopped for a moment as Padma slid the glove over her left hand, strapped it in place, and presented it before Draco Malfoy; who also stopped in place, took several deep breaths, raised his wand, executed a precise set of eight movements and bellowed ‘Colloportus!’

The Dragon Warrior raised her gloved hand, flexed it, and gave a small bow to Draco Malfoy, who returned it more shallowly, though the Dragon General was staggering slightly. Padma then returned to her place at Draco’s side, and the Dragons began marching once more.

‘Well,’ remarked Augusta Longbottom. ‘I don’t suppose someone would care to explain?’ Amelia Bones was frowning slightly as she gazed at the screen.

‘For some reason or other,’ said the amused voice of Professor Quirrell, ‘it seems that the scion of Malfoy is able to cast surprisingly strong magic for a first-year student. Due to the purity of his blood, of course. Certainly the good Lord Malfoy would not have openly flouted the underage magic laws by arranging for his son to receive a wand before his acceptance into Hogwarts.’

‘I suggest you be careful in your implications, Quirrell,’ Lucius Malfoy said coldly.

‘Oh, I am,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘A Colloportus cannot be dispelled by Finite Incantatem; it requires an Alohomora of equal strength. Until then, a glove so Charmed will resist lesser material forces, deflect the Sleep Hex and the Stunning Hex. And as neither Mr Potter nor Miss Granger can cast a counter-spell powerful enough, that Charm is invincible upon this battlefield. It is not the original intent of the Charm, nor the intent of whoever taught Mr Malfoy an emergency spell for evading his enemies. But it would seem that Mr Malfoy has been learning creativity.’

Lucius Malfoy had straightened as the Defence Professor spoke; he now sat erect upon his cushioned bench, his head held perceptibly higher than before, and when he spoke it was with quiet pride. ‘He will be the greatest Lord Malfoy that has yet lived.’

‘Faint praise,’ Augusta Longbottom said under her breath; Amelia Bones chuckled, as did Mr Davis for a tiny, fatal fraction of a second before he stopped with a strangled gargle.

‘I quite agree,’ said Professor Quirrell, though it wasn’t clear to whom he spoke. ‘Unfortunately for Mr Malfoy, he is still new to the art of creativity, and so he has committed a classic error of Ravenclaw.’

‘And what might that be?’ said Lucius Malfoy, his voice now turned chill once more.

Professor Quirrell had leaned back in his seat, the pale blue eyes briefly unfocusing as one of the windows shifted its viewpoint within the greater screen, zooming in to show the sweat now on Draco Malfoy’s forehead. ‘It is such a beautiful idea that Mr Malfoy has quite overlooked its pragmatic difficulties.’

‘Would someone care to explain that?’ said Lady Greengrass. ‘Not all of us present are experts at such … affairs.’

Amelia Bones spoke, the old witch’s voice somewhat dry. ‘It will tempt them to try to catch hexes that they would be wiser to simply dodge. The more so, if they have had little practise catching them. And the casting of so many Charms will tire their strongest warrior.’

Professor Quirrell gave the DMLE Director a half-nod of acknowledgement. ‘As you say, Madam Bones. Mr Malfoy is new to the business of having ideas, and so when he has one, he becomes proud of himself for having it. He has not yet had enough ideas to unflinchingly discard those that are beautiful in some aspects and impractical in others; he has not yet acquired confidence in his own ability to think of better ideas as he requires them. What we are seeing here is not Mr Malfoy’s best idea, I fear, but rather his only idea.’

Lord Malfoy simply turned to watch the screens again, as though the Defence Professor had used up his right to exist.

‘But –’ said Lord Greengrass. ‘But what in Merlin’s name is Harry Potter –’

Sixteen remaining soldiers of the Chaos Legion – or fifteen plus Blaise Zabini, rather – marched confidently through the forest, their shoes thudding over the still-dry ground. Their camouflage uniforms blended into the forest even more than usual, all colours washed out by the tints of an overcast day.

Sixteen Chaos Legionnaires, against twenty-eight Dragon Warriors and twenty-eight Sunshine Soldiers.

The common consensus had been that, with odds that bad, it was practically impossible for them to lose. After all, General Chaos was bound to come up with something really spectacular, facing odds like that.

There was something almost nightmarish about how everyone seemed to now expect Harry to pull miracles out of his hat, on demand, any time one was needed. It meant that if you couldn’t do the impossible, you were disappointing your friends and failing to live up to your potential …

Harry hadn’t bothered complaining to Professor Quirrell about too much pressure. Harry’s mental model of the Defence Professor had predicted him looking severely annoyed, saying things along the lines of You are perfectly capable of solving this problem, Mr Potter; did you even try? and then deducting several hundred Quirrell points.

From above, from where two broomsticks watched their march, the high young voice of Tess Walsh cried ‘Friend!’ and after another moment, ‘Gingersnap!’

A handful of seconds later, the soldier who’d code-named herself Gingersnap returned bearing a double handful of acorns, sweating slightly in the cool but humid air from the jog that had taken her to the oak tree Neville had spotted. Gingersnap approached to where Shannon was holding a uniform-shirt with the neck tied off, in lieu of anyone having to Transfigure a bag. When Gingersnap brought her hands forward to try and dump her acorns into the holding-shirt, Chaotic Shannon, giggling, jerked the shirt to the right, then to the left again as Gingersnap made another effort to dump the acorns, until a sharp ‘Miss Friedman!’ from Lieutenant Nott caused Shannon to sigh and hold the shirt still. Gingersnap dumped her acorns into those accumulated, and then headed out for more.

Somewhere in the background, Ellie Knight was singing her very own version of the Chaos Legion’s marching song, and around half the other soldiers were trying to step along with it despite not knowing the tune in advance. Nearby, Nita Berdine, who had a high Transfiguration score, finished creating yet another pair of green sunglasses, and handed them to Adam Beringer, who folded up the sunglasses before tucking them into his uniform pocket. Other soldiers were already wearing their own green sunglasses, despite the cloudy day.

You might guess that there was some sort of incredibly complicated and fascinating explanation behind this, and you would be right.

Two days earlier Harry had been sitting amid his bookcases in the comfy rocking-chair he’d obtained for his trunk’s cavern level, pondering silently in the quiet span between classes and dinnertime, thinking about power.

For sixteen Chaotics to defeat twenty-eight Sunnies and twenty-eight Dragons they would need a force amplifier. There were limits to what you could do with manoeuvre. There had to be a secret weapon and it had to be invincible, or at least moderately unstoppable.

Muggle artifacts were now illegal in Hogwarts’s mock battles, banned by Ministry edict. And the trouble with finding some other clever and unusual spell was that an army twice your own size could brute-force Finite almost anything you tried. The Sunshine Regiment might have missed that tactic with the Transfigured chain mail, but nobody would miss it again now that Professor Quirrell had pointed it out. And Finite Incantatem was a brute-force counter-spell which required at least as much magic as the spell being cancelled … which, if you were severely outnumbered, made it a whole new order of military challenge. The enemy could Finite anything you tried, and still have enough magic left over for shields and volleys of Sleep Hexes.

Unless, somehow, you could invoke potencies beyond the ordinary strength of first-year Hogwarts students, something too powerful for the enemy to Finite.

So Harry had asked Neville if he’d ever heard of any small, safe sacrificial rituals –

And then, after the screaming and the shouting had subsided, after Harry had stopped trying to argue about Unbreakable Vows and just given up the whole thing as impossible from a public relations standpoint, Harry had realized that he hadn’t even needed to go there. They taught you how to invoke potencies far beyond your own strength in ordinary Hogwarts classes.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question.

Defence. Charms. Transfiguration. Potions. History of Magic. Astronomy. Broomstick Flying. Herbology …

‘Foe!’ screamed the voice from above.

It was a good thing that Neville Longbottom hadn’t the tiniest idea that his grandmother was watching; or he would’ve been more self-conscious about screaming scary battlecries at the top of his lungs while casting Luminos every three seconds as he rocketed through a dense forest of trees, hot on the tail of Gregory Goyle.

(‘But –’ Augusta Longbottom said, her expression showing almost as much astonishment as worry. ‘But Neville is afraid of heights!’)

(‘Not all fears last,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the great screen before them with a measuring gaze. ‘Or perhaps he has found courage. It is much the same, in the end.’)

A glimmer of red –

Neville dodged, very nearly into a tree but he did dodge; and then Neville somehow also managed to dodge almost all of the branches before they smacked him in the face.

Now Mr Goyle’s broomstick was pulling further and further away – even though the two of them were riding exactly the same broomstick and Mr Goyle weighed more, somehow Neville was still falling behind. So Neville slowed down, pulled back, angled up out of the forest and began to accelerate back toward where the Chaos Legion still marched.

Twenty seconds later – it hadn’t been a long chase, just an exciting one – Neville was back among his fellow Chaotics, and dismounted his broom to walk on the ground for a little bit.

‘Neville –’ said General Potter. Harry’s voice was a little distant, as he walked carefully and steadily through the forest, his wand still applied to the almost-finished Form of the object he was slowly Transfiguring. Beside him, Blaise Zabini, working a smaller version of the same Transfiguration, looked like a shambling Inferi as he stumbled forward. ‘I told you – Neville – you don’t have to –’

‘Yes, I do,’ said Neville. He looked down at where his fingers grasped the broomstick, and saw that not just his hands, but his whole arms were shaking. But unless anyone else in Chaos had been practising duelling for an hour a day with Mr Diggory, and then practising their aim in private for another hour afterwards, Neville was probably the best shot from a broomstick even after taking into account that he wasn’t a very good flyer.

‘Good show, Neville,’ Theodore said from where he was walking ahead of them all, leading the Chaos Legion forward through the forest while wearing only his under-shirt.

(Augusta Longbottom and Charles Nott exchanged brief astonished glances and then wrenched their gazes away from one another as though stung.)

Neville took a few deep breaths, trying to steady his hands, trying to think; Harry might not be good for deep strategic thinking while he was in the middle of an extended Transfiguration. ‘Lieutenant Nott, do you have any idea why Dragon Army just did that? They lost a broom –’ The Dragons had started the combat with a feint to provide a distraction for Mr Goyle’s approach through the forest; Neville hadn’t realized there were two brooms attacking until almost too late. But the Chaos Legion had got the other pilot. That was why broomsticks usually didn’t attack before armies met, it meant a whole army would concentrate fire on the broomstick. ‘And the Dragons didn’t even get anyone, did they?’

‘Nope!’ Tracey Davis said proudly. She too was now marching by General Potter’s side, her wand gripped low and watchful as her eyes scanned the surrounding forest. ‘I threw up a Prismatic Sphere like a split second before Mr Goyle’s hex got Zabini, and the way Mr Goyle had his other arm stretched out I think he planned to knock down the General, too.’ The Slytherin witch smiled with vicious confidence. ‘Mr Goyle tried a Breaking Drill Hex, but learned to his dismay that his weak magic was no match for my newfound dark powers, hahahaha!’

Some Chaotics laughed with her, but a queasy sensation was starting in Neville’s stomach as he realized how close the Chaos Legion had come to complete disaster. If Mr Goyle had managed to disrupt both Transfigurations –

‘Report!’ snapped the Dragon General, doing his best to conceal the fatigue he felt after casting seventeen Locking Charms, with more yet to come.

Beads of sweat now dotted Gregory’s forehead. ‘The enemy downed Dylan Vaughan,’ Gregory said formally. ‘Harry Potter and Blaise Zabini were each Transfiguring something dark-grey and roundish, I don’t think it was finished but it looked like it would be big and hollow, sort of cauldron-shaped. Zabini’s was smaller than Potter’s. I couldn’t get either of them or disrupt their Transfigurations, Tracey Davis blocked me. Neville Longbottom is on a broomstick and he’s still a terrible flyer but his aim is really good.’

Draco listened, frowning, and then he glanced at Padma and Dean Thomas, who both shook their own heads, indicating that they also couldn’t think of what might be big and grey and shaped like a cauldron.

‘Anything else?’ said Draco. If that was it, they’d lost a broom for nothing –

‘The only other weird thing I saw,’ Gregory said, sounding puzzled, ‘was that some Chaotics were wearing … sort of like goggles?’

Draco thought about this, not noticing that he’d stopped marching or that all of Dragon Army had automatically stopped with him.

‘Was there anything special about the goggles?’ Draco said.

‘Um …’ Gregory said. ‘They were … greenish, maybe?’

‘Okay,’ said Draco. Again without thinking, he began walking once more and his Dragons followed. ‘Here’s our new strategy. We’re only going to send eleven Dragons against the Chaos Legion, not fourteen. That should be enough to beat them, now that we can neutralize their special advantage.’ It was a gamble, but you had to take gambles sometimes, if you wanted to come in first in a three-way battle.

‘You figured out Chaos’s plan, General Malfoy?’ said Mr Thomas with considerable surprise.

‘What are they doing?’ said Padma.

‘I haven’t the faintest idea,’ said Draco, with a smirk of the most refined smugness. ‘We’ll just do the obvious thing.’

Harry, having now finished his cauldron, was carefully scooping acorns into the container while the scouts searched for a nearby source of water that could be used as a liquid base. They’d come across frequent sinkholes and miniature creeks in the forest before, so it ought not to take long. Another scout had brought a straight stick that would serve as a stirrer, so Harry didn’t have to Transfigure one.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

How can I invoke magical powers that ought to be beyond the reach of first-year students?

There was a cautionary tale the Potions Master had told them (with much sneers and laughter to make the stupidity seem low-status instead of daring and romantic) about a second-year witch in Beauxbatons who’d stolen some extremely restricted and expensive ingredients, and tried to brew Polyjuice, so she could borrow the form of another girl for purposes better left unmentioned. Only she’d managed to contaminate the potion with cat hairs, and then instead of seeking a healer immediately, the witch had hidden herself in a bathroom, hoping the effects would just wear off; and when she’d finally been found, it had been too late to reverse the transformation completely, condemning her to a life of despair as a sort of cat-girl hybrid.

Harry hadn’t realized what that meant until the instant of thinking the right question – but what that implied was that a young wizard or witch could do things with Potions-Making that they couldn’t even come close to doing with Charms. Polyjuice was one of the most potent potions known … but what made Polyjuice a N.E.W.T.-level potion, apparently, wasn’t the required age before you had enough magical power; it was how difficult the potion was to brew precisely and what happened to you if you messed up.

Nobody in any army had tried brewing any potions up until then. But Professor Quirrell would let you get away with nearly anything, if it was something you could also have done in a real war. Cheating is technique, the Defence Professor had once lectured them. Or rather, cheating is what the losers call technique, and will be worth extra Quirrell points when executed successfully. In principle, there was nothing unrealistic about Transfiguring a couple of cauldrons and brewing potions out of whatever came to hand, if you had enough time before the armies met.

So Harry had retrieved his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions, and begun looking for a safe but useful potion he could brew in the minutes before the battle started – a potion which would win the battle too fast for counter-spells, or produce spell effects too strong for first-years to Finite.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

What potion can I brew using only components gathered from an ordinary forest?

Every recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions used at least one ingredient from a magical plant or animal. Which was unfortunate, because all the magical plants and animals were in the Forbidden Forest, not the safer and lesser woods where battles were held.

Someone else might have given up at that point.

Harry had turned the pages from one recipe to another, skimming faster and faster in dawning realization, confirming what he had already read and was now seeing for the first time.

Every single Potions recipe seemed to demand at least one magical ingredient, but why should that be true?

Charms required no material components at all; you just said the words and waved your wand. Harry had been thinking about Potions-Making as essentially analogous: instead of your spoken syllables triggering a spell effect for no comprehensible reason, you collected a batch of disgusting ingredients and stirred four times clockwise, and that arbitrarily triggered a spell effect.

In which case, given that most potions used ordinary components like porcupine quills or stewed slugs, you’d expect to see some potions using only ordinary components.

But instead every single recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions demanded at least one component from a magical plant or animal – an ingredient like silk from an Acromantula or petals from a Venus Fire Trap.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

If making a potion is like casting a Charm, why don’t I fall over from exhaustion after brewing a draught as powerful as boil-curing?

The Friday before last, Harry’s double Potions class had brewed potion of boil-curing … although even the most trivial healing Charms, if you tried to cast them with wand and incantation, were at least fourth-year spells. And afterwards, they’d all felt the way they usually felt after Potions class, namely, not magically exhausted to any discernible degree.

Harry had shut his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions with a snap, and rushed down to the Ravenclaw common room. Harry had found a seventh-year Ravenclaw doing his N.E.W.T. potions homework and paid the older boy a Sickle to borrow Moste Potente Potions for five minutes; because Harry hadn’t wanted to run all the way to the library to find confirmation.

After skimming through five recipes in the seventh-year book, Harry had read the sixth recipe, for a potion of fire breathing, which required Ashwinder eggs … and the book warned that the resulting fire could be no hotter than the magical fire which had spawned the Ashwinder which had laid the eggs.

Harry had shouted ‘Eureka!’ right in the middle of the Ravenclaw common room, and been severely rebuked by a nearby prefect, who’d thought Mr Potter was trying to cast a spell. Nobody in the wizarding world knew or cared about some ancient Muggle named Archimedes, nor the ur-physicist’s realization that the water displaced from a bathtub would equal the volume of the object entering the bathtub …

Conservation laws. They’d been the critical insight in more Muggle discoveries than Harry could easily count. In Muggle technology you couldn’t raise a feather one metre off the ground without the power coming from somewhere. If you looked at molten lava spilling from a volcano and asked where the heat came from, a physicist would tell you about radioactive heavy metals in the centre of the Earth’s molten core. If you asked where the energy to power the radioactivity came from, the physicist would point to an era before the Earth had formed, and a primordial supernova in the early days of the galaxy which had baked atomic nuclei heavier than the natural limit, the supernova compressing protons and neutrons into a tight unstable package that yielded back some of the supernova’s energy when it split. A light bulb was fuelled by electricity, fuelled by a nuclear power plant, fuelled by a supernova … You could play the game all the way back to the Big Bang.

Magic did not appear to work like this, to put it mildly. Magic’s attitude toward laws like Conservation of Energy was somewhere between a giant extended middle finger, and a shrug of total indifference. Aguamenti created water out of nothingness, so far as anyone knew; there was no known lake whose water level went down each time. That was a simple fifth-year spell, not considered impressive by wizards, because creating a mere glass of water didn’t seem amazing to them. They didn’t have the wacky notion that mass ought to be conserved, or that creating a gram of mass was somehow equivalent to creating 90,000,000,000,000 joules of energy. There was an upper-year spell Harry had run across whose literal incantation was Arresto Momentum! and when Harry had asked if the momentum went anywhere else he’d just got a puzzled look. Harry had kept an increasingly desperate eye out for some kind of conservation principle in magic, anywhere whatsoever …

… and the whole time it had been right in front of him in every Potions class. Potions-Making didn’t create magic, it preserved magic, that was why every potion needed at least one magical ingredient. And by following instructions like stir four times anticlockwise and once clockwise – Harry had hypothesized – you were doing something like casting a small spell that reshaped the magic in the ingredients. (And unbound the physical form so that ingredients like porcupine quills dissolved smoothly into a drinkable liquid; Harry strongly suspected that a Muggle following exactly the same recipe would end up with nothing but a spiny mess.) That was what Potions-Making really was, the art of transforming existing magical essences. So you were a little tired after Potions class, but not much, because you weren’t empowering the potions yourself, you were just reshaping magic that was already there. And that was why a second-year witch could brew Polyjuice, or at least get close.

Harry had kept scanning through Moste Potente Potions, looking for something that might disprove his shiny new theory. After five minutes he’d flipped the older boy another Sickle (over his protests) and kept going.

The potion of giant strength required a Re’em to trample the mashed Dugbogs you stirred into the potion. It was odd, Harry had realized after a moment, because crushed Dugbogs weren’t strong themselves, they were just … very, very crushed after the Re’em got through with them.

Another recipe said to touch with forged bronze, i.e., grasp a Knut in pliers so you could skim the potion’s surface; and if you dropped the Knut all the way in, the book warned, the potion would instantly superheat and boil over the cauldron.

Harry had stared at the recipes and their warnings, forming a second and stranger hypothesis. Of course it wouldn’t be as simple as Potions-Making using magical potentials imbued in the ingredients, like Muggle cars fuelled by the combustion potential of gasoline. Magic would never be as sensible as that …

And then Harry had gone to Professor Flitwick – since he didn’t want to approach Professor Snape outside of class – and Harry had told Professor Flitwick that he wanted to invent a new potion, and he knew what the ingredients ought to be and what the potion should do, but he didn’t know how to deduce the required stirring pattern –

After Professor Flitwick had stopped screaming in horror and running in little circles, and Professor McGonagall had been called into the ensuing fierce interrogation to promise Harry that in this case it was both acceptable and important for him to reveal his underlying theory, it had developed that Harry had not made an original magical discovery, but rediscovered a law so ancient that nobody knew who had first formulated it:

A potion spends that which is invested in the creation of its ingredients.

The heat of goblin forges that had cast the bronze Knut, the Re’em’s strength that had crushed the Dugbogs, the magical fire that had spawned the Ashwinder: all these potencies could be recalled, unlocked, and restructured by the spell-like process of stirring the ingredients in exact patterns.

(From a Muggle standpoint it was just odd, a deranged version of thermodynamics invented by someone who thought life ought to be fair. From a Muggle standpoint, the heat expended in forging the Knut hadn’t gone into the bronze, the heat had left and dissipated into the environment, becoming permanently less available. Energy was conserved, could be neither created nor destroyed; entropy always increased. But wizards didn’t think that way: from their perspective, if you’d put some amount of work into making a Knut, it stood to reason that you could get exactly the same work back out. Harry had tried to explain why this sounded a bit odd if you’d been raised by Muggles, and Professor McGonagall had asked bemusedly why the Muggle perspective was any better than the wizarding one.)

The fundamental principle of Potions-Making had no name and no standard phrasing, since then you might be tempted to write it down.

And someone who wasn’t wise enough to figure out the principle themselves might read it.

And they would start having all sorts of bright ideas for inventing new Potions.

And then they would be turned into cat-girls.

It had been made very clear to Harry that he wasn’t going to be sharing this particular discovery with Neville, or Hermione either after the next armies’ battle. Harry had tried to say something about Hermione seeming really off lately and this being just the sort of thing that might cheer her up. Professor McGonagall had said flatly that he wasn’t even to think it, and Professor Flitwick had raised his little hands and made a gesture as of snapping a wand in half.

Although the two Professors had been kind enough to suggest that if Mr Potter thought he knew what the potion’s ingredients should be, he might be able to find an already-existing recipe that did the same thing; and Professor Flitwick had mentioned several volumes in the Hogwarts library that might be useful …

The vast parchment-like screen now showed only an aerial view of the forest, from which you could barely make out the camouflaged forms of three armies, split up into two groups each, converging to fight their three-way battle.

The benches of the Quidditch stadium were now rapidly filling up with the more easily bored sort of spectator who only wanted to be there for the final battle and skip out on all the boring points along the way. (If there was anything wrong with Professor Quirrell’s battles, it was widely agreed, it was that his spectacles didn’t last nearly as long as Quidditch matches, once they actually started. To this Professor Quirrell had replied only, Such is realism, and that had been that.)

Within the huge window – it was all one window now, observing from a great height – the vague collections of tiny camouflaged forms grew closer.

Closer.

Almost touching –

The vast white parchment window showed the first touch of battle between Sunshine and Chaos, a screaming mass of running children with smiley-faces upon their breasts, charging forward with Contego shields held high and others shouting ‘Somnium!’ –

Until one of their number shrieked ‘Prismatis!’ in a terrified voice and the entire charge came to a sudden halt before the sparkling wall of force that had appeared in front of them.

Tracey Davis had walked out from behind the trees.

‘That’s right,’ said Tracey, her voice low and grim as she levelled her wand on the barrier. ‘You should fear me. For I am Tracey Davis, the Darke Lady! That’s Darke Lady spelled D-A-R-K-E, with an E!’

(Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement, was sending an inquiring look at Mr and Mrs Davis, both of whom looked like they would have dearly loved to die on the spot.)

Behind the Prismatic Barrier, there was some kind of hushed argument taking place among the Sunshine Soldiers, one of whom in particular seemed to be getting scolded by several of the others.

Then, a moment later, Tracey flinched.

Susan Bones had come to the front of the Sunshine contingent.

(‘Goodness,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘What do you suppose your grand-niece has been learning at Hogwarts?’)

(‘I don’t know,’ Amelia Bones said calmly, ‘but I shall owl her a Chocolate Frog and instructions to learn more of it.’)

The Prismatic Barrier vanished.

The Sunshine Soldiers resumed their charge forward.

Tracey yelled, her voice high with strain, ‘Inflammare!’ and the Sunshine charge came to another sudden halt as a line of fire blazed up between them in the half-dry grass, extending to follow the path of Tracey’s wand as she pointed it; an instant later Susan Bones cried ‘Finite Incantatem!’ and the flames dimmed, brightened, dimmed in the contest of their wills, other soldiers raising their wards to aim at Tracey; and that was when Neville Longbottom plunged shrieking out of the sky.

One of the Dragon Warriors, Raymond Arnold, made a hand-sign, pointing forward and oblique left; and there was a sudden hushed hiss of whispers among the Dragon Army contingent as they all quietly reoriented themselves in the direction of the enemy. The Sunnies knew they were there, of course both armies knew; but somehow, in this moment, they had all become instinctively quiet.

The Dragons crept forward further, and then further, the dull camouflaged forms of the Sunnies beginning to appear among the distant trees, and still nobody spoke, nobody bellowed the call to charge.

Draco was now at the forefront of his soldiers, Vincent behind him and Padma only a shade further back; if the three of them could take the shock of Sunshine’s best, the rest of Dragon Army might stand a chance.

Then Draco saw one Sunnie staring at him from the distance, in the vanguard of her own army; staring at him with a look of fury –

Across the forest battleground, their eyes met.

Draco had only a fraction of a second to wonder, in the back of his mind, what Hermione Granger was so angry about, before the shout went up from both their armies; and they were all running forward to the charge.

The other Chaotics had appeared now from among the trees, some had dropped out of trees, and the battle was in full force now, everyone firing in every direction at anything that looked like an enemy. Plus a number of Sunnies crying ‘Luminos!’ at Neville Longbottom as the Chaos Hufflepuff twisted and rocketed up through the air on courses that could only be described as, indeed, ‘chaotic’ –

And it happened, the way it happened only one time out of twenty in mock aerial combat, that Neville Longbottom’s broomstick glowed bright red beneath his clenched hands.

It should’ve meant that Longbottom was out of the game.

Then, in the Hogwarts stands, among the watching crowds of students, a scream went up –

Combat realism. It was Professor Quirrell’s one master rule. You could get away with anything if it was realistic, and in real life, a soldier didn’t just vanish when their broomstick got hit by a curse.

Neville was falling toward the ground and screaming ‘Chaotic landing!’ and the Chaotics were wrenching their attention away from fights to cast the Hover Charm (and run at the same time so they wouldn’t be sitting ducks), almost everyone else stopping to gape –

And Neville Longbottom slammed into the leaf-laden forest ground, landing on one knee, one foot, and both hands, as though he were kneeling down to be knighted.

Everything stopped. Even Tracey and Susan paused in their duel.

In the stadium, all crowd noises vanished.

There was a universal silence composed of astonishment, concern, and sheer dumbstruck gaping awe, as everyone waited to see what would happen next.

And then Neville Longbottom slowly rose to his feet, and levelled his wand at the Sunshine Soldiers.

Though nobody on the battlefield heard it, a large segment of the stadium audience had begun chanting, in steadily rising notes each time the word was uttered, ‘doom doom doom doom doom’, because you just couldn’t see that and not think it required musical accompaniment.

‘The crowd is cheering your grandson,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the screen with a measuring look.

‘So they are,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘Some, if I hear correctly, are cheering, Our blood for Neville! Our souls for Neville!’

‘Quite,’ said Amelia, taking a sip from a teacup which had not been there moments earlier. ‘It shows the lad has leadership potential.’

‘These cheers,’ continued Augusta, her voice taking on an even more stunned quality, ‘seem to be coming from the Hufflepuff benches.’

‘It is the House of the loyal, my dear,’ said Amelia.

‘Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore! What in Merlin’s name has been happening in this school?’

Lucius Malfoy was watching the screens with an ironic smile, his fingers tapping at his armrest in no discernible pattern. ‘I do not know what is more frightening, the thought that he has some hidden plan behind all this, or the thought that he does not.’

‘Look!’ cried the Lord of Greengrass. The dapper young man had risen half out of his chair, pointing his finger at the screen. ‘There she goes!’

‘We’ll both take him at once,’ Daphne whispered. She knew that a few fear-filled minutes of real combat experience, a handful of times each week, might not be enough to match Neville’s regular duelling practise with Harry and Cedric Diggory over the same period. ‘He’s too much for one of us, but both of us together – I’ll use my Charm, you just try to stun him –’

Hannah, beside her, nodded, and then they both screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward, the Hover Charms of two supporting Sunshine Soldiers moving them faster and making them light on their feet, Daphne already crying ‘Tonare!’ even as Hannah kept a huge Contego shield moving in front of them, and with a brief extra lift they leapt over the heads of the front screen of soldiers and landed in front of Neville with their hair billowing high around them –

(Photographs were strictly prohibited at all Hogwarts games, but somehow this moment still ended up on the front page of the next day’s Quibbler.)

– and in the same instant, because fighting older bullies had burned away the slightest traces of hesitation, Hannah fired her first Sleep Hex at Neville (she’d started the incantation while she was still in the air) even as Daphne, concentrating more on speed than on force, slashed down with her Ancient Blade at where she thought Neville’s thighs would be after he dodged –

But Neville leapt up, not sideways, leapt up higher than he should’ve been able to go, so that her glowing sword cut only the air beneath his feet. Somehow Daphne realized what it meant, that Neville still had other Chaotics Hovering him, in time for her to raise her Blade up over her head, but Neville fell too fast and when his Blade smashed into hers it was like being hit by a Bludger. It knocked Daphne off her feet and sent her sprawling backward onto the grass, hitting the ground hard on her back. It might have been all over for her, then, if Neville hadn’t landed too hard himself and gone to his knees with a pained gasp. And then before Neville could bring his glowing Blade down, Hannah shouted ‘Somnium!’ and Neville lurched frantically backward – though of course no spell had actually come from Hannah’s wand, the Hufflepuff girl couldn’t really have fired again that fast – which gave Daphne a second to scramble to her feet and get both hands around her wand again –

‘Dear Merlin,’ said Lady Greengrass. Her voice seemed unsteady, the aristocratic poise well-punctured. ‘My daughter is fighting with the Charm of the Most Ancient Blade. In her first year. I never knew she possessed – such extraordinary talent –’

‘Excellent blood,’ Charles Nott said approvingly, causing Augusta to snort.

‘My good Lady,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding grave. ‘Do not wrong your daughter so. That is not mere talent which you see.’ His voice grew a little dryer. ‘Rather, it is what happens when children put their competitive efforts into a game which involves actual spell-casting.’

‘Expelliarmus!’ shouted Draco, trying not to let his voice crack as he simultaneously dodged the blazing red stunbolt that Hermione Granger had fired at him, his muscles twisting with the need to dodge in the wrong direction – she’d pointed to his left, and then with a mysterious twitch fired right –

Hermione dodged the fast-moving duelling hex, and cried with hardly another moment’s pause, ‘Steleus!’, a wide-angle Hex that Draco couldn’t avoid, but he managed to point his wand at his own face and cry ‘Quiescus!’ before the sudden urge to inhale could devolve into a sneezing fit that would’ve ended the battle.

Draco Malfoy was already half-exhausted from all the Locking Charms and Transfigurations earlier, but his confusion was beginning to give way to a sense of his own blood boiling, he didn’t know why Granger was attacking him so angrily all of a sudden, but if she wanted a fight he’d give her one –

(The Dragons and Sunnies weren’t stopping to watch the duel of their Generals, the Dragons were too disciplined to stop and watch and that meant the Sunnies had to go on fighting too; but the gaping audience in the Hogwarts Quidditch stands were being distracted even from Neville and Daphne’s spectacle, shifting their eyes to the duel of two Generals as Malfoy and Granger fired hex after hex and jinx after jinx at each other, casting more rapidly than any other student in their year could have managed, the Dragon General’s trained duelling dance matched by the Sunshine General’s frantic energy, the combat between them beginning to resemble an adult duel as the two most magically powerful first-years resorted to spells more exotic than the usual Sleep Hex.)

– although, Draco was beginning to realize, when he and Harry and Professor Quirrell had dismissed Miss Granger as having as much intent to kill as a bowl of wet grapes, they’d never seen her angry.

Daphne lashed out with her Ancient Blade, again not trying to hit hard but just moving the Blade as fast as possible, at the same time Hannah cried ‘Somnium!’ and Neville leapt back again, but it had been another bluff and Hannah was moving in to fire a real spell almost point-blank –

– and Neville Longbottom did exactly what – he would explain afterwards – Cedric Diggory had trained him to do if he was fighting Bellatrix Black, which was to spin around and kick Hannah really hard in the pit of her stomach.

The Hufflepuff girl made a sad little sound, a gasping cry of pain, as she was knocked off her feet by the hard shoe sinking into her abdomen with the force of Neville’s whole body behind it.

For an instant the battlefield stood still, everything halted except Hannah’s falling form.

Then Neville’s face turned to absolute dismay and he lowered his wand, the Chaotic Lieutenant starting instinctively toward his House-mate as he reached for her with his other hand –

Even as Hannah turned her fall into a roll and came out with her wand raised and shot him.

A fractional second later, Daphne, who hadn’t hesitated either, sank her Most Ancient Blade squarely into Neville’s back, causing the Chaotic Lieutenant’s muscles to jerk convulsively with the stunning magic discharging into him even as Hannah’s Sleep Hex took effect, and then the last scion of Longbottom was sprawled still on the ground with a look of total surprise frozen to his face.

‘Today Mr Longbottom has learned a valuable lesson about his feelings of pity and remorse,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘And chivalry,’ said Amelia, sipping her tea again.

‘Are you all right?’ whispered Daphne, as she stood protectively over where Hannah lay on the ground clutching her stomach. The girl didn’t give anything back in reply except more retching sounds that sounded like Hannah was trying not to throw up while trying not to cry.

Somehow, even though it might not have been good tactics – it would’ve been better if Hannah had been hexed outright, than for other soldiers to be tied up protecting her – a number of Sunnies seemed to be standing in front of Hannah with their wands clutched tightly, staring angrily at the Chaotics. Someone had thrown up a Prismatic barrier between the two groups, Daphne couldn’t see who.

And for some reason the Chaotics didn’t seem to be pressing the attack. Even Tracey had completely dropped the grim look on her face and was shifting her weight nervously from one foot to another, as though she was having trouble remembering which side she was on –

‘Hold!’ shouted a voice. ‘Hold battle!’

There wasn’t much battle going on anyway, but it held.

General Potter, looking every inch the Boy-Who-Lived, strode out from the trees with something large and camouflage-cloth-covered held under one arm.

‘Is Miss Abbott breathing all right?’ General Potter yelled.

Daphne didn’t look back. She didn’t trust that this wasn’t a trap – it was absolutely certain that if the Chaotics took the opportunity to attack, Professor Quirrell would not only rule it legal but also award them extra points afterwards. But Daphne could hear the answer well enough with her ears, it wasn’t like Hannah was trying to breathe quietly, and so she said, ‘Sort of.’

‘She should get out of here and to someone who can use healing Charms,’ Harry said. ‘Just in case that broke something.’

From behind Daphne, a small gasping voice said, ‘I – can – still – fight –’

‘Miss Abbott, don’t –’ Harry said, just as there was the sound from behind Daphne of someone collapsing back to the grass after trying and failing to get to her feet. Everyone winced, but Daphne didn’t turn her back on Harry.

‘Why haven’t the teachers stopped the battle?’ said Susan, her voice angry.

‘I expect it’s because Miss Abbott is in no danger of permanent damage and Professor Quirrell thinks we’re learning valuable lessons,’ Harry said in a hard voice. ‘Look, Miss Abbott, if you go, Tracey will also retire from the battle. You already outnumber us, so that’s a very good deal for your side. Please take it.’

‘Hannah, just go!’ said Daphne. ‘I mean, just say you’re out!’

When Daphne glanced back she saw that Hannah was shaking her head, still curled up in a ball on the grass.

‘Oh, screw this,’ said Harry. ‘Chaotics! The faster we stun them, the faster she’s out of here! We’re going to do this very quickly, even if we take casualties! End truce! Tunafish!’

Daphne’s political hindbrain had only an instant to admire how Harry’s few words had just made the Chaotics the good guys, and then in almost perfect unison, the Chaotics were plunging their hands into the pockets of their uniforms and drawing out green sunglasses in an unfamiliar style. Not like anything you would wear to the beach, more like goggles for advanced Potions –

Then Daphne realized what was about to happen and snapped up her other hand to shield her eyes, just as Harry ripped the cloth off the cauldron.

The fluid that spilled forth as Harry Potter threw the cauldron’s contents into the air was too bright to be seen, too brilliant to be imagined, incandescent like the Sun magnified a dozen times –

(which was exactly what it was)

(the sunlight which had been invested to create the acorns, the bright energy that had fuelled a tree rising up from the bare dirt)

(blazing a searing purple, the colour of the mixed blue and red wavelengths that chlorophyll absorbed)

(with almost none of the green wavelengths that chlorophyll reflected to create the green colour of leaves)

(which was the colour of the Chaos Legion’s sunglasses, made to pass through green wavelengths, blocking red and blue, reducing even the most incandescent purple glare to something bearable)

– the violet light blazed on and on, Daphne tried dropping her arm from her eyes but found that she couldn’t look directly at anything, even the second-hand purple glare was so bright she had to squint; and she had only time to cry one Finite Incantatem, which didn’t work, before a Sleep Hex took her.

What was left of the battle didn’t take very long after that.

‘Now!’ bellowed Blaise Zabini, formerly of Sunshine, now commanding a detachment of Chaos Legionnaires. ‘I mean, Tunafish!’ The Slytherin boy’s hand grasped the cloth shielding the cauldron from the triggering touch of daylight, already beginning to move it aside.

‘Now!’ bellowed Dean Thomas, formerly of Chaos, commanding a consignment of Dragon Warriors. ‘Do whatever they do!’

The Chaotics of Zabini’s detachment plunged their hands into their uniform pockets, and came forth bearing green sunglasses –

– an action almost perfectly mirrored by Dean and the Dragon Warriors, who drew forth green-coloured Potions goggles, and quickly drew the straps over their own heads, even as the Chaotics put on their sunglasses and the violet incandescence blasted forth.

(As General Malfoy had explained, if Mr Goyle reported that the Chaos Legion was wearing green-coloured Potions goggles, you didn’t have to know why to Transfigure some copies.)

‘That’s cheating!’ shrieked Blaise Zabini.

‘That’s technique!’ Dean yelled back. ‘Dragons, charge!’

(‘Pardon me,’ the Lady Greengrass said. ‘Could you stop laughing like that, Mr Quirrell? It’s unnerving.’)

‘Finite their goggles!’ shouted Blaise Zabini, as the two armies ran headlong toward each other through omnipresent eye-searing purple glare. ‘We can still win!’

‘You heard him!’ bellowed Dean. ‘Get their glasses!’

Blaise Zabini’s reply to this wasn’t anything articulate.

That battle went on a lot longer.

‘Stupefy!’ shrieked the Sunshine General.

Draco didn’t dodge, he didn’t counter, he didn’t have enough energy left for either, all he could do was whip his left hand into position and hope –

The red stunbolt dissipated again on Draco’s Colloportused glove, which he’d Transfigured and spell-locked to his hand the same as the rest of Dragon Army. It was all that was saving him now, that shield.

It should have been a time to counter-attack, but Draco could only catch his breath, as the two of them danced backward and forward beneath the trees in the never-ending movements of their duel. Across from him, General Granger was panting hard, the young girl’s face glistening with sweat like dew, her chestnut hair wetted into brown plaits. Her camouflage uniform was stained with damp spots, her shoulders visibly trembling with exhaustion, but her wand was still steel-steady where it stayed level on Draco through all their motion. Her eyes glaring, her cheeks flushed with rage.

So, little girl, why’re you pretending to fight like a grown-up today?

The taunt came to mind, but he didn’t really think he needed Granger any angrier; so instead Draco just said – though he could hear his own voice cracking – ‘Any reason you’re feeling mad at me, Granger?’

The girl was gasping for breath herself, her own voice wobbling as she spoke. ‘I know what you’re up to,’ said Hermione Granger, her voice rising. ‘I know what you and Snape are up to, Malfoy, and I know who’s behind it!’

‘Huh?’ Draco said without even thinking about it.

That only seemed to increase Granger’s fury, and her fingers whitened on the wand she held levelled on him.

And then Draco got it, and it boiled his own blood in his veins. Even she thought he was secretly plotting against her –

‘You too?’ Draco yelled. ‘I helped you, you bucktoothed bint! You, you, you,’ – stuttering past all the Dark curses that came to mind until he found something he could actually cast at her – ‘Densaugeo!’

But Granger flashed and whirled around the Tooth-Lengthening Hex, and then her own wand came around and levelled at almost point-blank range, even as Draco brought up his left hand like a shield, placing the magic-locked glove between himself and whatever she was about to fire, and the Sunshine General’s own voice rose to a shriek audible across the whole battleground –

‘Alohomora!’

Time should have paused.

But it didn’t.

Instead the padlock clicked and fell off the glove.

Just like that.

Just like that.

The screens showed it all very clearly, to the entire watching Hogwarts stadium.

And the bone-dead-silent hush that fell over every bench in every stand said that everyone understood quite clearly what it meant, that the scion of House Malfoy had just had his magic overcome by a Muggleborn.

Hermione Granger didn’t pause in her fight, gave no sign that she even knew what she’d done; instead her foot snapped out in a Muggle-style kick that knocked Draco’s wand cleanly out of his hand, his shocked mind and body moving just a little too slowly. Draco dove after his wand, scrabbling frantically on the ground, but from behind him a girl’s cracking voice said ‘Somnium!’ and Draco Malfoy fell and didn’t rise again.

There was another moment of frozen silence. The Sunshine General was wobbling on her feet, looking like she might faint.

Then the Dragon Warriors screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward to avenge their fallen commander.

Mr and Mrs Davis were shaking as they stood up from the comfortable chairs of the faculty Quidditch box; they couldn’t quite clutch each other while walking, but they held hands tightly, pretending hard to be invisible. If they’d been children young enough for accidental magic they probably would’ve spontaneously Disillusioned themselves.

The elderly Charles Nott said nothing as he stood from his chair. The scarred Lord Jugson said nothing, as he stood from his own chair.

Lucius Malfoy said nothing as he stood.

All three of them turned without pause and strode toward the stairwell of the elevated stands, moving in eerie unison like an Auror trio –

‘Lord Malfoy,’ the Defence Professor said in mild tones. That man was still seated in his own chair, looking upon his parchment-like screens, arms limp at his side, as though for some reason he didn’t feel like moving.

The white-haired man halted just before reaching the exit archway, and the elderly man and the scarred man halted as well, flanking him. Lord Malfoy’s head turned, too slightly to be any form of acknowledgement, but in the Defence Professor’s direction.

‘Your son performed exceptionally well today,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I must confess that I underestimated him. And he has earned his army’s loyalty, as you have witnessed.’ Still very mild, the Defence Professor’s voice. ‘Speaking as your son’s teacher, it is my opinion that he will not benefit if you interfere in his –’

Lord Malfoy and his compatriots vanished down the stairs.

‘A fine try, Quirinus,’ Dumbledore said quietly. The old wizard’s face showed small lines of worry; he hadn’t risen from his own seat either, staring at the parchment screens as though they were still active. ‘Do you think he will listen?’

The Defence Professor’s shoulders twitched in a slight shrug, the only movement they’d shown since the battle ended.

‘Well,’ said the Lady Greengrass, as she rose up and cracked her knuckles, stretching, her husband silent beside her. ‘I must say, that was quite … interesting …’

Amelia Bones had risen from her own cushioned seat without any fuss. ‘Interesting indeed,’ said Director Bones. ‘I do confess, I find myself disturbed by the skill with which those children were fighting one another.’

‘The skill?’ Lord Greengrass said. ‘Their spells didn’t seem all that impressive to me. Except for Daphne’s, of course.’

The old witch did not move her eyes from where she was gazing at the Defence Professor’s balding head. ‘The Stunning Hex is not a first-year spell, Lord Greengrass, but that is not the skill I had in mind. They supported each other with those simple spells, they reacted at speed to surprises …’ The Director of the DMLE paused, as though searching for words that a mere civilian could understand. ‘In the midst of battle,’ she said finally, ‘with spells flying in every direction … those children seemed quite at home.’

‘Indeed, Director Bones,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Some arts are best begun in youth.’

The old witch’s eyes narrowed. ‘You are readying them to become a military force, Professor. To what end?’

‘Now hold on!’ interjected Lord Greengrass. ‘There’s plenty of schools where they teach duelling in first year!’

‘Duelling?’ said the Defence Professor. From behind it wasn’t visible if the pale face was smiling. ‘That is nothing, Lord Greengrass, to what my students have learned. They have learned not to hesitate in the face of ambushes and greater foes. They have learned to adapt when combat conditions change and change again. They have learned to protect their allies, to protect more those who are more valuable, to abandon pieces which cannot be rescued. They have learned that to survive they must follow orders. Some have even learned a little creativity. Oh, no, Lord Greengrass, these wizards will not hide in their manors and wait to be protected, when the next threat comes. They will know that they know how to fight.’

Augusta Longbottom loudly clapped her hands together three times.

We won.

It was the first thing Draco heard when he woke up on the battlefield, Padma telling him how his soldiers had rallied after he fell. How, thanks to the Dragon General’s foresight, Mr Thomas had led his detachment to victory over Chaos. How General Potter had defeated the portion of the Sunshine Regiment that clashed with him. How Mr Thomas’s Dragon Warriors had rejoined the main body of soldiers bearing both their own goggles and the sunglasses of the defeated Chaotics. How, only moments later, General Potter’s remaining contingent had attacked both other armies with a potion that emitted searing purple light. But Dragon had held the numerical advantage over Sunshine and Chaos both, and enough sunglasses for their warriors; and so Padma had managed to lead her inherited army to victory.

From the light in Padma’s eyes and her arrogant smile that would have done proud to a Malfoy, she was expecting congratulations. Draco managed to grit out some form of praise from between his clenched teeth, and couldn’t have said afterwards what it was. The foreign-born witch, it appeared, hadn’t any idea what’d happened, or what it meant.

I lost.

The Dragons trudged back to Hogwarts beneath grey skies, cold droplets landing heavy on Draco’s skin, one by one. While he’d been stunned, it had begun, the long-promised rain finally beginning to fall. There was only one option left to Draco now. A forced move, as Mr Macnair, who’d taught Draco chess, would have termed it. Harry Potter probably wouldn’t like it, if he really was in love with Granger the way everyone said. But the forced move, as Mr Macnair had defined it, was one you needed to make if you wanted the game to continue at all.

It kept on playing in Draco’s mind, over and over again, even as he walked like an automaton through the massive portals of Hogwarts, sent away Vincent and Gregory with two sharp words, and became alone within his private bedroom, sitting on his bed, staring at the wall above his desk. Filling his mind like a Dementor had locked him into the memory.

The padlock on his glove clicking and falling away –

Draco knew, he knew what he’d done wrong. He’d been so tired after casting twenty-seven Locking Charms for all the other Dragon Warriors. Less than a minute wasn’t enough time to recover after each spell. And so he’d just cast Colloportus on his own padlocked glove, just cast the spell, not put in all his strength to bind it stronger than Harry Potter or Hermione Granger could undo.

But nobody was going to believe that, even if it was true. Even in Slytherin, nobody would believe that. It sounded like an excuse, and an excuse was all that anyone would hear.

Granger whirled and spun and screamed ‘Alohomora!’ –

Draco’s mind kept playing it over and over as the resentment built. He’d helped Granger – cooperated with her on banning traitors – held her hand as she’d dangled off the roof – stopped a riot from breaking out around her in the Great Hall – did she have any idea what he’d risked, what he’d probably already lost, what it meant for the heir of House Malfoy to do that for a mudblood –

And now there was only one move left, and the thing about a forced move was that you had to make it, even if it meant getting detention and losing House points. Professor Snape would know and understand, but there were limits (Father had warned him) to what the Potions Master would overlook.

Challenge Granger to a wizard’s duel, in open defiance of Hogwarts regulations. Attack her outright, if she tried to refuse. Defeat her one-on-one, in public, not with clever duelling technique, but by overpowering her magic. Beat her solidly, completely, crush her as utterly as the Dark Lord himself had crushed his enemies. Make it absolutely clear to everyone, so that nobody could possibly doubt, that Draco had just been exhausted from casting the spell so many times. Prove that the Malfoy blood was stronger than any mudblood’s –

Only it’s not, Harry Potter’s voice whispered inside Draco’s mind. It’s easy to forget what’s really true, Draco, once you start trying to win at politics. But in reality there’s only one thing that makes you a wizard, remember?

Draco knew, then, he knew the reason for the disquiet in the back of his mind, as he stared at the blank wall above his desk contemplating his forced move. It should’ve been simple – when you only had one move, the thing to do was make it – but –

Granger whirling, spinning, sweat-dampened hair flying around her, bolts flying from her wand as fast as his own, jinx and counter-jinx, glowing bats flying at his face, and through all of it the look of fury in Granger’s eyes –

There’d been a part of him admiring that, before it had all gone wrong, admiring Granger’s fury and power; a part of him that had exulted in the first real fight he’d ever been in, against …

… an equal opponent.

If he challenged Granger, and lost …

It ought not to be possible, Draco had got his wand two full years before anyone else in his Hogwarts class.

Only there was a reason why they usually didn’t bother giving wands to nine-year-olds. Age counted too, it wasn’t just how long you’d held a wand. Granger’s birthday had been only a few days into the year, when Harry had bought her that pouch. That meant she was twelve now, that she’d been twelve almost since the start of Hogwarts. And the truth was, Draco hadn’t been practising much outside of class, probably not nearly as much as Hermione Granger of Ravenclaw. Draco hadn’t thought he needed any more practise to stay ahead …

And Granger was exhausted too, whispered the Voice of Contrary Evidence inside him. Granger must have been exhausted from all those Stunning Hexes, and even in that state she’d been able to undo his Locking Charm.

And Draco could not afford to challenge Granger publicly, one-on-one with no excuses, and lose.

Draco knew what you were supposed to do in this sort of situation. You were supposed to cheat. But if anyone discovered Draco cheating, it would be disastrous, perfect blackmail material even if it never got out publicly, and any Slytherins watching would know that, they’d be looking …

And then, if you were watching, you would have seen Draco Malfoy get up from his bed, and go to his desk, and take out a sheet of the finest sheepskin parchment, and a pearl-carven inkwell, filled with greenish-silver ink that had been made with true silver and crushed emeralds. From the great trunk at his bed’s foot, the Slytherin drew forth a book bound also in silver and emeralds, entitled The Etiquette of the Houses of Britain. And with a new, clean quill, Draco Malfoy began to write, frequently looking to the book where it lay open as a reference. There was a grim smile on the boy’s face, making the young Malfoy look very much like his father, as he carefully drew each letter as though it were a separate artwork.

From Draco, son of Lucius son of Abraxis Lords of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, son also of Narcissa daughter of Druella Lady of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Black, scion and heir of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy:

To Hermione, the first Granger:

(That form might have been meant to sound polite, long ago when it had been invented; nowadays, after centuries of being used to address mudbloods, it carried a lovely tinge of refined venom.)

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for

Draco paused, carefully moving the quill aside so that it wouldn’t drip. He needed a pretext for this, at least if he wanted to impose the duel’s conditions. The challenged had the choice of terms unless they had insulted a Noble House. He needed to make it look like Granger had insulted him …

What was he thinking? Granger had insulted him.

Draco flipped the book to the page of standard formulae, and found one that seemed appropriate.

I, Draco, of Most Ancient House, demand redress, for that I have thrice over helped you and offered you only my goodwill, and in return you falsely accused me of plotting against you,

Draco had to stop and take a breath, forcing down the seething anger; he was starting to genuinely feel the insult now, and he’d just written out the last phrase and underlined it without thinking, like it was an ordinary letter. After a moment’s reflection, he decided to let it stand; it might not be the exact formal phrasing but it had a raw, angry tone that seemed appropriate.

which insult you committed before the eyes of Britain.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by

‘The seventeenth ruling of the thirty-first Wizengamot,’ Draco said aloud without looking, a line delivered in many plays; he sat straighter as he said it, feeling every pulse of the noble blood in his veins.

Thus I, Draco, compel you, Hermione, by custom, by law, by the 17th ruling of the 31st Wizengamot, to meet me in wizard’s duel with terms: That we each come alone and in silence, speaking to none before or after,

If the duel went poorly, Draco could just say nothing and leave it at that. And if he did defeat Granger, he would have learned experimentally that he could beat her again in a public challenge. It wasn’t cheating, but it was Science, which was almost as good.

contesting by magic solely, without death or lasting injury,

… where? Draco had been told about a room in Hogwarts that was good for duels, where everything valuable was already protected by wards, and there were no portraits to tattle on you … which one had it been again …

in the trophy room of the Castle of the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry,

And their second and public duel had better be soon, like tomorrow, it would take very little time for his reputation in Slytherin to go irretrievably to sludge. He needed to fight Granger for the first time tonight.

upon midnight’s stroke that shall end this very day.

Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy.

Draco signed the formal parchment, and then drew forth his ordinary and lesser parchment, and his regular ink, for his post scriptum:

If you don’t know how the rules work, Granger, here’s how it is. You insulted a Most Ancient House, and I’ve got the lawful right to challenge. And if you affront the conditions of the duel, like by having Flitwick show up at the trophy room, or even just telling anyone else, my father will take you and your false honor straight to the Wizengamot.

Draco Malfo

On the last letter his quill pressed down on the parchment so viciously that the nib snapped off, creating a streak of ink and a small rip in the parchment, which Draco decided also looked appropriate.

Multiple Hypothesis Testing

(International news headlines of April 7th, 1992:)

Toronto Magical Tribune:

entire british wizengamot
reports seeing BOY-WHO-LIVED
frighten a dementor

expert on magical creatures:
‘Now you’re just lying’

france, germany accuse britain
of making the whole thing up

New Zealand Spellcrafter’s Diurnal Notice:

what drove british legislature insane?
could our government be next?

experts list top 28 REASONS
to believe it’s already happened

American Mage:

werewolf clan to become
first inhabitants of wyoming

The Quibbler:

malfoy flees hogwarts
as veela powers awaken

Daily Prophet:

legal tricks free
‘mad muggleborn’
as potter threatens ministry
with attack on azkaban

Hypothesis: Voldemort (April 8th, 1992, 7:22pm)

The four of them gathered once more around the ancient desk of the Headmaster of Hogwarts, with its drawers within drawers within drawers, wherein all the past paperwork of the Hogwarts School was stored; legend had it that Headmistress Shehla had once got lost in that desk, and was, in fact, still there, and wouldn’t be let out again until she got her files organized. Minerva didn’t particularly look forward to inheriting those drawers, when she inherited that desk someday – if any of them survived.

Albus Dumbledore was seated behind his desk, looking grave and composed.

Severus Snape was standing next to the dead Floo and its ashes, hovering ominously like the vampire that students sometimes accused him of pretending to be.

Mad-Eye Moody had been meant to join them, but was yet to arrive.

And Harry …

A boy’s small, thin frame, perched on the arm of his chair, as though the energies running through him were too great to allow ordinary seating. Set face, sweaty hair, intent green eyes, and within it all, the jagged lightning-bolt of his never-healing scar. He seemed grimmer, now; even compared to a single week earlier.

For a moment Minerva flashed back to her trip to Diagon Alley with Harry, what seemed like ages and ages ago. There’d been this sombre boy inside that Harry, somehow, even then. This wasn’t entirely her own fault, or Albus’s fault. And yet there was something almost unbearably sad about the contrast between the young boy she’d first met, and what magical Britain had made of him. Harry had never had much of an ordinary childhood, she’d gathered; Harry’s adoptive parents had said to her that he’d spoken little and played less with Muggle children. It was painful to think that Harry might have had only a few months of playing beside the other children in Hogwarts, before the war’s demands had stripped it all away. Maybe there was another face that Harry showed to the children his own age, when he wasn’t staring down the Wizengamot. But she couldn’t stop herself from imagining Harry Potter’s childhood as a heap of firewood, and herself and Albus feeding the wooden branches, piece by piece, into the flames.

‘Prophecies are strange things,’ said Albus Dumbledore. The old wizard’s eyes were half-lidded, as though in weariness. ‘Vague, unclear, meaning escaping like water held between loose fingers. Prophecy is ever a burden, for there are no answers there, only questions.’

Harry Potter was sitting tensely. ‘Headmaster Dumbledore,’ said the boy with soft precision, ‘my friends are being targeted. Hermione Granger almost went to Azkaban. The war has begun, as you put it. Professor Trelawney’s prophecy is key information for weighing up the balance of my hypotheses about what’s going on. Not to mention how silly it is – and dangerous – that the Dark Lord knows the prophecy and I don’t.’

Albus looked a grim question at her, and she shook her head in reply; in whatever unimaginable way Harry had discovered that Trelawney had made the prophecy and that the Dark Lord knew of it, he hadn’t learned that much from her.

‘Voldemort, seeking to avert that very prophecy, went to his defeat at your hands,’ the old wizard said then. ‘His knowledge brought him only harm. Ponder that carefully, Harry Potter.’

‘Yes, Headmaster, I do understand that. My home culture also has a literary tradition of self-fulfilling and misinterpreted prophecies. I’ll interpret with caution, rest assured. But I’ve already guessed quite a bit. Is it safer for me to work from partial guesses?’

Time passed.

‘Minerva,’ said Albus. ‘If you would.’

‘The one …’ she began. The words came falteringly to her throat; she was no actress. She couldn’t imitate the deep, chilling tone of the original prophecy; and yet somehow that tone seemed to carry all the meaning. ‘The one with the power to vanquish the Dark Lord approaches … born to those who have thrice defied him, born as the seventh month dies …’

‘And the Dark Lord shall mark him as his equal,’ came Severus’s voice, making her jump within her chair. The Potions Master loomed tall by the fireplace. ‘But he shall have power the Dark Lord knows not … and either must destroy all but a remnant of the other, for those two different spirits cannot exist in the same world.’

That last line Severus spoke with so much foreboding that it chilled her bones; it was almost like listening to Sybill Trelawney.

Harry was listening with a frown. ‘Can you repeat that?’ said Harry.

‘The one with the power to vanquish the Dark Lord approaches, born to those who have thrice defied him, born as the seventh month –’

‘Actually, hold on, can you write that down? I need to analyse this carefully –’

This was done, with both Albus and Severus watching the parchment hawklike, as though to make sure that no unseen hand reached in and snatched the precious information away.

‘Let’s see …’ Harry said. ‘I’m male and born on July 31st, check. I did in fact vanquish the Dark Lord, check. Ambiguous pronoun in line two … but I wasn’t born yet so it’s hard to see how my parents could have thrice defied me. This scar is an obvious candidate for the mark …’ Harry touched his forehead. ‘Then there’s the power the Dark Lord knows not, which probably refers to my scientific background –’

‘No,’ said Severus.

Harry looked at the Potions Master in surprise.

Severus’s eyes were closed, his face tightened in concentration. ‘The Dark Lord could obtain that power by studying the same books as you, Potter. But the prophecy did not say, power the Dark Lord has not. Nor even, power the Dark Lord cannot have. She spoke of power the Dark Lord knows not … it will be something stranger to him than Muggle artifacts. Something perhaps that he cannot comprehend at all, even having seen it …’

‘Science is not a bag of technological tricks,’ Harry said. ‘It’s not just the Muggle version of a wand. It’s not even knowledge like memorizing the periodic table. It’s a different way of thinking.’

‘Perhaps …’ the Potions Master murmured, but his voice was skeptical.

‘It is hazardous,’ Albus said, ‘to read too far into a prophecy, even if you have heard it yourself. They are things of exceeding frustration.’

‘So I see,’ Harry said. His hand rose up, rubbed the scar on his forehead. ‘But … okay, if this is really all we know … look, I’ll just put it bluntly. How do you know that the Dark Lord actually survived?’

‘What?’ she cried. Albus just sighed and leaned back in the vast Headmaster’s chair.

‘Well,’ Harry said, ‘imagine how this prophecy sounded back when it was made. You-Know-Who learns the prophecy, and it sounds like I’m destined to grow up and overthrow him. That the two of us are meant to have a final battle where either of us must destroy all but a remnant of the other. So You-Know-Who attacks Godric’s Hollow and immediately gets vanquished, leaving behind some remnant which may or may not be his disembodied soul. Maybe the Death Eaters are his remnant, or the Dark Mark. This prophecy could already be fulfilled, is what I’m saying. Don’t get me wrong – I do realize that my interpretation sounds stretched. Trelawney’s phrasing doesn’t seem natural for describing only the events that historically happened on October 31st, 1981. Attacking a baby and having the spell bounce off, isn’t something you’d normally call “the power to vanquish”. But if you think of the prophecy as being about several possible futures, only one of which was actually realized on Halloween, then the prophecy could already be complete.’

‘But –’ Minerva blurted. ‘But the raid on Azkaban –’

‘If the Dark Lord survived, then sure, he’s the most likely suspect for the Azkaban breakout,’ Harry said reasonably. ‘You could even say that the Azkaban breakout is Bayesian evidence for the Dark Lord surviving, because an Azkaban breakout is more likely to happen in worlds where he’s alive than worlds where he’s dead. But it’s not strong Bayesian evidence. It’s not something that can’t possibly happen unless the Dark Lord is alive. Professor Quirrell, who didn’t start from the assumption that You-Know-Who was still around, had no trouble thinking of his own explanation. To him, it was obvious that some powerful wizard might want Bellatrix Black because she knew a secret of the Dark Lord’s, like some of his magical knowledge that he’d told only her. The priors against anyone surviving their body’s death are very low, even if it’s magically possible. Most times it doesn’t happen. So if it’s just the Azkaban breakout … I’d have to say formally that it isn’t enough Bayesian evidence. The improbability of the evidence assuming that the hypothesis is false, is not commensurate with the prior improbability of the hypothesis.’

‘No,’ Severus said flatly. ‘The prophecy is not yet fulfilled. I would know if it were.’

‘Are you sure of that?’

‘Yes, Potter. If the prophecy had already come true, I would understand it! I heard Trelawney’s words, I remember Trelawney’s voice, and if I knew the events that matched the prophecy, I would recognize them. What has already happened … does not fit.’ The Potions Master spoke with certainty.

‘I’m not really sure what to do with that statement,’ Harry said. His hand rose up, absently rubbed at his forehead. ‘Maybe it’s just what you think happened that doesn’t fit, and the true history is different …’

‘Voldemort is alive,’ Albus said. ‘There are other indications.’

‘Such as?’ Harry’s reply was instant.

Albus paused. ‘There are terrible rituals by which wizards have returned from death,’ Albus said slowly. ‘That much, anyone can discern within history and legend. And yet those books are missing, I could not find them; it was Voldemort who removed them, I am sure –’

‘So you can’t find any books on immortality, and that proves that You-Know-Who has them?’

‘Indeed,’ said Albus. ‘There is a certain book – I will not name it aloud – missing from the Restricted Section of the Hogwarts library. An ancient scroll which should have been at Borgin and Burkes, with only an empty place on a shelf to show where it was –’ The old wizard stopped. ‘But I suppose,’ the old wizard said, as though to himself, ‘you will say that even if Voldemort tried to make himself immortal, it does not prove that he succeeded …’

Harry sighed. ‘Proof, Headmaster? There are only ever probabilities. If there are known, particular books on immortality rituals which are missing, that increases the probability that someone attempted one. Which, in turn, raises the prior probability of the Dark Lord surviving his death. This I concede, and thank you for contributing the fact. The question is whether the prior probability goes up enough.’

‘Surely,’ Albus said quietly, ‘if you concede even a chance that Voldemort survived, that is worth guarding against?’

Harry inclined his head. ‘As you say, Headmaster. Though once a probability drops low enough, it’s also an error to go on obsessing about it … Given that books on immortality are missing, and that this prophecy would sound somewhat more natural if it refers to the Dark Lord and I having a future battle, I agree that the Dark Lord being alive is a probability, not just possibility. But other probabilities must also be taken into account – and in the probable worlds where You-Know-Who is not alive, someone else framed Hermione.’

‘Foolishness,’ Severus said softly. ‘Utter foolishness. The Dark Mark has not faded, nor has its master.’

‘See, that’s what I mean by formally insufficient Bayesian evidence. Sure, it sounds all grim and foreboding and stuff, but is it that unlikely for a magical mark to stay around after the maker dies? Suppose the mark is certain to continue while the Dark Lord’s sentience lives on, but a priori we’d only have guessed a twenty percent chance of the Dark Mark continuing to exist after the Dark Lord dies. Then the observation, “The Dark Mark has not faded” is five times as likely to occur in worlds where the Dark Lord is alive as in worlds where the Dark Lord is dead. Is that really commensurate with the prior improbability of immortality? Let’s say the prior odds were a hundred-to-one against the Dark Lord surviving. If a hypothesis is a hundred times as likely to be false versus true, and then you see evidence five times more likely if the hypothesis is true versus false, you should update to believing the hypothesis is twenty times as likely to be false as true. Odds of a hundred to one, times a likelihood ratio of one to five, equals odds of twenty to one that the Dark Lord is dead –’

‘Where are you getting all these numbers, Potter?’

‘That is the admitted weakness of the method,’ Harry said readily. ‘But what I’m qualitatively getting at is why the observation, “The Dark Mark has not faded”, is not adequate support for the hypothesis, “The Dark Lord is immortal.” The evidence isn’t as extraordinary as the claim.’ Harry paused. ‘Not to mention that even if the Dark Lord is alive, he doesn’t have to be the one who framed Hermione. As a cunning man once said, there could be more than one plotter and more than one plan.’

‘Such as the Defence Professor,’ Severus said with a thin smile. ‘I suppose I must agree that he is a suspect. It was the Defence Professor last year, after all; and the year before that, and the year before that.’

Harry’s eyes dropped back to the parchment in his lap. ‘Let’s move on. Are we certain that this Prophecy is accurate? Nobody messed with Professor McGonagall’s memory, maybe edited or subtracted a line?’

Albus paused, then spoke slowly. ‘There is a great spell laid over Britain, recording every prophecy said within our borders. Far beneath the Most Ancient Hall of the Wizengamot, in the Department of Mysteries, they are recorded.’

‘The Hall of Prophecy,’ Minerva whispered. She’d read about that place, said to be a great room of shelves filled with glowing orbs, one after another appearing over the years. Merlin himself had wrought it, it was said; the greatest wizard’s final slap to the face of Fate. Not all prophecies conduced to the good; and Merlin had wished for at least those spoken of in prophecy, to know what had been spoken of them. That was the respect Merlin had given to their free will, that Destiny might not control them from the outside, unwitting. Those mentioned within a prophecy would have an glowing orb float to their hand, and then hear the prophet’s true voice speaking. Others who tried to touch an orb, it was said, would be driven mad – or possibly just have their heads explode, the legends were unclear on this point. Whatever Merlin’s original intention, the Unspeakables hadn’t let anyone enter in centuries, so far as she’d heard. Works of the Ancient Wizards had stated that later Unspeakables had discovered that tipping off the subjects of prophecies could interfere with seers releasing whatever temporal pressures they released; and so the heirs of Merlin had sealed his Hall. It did occur to Minerva to wonder (now that she’d spent a few months around Mr Potter) how anyone could possibly know that; but she also knew better than to ask Albus, in case Albus tried to tell her. Minerva firmly believed that you only ought to worry about Time if you were a clock.

‘The Hall of Prophecy,’ Albus confirmed quietly. ‘Those who are spoken of in a prophecy, may listen to that prophecy there. Do you see the implication, Harry?’

Harry frowned. ‘Well, I could listen to it, or the Dark Lord … oh, my parents. Those who had thrice defied him. They were also mentioned in the prophecy, so they could hear the recording?’

‘If James and Lily heard anything different from what Minerva reported,’ Albus said evenly, ‘they did not say so to me.’

‘You took James and Lily there?’ Minerva said.

‘Fawkes can go to many places,’ Albus said. ‘Do not mention the fact.’

Harry was staring directly at Albus. ‘Can I go to this Department of Mysteries place and hear the recorded prophecy? The original tone of voice might be helpful, from what I’ve heard.’

Light glinted from the reflection of Albus’s half-moon glasses as the old wizard slowly shook his head. ‘I think that would be unwise,’ Albus said. ‘For reasons beyond the obvious. It is dangerous, that place which Merlin made; more dangerous to some people than others.’

‘I see,’ Harry said tonelessly, and looked back down at the parchment. ‘I’ll take the prophecy as assumed accurate for now. The next part says that the Dark Lord has marked me as his equal. Any ideas on what that means exactly?’

‘Surely not,’ said Albus, ‘that you must imitate his ways, in any wise.’

‘I’m not dumb, Headmaster. Muggles have worked out a thing or two about temporal paradoxes, even if it’s all theoretical to them. I won’t throw away my ethics just because a signal from the future claims it’s going to happen, because then that becomes the only reason why it happened in the first place. Still, what does it mean?’

‘I do not know,’ said Severus.

‘Nor I,’ she said.

Harry took out his wand, turned it over in his hands, gazing meditatively at the wood. ‘Eleven inches, holly, with a core of phoenix feather,’ Harry said. ‘And the phoenix whose tail feather is in this wand, only ever gave one other, which Mr … what was his name, Olive-something … made into the core of the Dark Lord’s wand. And I’m a Parselmouth. It seemed like a lot of coincidence even then. And now I find out there’s a prophecy stating that I’ll be the Dark Lord’s equal.’

Severus’s eyes were thoughtful; the Headmaster’s gaze, unreadable.

‘Could it be,’ Minerva said falteringly, ‘that You-Know-Who – that Voldemort – transferred some of his own powers to Mr Potter, the night he gave him that scar? Not something he intended to do, surely. Still … I don’t see how Mr Potter could be his equal, if he had any less magic than the Dark Lord himself …’

‘Meh,’ said Harry, still looking meditatively at his wand. ‘I’d fight the Dark Lord without any magic at all, if I had to. Homo sapiens didn’t become the dominant species on this planet by having the sharpest claws or hardest armour – though I suppose some of that point may be lost on wizards. Still, it’s beneath my dignity as a human being to be scared of anything that isn’t smarter than I am; and from what I’ve heard, on that particular dimension the Dark Lord wasn’t very scary.’

The Potions Master spoke, his voice taking on some of his customary contemptuous drawl. ‘You imagine yourself more intelligent than the Dark Lord, Potter?’

‘Yes, in fact,’ said Harry, pulling back the left sleeve of his robes, and rolling up the shirtsleeve beneath to expose the bare elbow. ‘Oh, that reminds me! Let’s make sure nobody here has the clearly visible tattoo in the standard, easily checkable location which would mark them as a secret enemy spy.’

Albus made a quieting gesture that halted the Potions Master before he could say anything scathing. ‘Tell me, Harry,’ Albus said, ‘how would you have crafted the Dark Mark?’

‘Non-standard locations,’ Harry said promptly, ‘not easily found without embarrassment and fuss, though of course any security-conscious person would check anyway. Make it smaller, if possible. Overlay another non-magical tattoo to obscure the exact shape – better yet, cover it with a layer of fake skin –’

‘Cunning indeed,’ Albus said. ‘But tell me, suppose you could craft any conditions you wished into the Mark, fading it or raising it as you wished. What would you do then?’

‘Make it completely invisible at all times,’ Harry said in tones of stating the obvious. ‘You don’t want there to be any detectable difference between a spy and a non-spy.’

‘Suppose you are more cunning still,’ Albus said. ‘You are a master of trickery, a master of deception, and you employ your abilities to the fullest.’

‘Well –’ The boy stopped, frowning. ‘It seems unnecessarily complicated, more like a tactic a villain would use in a role-playing game than something you’d try in a real-life war. But I suppose you could put fake Dark Marks on people who aren’t really Death Eaters, and keep the Dark Marks on the real Death Eaters invisible. But then there’s the question of why people would start believing in the first place that the Dark Mark identified a Death Eater … I’d have to think about it for at least five minutes, if I were going to take the problem seriously.’

‘I ask you this,’ Albus said, still in that mild tone, ‘because I did indeed, in the early days of the war, perform such tests as you suggested. The Order survived my folly only because Alastor did not trust in the bare arms we saw. I had thought, afterwards, that the bearers of the Mark might hide it or show it at their will. And yet when we hauled Igor Karkaroff before the Wizengamot, that Mark showed clear on his arm, for all that Karkaroff wished to protest his innocence. What true rule may govern the Dark Mark, I do not know. Even Severus is still bound by his Mark not to reveal its secrets to any who do not know them.’

‘Oh, well that makes it obvious,’ Harry said promptly. ‘Wait, hold on – you were a Death Eater?’ Harry transferred his stare to Severus.

Severus returned a thin smile. ‘I still am, so far as they know.’

‘Harry,’ said Albus, eyes only for the boy. ‘What do you mean, that makes it obvious?’

‘Information theory 101,’ the boy said in a lecturing tone. ‘Observing variable X conveys information about variable Y, if and only if the possible values of X have different probabilities given different states of Y. The instant you hear about anything whatsoever that varies between a spy and a non-spy, you should immediately think of exploiting it to distinguish spies from non-spies. Similarly, to distinguish reality from lies, you need a process which behaves differently in the presence of truth and falsehood – that’s why “faith” doesn’t work as a discriminant, while “make experimental predictions and test them” does. You say someone with the Dark Mark can’t reveal its secrets to anyone who doesn’t already know them. So to find out how the Dark Mark operates, write down every way you can imagine the Dark Mark might work, then watch Professor Snape try to tell each of those things to a confederate – maybe one who doesn’t know what the experiment is about – I’ll explain binary search later so that you can play Twenty Questions to narrow things down – and whatever he can’t say out loud is true. His silence would be something that behaves differently in the presence of true statements about the Mark, versus false statements, you see.’

Minerva’s mouth was hanging open, she realized; and she closed it abruptly. Even Albus looked surprised.

‘And after that, like I said, any behavioural difference between spies and non-spies can be used to identify spies. Once you’ve identified at least one magically censored secret of the Dark Mark, you can test someone for the Dark Mark by seeing if they can reveal that secret to somebody who doesn’t already know it –’

‘Thank you, Mr Potter.’

Everyone looked at Severus. The Potions Master was straightening, his teeth bared in a grimace of angry triumph. ‘Headmaster, I can now speak freely of the Mark. If we know we are caught for a Death Eater, before others who have not yet seen our bare arms, our Mark reveals itself whether we will it or no. But if they have already seen our arms bare, it does not reveal itself; nor if we are only being tested from suspicion. Thus the Dark Mark seems to identify Death Eaters – but only those already found, you perceive.’

‘Ah …’ Albus said. ‘Thank you, Severus.’ He closed his eyes briefly. ‘That would indeed explain why Black escaped even Peter’s notice … ah, well. And Harry’s proposed test?’

The Potions Master shook his head. ‘The Dark Lord was no fool, despite Potter’s delusions. The moment such a test is suspected, the Mark ceases to bind our tongues. Yet I could not hint at the possibility, but only wait for another to deduce it.’ Another thin smile. ‘I would award you a good many House points, Mr Potter, if it would not compromise my cover. But as you can see, the Dark Lord was quite cunning.’ His gaze grew more distant. ‘Oh,’ Severus breathed, ‘he was very cunning indeed …’

Harry Potter sat still for a long moment.

Then –

‘No,’ Harry said. The boy shook his head. ‘No, that can’t actually be true. First of all, we’re talking about the kind of logic puzzle that would appear in chapter one of a Raymond Smullyan book, nowhere near the level of what Muggle scientists do for a living. And second, for all I know, it took the Dark Lord five months of thinking to invent the puzzle I just solved in five seconds –’

‘Is it that inconceivable to you, Potter, that anyone could be so intelligent as yourself?’ The Potions Master’s voice held more curiosity than scorn.

‘It’s called a base rate, Professor Snape. The evidence is equally compatible with the Dark Lord inventing that puzzle over the course of five months or over the course of five seconds, but in any given population there’ll be many more people who can do it in five months than in five seconds …’ Harry pasted a hand against his forehead. ‘Darn it, how can I explain this? I suppose, from your perspective, the Dark Lord came up with a clever puzzle and I cleverly solved it and that makes us look equal.’

‘I remember your first day of Potions class,’ the Potions Master said dryly. ‘I think you have some way still to go.’

‘Peace, Severus,’ Albus said. ‘Harry has already accomplished more than you know. Yet tell me, Harry – why do you believe the Dark Lord is less than you? Surely he is a damaged soul in many ways. But cunning for cunning – you are not yet ready to face him, I would judge; and I know the full tally of your deeds.’

The frustrating thing about this conversation was that Harry couldn’t say his actual reasons for disagreeing, which violated several basic principles of cooperative discourse.

He couldn’t explain how Bellatrix had really been removed from Azkaban – not by You-Know-Who in any guise, but by the combined wits of Harry and Professor Quirrell.

Harry didn’t want to say in front of Professor McGonagall that the existence of brain damage implied that there were no such things as souls. Which made a successful immortality ritual … well, not impossible, Harry certainly intended to forge a road to magical immortality someday, but it would be a lot harder and require much more ingenuity than just binding an already-existent soul to a lich’s phylactery. Which no intelligent wizard would bother doing in the first place, if they knew their souls were immortal.

And the true and honest reason Harry knew the Dark Lord couldn’t have been that smart … well … there wasn’t any tactful way to say it, but …

Harry had been to a convocation of the Wizengamot. He’d seen the laughable security precautions, if you could call them that, guarding the deepest levels of the Ministry of Magic. They didn’t even have the Thief’s Downfall which goblins used to wash away Polyjuice and Imperius Curses on people entering Gringotts. The obvious takeover route would be to Imperius the Minister of Magic and a few department heads, and owl a hand grenade to anyone too powerful to Imperius. Or owl them knockout gas, if you needed them alive and in a state of Living Death to take hairs for Polyjuice potions. Legilimency, False Memories, the Confundus Charm – it was ridiculous, the magical world was supersaturated with ways to cheat. Harry might not do any of those things himself, during his own takeover of Britain, since he was constrained by Ethics … well, Harry might do some of the lesser ones, since Polyjuice or a temporary Confundus or read-only Legilimency all sounded better than an extra day of Azkaban … but …

If Harry hadn’t been constrained by Ethics, it was possible he could’ve wiped out the eviller sections of the Wizengamot that day; all by himself, using only a first-year’s magical power, on account of being clever enough to figure out Dementors. Though Harry might not have been in such a great political position after that, the surviving Wizengamot members might’ve found it easy and cheap to disavow his actions for P.R. purposes and condemn him, even if the smarter ones realized it was for the greater good … but still.

If you were completely unrestrained by ethics, armed with the ancient secrets of Salazar Slytherin, had dozens of powerful followers including Lucius Malfoy, and it took you more than ten years to fail to overthrow the government of magical Britain, it meant you were stupid.

‘How can I put this …’ Harry said. ‘Look, Headmaster, you’ve got ethics, there’s a lot of battle tactics you don’t use because you’re not evil. And you fought the Dark Lord, a tremendously powerful wizard who wasn’t so restrained, and you held him off anyway. If You-Know-Who had been super-smart on top of that, you’d be dead. All of you. You’d have died instantly –’

‘Harry,’ Professor McGonagall said. Her voice was faltering. ‘Harry, we almost did all die. More than half the Order of the Phoenix died. If not for Albus – Albus Dumbledore, the greatest wizard in two centuries, Harry – we surely would have perished.’

Harry passed a hand across his forehead. ‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said. ‘I’m not trying to minimize what you went through. I know that You-Know-Who was a completely evil, incredibly powerful Dark Wizard with dozens of powerful followers, and that’s … bad, yes, definitely bad. It’s just …’ All that isn’t on remotely the same threat scale as the enemy being smart, in which case they Transfigure botulinum toxin and sneak a millionth of a gram into your teacup. Was there any safe way to convey that concept without citing specifics? Harry couldn’t think of one.

‘Please, Harry,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Please, Harry, I beg you – take the Dark Lord seriously! He is more dangerous than –’ The senior witch seemed to be having trouble finding words. ‘He is far more dangerous than Transfiguration.’

Harry’s eyebrows went up before he could stop himself. A dark chuckle came from Severus Snape’s direction.

Um, said the voice of Ravenclaw within him. Um, honestly Professor McGonagall is right, we’re not taking this as seriously as we’d take a scientific problem. The difficult thing is to react at all to new information, instead of just flushing it out the window. Right now it looks like we didn’t shift belief at all after encountering an unexpected, important argument. Our dismissal of Lord Voldemort as a serious threat was originally based on the Dark Mark being blatantly stupid. It would require a focused effort to de-update and suspect the whole garden-path of reasoning we went down based on that false assumption, and we’re not putting in that effort right now.

‘All right,’ Harry said, just as Professor McGonagall seemed to be about to speak again. ‘All right, to take this seriously, I need to stop and think for five minutes.’

‘Please do,’ said Albus Dumbledore.

Harry closed his eyes.

His Ravenclaw side divided into three.

Probability estimate, said Ravenclaw One, who was acting as moderator. That the Dark Lord is alive, and as smart as we are, and hence a genuine threat.

Why aren’t all his enemies already dead? said Ravenclaw Two, who was prosecuting.

Note, said Ravenclaw One, we had already thought of that argument so we can’t use it to shift belief again each time we rehearse it.

But what’s the actual flaw in the logic? said Ravenclaw Two. In worlds with a smart Lord Voldemort, everyone in the Order of the Phoenix died in the first five minutes of the war. The world doesn’t look like that, so we don’t live in that world. QED.

Is that really certain? asked Ravenclaw Three, who’d been appointed as the defender. Maybe there was some reason Lord Voldemort wasn’t fighting all-out back then –

Like what? demanded Ravenclaw Two. Furthermore, whatever your excuse, I demand that the probability of your hypothesis be penalized in accordance with its added complexity –

Let Three talk, said Ravenclaw One.

Okay … look, said Ravenclaw Three. First of all, we don’t know that anyone can take over the Ministry just with mind control. Maybe magical Britain is really an oligarchy and you need enough military power to intimidate the family heads into submission –

Imperius them too, interjected Ravenclaw Two.

– and the oligarchs have Thief’s Downfall in the entrances to their homes –

Complexity penalty! cried Ravenclaw Two. More epicycles!

– oh, be reasonable, said Ravenclaw Three. We haven’t actually seen anyone taking over the Ministry with a couple of well-placed Imperius curses. We don’t know that it can actually be done that easily.

But, said Ravenclaw Two, even taking that into account … it really seems like there should’ve been some other way. Ten years of failure, really? Using only conventional terrorist tactics? That’s just … not even trying.

Maybe Lord Voldemort did have more creative ideas, replied Ravenclaw Three, but he didn’t want to tip his hand to other countries’ governments, didn’t want them to know how vulnerable they were and install Thief’s Downfall in their Ministries. Not until he had Britain as a base and enough servants to subvert all the other major governments simultaneously.

You’re assuming he wants to conquer the whole world, noted Ravenclaw Two.

Trelawney prophesied that he would be our equal, intoned Ravenclaw Three solemnly. Therefore, he wanted to take over the world.

And if he is your equal, and you do have to fight him –

For an instant, Harry’s mind tried to imagine the spectre of two creative wizards fighting an all-out-war against each other.

Harry had noted all the Charms and Potions in his first-year books that could be creatively used to kill people. He hadn’t been able to help himself. Literally. He’d tried to stop his brain from doing it each time, but it was like looking at a fish and trying to stop your brain from noticing it was a fish. What someone could creatively do with seventh-year, or Auror-level, or ancient lost magic such as Lord Voldemort had possessed … didn’t bear thinking about. A magically-superpowered creative-genius psychopath wasn’t a threat, it was an extinction event.

Then Harry shook his head, dismissing the gloomy line his reasoning had been going down. The question was whether there was a significant probability of facing anything so terrible as a Dark Rationalist in the first place.

Prior odds that someone attempting an immortality ritual would actually have it work …

Call it one to a thousand, at a generous overestimate; it was not the case that roughly one wizard in a thousand survived their death. Though, admittedly Harry didn’t have data on how many had attempted immortality rituals first.

What if the Dark Lord is as smart as us? said Ravenclaw Three. You know, the way Trelawney prophesied him being our equal. Then he would make his immortality ritual work. P.S., don’t forget that destroy all but a remnant of the other line.

Requiring that level of intelligence was an additional burdensome detail; prior odds of a random population member being that intelligent were low …

But Lord Voldemort wasn’t a randomly selected wizard, he was one particular wizard in the population who’d come to everyone’s attention. The puzzle of the Mark implied a certain minimum level of intelligence, even if (hypothetically) the Dark Lord had taken longer to think it through. Then again, in the Muggle world, all of the extremely intelligent people Harry knew about from history had not become evil dictators or terrorists. The closest thing to that in the Muggle world was hedge-fund managers, and none of them had tried to take over so much as a third-world country, a point which put upper bounds on both their possible evil and possible goodness.

There were hypotheses where the Dark Lord was smart and the Order of the Phoenix didn’t just instantly die, but those hypotheses were more complicated and ought to get complexity penalties. After the complexity penalties of the further excuses were factored in, there would be a large likelihood ratio from the hypotheses The Dark Lord is smart versus The Dark Lord was stupid to the observation, The Dark Lord did not instantly win the war. That was probably worth a 10:1 likelihood ratio in favour of the Dark Lord being stupid … but maybe not 100:1. You couldn’t actually say that The Dark Lord instantly wins had a probability of more than 99 percent, assuming the Dark Lord started out smart; the sum over all possible excuses would be more than .01.

And then there was the Prophecy … which might or might not have originally included a line about how Lord Voldemort would immediately die if he confronted the Potters. Which Albus Dumbledore had then edited in Professor McGonagall’s memory, in order to lure Lord Voldemort to his doom. If there was no such line, the Prophecy did sound somewhat more like You-Know-Who and the Boy-Who-Lived were destined to have some later confrontation. But in that case, it was less likely that Dumbledore would’ve come up with a plausible-sounding excuse not to take Harry to the Hall of Prophecy …

Harry was wondering if he could even get a Bayesian calculation out of this. Of course, the point of a subjective Bayesian calculation wasn’t that, after you made up a bunch of numbers, multiplying them out would give you an exactly right answer. The real point was that the process of making up numbers would force you to tally all the relevant facts and weigh all the relative probabilities. Like realizing, as soon as you actually thought about the probability of the Dark Mark not-fading if You-Know-Who was dead, that the probability wasn’t low enough for the observation to count as strong evidence. One version of the process was to tally hypotheses and list out evidence, make up all the numbers, do the calculation, and then throw out the final answer and go with your brain’s gut feeling after you’d forced it to really weigh everything. The trouble was that the items of evidence weren’t conditionally independent, and there were multiple interacting background facts of interest …

… well, one thing at least was certain.

If the calculation could be done at all, it was going to take a piece of paper and a pencil.

In the fireplace at one side of the Headmaster’s office, the flames suddenly flared up, turning from orange to bright bilious green.

‘Ah!’ said Professor McGonagall into the uncomfortable non-silence. ‘That would be Mad-Eye Moody, I suppose.’

‘Let this matter bide for now,’ the Headmaster said in some relief, as he too turned to regard the Floo. ‘I believe we are about to receive some news regarding it, as well.’

Time Pressure

April 16th, 1992.

12:07pm.

Lunchtime.

Harry stomped over to the mostly-deserted Gryffindor table, determining at a glance that lunch today was breen and Roopo balls. The ambient conversation, Harry could likewise hear, was Quidditch-related; an auditory environment which rated somewhat worse than the sound of rusty chainsaws, but better than what the Ravenclaw table was still blithering about Hermione. Gryffindor House, at least, had started out less sympathetic to Draco Malfoy and had more political incentive to wish that everyone would just forget certain unfortunate facts; and if that wasn’t the right reason for silence, it was at least silence. Dean and Seamus and Lavender were all gone for the holidays, but at least that left …

‘What was all that ruckus at the Head Table?’ Harry said to the Weasley-twin group-mind, as he began to serve himself his own plate. ‘It looked like it was just ending as I walked in.’

‘Our beloved, but clumsy Professor Trelawney –’

‘Seems to have gone and dropped an entire soup tureen on herself –’

‘Not to mention Mr Hagrid.’

A quick glance at the Head Table confirmed that the Divination Professor was waving her wand frantically as the half-Giant dabbed at his clothes. Nobody else seemed to be paying much attention, even Professor McGonagall. Professor Flitwick was standing on his chair as usual, the Headmaster seemed to be absent again (he’d been gone most days of the holiday), Professors Sprout and Sinistra and Vector were eating in their usual grouping, and –

‘You know,’ Harry said, as he turned his head away to stare at the ceiling illusion of a clear blue sky, ‘that still creeps me out sometimes.’

‘What does?’ said Fred or George.

The powerful and enigmatic Defence Professor was resting or whatever-the-heck-was-wrong-with-him, his hands making fumbling, hesitant grabs at a chicken-leg that seemed to be eluding him on the plate.

‘Eh, nothing,’ said Harry. ‘I’m not quite used to Hogwarts, yet.’

Harry continued to eat in moderate silence, as various Weasleys discussed some bizarre mind-affecting substance called Chudley Cannons.

‘What sort of deep mysterious thoughts are you thinking?’ said a young-looking witch with short hair, sitting nearby. ‘I mean, just curious. I’m Brienne, by the way.’ She was gazing at him with one of those looks which Harry had firmly decided to just ignore until he was older.

‘So,’ Harry said, ‘you know those really simple Artificial Intelligence programs like ELIZA that are programmed to use words in syntactic English sentences only they don’t contain any understanding of what the words mean?’

‘Of course,’ the witch said. ‘I have a dozen of them in my trunk.’

‘Well, I’m pretty sure my understanding of girls is somewhere around that level.’

A sudden hush fell.

It took a few seconds for Harry to realize that, no, the entire Great Hall wasn’t staring at him, and then Harry twisted his head around to look.

The figure who’d just staggered into the Great Hall appeared to be Mr Filch, Hogwarts’s token hallway monitor; who, along with his predatory cat Mrs Norris, constituted a low-level random encounter whom Harry often breezed past wearing his epic-level Deathly Hallow. (Harry had once consulted the Weasley twins about pulling some sort of prank on this deserving target, whereupon Fred or George had quietly pointed out that Mr Filch was never seen to use a wand, which was odd, really, considering how many spells would be useful in that position, and it made you wonder why Dumbledore had given the man a position at Hogwarts, and Harry had shut up.)

Right now Mr Filch’s brown clothing was disarrayed and soaked with sweat, his shoulders were visibly heaving as he breathed, and his ever-present cat was missing.

‘Troll –’ gasped Mr Filch. ‘In the dungeons –’

Minerva McGonagall stood up from the Head Table so quickly that her chair fell to the ground behind her.

‘Argus!’ she cried. ‘What happened to you?’

Argus Filch staggered forward from the huge doors, his upper body streaked and dotted with small crimson dots as though someone had spattered steak sauce over his face. ‘Troll – grey – twice as tall as me – it – it –’ Argus Filch covered his face with his hands. ‘It ate Mrs Norris – ate her all up, in just one bite –’

Minerva felt a stab of dismay in her other self, she hadn’t liked the other cat very much but the two of them had still been felines.

An uproar started from the Great Hall. Severus stood up from the Head Table, somehow doing so without drawing any visible attention to himself, and strode out the huge doors without another word.

Of course, Minerva thought, the third-floor corridor – this could be a distraction –

She mentally consigned all such matters to Severus’s care, drew her wand, raised it high, and let out five sharp cracks of purple fire.

There was stunned silence but for Argus’s broken sobs.

‘It seems we have a dangerous creature loose in Hogwarts,’ she said to the faculty at the Head Table. ‘I will ask you all to aid in searching the halls.’ Then she turned to the stunned and watching students, and raised her voice. ‘Prefects – lead your houses back to the dormitories immediately!’

Percy Weasley leaped up from the Gryffindor table. ‘Follow me!’ he said in a high voice. ‘Stick together, first-years! No, not you –’ but by that time the other prefects were raising their own voices as a renewed babble sprang up.

Then a clear, cool voice spoke under the sudden rush of sound.

‘Deputy Headmistress.’

She turned.

The Defence Professor was calmly wiping off his hands on a napkin as he stood up from the Head Table. ‘With respect,’ said the man of unknown identity, ‘you are not expert in battle tactics, madam. In this situation, it would be wiser to –’

‘I do apologize, Professor,’ said Professor McGonagall, as she turned toward the great doors. Filius and Pomona had already risen to follow her, with Rubeus Hagrid towering over all of them as the half-giant stood up. She’d been through similar experiences too many times, at this point. ‘Sad experience has taught me that on occasions such as these, it is not a good time to take any advice the current Defence Professor may offer. Indeed, I think it wise that the two of us search for the troll together, so that no suspicions may be cast upon you for any untoward events which occur during that time.’

Without any hesitation, the Defence Professor swung smoothly on the Gryffindor table and clapped his hands with a sound like a floor cracking through.

‘Michelle Morgan of House Gryffindor, second in command of Pinnini’s Army,’ the Defence Professor said calmly into the resulting quiet. ‘Please advise your Head of House.’

Michelle Morgan climbed up onto her bench and spoke, the tiny witch sounding far more confident than Minerva remembered her being at the start of the year. ‘Students walking through the hallways would be spread out and impossible to defend. All students are to remain in the Great Hall and form a cluster in the centre … not surrounded by tables, a troll would jump right over tables … with the perimeter defended by seventh-year students. From the armies only, no matter how good they are at duelling, so they don’t get in each other’s lines of fire.’ Michelle hesitated. ‘I’m sorry, Mr Hagrid, but – it wouldn’t be safe for you, you should stay behind with the students. And Professor Trelawney shouldn’t confront a troll on her own either,’ Michelle sounded much less apologetic about this part, ‘but if she’s paired with Professor Quirrell the two of them together can form an additional trusted and effective battle unit. That concludes my analysis, Professor.’

‘Adequate, for being put on the spot,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘Twenty Quirrell points to you. But you neglect the still simpler point that home does not mean safe, and a troll is strong enough to rip a portrait door off its hinges –’

‘Enough,’ Minerva snapped. ‘Thank you, Miss Morgan.’ She looked to the watching tables. ‘Students, you will do as she said.’ Turned back to the Head Table. ‘Professor Trelawney, you will accompany the Defence Professor –’

‘Ah,’ Sybill said falteringly. Beneath her overdone make-up and heap of shawls, the woman looked rather pale. ‘I’m afraid – I’m not entirely well today – indeed, I feel rather faint –’

‘You won’t have to fight the troll,’ Minerva said sharply, her patience taxed as usual when dealing with the woman. ‘Just stay with the Defence Professor and do not let him out of your sight for an instant, you must be able to testify afterwards that you were with him at all times.’ She turned to Rubeus. ‘Rubeus, I am leaving you in charge here. Keep them safe.’ The huge man straightened at this, losing his glum look and nodding proudly to her.

Then Minerva looked at the students, and raised her voice. ‘It should go entirely without saying that anyone leaving the Great Hall for any reason, will be expelled. No excuses will be accepted. Am I understood?’

The Weasley twins, with whom she’d been making direct eye contact, nodded respectfully.

She turned without another word and marched off toward the hall doors with the other Professors behind her.

On the far side of the room, unnoticed on the wall, a clock showed 12:14pm.

… and he still didn’t realize.

Tick.

As Harry stared with narrowed eyes at where the Professors had gone out, wondering what was actually going on and what it meant, as the students came together into a more defensible mass and wands flicked to levitate the tables out of their way, Harry still didn’t realize.

Tick.

‘Shouldn’t the Professors all have formed up into pairs?’ said an older Gryffindor student whose name Harry didn’t know. ‘I mean – it’d be slower, but it’d be safer, I think –’

Tick.

Someone else replied to this, raising her voice, but Harry didn’t catch much of it, the gist was that mountain trolls were highly magic-resistant and incredibly strong and could regenerate but they were still noisy so if you heard them coming, it shouldn’t be that hard for a Hogwarts Professor to wrap them up in Vadim’s Unbreakable something something.

Tick.

And Harry still didn’t realize.

Tick.

The crowd noises were subdued, people were talking in low voices to each other while they glanced around, listening for the sound of a crashing door or an angry roar.

Tick.

Some students were speculating in whispers about what the Defence Professor could possibly be trying to achieve by smuggling in a troll, and whether he was angry that Professor McGonagall had caught on to his attempted distraction, and what it was a distraction from.

Tick.

And the thought still didn’t come to Harry, not until after all the students had formed a mass of perhaps a hundred bodies patrolled by proudly grim-looking seventh-year-students with their wands all pointed outward, and somebody suggested doing a headcount, and someone else replied sarcastically that this might have made sense on some other day, but right now practically everyone was gone for the spring holiday and nobody really knew how many students were supposed to be in the room, let alone if any were missing.

Tick.

That was when Harry wondered where Hermione was.

Tick.

Harry looked over at where the Ravenclaws had clustered, he didn’t see Hermione but then everyone was packed tightly-enough together that you wouldn’t expect to see smaller students through the crowd, amid the upper-years.

Tick.

Harry then looked over at the Hufflepuffs to see if he could spot Neville, and even though Neville was standing behind a much taller student, Harry’s visual processing managed to spot him almost immediately. Hermione wasn’t with the Hufflepuffs either, not that Harry could see – and she certainly wouldn’t be with the Slytherins –

Tick.

Harry pushed his way through the packed crowd, stepping beside or around older students and in one case just ducking between their legs, until he was standing among the Ravenclaws and could definitely verify that, nope, no Hermione.

Tick.

‘Hermione Granger!’ Harry said loudly. ‘Are you here?’

Nobody answered.

Tick.

Somewhere in the back of his mind was a rising sense of horror, as other parts of him tried to decide exactly how much to panic. The first Defence class of the year was rather fuzzy in Harry’s mind, but he distantly remembered something about trolls being able to track prey that was alone and undefended.

Tick.

Another line of thought searched frantically through inchoate possibilities, what could he do exactly? It wasn’t 3pm yet so he couldn’t reach this now using his Time-Turner. Even if he could sneak out of the room – there had to be some way to put on his Cloak without being noticed, some sort of distraction he could use – he had no idea where Hermione was, and Hogwarts was huge.

Tick.

Another part of his mind tried to model possibilities. From what that other student had said, trolls weren’t silent predators, they were noisy –

Hermione won’t have any idea it’s a troll, so she’ll go investigate the noise. She’s a heroine, isn’t she?

– but Hermione now had an invisibility cloak and a broomstick in her pouch. Harry had insisted on that part for both her and Neville, and Professor McGonagall had told him it’d been done. That ought to be enough to let Hermione get away, even if she was lousy on a broomstick. All she had to do was get onto a section of roof, it was a clear day and sunlight was supposed to be bad for trolls somehow, Harry remembered that part and therefore Hermione would remember it exactly. And surely, even if Hermione wanted to prove herself again, she couldn’t possibly be dumb enough to attack a mountain troll.

Tick.

She wouldn’t.

Tick.

That just wasn’t her.

Tick.

And then it occurred to Harry that somebody had previously tried to frame Hermione Granger for murder using Memory Charms. Had done so inside Hogwarts, without setting off any alarms. And had arranged for Draco to die slowly enough that it wouldn’t set off the wards until at least six hours later when nobody could use a Time-Turner to check. And that whoever was clever enough to infiltrate a troll past the ancient wards of Hogwarts without the Headmaster coming to investigate the strange creature, could be clever enough to also take the obvious step of jinxing Hermione’s magic items …

Tick.

There was a part of him that felt something like slowly rising panic as perspective shifted, a Necker Cube changing orientation, what the hell had Harry been thinking, letting Hermione and Neville be kept inside Hogwarts just because of them being given a few stupid trinkets, that wasn’t going to stop anyone who wanted to kill them.

Tick.

Another part of his mind put up resistance, that possibility wasn’t certain, it was complex and the probability could easily be under 50%. It was easy to imagine going into a huge panic in front of everyone and then Hermione getting back from the toilets outside the Great Hall. Or if the troll ended up not going anywhere near her … like in the story of the boy who cried wolf, nobody would believe him the next time if she really was in trouble; it could use up reputational credit that he would later need for something else …

Tick.

Harry recognized an instance of the fear-of-embarrassment schema that stopped most people from ever doing anything under conditions of uncertainty, and squashed it down hard. Even then it was strange how much willpower it took to muster the decision to shout out loud in front of everyone, if he just hadn’t seen Hermione in the crowd it was going to be embarrassing …

Tick.

Harry drew in a deep breath and shouted as loudly as he could, ‘Hermione Granger! Are you here?’

The students all turned to look at him. Then some of them turned around to look around themselves. The noise around the room went down in volume as some conversations stilled.

‘Has anyone seen Hermione Granger since – since around ten-thirty today or so? Does anyone have any idea where she might be?’

The background babble stilled further.

Nobody raised their voice to shout anything at him, in particular not, Don’t worry, Harry, I’m right here.

‘Oh, Merlin,’ somebody said from nearby, and then the background babble started up again, taking on a new and excited tone.

Precautionary Measures

May 13th, 1992.

Argus Filch’s face appeared twisted in the light of the oil lamp he held, shadows dancing over his face. Behind them the doors of Hogwarts quickly receded, and the dark grounds moved closer. The track they now walked was muddy and indistinct.

The trees, branches formerly bare with winter, were not yet fully clad with spring; their branches stretched up toward the sky like lean fingers, skeletons visible amid the thin foliage. The moon was bright, but clouds scudding across it often threw them into darkness, lit only by the dim flames of Filch’s lamp.

Draco kept a firm grip on his wand.

‘Where are you taking us?’ said Tracey Davis. She’d been caught along with Draco by Filch, on their way to an attempted meeting of the Silvery Slytherins after curfew hours, and likewise given a detention.

‘You just follow me,’ said Argus Filch.

Draco was feeling rather annoyed with the whole affair. The Silvery Slytherins ought to be recognized school business. There was no reason why a secret conspiracy shouldn’t have permission to meet after curfew, if it was for the greater good of Hogwarts. If this happened one more time he’d talk to Daphne Greengrass and Daphne would talk to her father and then Filch would learn the wisdom of looking the other way where Malfoys were concerned.

The lights of the Hogwarts castle had diminished in the distance when Filch spoke again. ‘I bet you’ll think twice about breaking a school rule again, won’t you, eh?’ Filch turned his head, away from the lamp, so that he could leer at the four students following him. ‘Oh yes … hard work and pain are the best teachers if you ask me … It’s just a pity they let the old punishments die out … hang you by your wrists from the ceiling for a few days, I’ve got the chains still in my office, keep ’em well oiled in case they’re ever needed …’

‘Hey!’ Tracey said, a touch of indignation entering her voice. ‘I’m too young to hear about that – that sort of – you know! Especially if the chains are well-oiled!’

Draco wasn’t paying attention. Filch simply wasn’t in Amycus Carrow’s league.

Behind them, one of the two older Slytherins following them snickered, though she didn’t say anything. Beside her was the other, a tall boy with a Slavic cast to his face, and who still spoke with an accent. They’d been caught for some unrelated offense, having to do with the type of thing Tracey went on about, and looked to be in their third or fourth year. ‘Pfeh,’ said the taller boy. ‘In Durmstrang they hang you upside-down by your toes. By one toe, if you are insolent. Hogwarts was soft even in the old days.’

Argus Filch was silent for around half a minute, as though trying to think of a proper rejoinder, and then gave a chuckle. ‘We’ll see what you say about that … when you learn what you’ll be doing tonight! Ha!’

‘I said, I’m too young for that sort of thing!’ said Tracey Davis. ‘It has to wait until I’m older!’

Ahead of them was a cottage with lighted windows, though the proportions seemed wrong.

Filch whistled, a high sharp sound, and a dog began barking.

From the cottage stepped forth a figure, making the trees seem too short around it. The figure was followed by a dog that seemed like a puppy by comparison, until you looked at it apart from the taller silhouette and realized the dog was huge, more like a wolf.

Draco’s eyes narrowed, before he caught himself. As a Silvery Slytherin he wasn’t supposed to be Prejudiced against any sentient being, especially not where other people might see him.

‘What’s this?’ said the figure, in the loud gruff voice of the half-giant. His umbrella lit up with a white glow, brighter than Filch’s dim lamp. In his other hand he held a crossbow; a quiver of short bolts was strapped to his upper arm.

‘Students serving detention,’ Filch said, loudly. ‘They’re to help you search the Forest for … whatever’s been eating ’em.’

‘The Forest?’ gasped Tracey. ‘We can’t go in there at night!’

‘That’s right,’ said Filch, turning from Hagrid to glare at them. ‘It’s into the Forest you’re going, and I’m much mistaken if you’ll all come out in one piece.’

‘But –’ said Tracey. ‘There’s werewolves, I’ve heard, and vampires, and everyone knows what happens when there’s a girl and a werewolf and a vampire all at the same time!’

The huge half-giant was frowning. ‘Argus, I ’ad in mind you an’ maybe a few seventh-years. ’Ere’s not much point in bringing along help if I’m to watch over ’em the whole time.’

Argus’s face lit with cruel satisfaction. ‘That’s their lookout, isn’t it? Should’ve thought of them werewolves before they got in trouble, shouldn’t they? Send them out alone. I shouldn’t be too friendly to them, Hagrid. They’re here to be punished, after all.’

The half-giant gave a massive sigh (it sounded like a normal man having all the air driven out of his lungs by a Bludgeoning Hex). ‘Yeh’ve done yer bit. I’ll take over from here.’

‘I’ll be back at dawn,’ said Filch, ‘for what’s left of them,’ he added nastily, and he turned and started back toward the castle, his lamp bobbing away in the darkness.

‘Right then,’ said Hagrid, ‘now, listen carefully, ’cause it’s dangerous what we’re gonna do tonight an’ I don’ want no one takin’ risks. Follow me over here a moment.’

He led them to the very edge of the Forest. Holding his lamp up high he pointed down a narrow, winding earth track that disappeared into the thick black trees. A light breeze blew over Draco’s head as he looked into the Forest.

‘There’s summat in there that’s bin eatin’ unicorns,’ the huge man said.

Draco nodded; he distantly remembered hearing something along those lines a couple of weeks ago, toward the end of April.

‘Did you call us to track down a trail of silvery blood to a wounded unicorn?’ Tracey said excitedly.

‘No,’ said Draco, though he managed to stop the reflexive sneer. ‘Filch gave us the detention note at lunch today, at noon. Mr Hagrid wouldn’t wait that long to find a wounded unicorn, and if we were looking for something like that, we’d look in the day when it’s bright. So,’ Draco held up a finger, like he’d seen Inspector León do in plays, ‘I infer that we’re looking for something that only comes out at night.’

‘Aye,’ said the half-giant, sounding thoughtful. ‘Yer not what I expected, Draco Malfoy. Not what I expected at all. An’ you’d be Tracey Davis, then. I’ve heard of yeh. One of poor Miss Granger’s lot.’ Rubeus Hagrid looked over at the two older Slytherins, peering at them in the light of his glowing umbrella. ‘An’ who’d yeh be, again? Don’t remember seeing much of yeh, boy.’

‘Cornelia Walt,’ said the witch, ‘and this is Yuri Yuliy,’ indicating the Slavic-looking boy who’d spoken of Durmstrang. ‘His family is visiting from the Ukrainian lands, so he’s in Hogwarts just for the year.’ The older boy nodded, a faintly contemptuous cast on his face.

‘This is Fang,’ Hagrid said, indicating the dog.

The five of them set off into the woods.

‘What could be killing unicorns?’ Draco said after they’d walked for a few minutes. Draco knew a bit about Dark creatures, but he couldn’t remember anything that was said to prey on unicorns. ‘What sort of creature does that, does anyone know?’

‘Werewolves!’ said Tracey.

‘Miss Davis?’ Draco said, and when she looked at him, he silently pointed a finger up at the moon. It was waxing gibbous, but not yet full.

‘Oh, right,’ said Tracey.

‘No weres in the Forest,’ said Hagrid. ‘They’re plain wizards most o’ the time, ’member. Couldn’t be wolves either, they’re not near fast enough ter catch a unicorn. Powerful magical creatures, unicorns are, I never knew one ter be hurt before.’

Draco listened to this, thinking about the puzzle almost despite himself. ‘Then what is fast enough to catch a unicorn?’

‘Wouldn’t ’ave been a matter of speed,’ Hagrid said, giving Draco an indecipherable glance. ‘’Ere’s no end ter the ways that creatures hunt. Poison, darkness, traps. Imps as can’t be seen or heard or remembered, even while they’re eatin’ yer face. Always summat new an’ wonderful to learn.’

A cloud passed over the moon, casting the forest into shadow lit only by the glow of Hagrid’s umbrella.

‘Meself,’ Hagrid continued, ‘I think we might ’ave a Parisian hydra on our ’ands. They’re no threat to a wizard, yeh’ve just got to keep holdin’ ’em off long enough, and there’s no way yeh can lose. I mean literally no way yeh can lose so long’s yeh keep fightin’. Trouble is, against a Parisian hydra, most creatures give up long before. Takes a while to cut down all the heads, yeh see.’

‘Bah,’ said the foreign boy. ‘In Durmstrang we learn to fight Buchholz hydra. Unimaginably more tedious to fight! I mean literally, cannot imagine. First-years not believe us when we tell them winning is possible! Instructor must give second order, iterate until they comprehend.’

They walked for nearly half an hour, deeper and deeper into the Forest, until the path became almost impossible to follow because the trees were so thick.

Then Draco saw it, thick splashes on the roots of trees, gleaming a brighter colour beneath the moonlight. ‘Is that –’

‘Unicorn’s blood,’ Hagrid said. The huge man’s voice was sad.

In a clearing ahead, visible through the tangled branches of a great oak, they saw the fallen creature, splayed beautiful and sad upon the ground, the dirt around her shining moon-silver with pooled blood. The unicorn was not white, but pale blue, or appearing so beneath the moon and night sky. Her slender legs stuck out at odd angles, obviously broken, and her mane spread across the dark leaves, green-black but with a sheen like pearls. On her flank was a small white shape like a starburst, a centre surrounded by eight straight rays. Half her side had been ripped away, the edges ragged like the marks of teeth, bones and inner organs exposed.

A strange choking sensation rose in Draco’s throat.

‘That’s ’er,’ Hagrid said, his sad whisper as loud as a normal man’s voice. ‘Just where I found ’er this mornin’, dead as a dead doorknob. She is – was – the first unicorn I e’er met in these woods. I called ’er Alicorn, not that it matters ter ’er any more, I s’pose.’

‘You named a unicorn Alicorn,’ said the older girl. Her voice was a bit dry.

‘But she doesn’t have wings,’ Tracey said.

‘An alicorn’s a unicorn’s horn,’ Hagrid said, now louder. ‘Don’t know where yeh all started thinking it meant a unicorn with wings, ’ere’s no such thing I ever heard. It’s just like naming a dog Fang,’ indicating the huge wolf-like dog that barely came to his knees. ‘What’d you have called ’er? Hannah, or some such? I gave ’er a name as would’ve meant summat ter ’er. Common courtesy, I call it.’

Nobody said anything to this, and after a further moment, the huge man gave a sharp nod. ‘We’ll start our search from ’ere, the last place it struck. We’re gonna split inter two parties an’ follow the trail in diff’rent directions. Yeh two, Walt and Yuliy – yeh’ll go that way, and take Fang. There’s nothin’ that lives in the Forest that’ll hurt yeh if yer with Fang. Send up green sparks if yeh find summat interestin’, an’ send up red sparks if anyone gets in trouble. Davis, Malfoy, with me.’

The Forest was black and silent. Rubeus Hagrid had dimmed the light of his umbrella after they’d set out, so that Draco and Tracey had to steer themselves by the light of the moon, not without occasional trips and falls. They walked past a mossy tree-stump, the sound of running water speaking of a stream somewhere close by. Now and then a ray of moonlight through the branches above lit a spot of silver blue blood on the fallen leaves; they were following the trail of blood, toward where the creature must have first struck the unicorn.

‘There’s rumours about yeh,’ Hagrid said in a low voice after they’d walked for a while.

‘Well, they’re all true,’ Tracey said. ‘All of them.’

‘Not yeh,’ Hagrid said. ‘Did yeh really testify under Veritaserum that yeh tried to help Miss Granger, three times it was?’

Draco weighed his words for a while, and finally said, ‘Yes.’ It wouldn’t have done to appear too eager to claim credit.

The huge man shook his head, his great feet still stomping silently through the woods. ‘I’m surprised, teh be honest. And yeh too, Davis, tryin’ to put the halls in order. Are yeh sure the Sorting Hat put yeh in the right place? There’s not a single witch or wizard who went bad who wasn’t in Slytherin, so it’s always been said.’

‘That’s not true,’ Tracey said. ‘What about Xiaonan Tong the Black Raven, Spencer of the Hill, and Mister Kayvon?’

‘Who?’ said Hagrid.

‘Just some of the best Dark Wizards from the last two centuries,’ Tracey said. ‘They’re probably the best from Hogwarts who weren’t from Slytherin.’ Her voice fell, lost its enthusiasm. ‘Miss Granger always told me I should read up on anything I –’

‘Anyway,’ Draco said quickly, ‘that’s not really relevant, Mr Hagrid. Even if –’ Draco worked it around in his head, trying to translate the difference between probability of Slytherin given Dark and probability of Dark given Slytherin into non-scientific language. ‘Even if most Dark Wizards are from Slytherin, very few Slytherins are Dark Wizards. There aren’t all that many Dark Wizards, so not all Slytherins can be one.’ Or as Father had said, while any Malfoy should certainly know much of the secret lore, the more … costly rituals were better left to useful fools like Amycus Carrow.

‘So yeh’re saying,’ Hagrid said, ‘that most Dark Wizards are Slytherins … but …’

‘But most Slytherins are not Dark Wizards,’ Draco said. He had a weary feeling they’d be at this a while, but like fighting a hydra, the important thing was to not give up.

‘I never thought of it that way,’ the huge man said, sounding awestruck. ‘But, well, if yeh’re not all a house of snakes, then why – get behind that tree!’

Hagrid seized Draco and Tracey and hoisted them off the path behind a towering oak. He pulled out a bolt and fitted it into his crossbow, raising it, ready to fire. The three of them listened. Something was slithering over dead leaves nearby: it sounded like a cloak trailing along the ground. Hagrid was squinting up the dark path, but after a few seconds, the sound faded away.

‘I knew it,’ Hagrid murmured. ‘There’s summat in here that shouldn’ be.’

They went after where the rustling sound had come from, with Hagrid in the lead and Tracey and Draco both gripping their wands at the ready, but they found nothing, despite searching in a widening circle with their ears straining for the faintest sound.

They walked on through the dense, dark trees. Draco kept looking over his shoulder, a feeling nagging at him that they were being watched. They had just passed a bend in the path when Tracey yelled and pointed.

In the distance, a shower of red sparks lit the air.

‘You two wait here!’ Hagrid shouted. ‘Stay where yeh are, I’ll come back for yeh!’

Before Draco could say a word, Hagrid spun and crashed away through the undergrowth.

Draco and Tracey stood looking at each other, until they heard nothing but the rustling of leaves around them. Tracey looked scared, but trying to hide it. Draco was feeling more annoyed than anything else. Apparently Rubeus Hagrid, when he had formed his plans for tonight, had not spent even five seconds visualizing the consequences if something actually went wrong.

‘Now what?’ said Tracey, her voice a little high.

‘We wait for Mr Hagrid to come back.’

The minutes dragged by. Draco’s ears seemed sharper than usual, picking up every sigh of the wind, every cracking twig. Tracey kept looking up at the moon, as though to reassure herself that it wasn’t full yet.

‘I’m –’ Tracey whispered. ‘I’m getting a little nervous, Mr Malfoy.’

Draco thought about it a bit. To be honest, there was something … well, it wasn’t that he was a coward, or even that he was scared. But there had been a murder at Hogwarts and if he’d been watching himself in a play, having just been abandoned in the Forbidden Forest by a half-giant, he would currently feel like yelling at the boy on stage that he should …

Draco reached into his robes, and took out a mirror. Tapping the surface showed a man in red robes, who frowned almost immediately.

‘Auror Captain Eneasz Brodski,’ the man said clearly, causing Tracey to start with the loudness in the quiet forest. ‘What is it, Draco Malfoy?’

‘Put me on ten-minute check-in,’ Draco said. He’d decided not to complain directly about his detention. He did not want to look like a spoiled brat. ‘If I don’t respond, come get me. I’m in the Forbidden Forest.’

Inside the mirror, the Auror’s brows rose. ‘What are you doing in the Forbidden Forest, Mr Malfoy?’

‘Looking for the unicorn-eater with Mr Hagrid,’ Draco said, and tapped the mirror off, putting it back in his robes before the Auror could ask anything about detentions or say anything about serving it out without complaining.

Tracey’s head turned toward him, though it was a little too dim to read her expression. ‘Um, thanks,’ she whispered.

The few leaves which had emerged on their branches rustled as another, colder breeze blew through the forest.

Tracey’s voice was a little louder when she spoke again. ‘You didn’t have to –’ she said, now sounding a little shy.

‘Don’t mention it, Miss Davis.’

The dark silhouette of Tracey put her hand to her cheek, as though to conceal a blush that wasn’t visible anyway. ‘I mean, not for me –’

‘No, really,’ Draco said. ‘Don’t mention it. At all.’ He would have threatened to take out the mirror and order Captain Brodski not to rescue her, but he was afraid she would consider that flirting.

Tracey’s silhouetted head turned from him, looked away. Finally she said, in a smaller voice, ‘It’s too soon, isn’t it –’

A high scream echoed through the woods, a not-quite-human sound, the scream of something like a horse; and Tracey shrieked and ran.

‘No, you numbskull!’ yelled Draco, plunging after her. The sound had been so eerie that Draco wasn’t certain where it came from – but he thought that Tracey Davis might, in fact, be running straight toward the source of that eerie scream.

Brambles whipped at Draco’s eyes, he had to keep one hand in front of his face to shield them, trying not to lose track of Tracey because it seemed obvious that, if this was a play, and they got separated, one of them was going to die. Draco thought of the mirror secured within his robes but he somehow knew that if he tried to take it out one-handed while running, the mirror would inevitably fall and be lost –

Ahead of them, Tracey had stopped, and Draco felt relieved for an instant, before he saw.

Another unicorn lay on the ground, surrounded by a slowly widening pool of silver blood, the edge of the blood creeping across the ground like spilled mercury. Her coat was purple, like the colour of the night sky, her horn exactly the same twilight colour as her skin, her visible flank marked by a pink star-blotch surrounded by white patches. The sight tore at Draco’s heart, even more than the other unicorn because this one’s eyes were staring glassily right at him, and because there was a –

– blurring, twisting form –

– feeding on an open wound on the unicorn’s side, like it was drinking from it –

– Draco couldn’t understand, somehow couldn’t recognize what he was seeing –

– it was looking at them.

The blurring, seething, unrecognisable darkness seemed to turn to regard them. A hiss came from it, like the hiss of the deadliest snake which ever had existed, something more dangerous by far than any Blue Krait.

Then it bent back over the wound in the unicorn, and continued to drink.

The mirror was in Draco’s hand, and it remained lifeless as his finger mechanically tapped at the surface, over and over.

Tracey was holding her wand now, saying things like ‘Prismatis’ and ‘Stupefy’ but nothing was happening.

Then the seething outline rose up, like a man rising to his feet only not so; and it seemed to scuttle forward, moving with a strange half-jump across the dying unicorn’s legs, approaching the two of them.

Tracey tugged at his sleeve and then turned to run, run from something that could hunt down unicorns. Before she could take three steps there came another terrible hiss, burning his ears, and Tracey fell to the ground and did not move.

Somewhere in the back of his mind, Draco knew that he was about to die. Even if the Auror checked his mirror this very instant, there was no way anyone could get here fast enough. There was no time.

Running hadn’t worked.

Magic hadn’t worked.

The seething outline came closer, while Draco tried, in his last moments, to solve the riddle.

Then a blazing silver ball of light plunged out of the night sky and hung there, illuminating the forest as bright as daylight, and the seething outline leapt backwards, as though in horror of the light.

Four broomsticks plunged out of the sky, three Aurors with bright multicoloured shields and Harry Potter holding his wand aloft, seated behind Professor McGonagall within a larger shield.

‘Get out of here!’ roared Professor McGonagall –

- an instant before the seething thing gave forth another terrible hiss, and all the shielding spells winked out. The three Aurors and Professor McGonagall fell off their broomsticks and dropped heavily to the forest floor, lying motionless.

Draco couldn’t breathe, the most intense fear he’d ever felt in his life gripping all through his chest, sending tendrils around his heart.

Harry Potter, who had remained untouched, silently guided his broomstick toward the ground –

- and then leapt off to stand between Draco and the seething outline, interposing himself like a living shield.

‘Run!’ said Harry Potter, turning his head half-back to look at Draco. The silver moonlight gleamed on his face. ‘Run, Draco! I’ll hold it off!’

‘You can’t fight that thing alone!’ Draco cried aloud. A nausea was in his stomach, a churning sensation that, looking back in memory, seemed both like and unlike a sense of guilt, as though it had the sensations but not quite all of the emotion.

‘I must,’ Harry Potter said grimly. ‘Go!’

‘Harry, I – I’m sorry, for everything – I’ Though later, looking back, Draco couldn’t quite remember what he’d meant to apologize for, maybe it’d been that he was planning to overthow Harry’s conspiracy, all that time ago.

The seething figure, now seeming blacker and more terrible, rose up into the air, hovering off the ground.

‘GO!’ shouted Harry.

Draco turned and fled headlong into the woods,with the branches whipping at his face. Behind him, Draco heard another terrible hiss, and Harry’s voice rising, crying something that Draco couldn’t make out from the distance; Draco turned his head for only an instant to look back, and in that moment ran into something, hitting his head HARD, and blacked out.

Harry held a tight grip on his wand, a Prismatic Sphere glowing around him. He stared levelly at the seething, blurring form in front of him, and said, ‘What on Earth are you doing?’

The seething blurs resolved, reformed, relaxed back into a hooded form. Whatever concealment had been at work – a device rather than a Charm, Harry guessed, since the magic had been able to affect him – had prevented his mind from recognizing the shape or even that the shape was human. But it hadn’t prevented Harry from recognizing the sharp sense of doom.

Professor Quirrell stood straight with silver blood all down the front of his enshrouding black cloak, and gave a sigh, looking at the fallen forms of three Aurors, Tracey Davis, Draco Malfoy, and Professor McGonagall. ‘I had honestly thought,’ Professor Quirrell murmured, ‘that I jammed that mirror without alarm. What were two first-year Slytherins doing alone in the Forbidden Forest? Mr Malfoy has more sense than this … What a fiasco.’

Harry didn’t answer. The sense of doom was as strong as Harry could ever remember feeling it, a feeling of power in the air so great that it was almost tangible. Some part of him was still viscerally shocked at how fast the shields surrounding the Aurors had been torn apart. He almost hadn’t been able to see the successive lashes of colour which had torn away the shields like tissue paper. It made the duel Professor Quirrell had fought against the Auror in Azkaban look like a mockery, a child’s game – though Professor Quirrell had claimed, then, that if he’d fought for real the Auror would have been dead in seconds; and Harry knew now that this was also true.

Just how high did the power ladder go?

‘I take it,’ Harry said, managing to keep his voice steady, ‘that your eating unicorns has something to do with why you’ll get fired from the Defence Professor position. I don’t suppose you’d care to explain in considerable detail?’

Professor Quirrell looked at him. The almost tangible sense of power in the air seemed to diminish, drawing back into the Defence Professor. ‘I shall indeed explain myself,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘I need to cast a few Memory Charms first, and then we may go off and discuss it, for it would not be wise for me to stay. You will return to this time later, as I know.’

Harry willed himself to be able to see through the Cloak he had mastered; and knew that another Harry stood beside him, hidden by his own Deathly Hallow. Harry then told his Cloak to hide himself from himself once more, and it did; being able to perceive your future self meant having to match the memory later.

Harry’s own voice said, then, sounding strange in present-Harry’s ears, ‘He has a surprisingly good explanation.’

Present-Harry remembered the words as best he could. Nothing more was said between them.

Professor Quirrell walked to Draco’s form, and chanted the spell of the False Memory Charm. The Defence Professor stood there for perhaps a minute, seemingly lost to the world.

Harry had been studying Obliviations, these last couple of weeks – though he couldn’t have helped cast the spells, unless he was willing to exhaust himself almost completely, and for some reason they wanted an Auror to lose every single life memory involving the colour blue. But Harry had some idea, now, of the concentration which the far more difficult False Memory Charm entailed. You had to try to live the other person’s entire life inside your own head, at least if you wanted to create the False Memories with less than a sixteen-to-one slowdown as you separately crafted sixteen major tracks of memory. It might have been quiet, there might have been no outward sign; but Harry knew something of the difficulties now, and he knew to be impressed.

Professor Quirrell finished, and moved on to Tracey Davis, then the three Aurors, and finally Professor McGonagall. Harry waited, but future-Harry made no protest. It was possible that even Professor McGonagall, if she’d been awake, wouldn’t have protested. It was not yet the Ides of May, and apparently there would be a surprisingly good explanation.

With a gesture, Draco’s stunned body was lifted, and sent a short distance into the woods, before being carefully deposited on the ground. Then a final gesture from Professor Quirrell ripped a huge chunk out of the unicorn’s side, leaving behind ragged edges; the raw meat hovered in the air, then wavered in Vanishment and was gone.

‘Done,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I must depart this place now, Mr Potter. Come with me, and remain here.’

Professor Quirrell strode away, and Harry followed and remained behind.

They walked through the woods in silence for a time, before Harry heard faint voices in the distance. The next set of Aurors, presumably, after the first set had fallen out of contact. What his future self was saying, Harry didn’t know.

‘They won’t detect us, nor hear our speech,’ said Professor Quirrell. The sense of power and doom around the Defence Professor was still strong. The man seated himself on a tree stump, one where the light of the almost-full moon fell full on him. ‘I should first say that when you speak to the Aurors, in the future, you should tell them that you frightened away the seething dark, the same as you did that Dementor. It is what Mr Malfoy will remember seeing.’ Professor Quirrell gave a small sigh. ‘It may cause some alarm, if they conclude that some horror kin to Dementors, and strong enough to break the Aurors’ shields, is loose in the Forbidden Forest. But I could not think of what else to do. If the forest is better-guarded after this – but with any luck I have already consumed what I need. Would you mind telling me how you arrived so quickly? How did you know Mr Malfoy was in trouble?’

After Captain Brodski had learned that Draco Malfoy was in the Forbidden Forest, seemingly in the company of Rubeus Hagrid, Brodski had begun inquiring to find out who had authorized this, and had still been unable to find out when Draco Malfoy had missed check-in. Despite Harry’s protests, the Auror Captain, who was authorized to know about Time-Turners, had refused to allow deployment to before the time of the missed check-in; there were standard procedures involving Time. But Brodski had given Harry written orders allowing him to go back and deploy an Auror trio to arrive one second after the missed check-in time. There had been a Patronus Charm to locate Draco, which Harry had successfully willed to take the form of a ball of pure silver light, and the flight of Aurors had arrived on time to the second.

‘I’m afraid I couldn’t say,’ Harry replied evenly. Professor Quirrell was still a major suspect, and it was good for him not to know the details. ‘Now why are you eating unicorns?’

‘Ah,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘As to that …’ The man hesitated. ‘I was drinking the blood of unicorns, not eating them. The missing flesh, the ragged marks upon the body – those were to obscure the case, to make it seem like some other predator. The use of unicorn’s blood is too well-known.’

‘I don’t know it,’ Harry said.

‘I know you do not,’ the Defence Professor said sharply. ‘Or you would not be pestering me about it. The power of unicorn’s blood is to preserve your life for a time, even if you are on the very verge of death.’

There was a stretch of time when Harry’s brain claimed to be refusing to process the words, which was of course a lie, because you couldn’t know the meaning you weren’t allowed to process, without having already processed it.

A strange sense of blankness overtook Harry, an absence of reaction, maybe this was what other people felt like when someone went off-script, and they couldn’t say or think of anything to do.

Of course Professor Quirrell was dying, not just occasionally ill.

Professor Quirrell had known he was dying. He’d volunteered to take the Defence Professor position at Hogwarts, after all.

Of course he’d been getting worse the whole school year. Of course illnesses which kept getting worse had a predictable destination at their end.

Harry’s brain had surely known already, somewhere in the safe back of his mind where he could refuse to process things he’d already processed.

Of course that was why Professor Quirrell wouldn’t be able to teach Battle Magic next year. Professor McGonagall wouldn’t even have to fire him. He would just be –

– dead.

‘No,’ Harry said, his voice a little shaky. ‘There has to be a way –’

‘I am not stupid nor particularly eager to die. I have already looked. I had to go this far simply to last out my lesson plans, having less time than I had thought, and –’ The head of the dark moonlit figure turned away. ‘I think I do not want to hear about it, Mr Potter.’

Harry’s breath hitched. Too many emotions were bubbling up in him at once. After denial came anger, according to a ritual someone had just made up. And yet it seemed surprisingly appropriate.

‘And why –’ Harry’s breath hitched again. ‘Why isn’t unicorn’s blood standard in healer’s kits, then? To keep someone alive, even if they’re on the very verge of dying from their legs being eaten?’

‘Because there are permanent side effects,’ Professor Quirrell said quietly.

‘Side effects? Side effects? What kind of side effect is medically worse than DEATH?’ Harry’s voice rose on the last word until he was shouting.

‘Not everyone thinks the same way we do, Mr Potter. Though, to be fair, the blood must come from a live unicorn and the unicorn must die in the drinking. Would I be here otherwise?’

Harry turned, stared at the surrounding trees. ‘Have a herd of unicorns at St. Mungo’s. Floo the patients there, or use portkeys.’

‘Yes, that would work.’

Harry’s face tightened, the only outward sign behind his trembling hands of everything that was welling up inside him. He needed to scream, needed some outlet, needed something he couldn’t name and finally Harry levelled his wand at a tree and shouted ‘Diffindo!’

There was a sharp tearing sound, and a cut appeared across the wood.

‘Diffindo!’

Another cut. Harry had learned the Charm only ten days previously, after he’d started getting serious about self-defence. It was theoretically a second-year Charm, but the anger pouring through him seemed to know no bounds, he knew enough now not to exhaust himself and he still had power yet.

‘Diffindo!’ Harry had aimed at a branch this time, and it plummeted to the ground with a sound of twigs and leaves.

There didn’t seem to be any tears inside him, only pressure with no outlet.

‘I shall leave you to it,’ Professor Quirrell said quietly. The Defence Professor rose from his tree stump, the unicorn’s blood still moonlit on the black cloak he wore, and drew his hood back over his head.

Harry stood, panting, in the midst of a brief wasted circle amid the forest, more destruction than a first-year should have been able to reach, by himself. The Severing Charm wouldn’t bring down a tree, so he’d started partially Transfiguring cross-sections through the wood. It hadn’t let out what was inside him, bringing down a small circle of trees hadn’t made him feel any better, all the emotions were still there but while he was destroying trees he at least wasn’t thinking about how the feelings couldn’t be let out.

After Harry had run out of available magic he’d started tearing off branches with his bare hands and snapping them. His hands were bleeding, though nothing that Madam Pomfrey couldn’t fix in the morning. Only Dark magic left permanent scars on wizards.

There came a sound of something moving in the woods, like the hoof-beats of a horse, and Harry whirled, his wand rising once more; some part of his magic had returned while he was working with his hands. It occurred to him for the first time that he was out in the Forbidden Forest alone, and making noise.

What emerged into the moonlight was not the unicorn Harry had expected, but a creature with a lower body like that of a horse, gleaming white-brown beneath the moonlight, and the bare upper chest of a male human with long white hair. The moonlight caught the centaur’s face, and Harry saw that the eyes were almost as blue as Dumbledore’s, halfway to sapphire.

In one hand the centaur held a long wooden spear, with an overlarge metal blade whose edge did not gleam beneath the moonlight; a gleaming edge, Harry had once read, was the sign of a dull blade.

‘So,’ the centaur said. His voice was low, powerful and male. ‘Here you are, surrounded by destruction. I can smell the unicorn’s blood in the air, the blood of something innocent, slain to save oneself.’

A jolt of sudden fear brought Harry into the now, and he said quickly, ‘It’s not what it looks like.’

‘I know. The stars themselves proclaim your innocence, ironically enough.’ The centaur took a step toward Harry within the small clearing, still holding his spear upright. ‘A strange word, innocence. It means lack of knowledge, like the innocence of a child, and also means lack of guilt. Only those entirely ignorant can lack all responsibility for the consequences of their actions. He knows not what he does, and therefore can be without harmful intent; so says that word.’ The deep voice did not echo in the woods.

Harry’s eyes flickered to the spear-tip, and he realized that he should have grabbed his Time-Turner the moment he saw the centaur. Now, if Harry tried to reach beneath his robes, the spear could strike him before then, if the centaur was fast enough. ‘I read once,’ Harry said, his voice a bit unsteady as he tried to match deep-sounding words to deep-sounding words, ‘that it’s wrong to think of little children as innocent, because not knowing isn’t the same as not choosing. That children do little harms to each other with school-yard fights, because they don’t have the power to do great harm. And some adults do great harm. But the adults who don’t, aren’t they more innocent than children, not less?’

‘The wisdom of wizards,’ the centaur said.

‘Muggle wisdom, actually.’

‘Of the magicless I know little. Mars has been dim of late, but it grows brighter.’ The centaur took another step forwards, bringing him almost within striking distance of Harry.

Harry didn’t dare look up to the sky. ‘That means Mars is coming closer to the Earth, as both planets go around the Sun. Mars is reflecting the same amount of sunlight as always, it’s just getting nearer to us. What do you mean, the stars proclaim my innocence?’

‘The night sky speaks to centaurs. It is how we know what we know. Or do they not even tell wizards that much, these days?’ A look of contempt crossed the centaur’s face.

‘I … tried to look up centaurs, when I was checking out Divination. Most of the authors just ridiculed centaur Divination without explaining why, wizards don’t understand argumentative norms, to them ridiculing an idea or a person feels like casting that idea down just as much as bringing evidence against it … I thought the part about centaurs using astrology was just more ridicule …’

‘Why?’ the centaur intoned. His head cocked curiously.

‘Because the course of the planets is predictable for thousands of years in advance. If I talked to the right Muggles, I could show you a diagram of exactly what the planets will look like from this spot ten years later. Would you be able to make predictions from that?’

The centaur shook his head. ‘From a diagram? No. The light of the planets, the comets, the subtle shifts in the stars themselves, those I would not see.’

‘Cometary orbits are also set thousands of years in advance so they shouldn’t correlate much to current events. And the light of the stars takes years to travel from the stars to Earth, and the stars don’t move much at all, not visibly. So the obvious hypothesis is that centaurs have a native magical talent for Divination which you just, well, project onto the night sky.’

‘Perhaps,’ the centaur said thoughtfully. His head lowered. ‘The others would strike you for saying such a thing, but I have ever sought to know what I do not know. Why the night sky can foretell the future – that I surely do not know. It is hard enough to grasp the skill itself. All I can say, son of Lily, is that even if what you are saying is true, it does not seem useful.’

Harry allowed himself to relax a little; being addressed as son of Lily implied that the centaur thought of him as more than a random intruder in the forest. Besides, attacking a Hogwarts student would probably bring some kind of huge reprisal upon the non-wizard centaur tribe in the forests, and the centaur probably knew that … ‘What Muggles have learned is that there is a power in the truth, in all the pieces of the truth which interact with each other, which you can only find by discovering as many truths as possible. To do that you can’t defend false beliefs in any way, not even by saying the false belief is useful. It might not seem to matter whether your predictions are really based on the stars or if it’s an innate talent being projected. But if you wanted to really understand Divination, or for that matter the stars, the real truth about centaur predictions would be a fact that matters to other truths.’

Slowly the centaur nodded. ‘So the wandless have become wiser than the wizards. What a joke! Tell me, son of Lily, do the Muggles in their wisdom say that soon the skies will be empty?’

‘Empty?’ Harry said. ‘Er … no?’

‘The other centaurs in this forest have stayed from your presence, for we are sworn not to set ourselves against the heavens’ course. Because, in becoming entangled in your fate, we might become less innocent in what is to come. I alone have dared approach you.’

‘I … don’t understand.’

‘No. You are innocent, as the stars say. And to slay something innocent to save oneself, that is a terrible deed. One would live only a cursed life, a half-life, from that day. For any centaur would surely be cast out, if he slew a foal.’

The spear made a lightning motion, too fast for Harry’s eyes to follow, and smashed his wand out of his hand.

Another powerful blow smashed into Harry’s solar plexus, and he went gasping and retching to the forest floor.

Harry’s hand reached up toward his robes, for his Time-Turner, and the spear-butt knocked his hand away, almost hard enough to break fingers, he reached with his other hand and that was knocked away too –

‘I am sorry, Harry Potter,’ the centaur said, and then looked up with widened eyes. The spear spun about and came up, intercepting a red spellbolt. Then the centaur dropped the spear and leaped away desperately, a green flash of light went past him and another green flash of light followed in its wake, then a third green flash hit the centaur straight-on.

The centaur fell and did not move again.

It took a long time for Harry to catch his breath, to stagger to his feet, to pick up his wand, to croak, ‘What?’

By that time the sense of doom, of power almost tangible in the air, had approached once more.

‘P-Professor Quirrell? What are you doing here?’

‘Well,’ the man in the black cloak said thoughtfully, ‘you needed to fly into a rage and have a loud tantrum in the Forbidden Forest in the middle of the night, and I needed to go just outside your ability to detect me and keep watch. One does not leave a student alone in the Forbidden Forest. That should be obvious in retrospect.’

Harry stared at the fallen centaur.

The horse-form wasn’t breathing.

‘You – you killed him, that was Avada Kedavra –’

‘I do not always understand how other people imagine morality to work, Mr Potter. But even I know that on conventional morality, it is acceptable to kill non-human creatures which are about to slay a wizard child. Perhaps you do not care about the non-human part, but he was about to kill you. He was hardly innocent –’

The Defence Professor stopped, looking at Harry, who had raised one trembling hand to his mouth.

‘Well,’ the Defence Professor said then, ‘I have made my point, and you may think on it. Centaur spears can block many spells, but no one tries to block if they see that the spell is a certain shade of green. For this purpose it is useful to know some green stunning hexes. Really, Mr Potter, you should understand by now how I operate.’

The Defence Professor came nearer the centaur’s body, and Harry took an involuntary step back, then another, at the terrible rising sense of stop, don’t –

The Defence Professor knelt and pressed his wand to the centaur’s head.

The wand stayed there for a time.

And the centaur rose, eyes blank, breathing once more.

‘Remember nothing of this time,’ the Defence Professor commanded. ‘Wander away and forget everything about this night.’

The centaur walked away, the four horse-legs moving in strange synchrony.

‘Happy now?’ the Defence Professor said, sounding rather sardonic about it.

Harry’s brain still felt broken. ‘He was trying to kill me.’

‘Oh, for Merlin’s sake – yes, he was trying to kill you. Get used to it. Only boring people never have that experience.’

Harry’s voice emerged, hoarse. ‘Why – why did he want to –’

‘Any number of reasons. I would be lying if I said I’d never considered killing you myself.’

Harry stared at where the centaur had wandered into the trees.

His brain still felt half-broken, like an engine misfiring, but Harry did not see how this could possibly be a good sign.

The news of Draco Malfoy nearly being eaten by a horror had been sufficient to summon back Dumbledore from wherever he’d gone, to wake Lord Malfoy and the Lady Greengrass’s handsome husband, to bring forth Amelia Bones. The supposed presence of the horror had provoked skepticism even from Dumbledore, and the possibility of False Memory Charms had been raised. Harry had said (after some internal debate about the consequences of people believing a demon was on the loose) that he didn’t actually remember making the same effort he’d put forth to frighten the Dementor, the dark thing had just left; which was what you would expect someone to create as a False Memory, if they hadn’t actually known how Harry had done it. The names of Bellatrix Black, Severus Snape, and Quirinus Quirrell had been mentioned in connection with wizards strong enough to subdue everyone present and cast False Memory Charms, and Harry had known that Lucius was thinking of Dumbledore. There had been Aurors testifying, and discussions going in circles, and glares of accusation, and cutting remarks at 2AM in the morning. There had been motions, and votes, and consequences.

‘Do you believe,’ Headmaster Dumbledore said quietly to Harry, when all of it was done, and the two of them alone, ‘that the Hogwarts you have wrought is an improvement?’

Harry sat with his elbows on his knees, his face resting on his palms, in the conference room from which all the others had now departed. Professor McGonagall, who did not use a Time-Turner as routinely as the two of them, had departed swiftly for her bed.

‘Yes,’ Harry answered after too long a hesitation. ‘From my perspective, Headmaster, things in Hogwarts are finally, finally normal. This is how things should be, when four children get sent into the Forbidden Forest at night. There should be a huge fuss, constables showing up, and the responsible party getting sacked.’

‘You believe it is good,’ Dumbledore said quietly, ‘that the man who you call responsible was, as you put it, sacked.’

‘Yes, in fact, I do.’

‘Argus Filch has served this institution for decades.’

‘And when given Veritaserum,’ Harry said tiredly, ‘Argus Filch revealed that he had sent an eleven-year-old boy into the Forbidden Forest, hoping something awful would happen to him, because he thought the boy’s father had been responsible for the death of his cat. The three other students in Draco’s company don’t seem to have fazed him. I would have argued for jail time, but your concept of jail in this country is Azkaban. I’ll also note that Filch was remarkably unpleasant to the children in Hogwarts and I expect the school’s hedonic index to be improved by his departure, not that it matters to you, I suppose.’

The Headmaster’s eyes were impenetrable behind the half-moon glasses. ‘Argus Filch is a Squib. His work at Hogwarts is all he has. Had, rather.’

‘The purpose of a school is not to provide work for its employees. I know you probably spent more time around Filch than around any individual student, but that shouldn’t make Filch’s inner experiences loom larger in your thoughts. Students have inner lives too.’

‘You don’t care at all, do you Harry?’ Dumbledore’s voice was quiet. ‘About those you hurt.’

‘I care about the innocent,’ Harry said. ‘Like Mr Hagrid, who you’ll note I argued should not be considered malicious, just oblivious. I was fine with Mr Hagrid working here so long as he didn’t take anyone into the Forbidden Forest again.’

‘I had thought that with Rubeus vindicated, he might teach Care of Magical Creatures after Silvanus departs the position. But much of that teaching is done in the Forbidden Forest. So that too shall not be, in the wake of your passage.’

Harry said slowly, ‘But – you told us that Mr Hagrid has a blind spot when it comes to magical creatures threatening wizards. That Mr Hagrid had a cognitive deficit and couldn’t really imagine Draco and Tracey getting hurt, which was why Mr Hagrid didn’t see anything wrong with leaving them alone in the Forbidden Forest at night. Was that not true?’

‘It is true.’

‘Then wouldn’t Mr Hagrid be the worst possible teacher for Magical Creatures?’

The old wizard gazed down at Harry through the half-moon glasses. His voice was thick when he spoke. ‘Mr Malfoy himself saw nothing awry. It was not so implausible a trick which Argus played, Harry Potter. And Rubeus might have grown into his position. It would have been – all Rubeus wished, his one greatest desire –’

‘Your mistake,’ Harry said, looking down at his knees, feeling at least ten percent as exhausted as he’d ever been, ‘is a cognitive bias we would call, in the trade, scope insensitivity. Failure to multiply. You’re thinking about how happy Mr Hagrid would be when he heard the news. Consider the next ten years and a thousand students taking Magical Creatures and ten percent of them being scalded by Ashwinders. No one student would be hurt as much as Mr Hagrid would be happy, but there’d be a hundred students being hurt and only one happy teacher.’

‘Perhaps,’ the old wizard said. ‘And your own error, Harry, is that you do not feel the pain of those you hurt, once you have done your multiplication.’

‘Maybe.’ Harry went on staring at his knees. ‘Or maybe it’s worse than that. Headmaster, what does it mean if a centaur doesn’t like me?’ What does it mean when a member of a race of magical creatures known for Divination gives you a lecture on people who are ignorant of consequences, apologizes, and then tries to stab you with a spear?

‘A centaur?’ the Headmaster said. ‘When did you – ah, the Time-Turner. You are the reason why I could not travel back to before the event, on pain of paradox.’

‘Am I? I guess I am.’ Harry shook his head distantly. ‘Sorry.’

‘With very few exceptions,’ Dumbledore said, ‘centaurs do not like wizards, at all.’

‘This was a bit more specific than that.’

‘What did the centaur say to you?’

Harry didn’t reply.

‘Ah.’ The Headmaster hesitated. ‘Centaurs have been wrong many times, and if there is anyone in the world who could confuse the stars themselves, it is you.’

Harry looked up, and saw the blue eyes once more gentle behind the half-circle glasses.

‘Do not fret too much about it,’ said Albus Dumbledore.

Caring

June 3rd, 1992.

Professor Quirrell was very sick.

He’d seemed better for a while, after drinking his unicorn’s blood in May, but the air of intense power which had surrounded him afterwards hadn’t lasted even a day. By the Ides of May, Professor Quirrell’s hands had been trembling again, though subtly. The Defence Professor’s medical regimen had been interrupted too early, it seemed.

Six days ago Professor Quirrell had collapsed at dinnertime.

Madam Pomfrey had tried to forbid Professor Quirrell from teaching classes, and Professor Quirrell had shouted at her in front of everyone. The Defence Professor had shouted that he was dying regardless, and would use his remaining time as he chose.

So Madam Pomfrey, blinking hard, had forbidden the Defence Professor from doing anything except teaching his classes. She’d asked for a volunteer to help her take Professor Quirrell to a room in the Hogwarts infirmary. More than a hundred students had risen to their feet, only half wearing green.

The Defence Professor no longer sat at the Head Table during mealtimes. He didn’t cast spells during lessons. The oldest students who had the most Quirrell points helped him to teach, the seventh-years who had already sat their Defence N.E.W.T.s in May. They took turns floating him from his room in the infirmary to his classes, and brought him food at mealtimes. Professor Quirrell proctored his Battle Magic classes from a chair, sitting.

Watching Hermione die had hurt more than this, but that had ended much more quickly.

This is the true Enemy.

Harry had already thought that, after Hermione had died. Being forced to watch Professor Quirrell die, day by day, week by week, had not done much to change his mind.

This is the true Enemy I have to face, Harry thought in Wednesday’s Defence class, watching Professor Quirrell leaning far to one side of his chair before that day’s seventh-year assistant caught him. Everything else is just shadows and distraction.

Harry had been turning over Trelawney’s prophecy in his mind, wondering if maybe the true Dark Lord had nothing to do with Lord Voldemort at all. Born to those who have thrice defied him seemed to strongly invoke the Peverell brothers and the three Deathly Hallows – though Harry didn’t exactly see how Death could have marked him as an equal, which seemed to imply some sort of deliberate action on Death’s part.

This alone is the true Enemy, Harry thought. After this will come Professor McGonagall, Mum and Dad, even Neville in his time, unless the wound in the world can be healed before then.

There was nothing Harry could do. Madam Pomfrey was already doing for Professor Quirrell what magic could do, and magic seemed strictly superior to Muggle techniques when it came to healing.

There was nothing Harry could do.

Nothing he could do.

Nothing.

Nothing at all.

Harry raised his hand, and knocked upon the door, in case the person there could no longer detect him.

‘What is it?’ came a strained voice from the infirmary room.

‘It’s me.’

There was a long pause. ‘Come in,’ said that voice.

Harry slipped inside and closed the door behind him, and cast the Quieting Charm. He stood as far away from Professor Quirrell as he could, just in case his own magic was making the Professor feel uncomfortable.

Though the sense of doom was fading, fading with each passing day.

Professor Quirrell was lying back in his infirmary bed, only his head propped up by a pillow. A coverlet of cottony material, red with black stitching, covered him to his chest. A book hovered before his eyes, outlined in a pale glow which also surrounded a black cube lying by the bed. Not the Defence Professor’s own magic, then, but a device of some kind.

The book was Thinking Physics by Epstein, the same book Harry had lent to Draco a few months back. Harry had stopped fretting about its possible misuse several weeks earlier.

‘This –’ Professor Quirrell said, and coughed; it didn’t sound quite right. ‘This is a fascinating book … if I’d ever realized …’ A laugh, mixed with another cough. ‘Why did I assume the Muggle arts … must not be mine? That they would be … of no use to me? Why did I never bother trying … to test it experimentally … as you would say? In case … my assumption … was wrong? It seems sheerly foolish of me … in retrospect …’

Harry was having more trouble speaking than Professor Quirrell was. Wordlessly, Harry reached into his pocket, and laid a kerchief on the floor; which he unfolded to reveal a small white pebble, smooth and round.

‘What’s that?’ said the Defence Professor.

‘It’s a, it’s a, Transfigured, unicorn.’

Harry had checked the books, had learned that since he was too young to have sexual thoughts he would be able to approach a unicorn without fear. The same books had said nothing about unicorns being smart. Harry had already noticed that every intelligent magical species was at least partially humanoid, from merfolk to centaurs to giants, from elves to goblins to Veela. All had essentially human-like emotions, many were known to interbreed with humans. Harry had already reasoned out that magic didn’t create new intelligence but just changed the shape of genetically human beings. Unicorns were equine, were not even partially humanoid, didn’t talk, used no tools, they were almost certainly just magical horses. If it was right to eat a cow to feed yourself for a day, then it had to be right to drink a unicorn’s blood in order to stave off death for weeks. You couldn’t have it both ways.

So Harry had gone into the Forbidden Forest wearing his Cloak. He had searched the Grove of Unicorns until he saw her, a proud creature with a pure white coat and violet hair, with three blue blotches on her flank. Harry had gone over, and the sapphire eyes had stared at him inquisitively. Harry had tapped out the sequence 1–2–3 on the ground several times with his shoes. The unicorn had shown no sign of responding in kind. Harry had reached over, taken her hoof in his hand, and tapped the same sequence with the unicorn’s hoof. The unicorn had only looked at him curiously.

And something about feeding the unicorn the sleeping-potion-laced sugar cubes had still felt like murder.

That magic gives their existence a weight of meaning which no mere animal could possess … to slay something innocent to save oneself, that is a very grave sin. Those two phrases, from Professor McGonagall, from the centaur, had both run through Harry’s mind, over and over as the white unicorn had yawned, laid down on the ground, and closed its eyes for what would be the last time. The Transfiguration had lasted an hour, and Harry’s eyes had watered repeatedly as he worked. The unicorn’s death might not have come then, but it would come soon enough, and it was foreign to Harry’s nature to try to refuse responsibility of any kind. Harry would just have to hope that, if you didn’t kill the unicorn to save yourself, if you did it to help a friend, it would be acceptable in the end.

Professor Quirrell’s eyebrows had climbed toward his hairline. His voice was less soft, had something of his normal sharpness, as he said, ‘I forbid you from doing that again.’

‘I wondered if you’d say that,’ Harry said. He swallowed again. ‘But this unicorn is already, already doomed, so you might as well take it, Professor …’

‘Why have you done this?’

If the Defence Professor really didn’t understand that, he was slower on the uptake than anyone Harry had ever met. ‘I kept thinking there was nothing I could do,’ Harry said. ‘I got tired of thinking it.’

Professor Quirrell closed his eyes. His head leaned back into the pillow. ‘You were lucky,’ the Defence Professor said in a soft voice, ‘that a unicorn in Transfigured form … did not set off the Hogwarts wards, as a strange creature … I shall have to … take this outside the grounds, to make use of it … but that can be managed. I shall tell them that I wish to look upon the lake … I will ask you to sustain the Transfiguration before you go, and it should last long enough, after that … and with my last strength, dispel whatever death-alarms were placed to watch over the herd … which, the unicorn being not yet dead, but only Transfigured, will not yet have triggered … you were very lucky, Mr Potter.’

Harry nodded. He started to speak, then stopped again. Words seemed to stick in his throat once more.

You already calculated the expected utilities, if it works, if it goes wrong. You assigned probabilities, you multiplied, and then you threw out the answer and went with your new gut feeling, which was the same. So say it.

‘Do you know,’ Harry said unsteadily, ‘of any way at all, by which your life might be saved?’

The Defence Professor’s eyes opened. ‘Why … do you ask me that, boy?’

‘There’s … a spell I heard of, a ritual –’

‘Be silent,’ said the Defence Professor.

An instant later a snake lay in the bed.

Even the snake’s eyes were dull.

It did not rise.

‘Speak on,’ hissed that snake, its flickering tongue its only motion.

‘There is … there iss a ritual, I heard of from the sschoolmasster, by which he thinkss the Dark Lord might have lived on. It iss called –’ and Harry stopped, as he realized that he did know how to say the word in Parseltongue. ‘Horcrux. It requires a death, I have heard. But if you are dying in any case, you might try to adapt the ritual, even at great risk for the new spell, so that it can be done with a different sacrifice. It would change the whole world, if you succeed – though I don’t know anything about the spell – the schoolmaster thought it tore off a piece of soul, though I don’t see how that could be true –’

The snake was hissing laughter, strange sharp laughter, almost hysterical. ‘You tell me of that spell? Me? You must learn more caution in the future, boy. But it matters not. I learned of the horcrux spell since long ago. It is meaningless.’

‘Meaningless?’ Harry said aloud in surprise.

‘Would be pointless spell from beginning, if souls existed. Tear piece of soul? That is lie. Misdirection to hide true secret. Only one who does not believe in common lies will reason further, see beneath obscuration, realise how to cast spell. Required murder is not sacrificial ritual at all. Sudden death sometimes makes ghost, if magic bursts and imprints on nearby thing. Horcrux spell channels death-burst through caster, creates your own ghost instead of victim’s, imprints ghost in special device. Second victim picks up horcrux device, device imprints your memories into them. But only memories from time horcrux device was made. You see flaw?’

The burning sensation was back in Harry’s throat. ‘No continuity of –’ there wasn’t a snake word for consciousness ‘- self, you would go on thinking after making the horcrux, then self with new memories dies and is not restored –’

‘Yes, you do see. Also Merlin’s Interdict prevents powerful spells from pasing through such a device, since it is not truly alive. Dark Wizards who think to return thus are weaker, easily dispatched. None have persisted long by such means. Personalities change, mix with victim’s. Death is not truly gainsaid. Real self is lost, as you say. Not to my present taste. Admit I considered it, long ago.’

A man was lying in the infirmary bed once more. The Defence Professor breathed, then made a wretched coughing sound.

‘Can you give me a full recipe for the spell?’ Harry said, after a moment’s deliberation. ‘There might be some way to improve on the flaws, with enough research. Some way to do it ethically and have it work.’ Like doing the transfer into a clone body with a blank brain, instead of an innocent victim, which might also improve the fidelity of the personality transfer … though that still left the other problems.

Professor Quirrell made a short sound, under his breath, that might have been laughter. ‘You know, boy,’ Professor Quirrell whispered, ‘I had thought … to teach you everything … the seeds of all the secrets I knew … from one living mind to another … so that later, when you found the right books, you would be able to understand … I would have passed on my knowledge to you, my heir … we would have begun as soon as you asked me … but you never asked.’

Even the grief surrounding Harry like thick water gave way to that, to the sheer magnitude of the missed opportunity. ‘I was supposed to – ? I didn’t know I was supposed to – !’

Another coughing chuckle. ‘Ah yes … the unknowing Muggleborn … in heritage if not in blood … that is you. But I thought … better of it … that you should not walk my path … it was not a good path, in the end.’

‘It’s not too late, Professor!’ Harry said. A part of Harry yelled that he was being selfish, and then another part shouted that down; there would be other people to help.

‘Yes, it is too late … and you shall not … persuade me otherwise … I have … thought better of it … as I said … I am too full … of secrets better left unknown … look at me.’

Harry looked, almost despite himself.

He saw a still-unwrinkled face, looking old and pained, beneath a head rapidly losing its hair, even the sides looking wispy now; Harry saw a face he’d always thought was sharp, now revealed as thin, muscle and fat fading away from the face, as from the arms beneath it, like the skeletal form of Bellatrix Black he’d seen in Azkaban –

Harry’s head wrenched aside, unthinkingly.

‘You see,’ whispered the Professor. ‘I dislike to sound cliched … Mr Potter … but the truth is … the Arts called Dark … really are not good for a person … in the end.’

Professor Quirrell breathed in, breathed out. There was quiet for a time in the infirmary, the two of them watched only by the elaborately ornamented stone of the walls.

‘Is there anything left … unsaid between us?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I am not dying today … mind you … not right now … but I do not know how long … I shall be able to converse.’

‘There’s,’ Harry said, swallowed again. ‘There’s a lot of things, way too many things, but … it might be the wrong thing to ask, but I don’t want – this one question unanswered – snake?’

A snake lay on the bed.

‘I learned how the Killing Curse works. Requires true hate to cast, not much hate, but must want target dead, they say. In prison with life-eaters, you cast Killing Curse at guard – said you did not want him dead – was that lie? Here, now, at this distance – you may speak truth – even if you fear it reflects poorly on you – it should not matter now, teacher. I wish to know. Must know. Will not abandon you, either way.’

A man lay on the bed.

‘Listen carefully,’ Professor Quirrell whispered. ‘I will tell you a conundrum … a riddle of a dangerous spell … when you know the answer to that puzzle … you will also know … the answer to your question … are you listening?’

Harry nodded.

‘There is a limitation … to the Killing Curse. To cast it once … in a fight … you must hate enough … to want the other dead. To cast Avada … Kedavra twice … you must hate enough … to kill twice … to cut their throat with your own hands … to watch them die … then do it again. Very few … can hate enough … to kill someone … five times … they would … get bored.’ The Defence Professor breathed several times, before continuing. ‘But if you look at history … you will find some Dark Wizards … who could cast the Killing Curse … over and over. A nineteenth-century witch … who called herself Dark Evangel … the Aurors called her A. K. McDowell. She could cast the Killing Curse … a dozen times … in one fight. Ask yourself … as I asked myself … what is the secret … that she knew? What is deadlier than hate … and flows without limit?’

A second level to the Avada Kedavra spell, just like with the Patronus Charm …

‘I don’t really care,’ Harry answered.

The Defence Professor chuckled wetly. ‘Good. You are … learning. So you see …’ A pause of transformation. ‘I did not wish guard dead, after all. Cast Killing Curse, but not with hate.’ And then a man.

Harry swallowed hard. It was both better, and worse, than what Harry had suspected; and characteristic enough of Professor Quirrell. A cracked soul, for certain; but Professor Quirrell had never claimed to be whole.

‘Any else … to say?’ said the man in the bed.

‘Are you absolutely sure,’ Harry said, ‘that there is nothing you’ve ever heard of that might save you, Professor? In all your lore? Finding and uniting all three Deathly Hallows, an ancient artefact that Merlin sealed behind a riddle nobody’s ever figured out? You’ve seen some of what I can do. That I’m good at solving riddles. You know I can figure things out, sometimes, that other wizards can’t. I –’ Harry’s voice broke. ‘I have a strong preference for your life, over your death, Professor Quirrell.’

There was a long pause.

‘One thing,’ whispered Professor Quirrell. ‘One thing … that might do it … or it might not … but to obtain it … is beyond your power, or mine …’

Oh, it was just the setup for a sub-quest, said Harry’s Inner Critic.

All the other parts screamed for that part to shut up. Life didn’t work like that. Ancient artifacts could be found, but not in a month, not when you couldn’t leave Hogwarts and were still in your first year.

Professor Quirrell took in a deep breath. Exhaled. ‘I’m sorry … that came out … too dramatic. Do not … get your hopes up … Mr Potter. You asked … for anything … no matter how unlikely. There is … a certain object … called …’

A snake lay on the bed.

‘The Philosopher’s Stone,’ hissed the snake.

If there’d been a mass-manufacturable means of safe immortality this entire time and nobody had bothered, Harry was going to snap and kill everyone.

‘I read of it in a book,’ Harry hissed. ‘Concluded it was obvious myth. No reason why same device would provide immortality and endless gold. Not unless someone was just inventing happy stories. Not to mention, every sane person should have been researching ways to make more Stones, or kidnapping maker to produce. Thought of you specifically, teacher.’

A hissing of cold laughter. ‘Reasoning is wise, but not wise enough. Like with horcrux spell, absurdity hides true secret. True Stone is not what that legend says. True power is not what stories claim. Stone’s supposed maker was not one who made it. One who holds it now, was not born to name now used. Yet Stone is powerful healing device in truth. Have you heard it spoken of?’

‘Just in the book.’

‘One who holds Stone is repository of much lore. Taught schoolmaster many secrets. Schoolmaster has said nothing of Stone’s holder, nothing of Stone? No hints?’

‘Not that I can easily recall,’ Harry replied honestly.

‘Ah,’ hissed the snake. ‘Ah, well.’

‘Could ask schoolmaster –’

‘No! Do not ask him, boy. He would not take question well.’

‘But if the Stone only heals –’

‘Schoolmaster does not believe that, would not believe that. Too many have sought Stone, or sought holder’s lore. Do not ask. Must not ask. Do not try to obtain Stone yourself. I forbid.’

A man lay on the bed once more. ‘I am at … my limit …’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I must regain … my strength … before I go … to the forest … with your gift. Leave now … but sustain the Transfiguration … before you go.’

Harry reached out, touched the white pebble lying within the kerchief, renewing the Transfiguration on it. ‘It should last for one hour and fifty-three minutes after this,’ Harry said.

‘Your studies … do well.’

It was far longer than Harry’s Transfigurations had lasted at the start of the school year. Second-year spells came to him easily now, without strain; which wasn’t surprising, since he would be twelve in less than two months. Harry could even have cast a Memory Charm, if it had been good for someone to forget every memory involving their left arm. He was climbing the power ladder, slowly, from very far down.

The thought came with a potential for sadness, a thought of one door opening as another closed; which Harry also rejected.

The door to the infirmary closed behind Harry, as the Boy-Who-Lived walked swiftly and with purpose, shrugging on his Invisibility Cloak as he moved. Soon, presumably, Professor Quirrell would call for assistance; and an older student trio would guide the Defence Professor into some quiet place, maybe the forest, with an excuse of viewing the lake or some such. Somewhere the Defence Professor could eat a unicorn undetected, after Harry’s Transfiguration wore off.

And then Professor Quirrell would be healthier, for a time. His power would return to him as strong as he’d ever been, for a much shorter time.

It wouldn’t last.

Harry’s fists clenched as he strode, the tension radiating up his arm muscles. If the Defence Professor’s treatment regimen hadn’t been interrupted, by Harry and the Aurors that he had brought to Hogwarts …

It was stupid to blame himself, Harry knew it was stupid and somehow his brain was doing it anyway. Like his brain was searching, carefully finding and selecting some way for this to be his fault, no matter how far it had to stretch.

As if having things be his fault were the only way that his brain knew how to grieve.

A trio of seventh-year Slytherins passed Harry’s invisible form in the hallway, heading for the healer’s offices where the Professor waited, looking deeply serious and concerned. Was that how other people grieved?

Or did they, on some level, not really care, as Professor Quirrell thought?

There is a second level to the Killing Curse.

Harry’s brain had solved the riddle instantly, in the moment of first hearing it; as though the knowledge had always been inside him, waiting to make itself known.

Harry had read once, somewhere, that the opposite of happiness wasn’t sadness, but boredom; and the author had gone on to say that to find happiness in life you asked yourself not what would make you happy, but what would excite you. And by the same reasoning, hatred wasn’t the true opposite of love. Even hatred was a kind of respect that you could give to someone’s existence. If you cared about someone enough to prefer their dying to their living, it meant you were thinking about them.

It had come up much earlier, before the Trial, in conversation with Hermione; when she’d said something about magical Britain being Prejudiced, with considerable and recent justification. And Harry had thought – but not said – that at least she’d been let into Hogwarts to be spat upon.

Not like certain people living in certain countries, who were, it was said, as human as anyone else; who were said to be sapient beings, worth more than any mere unicorn. But who nonetheless wouldn’t be allowed to live in Muggle Britain. On that score, at least, no Muggle had the right to look a wizard in the eye. Magical Britain might discriminate against Muggleborns, but at least it allowed them inside so they could be spat upon in person.

What is deadlier than hate, and flows without limit?

‘Indifference,’ Harry whispered aloud, the secret of a spell he would never be able to cast; and kept striding toward the library to read anything he could find, anything at all, about the Philosopher’s Stone.

Riddles and Answers

June 13th, 1992.

It was the last week of school in Hogwarts, and Professor Quirrell was still alive, barely. The Defence Professor himself would be in a healer’s bed, this day, as he’d been for almost the last week.

Hogwarts tradition said that exams were given in the first week of June, that results were released in the second week, and that in the third week, there would be the Leave-Taking Feast on Sunday and the Hogwarts Express transporting you to London on Monday.

Harry had wondered, a long time ago when he’d first read about that schedule, just what exactly the students did during the rest of the second week of June, since waiting for exam results didn’t sound like much; and the answer had surprised him when he’d found out.

But now the second week of June was over as well, and it was Saturday; there was nothing left of the year but the Leave-Taking Feast on the 14th and the Hogwarts Express ride on the 15th.

And nothing had been answered.

Nothing had been resolved.

Hermione’s killer hadn’t been found.

Somehow Harry had been thinking that, surely, all the truth would come out by the end of the school year; like that was the end of a mystery novel and the mystery’s answer had been promised him. Certainly it had to be known by the time the Defence Professor … died, it couldn’t be allowed for Professor Quirrell to die without knowing the answer, without everything being neatly resolved. Not exam grades, certainly not death, it was only truth that finished a story …

But unless you bought Draco Malfoy’s latest theory that Professor Sprout had been assigning and grading less homework around the time of Hermione being framed for attempted murder, thereby proving that Professor Sprout had been spending her time setting it up, the truth remained unfound.

And instead, as if the world had priorities that were more like other people’s way of thinking, the year was going to end with a climactic Quidditch match.

In the air above the stadium, distant figures on broomsticks swooped and pirouetted and spun around each other. The red-purplish truncated tetrahedron that was the Quaffle was caught, tossed, blocked, and occasionally thrown through floating hoops, accompanied by stadium-rocking cries of triumph or dismay. Blue and green and yellow and red-trimmed robes shouted with the enthusiasm that people felt so easily when no action would be required from them personally.

It was the first Quidditch match Harry had attended at Hogwarts, and he’d already decided that it would be the last.

‘Davies has the Quaffle!’ shouted the amplified voice of Lee Jordan. ‘That’s another ten points for Ravenclaw in seven … six … five … holy smokes, he’s done it already! Smack through the centre of the central hoop! I’ve never seen such a winning streak – I’m calling it right now for Davies becoming Captain next year after Bortan steps down –’

Lee’s voice cut out abruptly and Professor McGonagall’s own amplified voice said, ‘That’s the Ravenclaw team’s own business, Mr Jordan. Confine yourself to the match, please.’

‘And the Slytherins take possession – Flint hands off the Quaffle to the lovely –’

‘Mr Jordan!’

‘To the merely acceptable Sharon Vizcaino, whose hair trails behind her like a comet as she blazes toward the Ravenclaw defence – now with two Bludgers in close pursuit! Pucey’s on Sharon’s tail – what are you doing, Inglebee? – and she swerves in mid-air to avoid – is that the snitch? Go, Cho Chang, go, Higgs is already – what are you two doing?’

‘Calm down, Mr Jordan!’

‘How am i supposed to calm down? That was the worst missed play I’ve ever seen! And the Snitch is gone – maybe gone for good, after being missed that badly – Pucey’s heading off towards the goal posts, Inglebee’s nowhere near him –’

In a distant era of history, maybe in another world entirely, Professor Quirrell had undertaken that the House Cup would be awarded to either Slytherin or Ravenclaw. Or possibly, somehow, both; for he had promised that three wishes would be granted. So far it was looking good on two out of three.

If you just went by the current score, Hufflepuff was leading the race for the House Cup by something like five hundred points, thanks to Hufflepuff’s students doing their homework and staying out of trouble. It appeared that Professor Snape had been strategically taking quite a lot of points from Hufflepuffs for, er, the last seven years or so. Slytherin House, reigning champion for the last seven years, still had to its advantage a certain generosity of its Head of House in handing out points; and this was sufficient to put it neck-and-neck with Ravenclaw House, home of the academic achievers. Gryffindor was far behind in last place, as befit the House of nonconformists; Gryffindor had Slytherin’s profile when it came to academics and mischief, only without the advantage of Professor Snape. Even Fred and George had barely broken even on the year.

Ravenclaw House and Slytherin House both needed a lot of points from somewhere if either wanted to catch up with Hufflepuff in the next two days.

And so far as anyone knew, Professor Quirrell hadn’t done a single thing leading to the obvious result. It was happening all by itself, now that one lone Professor in Hogwarts had taught a class with creative problem-solving.

The final Quidditch match of the year was between Ravenclaw and Slytherin. Earlier in the year, Gryffindor’s initial Quidditch lead had vanished after their new Seeker, Emmett Shear, fell off a possibly malfunctioning broomstick during his second game. This had also required some hasty rescheduling of the remaining games.

This, the final game of the year, wouldn’t end until the Snitch was caught.

Quidditch scores added directly onto the House points total.

And what did you know, today it seemed that both the Slytherin and Ravenclaw Seekers just could … not … catch … the … Snitch.

‘The snitch was practically on top of you, you dim-eyed dimwit!’

‘Language, Mr Jordan, or I’ll remove you from this game! Though it was terrible play, I admit.’

Harry had to admit that Lee Jordan and Professor McGonagall had a wonderful comedic routine, with Jordan as the banana-man and Professor McGonagall as the straight-woman; Harry now felt a little sorry to have missed it at the earlier Quidditch matches. It was a side of Professor McGonagall he hadn’t seen before.

A few seats down from where Harry sat in the Hufflepuff section of the stands, there lurked the hulking form of Cedric Diggory. The Super Hufflepuff had observed the most recent near-air-collision between Cho Chang and Terence Higgs with the keen eye of a wizard who was a Seeker and a Quidditch Captain in his own right.

‘The Ravenclaw Seeker is new,’ Cedric said. ‘But Higgs is in his seventh year; I’ve played against him. He’s better than that.’

‘You think it’s a strategy?’ asked one of the Hufflepuffs sitting next to Cedric.

‘It would make sense if Slytherin needed some extra points to win the Quidditch Cup,’ Cedric said. ‘But Slytherin already has the title in the bag. What are they thinking? They could’ve won right there!’

The game had started at six o’clock in the evening. A typical game would have gone until seven or so, at which point it would have been time for dinner. June in Scotland meant plenty of daylight; sunset wasn’t until ten.

It was at eight pm and six minutes, according to Harry’s watch, when Slytherin had just scored another 10 points bringing the score to 170–140, when Cedric Diggory leapt out of his seat and shouted ‘Those bastards!’

‘Yeah!’ cried a young boy beside him, leaping to his own feet. ‘Who do they think they are, scoring points?’

‘Not that!’ cried Cedric Diggory. ‘They’re – they’re trying to steal the Cup from us!’

‘But we’re not in the running any more for –’

‘Not the Quidditch Cup! The House Cup!’

The word spread, with cries of outrage.

That was Harry’s cue.

Harry politely asked a Hufflepuff witch sitting next to him, and another Hufflepuff sitting one row above him, if they could move aside. Then Harry drew forth from his pouch a huge scroll, and unfurled it into a 2-metre-tall banner which stuck in place in mid-air. The enchantment had been done courtesy of a sixth-year Ravenclaw who had a reputation for knowing less about Quidditch than Harry did.

In huge, glowing purple letters, the sign read:

Just Buy a Clock

2 : 06 : 47

Beneath it was a Snitch, with a blinking red X over it.

Second, after second, after second, the time counter incremented.

As that counter rose higher, there seemed to be an awful lot of Hufflepuffs who’d decided that they wanted to sit next to Harry’s banner.

As the game dragged on past nine, there also seemed to be a lot of Gryffindors.

As the Sun set and Harry started using Lumos to read his books – he’d given up on the actual game a long time ago – there were a noticeable number of Ravenclaws who’d betrayed patriotism for sanity.

And Professor Sinistra.

And Professor Vector.

And as the stars began to come out, Professor Flitwick.

The climactic final Quidditch game of the year … dragged on.

The Truth

Tom Riddle.

The words seemed to echo inside Harry’s head, sparking resonances that as quickly died away, broken patterns trying to complete themselves and failing.

Tom Riddle is a

Tom Riddle was the

Riddle

There were other priorities occupying Harry’s attention.

Professor Quirrell was pointing a gun at him.

And for some reason Lord Voldemort hadn’t fired it yet.

Harry’s voice came out in more of a croak. ‘What is it that you want from me?’

‘Your death,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘is clearly not what I am about to say, since I have had plenty of time to kill you if I wished. The fateful battle between Lord Voldemort and the Boy-Who-Lived is a figment of Dumbledore’s imagination. I know where to find your family’s house in Oxford, and I am familiar with the concept of sniper rifles. You would have died before you ever touched a wand. I hope this is clear to you, Tom?’

‘Crystal,’ Harry whispered. His body was still shaking, running programs more suited to fleeing a tiger than casting delicate spells or thinking. But Harry could think of one thing the person pointing a gun at him obviously wanted him to do, a question that person was waiting for him to ask, and Harry did so. ‘Why are you calling me Tom?’

Professor Quirrell regarded him steadily. ‘Why am I calling you Tom? Answer. Your intellect is not everything I hoped for, but it should suffice for this.’

Harry’s mouth seemed to know the answer before his brain could manage to focus on the question. ‘Tom Riddle is your name. Our name. That’s who Lord Voldemort is, or was, or – something.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘Better. You have already vanquished the Dark Lord, the one and only time that you will ever do so. I have already destroyed all but a remnant of Harry Potter, eliminating the difference between our spirits and enabling us to reside in the same world. Now that it is clear to you that the battle between us is a lie, you might act sensibly to advance your own interests. Or you might not.’ The gun jabbed slightly forward, causing prickles of sweat to appear on Harry’s forehead. ‘Drop your wand. Now.’

Harry dropped it.

‘Step away from the wand,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry obeyed.

‘Reach toward your neck,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘and remove your Time-Turner, touching it by the chain only. Place the Time-Turner on the ground, then step away from it as well.’

This also Harry did. Even in his state of shock, his mind still looked for a way to spin the Time-Turner in the process, a sudden move that would win; but Harry knew that Professor Quirrell would already be imagining himself in Harry’s position, looking for the same possible opportunities.

‘Remove your pouch and place it also on the ground, then step away.’

Harry did this.

‘Very good,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Now. It is time for me to obtain the Philosopher’s Stone. I mean to bring along these four first-years here, suitably Obliviated of their most recent memories so that they still recall their original purpose. Snape I shall control and set to guard this door. After this day’s work is done, I intend to kill Snape for the betrayals he has offered my other identity. The three heir-children I shall take with me afterwards, to shape their future loyalties. And know this, I have taken hostages. I have already set in motion a spell that will kill hundreds of Hogwarts students, including many you called friends. I can stop that spell using the Stone, if I obtain it successfully. If I am interrupted before then, or if I choose not to stop the spell, hundreds of students will die.’ Professor Quirrell’s voice was still mild. ‘Do you yet perceive any interests you have at stake, boy? I would smile to hear you say “no”, but that is too much to hope.’

‘I’d like,’ Harry managed to say, through the horror, and the heartbreak, and the knives slicing away at an emotional connection that hurt like living flesh as it was cut, ‘for you not to do those things, Professor.’ Why, Professor Quirrell, why, why did it have to turn out like this, I don’t, I don’t, I don’t want this to be happening …

‘Very well,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I grant you permission to offer me something I want.’ The gun gestured invitingly. ‘That is a rare privilege, child. Lord Voldemort does not usually negotiate for what he wants.’

Some part of Harry’s mind scrabbled frantically, looking for something, anything that might be of more value to Lord Voldemort or Professor Quirrell than child hostages or Severus’s death.

Another part of him, the part that had never stopped thinking, already knew his answer.

‘You already have an idea for what you want from me,’ Harry said, through the sickness and the bleeding wounds in his soul. ‘What is it?’

‘Your help in obtaining the Philosopher’s Stone.’

Harry swallowed. He couldn’t stop his eyes from going to the gun, then back up at Professor Quirrell’s face.

He was aware that the hero in a storybook was supposed to say No, but now that he was actually in a situation like this, saying No didn’t seem to make sense.

‘I am disappointed that you need to think about this,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It is straightforward that you should obey me for now, since I hold every advantage over you. I have taught you better than this; in this situation you should certainly pretend to lose. You can expect to gain nothing by resisting, except pain. You should have calculated that it was better to answer sooner, and not earn my distrust.’ Professor Quirrell’s eyes studied him curiously. ‘Perhaps Dumbledore has filled your ears with nonsense about noble defiance? I find such morals amusing, since they are so easy to manipulate. I assure you that I can make defiance seem morally worse, and you would be well advised to submit before I demonstrate how.’ The gun stayed pointed at Harry; but with a wave of Professor Quirrell’s other hand, Tracey Davis rose up into the air, spun lazily, her limbs spread-eagled –

– then, even as new adrenaline hammered at Harry’s heart, Tracey floated back down again.

‘Choose,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘This begins to try my patience.’

I should have spoken just then, before he might’ve ripped off Tracey’s legs, no, I shouldn’t have, the Headmaster said I mustn’t show Lord Voldemort that I’ll do things if he threatens my friends because that will just make him threaten more of them – only what he said before isn’t a threat it’s just the sort of thing Lord Voldemort does –

Harry took a deep breath, several of them. Whatever part of him kept on running on full automatic was screaming at the remainder of his mind that it could not afford to stay in shock. Shocks were of finite duration, neurons kept firing regardless, the only reason Harry’s mind would shut down while his brain kept running was if Harry’s self-model believed his mind would shut down –

‘I don’t mean to try your patience,’ Harry said. His voice was cracking. That was good. Sounding like he was still in shock meant that Lord Voldemort might give him more time. ‘But if Lord Voldemort had a reputation for keeping his bargains, I don’t know about it.’

‘An obvious concern,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘There is a simple answer, and I would have enforced it upon you in any case. Ssnakes can’t lie. And since I have a tremendous distaste for stupidity, I suggest you do not say anything like “What do you mean?” You are smarter than that, and I do not have time for such conversations as ordinary people inflict on one another.’

Harry swallowed. Snakes can’t lie. ‘Two plus two equals four.’ Harry had tried to say that two plus two equalled three, and the word four had slipped out instead.

‘Good. When Salazar Slytherin invoked the Parselmouth curse upon himself and all his children, his true plan was to ensure his descendants could trust one another’s words, whatever plots they wove against outsiders.’ Professor Quirrell had adopted his lecturing pose from Battle Magic, like someone putting on a well-worn mask, but the gun remained pointed in his hand. ‘Occlumency cannot fool the Parselmouth curse as it can fool Veritaserum, and you may put that to the trial also. Now listen well. Come with me, promise your besst aid in getting Stone, and I shall leave these children behind unharmed. Hostages are real, hundreds of students die tonight unless I stop events already set in motion. Will spare hosstages if I obtain Stone succesfully. And mark also this, mark it well: I cannot be truly slain by any means known to me, and losing Stone will not stop me from returning, nor spare you or yours my wrath. Any impetuous act you are contemplating cannot win the game for you, boy. I do credit your ability to annoy me, and suggest you avoid doing so.’

‘You said,’ Harry’s voice was strange in his own ears, ‘that the Philosopher’s Stone had different powers from what legend said. You said that to me in Parseltongue. Tell me what the Stone really does, before I agree to help you get it.’ If it was something along the lines of gaining total power over the universe, then nothing was worth an incrementally greater chance of Lord Voldemort getting the Stone.

‘Ah,’ said Professor Quirrell, and smiled. ‘You are thinking. That is better, and as a reward I shall offer you a further incentive for cooperation. Eternal life and youth, the creation of gold and silver. Suppose these are true benefits of holding the Stone. Tell me, boy. What is the Stone’s power?’

It might have been the adrenaline still in him, being actually useful for his brain for once. It might have been the power of being told that an answer existed, and that the evidence wasn’t a lie. ‘It can make Transfigurations permanent.’

Then Harry stopped, as he heard what his own mouth had just said.

‘Correct,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Thus, whoever holds the Philosopher’s Stone is able to perform human Transfiguration.’

Harry’s torn mind was knocked about yet again, as he realized what further incentive would be offered him.

‘You stole Miss Granger’s remains and Transfigured them into some innocuous-appearing target,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘A Transfigured target that you must keep somewhere about your own person, in order to sustain the Transfiguration. Ah, I see your eyes going to that ring upon your hand, but of course Miss Granger would not be the little jewel set into the ring, would it? That would be too obvious. No, I expect you Transfigured Granger’s remains into the ring itself, letting the aura of the Transfigured jewel mask the magic in the Transfigured ring.’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, forcing out the word. It was a lie, for once, and Harry’s glance had been deliberate. Harry had expected someone to challenge him on the steel ring, he’d tried to provoke that challenge so he could prove to be innocent yet again, though nobody had taken him up on it – maybe Dumbledore had just sensed that the steel by itself wasn’t magical.

‘Fine and good,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Now come with me, help me to obtain the Stone, and I will resurrect Hermione Granger on your behalf. Her death has had unfortunate effects on you, and I would not mind undoing them. That, as I understand you, is your greatest desire. I have done you many kindnesses, and I would not mind doing you this one more.’ A blank-eyed Professor Sprout had now risen from the ground and was pointing her own wand at Harry. ‘Help me obtain Stone of Transfiguration, and I shall try my hardest to resurrect your girl-child friend to true and lasting life. That said, boy, I am swiftly running out of patience with you, and you shall not like what comes next.’ This last line was hissed out in a voice that conveyed the impression of a snake rearing its head to strike.

Even then.

Even then, with all the world upturned, with shock after shock, even then Harry’s brain did not stop being a brain, or completing the patterns its circuits had been wired to complete.

Harry knew that this was too good an offer to make to someone at whom you were pointing a gun.

Unless you desperately needed their help to get the Philosopher’s Stone out of the magic mirror.

And there wasn’t any time left to plan, only the thought that, if Professor Quirrell really was going this far to get his help – what Harry wanted was to demand Professor Quirrell promise not to kill anyone in the future in exchange for his help now, but Harry had a strong sense that Professor Quirrell would reply Don’t be ridiculous and there wasn’t time for ordinary conversation Harry had to guess the highest safe request in advance –

Professor Quirrell’s eyes narrowed, his lips parted –

‘If I help you,’ Harry’s mouth said, ‘I want your promise that you aren’t planning to turn on me when this is over. I want you to not kill Professor Snape or anyone else in Hogwarts for at least a week. And I want answers, the truth about everything that’s been going on this whole time, everything you know about my nature.’

The pale blue eyes regarded him dispassionately.

I really think we could have thought of something better to ask for than that, said Harry’s Slytherin side. But I suppose we were legitimately out of time, and whatever we need to do next, answers will help.

Harry wasn’t listening to that voice right now. Cold chills were still going down his spine from hearing the words that had just come out of his lips, addressed to the man with the gun.

‘That is your condition for helping me to obtain the Stone?’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry nodded, unable to form words.

‘Agreed,’ hissed Professor Quirrell. ‘Help me, and you shall have answers to your questions, so long as they are about past events, and not my plans for the future. I do not intend to raise my hand or magic against you in future, so long as you do not raise your hand or magic against me. Shall kill none within school grounds for a week, unless I must. Now promise that you will not attempt to warn against me or escape. Promise to put forth your own best efforts toward helping me to obtain the Stone. And your girl-child friend shall be revived by me, to true life and health; nor shall me or mine ever seek to harm her.’ A twisted smile. ‘Promise, boy, and the bargain will be struck.’

‘I promise,’ whispered Harry.

WHAT? screamed other parts of his mind.

Um, he’s still pointing a gun at us, pointed out Slytherin. We don’t actually have a choice, we’re just getting as much mileage out of this as possible.

You bastard, said Hufflepuff. Do you think this is what Hermione would have wanted? This is Lord Voldemort we’re talking about, do we even know how many people he’s killed, and will kill?

I deny that we are compromising with Lord Voldemort for Hermione’s sake, said Slytherin. Since there is, in fact, a gun and we can’t otherwise stop him. Also, Mum and Dad would want us to just go along and stay safe.

Professor Quirrell regarded him steadily. ‘Repeat the full promise in Parseltongue, boy.’

‘I shall help you obtain the Stone … I cannot promise I will use my best efforts, my heart will not be in it, I fear. I intend to try. Shall not do anything I think will annoy you to no good end. Shall call no help if I expect them to be killed by you or for hostages to die. I’m sorry, teacher, but it is best I can do.’ Harry’s mind was settling, composing itself, as the decision was made. He would stay with Professor Quirrell, go with him to get the Stone, save the student hostages, and … and … and Harry didn’t know, except that he’d go on thinking.

‘You actually are sorry about that?’ Professor Quirrell looked amused. ‘I suppose it shall have to do. Then keep two other things in mind: I have plan to sstop even sschoolmasster, if he appearss before uss. And also this: I will occasionally ask you to say in Parseltongue whether you have betrayed me. The bargain is sstruck.’

The Truth

Tom Riddle.

The words seemed to echo inside Harry’s head, sparking resonances that as quickly died away, broken patterns trying to complete themselves and failing.

Tom Riddle is a

Tom Riddle was the

Riddle

There were other priorities occupying Harry’s attention.

Professor Quirrell was pointing a gun at him.

And for some reason Lord Voldemort hadn’t fired it yet.

Harry’s voice came out in more of a croak. ‘What is it that you want from me?’

‘Your death,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘is clearly not what I am about to say, since I have had plenty of time to kill you if I wished. The fateful battle between Lord Voldemort and the Boy-Who-Lived is a figment of Dumbledore’s imagination. I know where to find your family’s house in Oxford, and I am familiar with the concept of sniper rifles. You would have died before you ever touched a wand. I hope this is clear to you, Tom?’

‘Crystal,’ Harry whispered. His body was still shaking, running programs more suited to fleeing a tiger than casting delicate spells or thinking. But Harry could think of one thing the person pointing a gun at him obviously wanted him to do, a question that person was waiting for him to ask, and Harry did so. ‘Why are you calling me Tom?’

Professor Quirrell regarded him steadily. ‘Why am I calling you Tom? Answer. Your intellect is not everything I hoped for, but it should suffice for this.’

Harry’s mouth seemed to know the answer before his brain could manage to focus on the question. ‘Tom Riddle is your name. Our name. That’s who Lord Voldemort is, or was, or – something.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘Better. You have already vanquished the Dark Lord, the one and only time that you will ever do so. I have already destroyed all but a remnant of Harry Potter, eliminating the difference between our spirits and enabling us to reside in the same world. Now that it is clear to you that the battle between us is a lie, you might act sensibly to advance your own interests. Or you might not.’ The gun jabbed slightly forward, causing prickles of sweat to appear on Harry’s forehead. ‘Drop your wand. Now.’

Harry dropped it.

‘Step away from the wand,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry obeyed.

‘Reach toward your neck,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘and remove your Time-Turner, touching it by the chain only. Place the Time-Turner on the ground, then step away from it as well.’

This also Harry did. Even in his state of shock, his mind still looked for a way to spin the Time-Turner in the process, a sudden move that would win; but Harry knew that Professor Quirrell would already be imagining himself in Harry’s position, looking for the same possible opportunities.

‘Remove your pouch and place it also on the ground, then step away.’

Harry did this.

‘Very good,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Now. It is time for me to obtain the Philosopher’s Stone. I mean to bring along these four first-years here, suitably Obliviated of their most recent memories so that they still recall their original purpose. Snape I shall control and set to guard this door. After this day’s work is done, I intend to kill Snape for the betrayals he has offered my other identity. The three heir-children I shall take with me afterwards, to shape their future loyalties. And know this, I have taken hostages. I have already set in motion a spell that will kill hundreds of Hogwarts students, including many you called friends. I can stop that spell using the Stone, if I obtain it successfully. If I am interrupted before then, or if I choose not to stop the spell, hundreds of students will die.’ Professor Quirrell’s voice was still mild. ‘Do you yet perceive any interests you have at stake, boy? I would smile to hear you say “no”, but that is too much to hope.’

‘I’d like,’ Harry managed to say, through the horror, and the heartbreak, and the knives slicing away at an emotional connection that hurt like living flesh as it was cut, ‘for you not to do those things, Professor.’ Why, Professor Quirrell, why, why did it have to turn out like this, I don’t, I don’t, I don’t want this to be happening …

‘Very well,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I grant you permission to offer me something I want.’ The gun gestured invitingly. ‘That is a rare privilege, child. Lord Voldemort does not usually negotiate for what he wants.’

Some part of Harry’s mind scrabbled frantically, looking for something, anything that might be of more value to Lord Voldemort or Professor Quirrell than child hostages or Severus’s death.

Another part of him, the part that had never stopped thinking, already knew his answer.

‘You already have an idea for what you want from me,’ Harry said, through the sickness and the bleeding wounds in his soul. ‘What is it?’

‘Your help in obtaining the Philosopher’s Stone.’

Harry swallowed. He couldn’t stop his eyes from going to the gun, then back up at Professor Quirrell’s face.

He was aware that the hero in a storybook was supposed to say →No←, but now that he was actually in a situation like this, saying →No← didn’t seem to make sense.

‘I am disappointed that you need to think about this,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It is straightforward that you should obey me for now, since I hold every advantage over you. I have taught you better than this; in this situation you should certainly pretend to lose. You can expect to gain nothing by resisting, except pain. You should have calculated that it was better to answer sooner, and not earn my distrust.’ Professor Quirrell’s eyes studied him curiously. ‘Perhaps Dumbledore has filled your ears with nonsense about noble defiance? I find such morals amusing, since they are so easy to manipulate. I assure you that I can make defiance seem morally worse, and you would be well advised to submit before I demonstrate how.’ The gun stayed pointed at Harry; but with a wave of Professor Quirrell’s other hand, Tracey Davis rose up into the air, spun lazily, her limbs spread-eagled –

– then, even as new adrenaline hammered at Harry’s heart, Tracey floated back down again.

‘Choose,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘This begins to try my patience.’

I should have spoken just then, before he might’ve ripped off Tracey’s legs, no, I shouldn’t have, the Headmaster said I mustn’t show Lord Voldemort that I’ll do things if he threatens my friends because that will just make him threaten more of them – only what he said before isn’t a threat it’s just the sort of thing Lord Voldemort does –

Harry took a deep breath, several of them. Whatever part of him kept on running on full automatic was screaming at the remainder of his mind that it could not afford to stay in shock. Shocks were of finite duration, neurons kept firing regardless, the only reason Harry’s mind would shut down while his brain kept running was if Harry’s self-model believed his mind would shut down –

‘I don’t mean to try your patience,’ Harry said. His voice was cracking. That was good. Sounding like he was still in shock meant that Lord Voldemort might give him more time. ‘But if Lord Voldemort had a reputation for keeping his bargains, I don’t know about it.’

‘An obvious concern,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘There is a simple answer, and I would have enforced it upon you in any case. Ssnakes can’t lie. And since I have a tremendous distaste for stupidity, I suggest you do not say anything like “What do you mean?” You are smarter than that, and I do not have time for such conversations as ordinary people inflict on one another.’

Harry swallowed. Snakes can’t lie. ‘Two pluss two equalss four.’ Harry had tried to say that two plus two equalled three, and the word four had slipped out instead.

‘Good. When Salazar Slytherin invoked the Parselmouth curse upon himself and all his children, his true plan was to ensure his descendants could trust one another’s words, whatever plots they wove against outsiders.’ Professor Quirrell had adopted his lecturing pose from Battle Magic, like someone putting on a well-worn mask, but the gun remained pointed in his hand. ‘Occlumency cannot fool the Parselmouth curse as it can fool Veritaserum, and you may put that to the trial also. Now listen well. Come with me, promisse your besst aid in getting Sstone, and I sshall leave thesse children behind unharmed. Hosstagess are real, hundredss of sstudentss die tonight unlesss I sstop eventss already sset in motion. Will sspare hosstagess if I obtain Sstone ssuccessfully. And mark also this, mark it well: I cannot be truly sslain by any means known to me, and lossing Sstone will not sstop me from returning, nor sspare you or yourss my wrath. Any impetuous act you are contemplating cannot win the game for you, boy. I do credit your ability to annoy me, and suggest you avoid doing so.’

‘You said,’ Harry’s voice was strange in his own ears, ‘that the Philosopher’s Stone had different powers from what legend said. You said that to me in Parseltongue. Tell me what the Stone really does, before I agree to help you get it.’ If it was something along the lines of gaining total power over the universe, then nothing was worth an incrementally greater chance of Lord Voldemort getting the Stone.

‘Ah,’ said Professor Quirrell, and smiled. ‘You are thinking. That is better, and as a reward I shall offer you a further incentive for cooperation. Eternal life and youth, the creation of gold and silver. Suppose these are true benefits of holding the Stone. Tell me, boy. What is the Stone’s power?’

It might have been the adrenaline still in him, being actually useful for his brain for once. It might have been the power of being told that an answer existed, and that the evidence wasn’t a lie. ‘It can make Transfigurations permanent.’

Then Harry stopped, as he heard what his own mouth had just said.

‘Correct,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Thus, whoever holds the Philosopher’s Stone is able to perform human Transfiguration.’

Harry’s torn mind was knocked about yet again, as he realized what further incentive would be offered him.

‘You stole Miss Granger’s remains and Transfigured them into some innocuous-appearing target,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘A Transfigured target that you must keep somewhere about your own person, in order to sustain the Transfiguration. Ah, I see your eyes going to that ring upon your hand, but of course Miss Granger would not be the little jewel set into the ring, would it? That would be too obvious. No, I expect you Transfigured Granger’s remains into the ring itself, letting the aura of the Transfigured jewel mask the magic in the Transfigured ring.’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, forcing out the word. It was a lie, for once, and Harry’s glance had been deliberate. Harry had expected someone to challenge him on the steel ring, he’d tried to provoke that challenge so he could prove to be innocent yet again, though nobody had taken him up on it – maybe Dumbledore had just sensed that the steel by itself wasn’t magical.

‘Fine and good,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Now come with me, help me to obtain the Stone, and I will resurrect Hermione Granger on your behalf. Her death has had unfortunate effects on you, and I would not mind undoing them. That, as I understand you, is your greatest desire. I have done you many kindnesses, and I would not mind doing you this one more.’ A blank-eyed Professor Sprout had now risen from the ground and was pointing her own wand at Harry. ‘Help me obtain Sstone of Transsfiguration, and I sshall try my hardesst to ressurrect your girl-child friend to true and lassting life. That ssaid, boy, I am sswiftly running out of patience with you, and you sshall not like what comess next.’ This last line was hissed out in a voice that conveyed the impression of a snake rearing its head to strike.

Even then.

Even then, with all the world upturned, with shock after shock, even then Harry’s brain did not stop being a brain, or completing the patterns its circuits had been wired to complete.

Harry knew that this was too good an offer to make to someone at whom you were pointing a gun.

Unless you desperately needed their help to get the Philosopher’s Stone out of the magic mirror.

And there wasn’t any time left to plan, only the thought that, if Professor Quirrell really was going this far to get his help – what Harry wanted was to demand Professor Quirrell promise not to kill anyone in the future in exchange for his help now, but Harry had a strong sense that Professor Quirrell would reply →Don’t be ridiculous← and there wasn’t time for ordinary conversation Harry had to guess the highest safe request in advance –

Professor Quirrell’s eyes narrowed, his lips parted –

‘If I help you,’ Harry’s mouth said, ‘I want your promise that you aren’t planning to turn on me when this is over. I want you to not kill Professor Snape or anyone else in Hogwarts for at least a week. And I want answers, the truth about everything that’s been going on this whole time, everything you know about my nature.’

The pale blue eyes regarded him dispassionately.

I really think we could have thought of something better to ask for than that, said Harry’s Slytherin side. But I suppose we were legitimately out of time, and whatever we need to do next, answers will help.

Harry wasn’t listening to that voice right now. Cold chills were still going down his spine from hearing the words that had just come out of his lips, addressed to the man with the gun.

‘That is your condition for helping me to obtain the Stone?’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry nodded, unable to form words.

‘Agreed,’ hissed Professor Quirrell. ‘Help me, and you sshall have ansswerss to your quesstions, sso long ass they are about passt eventss, and not my planss for the future. I do not intend to raisse my hand or magic againsst you in future, sso long ass you do not raisse your hand or magic againsst me. Sshall kill none within sschool groundss for a week, unlesss I musst. Now promisse that you will not attempt to warn againsst me or esscape. Promisse to put forth your own besst efforts toward helping me to obtain the Sstone. And your girl-child friend sshall be revived by me, to true life and health; nor sshall me or mine ever sseek to harm her.’ A twisted smile. ‘Promisse, boy, and the bargain will be sstruck.’

‘I promise,’ whispered Harry.

WHAT? screamed other parts of his mind.

Um, he’s still pointing a gun at us, pointed out Slytherin. We don’t actually have a choice, we’re just getting as much mileage out of this as possible.

You bastard, said Hufflepuff. Do you think this is what Hermione would have wanted? This is Lord Voldemort we’re talking about, do we even know how many people he’s killed, and will kill?

I deny that we are compromising with Lord Voldemort for Hermione’s sake, said Slytherin. Since there is, in fact, a gun and we can’t otherwise stop him. Also, Mum and Dad would want us to just go along and stay safe.

Professor Quirrell regarded him steadily. ‘Repeat the full promise in Parseltongue, boy.’

‘I sshall help you obtain the Sstone … I cannot promisse I will usse my besst efforts, my heart will not be in it, I fear. I intend to try. Sshall not do anything I think will annoy you to no good end. Sshall call no help if I expect them to be killed by you or for hosstagess to die. I’m ssorry, teacher, but it iss besst I can do.’ Harry’s mind was settling, composing itself, as the decision was made. He would stay with Professor Quirrell, go with him to get the Stone, save the student hostages, and … and … and Harry didn’t know, except that he’d go on thinking.

‘You actually are sorry about that?’ Professor Quirrell looked amused. ‘I suppose it shall have to do. Then keep two other things in mind: I have plan to sstop even sschoolmasster, if he appearss before uss. And also this: I will occasionally ask you to say in Parseltongue whether you have betrayed me. The bargain is sstruck.’

After that, Professor Sprout picked up Harry’s wand, and wrapped it in shimmering cloth; then she placed it on the floor, and again pointed her wand at Harry. Only then did Professor Quirrell lower his gun, which seemed to disappear into his hand, and pick up Harry’s wrapped wand, tucking it into his robes.

The True Cloak of Invisibility was removed from the sleeping form of Lesath Lestrange, and Professor Quirrell took the Cloak, as well as Harry’s pouch and Time-Turner.

Then Professor Quirrell cast a mass Obliviation followed by the mass version of the False Memory Charm, the one that just had the subject fill in the blanks using their own suggestibility, on all the students present. Afterwards Professor Sprout floated away the sleeping children, now wearing an expression that seemed annoyed and preoccupied, as if they’d been in some Herbology accident.

Professor Quirrell then turned back to where the Potions Master lay sprawled, bent over and placed his wand on Professor Snape’s forehead. ‘Alienis nervus mobile lignum.’

The Defence Professor stepped back, and began to move his left fingers in the air as though manipulating a puppet on strings.

Professor Snape pushed himself up from the ground by smooth motions, and stood once more before the corridor door.

‘Alohomora,’ Professor Quirrell said, pointing his wand at the forbidden door. The Defence Professor looked rather amused. ‘Would you do the honours, boy?’

Harry swallowed. He was once again having second thoughts, and third thoughts.

It was strange how you could do something even while knowing it was the wrong thing, not the selfish thing but the wrong thing to do on some deeper level.

But the man behind him was holding the gun; it had once more appeared in his hand at Harry’s hesitation.

Harry laid his hand on the door-knocker, and took several deep breaths, again composing his mind as best he could. Go through with it, don’t get shot, don’t let the hostages die, be there to optimize events, be there to watch for opportunities and stay capable of taking them. It wasn’t a good choice, but all the other ones seemed worse.

Harry pushed open the forbidden door, and stepped through.

After a single step into Dumbledore’s forbidden chamber, Harry shrieked and jumped back and collided with Professor Snape, sending the two of them down in a heap.

Professor Snape picked himself up and resumed standing in front of the door. His head tracked to look at Harry. ‘I am guarding this door at the Headmaster’s orders,’ said Professor Snape in his usual sardonic tones. ‘Be off with you at once, or I shall deduct House Points.’

This was bone-chillingly creepy, but Harry’s attention was occupied by the gigantic three-headed dog which had lunged forward, only to be stopped metres from Harry by the chains upon its three collars.

‘That – that – that – ’ Harry said.

‘Yes,’ Professor Quirrell said from some way behind him, ‘that is indeed the usual occupant of that chamber, which is off-limits to all students, especially first-years.’

‘That’s not safe even by wizard standards!’ Within the chamber, the enormous black beast gave a multi-voiced bellow, flecks of white saliva flying from three fanged mouths.

Professor Quirrell sighed. ‘It is enchanted not to eat students, just spit them back out through the door. Now, boy, how would you recommend that we deal with this dangerous creature?’

‘Uh,’ Harry stuttered, trying to think over the continued roaring of the chamber’s guardian. ‘Uh. If it’s like the Cerberus from the Muggle legend of Orpheus and Eurydice, then we have to sing it to sleep so we can pass –’

‘Avada Kedavra.’

The three-headed beast fell over.

Harry looked back at Professor Quirrell, who was giving him a look of extreme disappointment, as if to ask whether Harry had attended any of his classes, ever.

‘I sort of assumed,’ Harry said, still trying to catch his breath, ‘that going through this challenge in any way except the one used by first-years, might perhaps trigger an alarm.’

‘That is a lie, boy, you simply did not remember your lessons when you faced the occasion in true life. As for alarms, I have spent months befuddling all the wards and tripsigns upon these chambers.’

‘Then why did you send me in first, exactly?’

Professor Quirrell just smiled. It looked significantly more evil than usual.

‘Never mind,’ Harry said, and walked slowly into the chamber, his limbs still shaking.

The chamber was all of stone, illuminated by a pale blue light that shone from arched nooks carved into the wall; as if the light of a grey sky were passing through windows, though there were no windows. At the far end of the chamber was a wooden trapdoor upon the floor, with a single ring attached. In the middle of the chamber lay a gigantic dead dog with three lifeless heads.

Harry turned toward one of the arched nooks and looked inside it. There was nothing there but the sourceless blue glow, so he walked over and looked in the next one, also scrutinizing the wall as he passed.

‘What,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘are you doing?’

‘Searching the room,’ Harry said. ‘There could be a clue, or an inscription, or a key we’ll need later, or something –’

‘Are you serious, or are you deliberately trying to slow us down? Answer in Parseltongue.’

Harry looked back. ‘Wass sseriouss,’ hissed Harry. ‘Would have done ssame if came by mysself.’

Professor Quirrell briefly massaged his forehead. ‘I confess,’ he said, ‘that your approach would serve you well in, say, exploring the tomb of Amon-Set, so I will not quite call you an idiot, but still. The false puzzle, the outer form of the challenge, is a game meant for first-years. We simply go down through the trapdoor.’

Beneath the trapdoor was a gigantic plant, something like an enormous dieffenbachia with wide leaves emerging from the central stem like a spiral staircase, but darker-coloured than a normal dieffenbachia, with tendril-like vines emerging from the central stem and hanging down. The base spread out wide with bigger leaves and tendrils, as though promising to cushion anyone’s fall. Beneath was another stone chamber like the first, with the same nooks like false arched windows, emitting the same grey-blue light.

‘The obvious thought is to fly down on the broomstick in my pouch, or toss something heavy to see if those tendrils are traps,’ Harry said, peering down. ‘But I’m guessing you’ll say that we just walk down the leaves.’ They certainly looked like they were meant to be a spiral staircase.

‘After you,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry carefully put a foot down on a leaf and found that it indeed supported his weight. Then Harry took a last look around the room before departing, to see if there was anything worth noticing.

The enormous dead dog called enough attention to itself that it was hard to focus on anything else.

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Harry said, omitting the phrase your approach to dealing with obstacles has certain drawbacks, ‘what if somebody looks in the door and sees that the Cerberus is dead?’

‘Then they have probably already noticed something wrong with Snape,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘But since you insist …’ The Defence Professor walked over to the three-headed corpse and placed his wand against it. He began a Latin-sounding incantation that was accompanied by a sense of rising apprehension, the Boy-Who-Lived feeling the Dark Lord’s power as he always had.

The last word spoken was ‘Inferius’ and it was accompanied by a final surge of STOP, DON’T.

And the three-headed dog rose to a stand, its six eyes dull and blank, turning to watch the door once more.

Harry stared at the huge Inferius with a horrible sinking sensation in his stomach, the third-worst feeling he’d ever felt in his life.

He knew then that he’d seen and sensed this procedure before, only without the spoken Latin.

The centaur who’d confronted him in the Forbidden Forest was dead. The Defence Professor had hit it with a real Avada Kedavra, not a fake one.

Somewhere in the back of his mind, Harry had thought that if he could just get Hermione back then he could return to the code of nobody dying, the ethic of Batman. Most people went through their whole lives without anyone getting killed on whatever adventures they had.

And that was not to be.

He hadn’t even noticed, the day he lost his last chance to win. Even if Hermione was resurrected, now, Harry wouldn’t have come through the whole mess without anyone getting killed.

He hadn’t even learned the centaur’s name.

Harry said nothing aloud. The Defence Professor would either confirm the accusation in Parseltongue or lie in plain speech, and either way the Defence Professor would have more reason to suspect Harry’s next actions. But Harry knew that – although he didn’t know how he would stop Professor Quirrell, although he didn’t dare any positive act of betrayal, maybe not even making the decision, until it was almost time to win – there would never be an amicable settlement between him and Lord Voldemort, for those two different spirits could not exist in the same world.

And it was as if that resolution, that knowledge of opposition, invoked a strength from what Harry had thought of as his dark side. Harry had stopped trying to call deliberately on his dark side after the day he’d killed the troll. But his dark side had never been something separate from him. It had been something remembered from Tom Riddle. Harry didn’t know how that had happened, but taking the assumption and running with it, whatever echoes of cognitive skill were in his dark side should be there for him to use. Not as a separate mode, as Harry had conceptualized at first, but just as neural patterns with a strong tendency to chain into one another since they had once formed part of a connected whole.

This unfortunately did not change that Professor Quirrell had the same skills with far more life experience backing them up, and also had the gun.

Harry turned, and set foot on the giant plant, and began to walk down the spiral staircase provided by the leaves. It had taken Harry too long this time, but he’d recovered himself to some degree, despite the grief still weighing him down like thick water. It wasn’t a cold steel rod in his spine, but it was something straight and solid nonetheless. He was going to play this through, see Hermione returned to life first, and then, somehow, stop Professor Quirrell. Or stop Professor Quirrell first and then get the Stone himself. There had to be something, some possibility, some opportunity that would present itself, some way to stop Voldemort and return Hermione to life …

Harry continued his descent.

Behind him, the three-headed dog waited, guarding the gate.

The spiraling leaves of the gigantic dieffenbachia felt like forest loam beneath Harry’s shoes, not as unyielding as concrete, but supporting his weight. Harry kept a wary eye on the tendrils, but they remained passive.

When Harry reached the bottom of the leafy spiral staircase, the tendrils suddenly whipped out and grasped Harry’s arms and legs.

After a brief struggle, Harry allowed himself to go limp.

‘Interesting,’ said Professor Quirrell, as he floated down from above, not touching any of the plant’s leaves or tendrils. ‘I notice that you seem to have no trouble losing to a plant.’

Harry looked more closely at the Defence Professor, seeing him now without the lens of panic. Professor Quirrell was upright and moving, flying without apparent difficulty; the sense of doom about him was strong. But his eyes were still sunken in the skull, his arms thin and wasted. The sickness had not been a bluff, and the obvious hypothesis was that the Defence Professor had recently killed another unicorn to temporarily regain some strength.

And the Defence Professor was also speaking like the mask of Professor Quirrell, not like Lord Voldemort, which might not be a bad thing from Harry’s perspective. Harry didn’t know why – unless it was that the Defence Professor still needed him for something – but it certainly seemed to be in Harry’s own interests to play along.

‘You specifically let me walk into this trap, Professor,’ Harry answered, just the way he’d have spoken to Professor Quirrell. Roles, masks, remind him of how it was between us … ‘On my own, I’d have used my broomstick.’

‘Perhaps. How would an ordinary first-year solve this challenge? If they had their wand, that is.’ The plant was now reaching tendrils out toward Professor Quirrell, but Professor Quirrell was hovering just out of their reach.

Harry had now remembered Professor Sprout talking about a Devil’s Snare plant, which the Herbology textbook had said liked cool, dark places like caves – though how that could be true of a leafy plant was anyone’s guess. ‘At a guess, I’d say this is a Devil’s Snare plant and it might retreat from light or heat. So maybe a first-year could use Lumos? Today I’d use Inflammare, but I didn’t learn that spell until May.’

A twirl of the Defence Professor’s wand, and a pattern of sprays of liquid shot out from it, striking the plant near the bases of its tendrils, hitting with a quiet splat and then a quiet hissing. All the tendrils touching Harry frantically shot back and began to beat at the growing wounds appearing on the plant’s skin, as if trying to remove the pain-stimulus; something about the plant gave the impression that it was screaming soundlessly.

Professor Quirrell finished drifting downward. ‘Now it is afraid of light, heat, acid, and me.’

Harry stepped off the final leaves onto the floor, after a careful glance at his robes and then the floor to make sure that none of the acid had splashed anywhere. Harry had begun to suspect that Professor Quirrell was trying to make some sort of point, but Harry did not know what that point might be. ‘I thought we were on a mission, Professor. I can’t stop you, but is it smart to spend this much time on messing with me?’

‘Oh, we have time,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding amused. ‘There would be a great uproar if we were discovered here, guarded by an Inferius. You did not act like you had heard of such an uproar at your Quidditch match, before you arrived in this time and spoke to Snape as you did.’

A slight chill came over Harry, as he comprehended this. Anything he did to beat Professor Quirrell would have to not disrupt the school, or at least the Quidditch game, because it hadn’t disrupted the Quidditch game. Even if enough forces could be called in to subdue Lord Voldemort, it might not be easy to do it without Professor McGonagall or Professor Flitwick or anyone else at the Quidditch game noticing …

Fighting a smart enemy was hard.

And even so … even so it seemed to Harry that if he stood in Professor Quirrell’s shoes, he would not be having leisurely conversations and playing mind games. Professor Quirrell was gaining something by taking his time here. But what? Was there some other process that had to run to completion?

‘By the by, have you betrayed me yet?’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘Have not betrayed you yet,’ Harry hissed.

The Defence Professor gestured pointedly with the gun he was now holding in his left hand, and Harry walked ahead to the great wooden door at the end of the room, and opened it.

The next chamber was smaller in diameter, with a higher ceiling. The light shining out of the arched alcoves was white, instead of blue.

Around them whizzed hundreds of winged keys, beating frantically through the air. After watching for a few seconds, it became clear that only a single key was the golden colour of a Snitch – though it was moving slower than a Snitch in a real Quidditch game.

On the other end of the room was a door containing a large, prominent keyhole.

Against the left wall leaned a broomstick, the school’s workhorse Cleansweep Seven.

‘Professor,’ Harry said, staring up at the clouds and flocks of whizzing keys, ‘you said you would answer my questions. What exactly is all this about? If you think you’ve secured a door so that it won’t open without a key, you keep the key in a safe place and only give a copy to authorized entrants. You don’t give the key wings and then leave a broomstick propped against the wall. So what the heck are we doing in here and what is going on? It’s an obvious guess that the magic mirror is the only real factor guarding the Stone, but why the rest of this – and why encourage first-years to come here?’

‘I am truly not sure,’ said the Defence Professor. He had entered the room and taken up station well to Harry’s right, maintaining the distance between them. ‘But I shall answer, as I said I would. Dumbledore’s way is to do a dozen things which seem mad, and then only eight of them, or perhaps nine, conceal an inner meaning. My guess is that Dumbledore intends to make it seem like I am invited to send a student as my proxy. Precisely so that Lord Voldemort, as Dumbledore conceives of him, is less tempted to think himself clever by doing so. Imagine Dumbledore first considering the issue of how to ward the Stone. Imagine Dumbledore considering whether to set true dangers to guard the Mirror. Imagine him imagining some young student blundering through those dangers at my behest. I think that is what Dumbledore is trying to avoid, by making it seem as though that strategy is invited, and so not cunning. Unless, of course, I have misunderstood what Dumbledore thinks Lord Voldemort will think.’ Professor Quirrell grinned, and it looked just as natural, on him, as any grin he’d shown Harry before. ‘Plotting does not come naturally to Dumbledore, but he tries because he must. To that task Dumbledore brings intelligence, dedication, the ability to learn from his mistakes, and an utter lack of native talent. He is marvellously hard to predict for that reason alone.’

Harry turned away, looking at the door on the opposite side of the room. It wasn’t a game to him, Professor. ‘My guess is that the intended solution for first-years is to ignore the broomstick and use Wingardium Leviosa to grab the key, since this isn’t a Quidditch game and there are no rules forbidding that. So what absurdly overpowered spell are you going to unleash on this one, then?’

There was a brief silence but for the whizzing of keys.

Harry took several steps away from Professor Quirrell. ‘I probably shouldn’t have said that, should I.’

‘Oh, no,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I think that is a quite reasonable thing to say to the most powerful Dark Wizard in the world when he is standing not a dozen paces from you.’

Professor Quirrell put his wand back into the sleeve of his other hand, the hand that sometimes held the gun.

Then the Defence Professor reached into his mouth and took out what appeared to be a tooth. He tossed the false tooth high in the air, and when it came down, it had transformed into a wand that sparked a strange sense of recognition in Harry’s mind, as though some part of him recognized that wand as being … part of him …

Thirteen and a half inches, yew, with a core of phoenix feather. Harry had memorized the information when the wand-maker Olli-something had given it, because it had seemed like it might be Plot-Relevant. The event, and the thinking that had underlain it, both felt a lifetime distant.

The Defence Professor raised that wand, and traced in the air a flaming rune that was all jagged edges and malevolence; Harry took another instinctive step back. Then Professor Quirrell spoke. ‘Az-reth. Az-reth. Az-reth.’

The flaming rune began pouring out fire that was … twisted, as though the jagged edges of the rune had become the nature of the fire itself. The fire was blazing crimson, shaded further red than blood, glowing as searingly intense as an arc-welder. That brilliance in that shade seemed wrong in its own right, like nothing shaded so far red should give off that much light; and the searing crimson was shot through with veins of black that seemed to suck the light from the fire. Within the blackened fire, outlined in the interplay of crimson and darkness, animal shapes twisted wildly from one predator to another, cobra to hyena to scorpion.

‘Az-reth. Az-reth. Az-reth.’ When Professor Quirrell had repeated the word six times, a small cauldron-full of black–crimson fire had poured out.

The cursed fire slowed in its changes as Professor Quirrell locked eyes upon it, taking on a single form, the form of a blackened blood-burning phoenix.

And something told Harry with a terrible certainty that if that black burning phoenix met Fawkes, the true phoenix would die and never be reborn.

Professor Quirrell made a single gesture with his wand, and the blackened fire went soaring across the room. It met the door and its keyhole, and with a single sweep of crimson-burning wings, most of the door and part of the archway was consumed. Then the tainted crimson blaze swept on.

Harry had only a glance through the hole to see huge statues just beginning to raise swords and clubs, when the blackened fire came among them, and they cracked and burned.

When it ended, the blackened-fire phoenix swept back in through the hole, and hovered above Professor Quirrell’s left shoulder, the Sun-intense crimson claws staying an inch from his robes.

‘Go on ahead,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It’s safe now.’

Harry walked forward, needing to invoke his dark side’s cognitive patterns in order to maintain calm enough to do it. Harry stepped over the glowing edges of the remaining part of the door, and gazed at a chessboard of ruined huge chess-pieces. The alternating tiles of black and white marble on the floor started five metres after the ruined doorway, and extended from wall to wall, but stopped five metres short of the next door on the opposite side of the room. The ceiling was significantly higher than any of the statues should have been able to reach.

‘I would guess,’ Harry said, and his dark side’s cognitive patterns kept his voice calm, ‘that the intended solution is to fly over the statues using the broomstick from the previous room, since it wasn’t actually needed to get the key?’

From behind, Professor Quirrell laughed, and it was Lord Voldemort’s laugh. ‘Proceed,’ said a voice grown colder and higher. ‘Go to the next room. I wish to see what you will make of what is there.’

Arranged by Dumbledore for first-years, Harry reminded himself, it will be safe, and he walked across the ruined chessboard, laid his hand upon that door’s handle, and pushed it inward.

Half a second later, Harry slammed the door and leapt back.

It took Harry several seconds to master his breathing, and master himself. From behind the door came continued loud bellows, and great slams as of a rock club pounding the floor.

‘I suppose,’ Harry said in a voice grown cold as well, ‘that since Dumbledore would hardly put a real mountain troll in there, the next challenge is an illusion of my worst memories. Like a Dementor, with the memory projected into the outside world. Very amusing, Professor.’

Professor Quirrell advanced himself toward the door, and Harry stepped well aside. Besides the sense of doom that was now strong about the Professor, Harry’s dark side or just plain instinct was advising him not to get anywhere near that black-crimson fire hovering above Professor Quirrell’s shoulder.

Professor Quirrell swung open the door, and looked in. ‘Hm,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Just the troll, as you say. Ah, well. I had hoped to learn something about you more interesting than that. What lies within is a Kokorhekkus, also known as the common boggart.’

‘A boggart? What does that – no, I suppose I know what it does.’

‘A boggart,’ Professor Quirrell said, and now his voice was again that of a Hogwarts Professor lecturing, ‘gravitates to dark enclosures that are rarely opened, such as a neglected cupboard in the attic. It seeks to be left alone, and it will manifest in whatever form it thinks will scare you away.’

‘Scare me away?’ Harry said. ‘I killed the troll.’

‘You leapt backward out of the room without thinking. A boggart seeks out the instinctive flinch, not the reasoned threat. Else it would have selected something more believable. In any case, the standard counter-Charm for a boggart is, of course, Fiendfyre.’ Professor Quirrell gestured, and the blackened fire leapt off his shoulder and poured through the doorway.

From within the room there was a single squeak, and then nothing.

They advanced into the boggart’s former room, Professor Quirrell going first this time. With the seeming mountain troll gone, the room was just another huge chamber lit by sconces of cold blue light.

Professor Quirrell’s gaze seemed distant, thoughtful. He crossed the room without waiting for Harry, and swung open the door on the opposite wall of his own accord.

Harry followed after, and not closely.

The next chamber contained a cauldron, a rack of bottled ingredients, chopping boards, stirring sticks, and the other apparatus of Potions. The light coming from the arched alcoves was white instead of blue, presumably because colour vision was important to Potions-brewing. Professor Quirrell was already standing next to the brewing apparatus, scrutinizing a long parchment he had picked up. The door to the next chamber was guarded by a curtain of purple fire that would have looked a lot more threatening, if it hadn’t seemed pale and weak by comparison to the blackened flame hovering over Professor Quirrell’s shoulder.

Harry’s suspension of disbelief had already checked out on holiday at this point, so he didn’t say anything about how real-world security systems had the goal of distinguishing authorized from unauthorized personnel, which meant issuing challenges that behaved differently around people who were or weren’t supposed to be there. For example, a good security challenge would be testing whether the entrant knew a lock combination that only authorized people had been told, and a bad security challenge would be testing whether the entrant could brew a potion according to written instructions that had been helpfully included.

Professor Quirrell tossed the parchment toward Harry, and it fluttered to the ground between them. ‘What do you make of this?’ said Professor Quirrell, who then stepped back so that Harry could come forward and pick up the parchment.

‘Nope,’ Harry said after skimming the parchment. ‘Testing whether the entrant can solve a ridiculously straightforward logic puzzle about the order of the ingredients is still not a challenge that behaves differently for authorized and unauthorized personnel. It doesn’t matter if you use a more interesting logic puzzle about three idols or a line of people wearing coloured hats, you’re still completely missing the point.’

‘Look at the other side,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry turned over the two-foot parchment.

On the other side, written in tiny letters, was the longest list of brewing instructions Harry had ever seen. ‘What on Earth –’

‘A potion of effulgence, to quench the purple fire,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘It is made by adding the same ingredients, over and over again, in slightly different ways. Imagine some eager young group of first-years, passing all the other chambers, thinking they are just about to reach the magic mirror, and then encountering this task. This room is the handiwork of the Potions Master indeed.’

Harry glanced pointedly at the blackfire shape on Professor Quirrell’s shoulder. ‘Fire can’t beat fire?’

‘It can,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I am not sure it should. Suppose this room is trapped?’

Harry did not want to be stuck brewing this potion for laughs, or for whatever other reason Professor Quirrell was taking them through these chambers so slowly. The potions recipe had thirty-five separate occasions for adding bellflowers, fourteen times to add →a lock of bright hair← … ‘Maybe the potion gives off a lethal gas that is fatal to adult wizards but not children. Or any of a hundred other deadly tricks, if we’re suddenly being serious. Are we being serious?’

‘This room is the handiwork of Severus Snape,’ Professor Quirrell said, once more looking thoughtful. ‘Snape is not a bystander in this game, not quite. He lacks Dumbledore’s intelligence, but possesses the killing intent that Dumbledore never had.’

‘Well, whatever’s going on here, it doesn’t actually keep out children,’ Harry observed. ‘Lots of first-years made it through. And if you can somehow keep out everyone except children, then that, from Dumbledore’s perspective, forces Lord Voldemort to possess a child to enter. I don’t see the point, given their goals.’

‘Indeed,’ Professor Quirrell said, rubbing the bridge of his nose. ‘But see, boy, this room lacks the triggers and tripsigns that are upon the others. There are no subtle wards to be defeated. It is as if I am invited to bypass the Potion and simply enter – but Snape knows that Lord Voldemort will perceive this. If in fact there was a trap laid for anyone who did not brew the potion, then it would be wiser to lay wards, and give no sign that this room was different from the others.’

Harry listened, frowning in concentration. ‘So … the only point of leaving off the detection webs is to make you not bulldoze this room.’

‘I expect Snape expects me to deduce that as well,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘And past that point I cannot predict at what level he thinks I will play. I am patient, and I have given myself plenty of time for this endeavour. But Snape does not know me, he only knows Lord Voldemort. He has sometimes seen Lord Voldemort shriek in frustration, and act on impulses that appear counterproductive. Consider this matter from Snape’s perspective: it is the Potions Master of Hogwarts telling Lord Voldemort to be patient and follow instructions if he wants to enter, as though Lord Voldemort were a mere schoolboy. I would find it easy to comply, smiling the while, and take my vengeance later. But Snape does not know that Lord Voldemort finds it easy to think this way.’ Professor Quirrell looked at Harry. ‘Boy, you saw me floating in the air by the Devil’s Snare, did you not?’

Harry nodded. Then he noticed his confusion. ‘My Charms textbook says that it’s impossible for wizards to levitate themselves.’

‘Yes,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘that is what it says in your Charms textbook. No wizard may levitate themselves, or any object supporting their own weight; it is like trying to lift yourself up by your own bootstraps. Yet Lord Voldemort alone can fly – how? Answer as quickly as you can.’

If the question was answerable by a first-year student – ‘You had someone else cast broomstick enchantments on your underwear, then you Obliviated them.’

‘Not quite,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘The broomstick enchantments require a long narrow shape, which must be solid. Cloth will not do.’

Harry’s eyebrows furrowed. ‘How long does the shape have to be? Can you attach some short broomstick rods to a fabric harness, and fly using those?’

‘Indeed, at first I strapped enchanted rods to my arms and legs, but that was only to teach myself a new mode of flight.’ Professor Quirrell drew back the sleeve of his robes, revealing the bare arm. ‘As you can see, I have nothing up my sleeve right now.’

Harry absorbed this further constraint. ‘You had someone cast broomstick enchantments on your bones?’

Professor Quirrell sighed. ‘And that was one of Voldemort’s most feared feats, or so I am told. After all these years, and some amount of reluctant Legilimency, I still do not truly comprehend what is wrong with ordinary people … But you are not one of them. It is time for you to begin contributing to this expedition. You have known Severus Snape more recently than I. Tell me your own analysis of this room.’

Harry hesitated, trying to look thoughtful.

‘I will mention,’ said Professor Quirrell, as the blackened-fire-phoenix on his shoulder seemed to extend its head and glare at Harry, ‘that if you knowingly allow me to fail, I will call it betrayal. I remind you that the Stone is key to Miss Granger’s resurrection, and that I hold hostage the lives of hundreds of students.’

‘I remember,’ Harry said, and on the heels of this Harry’s wonderful inventive brain came up with a thought.

Harry wasn’t sure if he should say it.

The silence stretched.

‘Have you thought of anything yet?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Answer in Parseltongue.’

No, this was not going to be easy, not against a smart opponent who could force you to tell the literal truth at any time. ‘Severus, at least the modern-day Severus, respects your intelligence a great deal,’ Harry said instead. ‘I think … I think he might expect Voldemort to believe that Severus wouldn’t believe that Voldemort could pass his test of patience, but Severus would expect Voldemort to pass it.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘That is a plausible theory. Do you believe it yourself? Answer in Parseltongue.’

‘Yess,’ Harry hissed. It might not be safe to withhold information, not even thoughts and ideas … ‘Therefore, the point of this room is to delay Lord Voldemort for an hour. And if I wanted to kill you, believing what Dumbledore believes, the obvious thing to try would be a Dementor’s Kiss. I mean, they think you’re a disembodied soul – are you, by the way?’

Professor Quirrell was still. ‘Dumbledore would not think of that method,’ the Defence Professor said after a time. ‘But Severus might.’ Professor Quirrell began to tap a finger against his cheek, his gaze distant. ‘You have power over Dementors, boy, can you tell me if there are any nearby?’

Harry closed his eyes. If there were voids in the world, he could not feel them. ‘None that I can sense.’

‘Answer in Parseltongue.’

‘Do not ssensse life-eaterss.’

‘But you were being honest with me when you suggested the possibility? You intended no clever trickery?’

‘Wass honesst. Not trick.’

‘Perhaps there is some means by which Dementors might be concealed, being told to leap out and eat a possessing soul if they see one …’ Professor Quirrell was still tapping his cheek. ‘It is not impossible that I would qualify. Or it can be told to eat anyone who passes through this room too quickly, or anyone who is not a child. Bearing in mind that I hold Hermione and hundreds of other students hostage over you, would you use your power over Dementors to defend me, if a Dementor unmasked itself? Answer in Parseltongue.’

‘Don’t know,’ Harry hissed.

‘Life-eaterss cannot desstroy me, I think,’ hissed Professor Quirrell. ‘And I will ssimply abandon thiss body if they approach too closse. Sshall return sswiftly thiss time, and then there will be no sstopping me. Will torture your parentss for yearss, to punissh you for balking me. Hundredss of hosstage sstudentss die, including thosse you call friendss. Now I assk again. Will you usse power over life-eaterss to protect me, if life-eaterss come?’

‘Yess,’ Harry whispered. The sadness and horror that Harry had pushed down flared up again, and his dark side had no stored patterns for handling the emotions. Why, Professor Quirrell, why are you like this …

Professor Quirrell smiled. ‘That reminds me. Have you betrayed me yet?’

‘Have not betrayed you yet.’

Professor Quirrell went over to the Potions equipment, and began chopping a root one-handed, the knife moving almost invisibly fast and with no apparent effort. The Fiendfyre phoenix drifted over to the opposite corner of the room and waited there. ‘All matters considered in their uncertainty, it seems wiser to expend the time to pass this room as a first-year would,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘We may as well talk while we are waiting. You had questions, boy? I said that I would answer them, so ask.’

Ch. 108 (long) will post on February 20th, 2015 at 1pm Pacific Time (9pm UTC).

Those of you who have outstanding disputes regarding the Defence Professor’s secrets should bet now, or forever hold your peace.

Failure

The Dark Lord was laughing.

From the empty air came the voice of the Defence Professor laughing wildly, so high and terrible his laughter; it was Voldemort’s laughter now, the Dark Lord’s laughter beyond all hiding or restraint.

Harry’s mind was disarrayed. His eyes kept staring at where Albus Dumbledore had been. There was a horror in him that was too huge for understanding or reflection. His mind kept trying to fall back through time and undo reality, but that wasn’t a sort of magic that existed, and reality stayed the same.

He had lost, he had lost Dumbledore, there were no take-backs, and that meant he had lost the war.

And the Dark Lord went on laughing.

‘Ah, ah hah, ah hah hah ha! Professor Dumbledore, ah, Professor Dumbledore, such a fitting end to our game!’ Another burst of wild laughter. ‘The wrong sacrifice even at the finish, for the piece you gave up everything to save was already in my possession! The wrong trap even from the beginning, for I could have abandoned this body at any time! Ah, hahahahaha, aha! You never did learn cunning, you poor old fool.’

‘You –’ A voice was coming from Harry’s throat. ‘You –’

‘Ahahahaha! Why, yes, little child, you were always along on this adventure as my hostage, it was your whole purpose in being here. Ha, hahahaha! You are decades too young to play this game against the real Tom Riddle, child.’ The Dark Lord drew back the hood of the Cloak, his head becoming visible, and began to remove the rest of the Cloak. ‘And now, boy, you have helped me, yess indeed, and so it iss time to ressurrect your girl-child friend. To keep promisse.’ The Dark Lord’s smile was cold, cold indeed. ‘I suppose you have doubts? Mark well, I could kill you this instant, for there is no longer a Headmaster of Hogwarts to be informed of it. Doubt me all you wish, but remember that.’ The hand was once more holding the gun. ‘Now come along, foolish child.’

And they left.

They went back out through the door into the Potions room, the Dark Lord banishing the returned purple fire with a stroke of his wand. They went through the chamber where the boggart had been, and the chamber of ruined chess statues, and through the burned door of the chamber of keys. The Dark Lord floated up through the trapdoor, and Harry struggled up afterwards through the spiral staircase of leaves, the tendrils of the Devil’s Snare twitching and then moving back as though afraid. The Boy-Who-Lived was trying hard not to burst into tears, and his dark-side patterns weren’t helping, maybe because Voldemort had never known or dealt with guilt.

They passed the huge three-headed Inferi, and at a whispered word from the Dark Lord it collapsed over the trapdoor and became a corpse again.

They passed Severus Snape standing guard, who told them both that he was guarding the door, and that they must leave or he would deduct House points.

The Dark Lord spoke the words ‘Hyakuju montauk’ without pausing in his stride, accompanied by a jab of his wand; and Severus staggered before he lifelessly drew himself up beside the door once more.

‘What –’ Harry said, as he followed. ‘What did you –’

‘Just fulfilling my obligation to my faithful servant. It shall not kill him, as I promised you.’ The Dark Lord laughed again.

‘The hostages –’ Harry said. It was hard to keep his voice steady. ‘The students, you said you’d stop whatever is going to kill them –’

‘Yes. Stop worrying. Will do on our way out.’

‘Out?’

‘We are leaving, child.’ The Dark Lord was still smiling.

The bad feeling this raised was lost in a sea of other bad feelings.

The Dark Lord was now consulting what he’d called the Hogwarts Map, the handwritten lines upon it seeming to move as they walked. Some part of Harry’s mind that had been considering what to do if they ran into Aurors on patrol (whom the Dark Lord could kill, or Obliviate, in an instant) gave up that hope as well.

They went down the Grand Staircase to the second floor, encountering no one.

The Dark Lord made a turn Harry did not know, and went down another stair-flight. As they descended past one floor and another, the windows stopped and the torches began, they were within the Slytherin dungeons now.

Ahead, the form of a person in Hogwarts robes appeared.

The Dark Lord kept walking toward that person.

Harry followed.

A sixth or seventh-year Slytherin was waiting by a section of wall that was set with an artistic carving of Salazar Slytherin wielding his wand, against what looked like a giant covered in icicles. The witch made no comment at seeing Professor Quirrell walking upright, or seeing Harry in his company, or seeing the gun in the Defence Professor’s hand. If her eyes were blank, Harry couldn’t tell the difference.

The Dark Lord reached into his robes, took out a Knut, and flipped it to her. ‘Klaudia Alicja Tabor, I command you thus. Take this Knut to the spell circle I showed you beneath the Quidditch stands and put it in the centre. Then Obliviate yourself of the last six hours.’

‘Yes, lord,’ the witch said, bowing to him, and went on her way.

‘I thought –’ Harry said. ‘I thought you needed the Stone to –’

The Dark Lord was still smiling, he had never stopped smiling. ‘I did not say that part in Parseltongue, child. All I said in Parseltongue was that I had set events in motion to kill students, events that I would stop if I obtained the Stone. The rest was in human speech. I would also have stopped the Blood Fort sacrifice if I had not obtained the Stone, so long as I was not discovered and restrained. The students of Hogwarts are a valuable resource, whom I have already spent much time training.’ Then the Dark Lord hissed to the wall, ‘Open.’

Harry’s eyes saw the tiny snake that had been set in the upper-left of the carving, even as the wall slowly swung backward, revealing the opening of a huge pipe. Moss grew on its sides and a musty dusty smell welled up from it; the interior was also covered with cobwebs in multiple sheets.

‘Spiders …’ murmured the Dark Lord. He sighed, and for that brief moment he sounded once more like Professor Quirrell.

The Dark Lord walked into the huge pipe, the cobwebs burning away before him. Harry, not seeing any other better options, followed.

The pipe branched in a Y-shape, then branched again. The Dark Lord went left, then right.

The pipe came to a solid metal wall. ‘Open,’ the Dark Lord hissed, and a crack appeared in the metal; it seemed to fold into itself.

Beyond was the middle of a long, stone tunnel.

‘We shall be walking a while,’ said the Dark Lord. ‘Did you have more questions to ask, little child?’

‘I – I can’t think of any – right now –’

Another cold laugh replied to this, and they walked into the tunnel, turning right.

Harry didn’t know, then or ever, how long he walked; the light of burning spiderwebs was too dim to read his mechanical watch, and Harry had not thought to look at the time before entering. It felt like they walked for miles, miles beneath the ground.

Slowly, Harry’s mind tried to recover itself a final time. Very possibly final, if he was right about the Dark Lord killing him after this … though the Dark Lord had said that he would resurrect Hermione, which seemed pointless if that was true … was that simply the Dark Lord following through on a promise he would not otherwise have been able to make in Parseltongue … why had he not just shot Harry on the spot …

Seriously, some last functioning part of his brain said to all the other parts, this would be a good time to think of something, something that the Dark Lord has not already thought of, something we can do without our pouch or our wand or our Time-Turner, something that Professor Quirrell has not imagined we can do … think, think, pretty pretty please think of something? Don’t shut down now, even if you’re scared, even if we’ve never really really faced death before in the sense of being about to die in the next hour, this is not the time to shut down –

Harry’s mind stayed blank.

Suppose, said that last remaining part, suppose we try to condition on the fact that we win this, or at least get out of this alive. If someone told you as a fact that you had survived, or even won, somehow made everything turn out okay, what would you think had happened –

Not legitimate procedure, whispered Ravenclaw, the universe doesn’t work like that, we’re just going to die.

Someone realises we’re missing, thought Hufflepuff, and Mad-Eye Moody shows up with a squad of Aurors and rescues us. I think the time has come to admit we’re not more competent than the standard authorities.

The saving factor does have to be something we do somehow, said the last voice. Otherwise there’s no point in our thinking about it.

Problem two, said Gryffindor. Harry Potter isn’t missing, he’s right there at the Quidditch match where everyone can see him. Professor Quirrell thought of that too, it’s part of why he sent that fake note. Problem three. I don’t think Mad-Eye Moody and an Auror squad can beat the Dark Lord, and certainly not before he kills us. I’m not sure the entire DMLE can beat the Dark Lord if he’s fighting seriously and Dumbledore is gone. Problem four. The Quidditch match was not disrupted, that’s probably the only reason why Professor Quirrell was willing to try something as complicated as bringing us along on this trip in the first place.

Thinking along different lines, ventured Slytherin, maybe Professor Quirrell calls in someone else to Memory-Charm us. Legilimency, Imperius, Confundus, who knows what else, we’re not a perfect Occlumens. Then the Dark Lord would have a smart – well, sort-of smart lieutenant that he could use. That could be another reason why Professor Quirrell was so willing to tell us secrets, if he knew that the memory would disappear. It’s also a reason to leave the Hogwarts wards, so the Dark Lord can call Bellatrix to Apparate in and do the work …

This entire reasoning process is illegitimate and I refuse to participate, said Ravenclaw.

What lovely last words, said the last voice. Now shut up and think.

Rough stone tunnel went by underfoot, Harry’s shoes sometimes dipping into moisture or nearly slipping on a curved surface. The neurons in his brain, which kept on firing, imagined voices talking to each other, yelling at each other, even as the Listener stayed numb with horror and shame.

Gryffindor and Hufflepuff were conducting a debate about suicide by charging the Dark Lord’s gun, or by swallowing the little jewel on Harry’s steel ring. It seemed unclear whether the fate of the world was better or worse if the Dark Lord had Harry as a mind-slave; if the Dark Lord was going to win anyway, it might be better if he won faster.

And the last voice kept talking through it all; even in the depths of failure that last voice remained. What else did the Dark Lord always say in human speech and never in Parseltongue? Do we remember? Anything like that, anything at all?

It was all too distant in time, too distant in time even though it had all happened this very day. The Dark Lord had told him in Parseltongue just now that it was time to revive Hermione, and then he’d said other things all in English, Harry could hardly remember for all that they’d just been spoken. Before then … before then there’d been the Circle of Concealment, when Professor Quirrell had hissed that the barrier would explode if touched. And the Defence Professor had said in English for Harry not to take off his Cloak or try crossing the Circle, said in English that the resonance might strike Professor Quirrell afterwards but Harry would be dead. Said in English that if Harry touched the magic and Professor Quirrell didn’t remember how to halt the resonance, it would kill them both …

Suppose it doesn’t kill us both, said the last voice. On Halloween in Godric’s Hollow, the Dark Lord’s body was burned and we only ended up with a scar on our forehead. Suppose the resonance between us is deadlier to the Dark Lord than to us. What if this entire time we’ve been able to kill the Dark Lord at any time, just by dashing forward and touching our hands to any part of his exposed skin? And then it makes our scar bleed again, but that’s all. The sense of stop, don’t do that is inherited from the Dark Lord’s worst memory of his mistake in Godric’s Hollow, it may not actually apply to the Boy-Who-Lived.

A small note of hope rose.

Rose, and was quashed.

The Dark Lord can just throw away his wand, droned Ravenclaw. Professor Quirrell can turn into his Animagus form. Even if he dies the Dark Lord will possess someone else and return, and then torture our parents, to punish us.

We might be able to get to our parents in time, said the last voice. We might be able to hide them. We might be able to get the Philosopher’s Stone away from the Dark Lord if we killed his current body now, and that Stone could provide the nucleus of a counter-army.

The Dark Lord was moving on through the stony corridor. His hand still held the gun. He was at least four metres away from Harry.

If we dart forward, he will sense us approaching through the resonance, said Hufflepuff. He will fly forward rapidly, he can do that, he has the broomstick-enchantments that let him fly. He will fly forward, turn around, and fire the gun. He knows about the resonance, he’s thought of this already. This is not something the Dark Lord has failed to consider. He will be ready for it, and waiting.

Continuing the same line of argument, said the last voice. Suppose we can freely cast magic on Professor Quirrell but he can’t cast it on us.

Why would that be true? demanded Ravenclaw. In fact, we have evidence that it’s false. In Azkaban, when Professor Quirrell’s Avada Kedavra hit our Patronus Charm, it felt like our head was splitting apart –

Suppose that was all his magic going out of control. Suppose if we’d just cast, say, a Luminos targeting him, nothing bad would have happened.

But why? said Ravenclaw. Why suppose that?

Because, thought Harry, it explains why Professor Quirrell didn’t warn me not to cast any magic on him in Azkaban. Because Professor Quirrell never said in Parseltongue, that I can remember, that I’d hurt myself if I tried to cast magic on him. He could have given me that warning, but he didn’t, even though he gave me a lot of other warnings. Absence of evidence is weak evidence of absence.

There was a pause while Harry’s parts considered this.

We don’t actually have our wand, said Ravenclaw.

We might get it back at some point, thought the last voice.

But even then, Harry thought, and the grey hopelessness returned, the resonance is something the Dark Lord knows about. He’s already thought of everything I can do with that, he already has a response prepared. That was my mistake from the beginning. I didn’t respect the Dark Lord’s intelligence, I didn’t think that maybe he knew everything I knew and could see everything I saw and had already taken it into account.

Then, said the last voice, conditional on our winning, we must have hit him with something he doesn’t know about.

Dementors, offered Gryffindor.

The Dark Lord knows we can destroy, deflect, and possibly control Dementors, said Ravenclaw. He doesn’t know how, but he knows we have the capability, and where the heck would we get a Dementor anyway?

Maybe, ventured Hufflepuff, the Dark Lord’s whole horcrux system would short out via the resonance if we grabbed him and held him, sacrificing our own life to destroy him forever.

Balderdash, said Ravenclaw. But I guess it doesn’t hurt to engage in some pleasant fantasy before we die, no matter how stupid.

If Lord Voldemort had a strong enough fear of death, Hufflepuff argued, if he wanted strongly enough to just not need to think about death again, then the horcrux system could have design flaws like that. It never occurred to Voldemort to test his horcruxes on someone else, that could indicate he wasn’t able to think about the subject clearly –

So his fear of death is his fatal weakness? said Ravenclaw. Yeah, no. I’m thinking someone with over a hundred horcruxes might have a few fail-safe mechanisms in there.

And Harry’s brain went on thinking.

A genuine asymmetry in the magical resonance between them … seemed improbable, there was no reason for the magical effect to work like that. But the magical backlash could hit the stronger wizard harder, the more powerful magic resonating more dangerously. That could explain the observed event in Godric’s Hollow (Voldemort explodes, baby survives), and also explain the observed event in Azkaban (Voldemort severely impaired by backlash of his strong magic, first-year Boy-Who-Lived hit by lighter backlash of his weak magic). Or if it was only the caster’s magic that resonated, that could also explain both those two observations. That might even explain why Professor Quirrell had been in no rush to warn Harry against casting any magic on him. Though there was another obvious reason why Professor Quirrell would avoid raising the subject of the resonance; it was a gigantic hint about the mystery of Godric’s Hollow, if Harry had ever made the connection.

The part that was numb with grief and guilt took this opportunity to observe, speaking of obliviousness, that after events at Hogwarts had turned serious, they really really really REALLY should have reconsidered the decision made on First Thursday, at the behest of Professor McGonagall, not to tell Dumbledore about the sense of doom that Harry got around Professor Quirrell. It was true that Harry hadn’t been sure who to trust, there was a long stretch where it had seemed plausible that Dumbledore was the bad guy and Professor Quirrell the heroic opposition, but …

Dumbledore would have realised.

Dumbledore would have realised instantly.

The wise old wizard with the true phoenix on his shoulder would have known, and Harry hadn’t trusted him, Harry hadn’t told him all the relevant facts, and the reason for this had been sheer neglect to reconsider a cached decision made four days into the start of the school year. It had been marked something not to tell Dumbledore and even after Azkaban, even after Hermione died, even after everything, Harry had simply forgot to promote the question to deliberation and reconsider the trade-off.

Another wave of grief and shame washed over Harry, and for a time he walked on in the silence of the last voice, other voices being happy enough to fill the gap.

After what was at least several miles, and many grey thoughts, the stone tunnel ended.

The Dark Lord climbed up stone steps, and Harry followed after.

Failure

The Dark Lord was laughing.

From the empty air came the voice of the Defence Professor laughing wildly, so high and terrible his laughter; it was Voldemort’s laughter now, the Dark Lord’s laughter beyond all hiding or restraint.

Harry’s mind was disarrayed. His eyes kept staring at where Albus Dumbledore had been. There was a horror in him that was too huge for understanding or reflection. His mind kept trying to fall back through time and undo reality, but that wasn’t a sort of magic that existed, and reality stayed the same.

He had lost, he had lost Dumbledore, there were no take-backs, and that meant he had lost the war.

And the Dark Lord went on laughing.

‘Ah, ah hah, ah hah hah ha! Professor Dumbledore, ah, Professor Dumbledore, such a fitting end to our game!’ Another burst of wild laughter. ‘The wrong sacrifice even at the finish, for the piece you gave up everything to save was already in my possession! The wrong trap even from the beginning, for I could have abandoned this body at any time! Ah, hahahahaha, aha! You never did learn cunning, you poor old fool.’

‘You –’ A voice was coming from Harry’s throat. ‘You –’

‘Ahahahaha! Why, yes, little child, you were always along on this adventure as my hostage, it was your whole purpose in being here. Ha, hahahaha! You are decades too young to play this game against the real Tom Riddle, child.’ The Dark Lord drew back the hood of the Cloak, his head becoming visible, and began to remove the rest of the Cloak. ‘And now, boy, you have helped me, yess indeed, and so it iss time to ressurrect your girl-child friend. To keep promisse.’ The Dark Lord’s smile was cold, cold indeed. ‘I suppose you have doubts? Mark well, I could kill you this instant, for there is no longer a Headmaster of Hogwarts to be informed of it. Doubt me all you wish, but remember that.’ The hand was once more holding the gun. ‘Now come along, foolish child.’

And they left.

They went back out through the door into the Potions room, the Dark Lord banishing the returned purple fire with a stroke of his wand. They went through the chamber where the boggart had been, and the chamber of ruined chess statues, and through the burned door of the chamber of keys. The Dark Lord floated up through the trapdoor, and Harry struggled up afterwards through the spiral staircase of leaves, the tendrils of the Devil’s Snare twitching and then moving back as though afraid. The Boy-Who-Lived was trying hard not to burst into tears, and his dark-side patterns weren’t helping, maybe because Voldemort had never known or dealt with guilt.

They passed the huge three-headed Inferi, and at a whispered word from the Dark Lord it collapsed over the trapdoor and became a corpse again.

They passed Severus Snape standing guard, who told them both that he was guarding the door, and that they must leave or he would deduct House points.

The Dark Lord spoke the words ‘Hyakuju montauk’ without pausing in his stride, accompanied by a jab of his wand; and Severus staggered before he lifelessly drew himself up beside the door once more.

‘What –’ Harry said, as he followed. ‘What did you –’

‘Just fulfilling my obligation to my faithful servant. It shall not kill him, as I promised you.’ The Dark Lord laughed again.

‘The hostages –’ Harry said. It was hard to keep his voice steady. ‘The students, you said you’d stop whatever is going to kill them –’

‘Yes. Stop worrying. Will do on our way out.’

‘Out?’

‘We are leaving, child.’ The Dark Lord was still smiling.

The bad feeling this raised was lost in a sea of other bad feelings.

The Dark Lord was now consulting what he’d called the Hogwarts Map, the handwritten lines upon it seeming to move as they walked. Some part of Harry’s mind that had been considering what to do if they ran into Aurors on patrol (whom the Dark Lord could kill, or Obliviate, in an instant) gave up that hope as well.

They went down the Grand Staircase to the second floor, encountering no one.

The Dark Lord made a turn Harry did not know, and went down another stair-flight. As they descended past one floor and another, the windows stopped and the torches began, they were within the Slytherin dungeons now.

Ahead, the form of a person in Hogwarts robes appeared.

The Dark Lord kept walking toward that person.

Harry followed.

A sixth or seventh-year Slytherin was waiting by a section of wall that was set with an artistic carving of Salazar Slytherin wielding his wand, against what looked like a giant covered in icicles. The witch made no comment at seeing Professor Quirrell walking upright, or seeing Harry in his company, or seeing the gun in the Defence Professor’s hand. If her eyes were blank, Harry couldn’t tell the difference.

The Dark Lord reached into his robes, took out a Knut, and flipped it to her. ‘Klaudia Alicja Tabor, I command you thus. Take this Knut to the spell circle I showed you beneath the Quidditch stands and put it in the centre. Then Obliviate yourself of the last six hours.’

‘Yes, lord,’ the witch said, bowing to him, and went on her way.

‘I thought –’ Harry said. ‘I thought you needed the Stone to –’

The Dark Lord was still smiling, he had never stopped smiling. ‘I did not say that part in Parseltongue, child. All I said in Parseltongue was that I had set events in motion to kill students, events that I would stop if I obtained the Stone. The rest was in human speech. I would also have stopped the Blood Fort sacrifice if I had not obtained the Stone, so long as I was not discovered and restrained. The students of Hogwarts are a valuable resource, whom I have already spent much time training.’ Then the Dark Lord hissed to the wall, ‘Open.’

Harry’s eyes saw the tiny snake that had been set in the upper-left of the carving, even as the wall slowly swung backward, revealing the opening of a huge pipe. Moss grew on its sides and a musty dusty smell welled up from it; the interior was also covered with cobwebs in multiple sheets.

‘Spiders …’ murmured the Dark Lord. He sighed, and for that brief moment he sounded once more like Professor Quirrell.

The Dark Lord walked into the huge pipe, the cobwebs burning away before him. Harry, not seeing any other better options, followed.

The pipe branched in a Y-shape, then branched again. The Dark Lord went left, then right.

The pipe came to a solid metal wall. ‘Open,’ the Dark Lord hissed, and a crack appeared in the metal; it seemed to fold into itself.

Beyond was the middle of a long, stone tunnel.

‘We shall be walking a while,’ said the Dark Lord. ‘Did you have more questions to ask, little child?’

‘I – I can’t think of any – right now –’

Another cold laugh replied to this, and they walked into the tunnel, turning right.

Harry didn’t know, then or ever, how long he walked; the light of burning spiderwebs was too dim to read his mechanical watch, and Harry had not thought to look at the time before entering. It felt like they walked for miles, miles beneath the ground.

Slowly, Harry’s mind tried to recover itself a final time. Very possibly final, if he was right about the Dark Lord killing him after this … though the Dark Lord had said that he would resurrect Hermione, which seemed pointless if that was true … was that simply the Dark Lord following through on a promise he would not otherwise have been able to make in Parseltongue … why had he not just shot Harry on the spot …

Seriously, some last functioning part of his brain said to all the other parts, this would be a good time to think of something, something that the Dark Lord has not already thought of, something we can do without our pouch or our wand or our Time-Turner, something that Professor Quirrell has not imagined we can do … think, think, pretty pretty please think of something? Don’t shut down now, even if you’re scared, even if we’ve never really really faced death before in the sense of being about to die in the next hour, this is not the time to shut down –

Harry’s mind stayed blank.

Suppose, said that last remaining part, suppose we try to condition on the fact that we win this, or at least get out of this alive. If someone told you as a fact that you had survived, or even won, somehow made everything turn out okay, what would you think had happened –

Not legitimate procedure, whispered Ravenclaw, the universe doesn’t work like that, we’re just going to die.

Someone realises we’re missing, thought Hufflepuff, and Mad-Eye Moody shows up with a squad of Aurors and rescues us. I think the time has come to admit we’re not more competent than the standard authorities.

The saving factor does have to be something we do somehow, said the last voice. Otherwise there’s no point in our thinking about it.

Problem two, said Gryffindor. Harry Potter isn’t missing, he’s right there at the Quidditch match where everyone can see him. Professor Quirrell thought of that too, it’s part of why he sent that fake note. Problem three. I don’t think Mad-Eye Moody and an Auror squad can beat the Dark Lord, and certainly not before he kills us. I’m not sure the entire DMLE can beat the Dark Lord if he’s fighting seriously and Dumbledore is gone. Problem four. The Quidditch match was not disrupted, that’s probably the only reason why Professor Quirrell was willing to try something as complicated as bringing us along on this trip in the first place.

Thinking along different lines, ventured Slytherin, maybe Professor Quirrell calls in someone else to Memory-Charm us. Legilimency, Imperius, Confundus, who knows what else, we’re not a perfect Occlumens. Then the Dark Lord would have a smart – well, sort-of smart lieutenant that he could use. That could be another reason why Professor Quirrell was so willing to tell us secrets, if he knew that the memory would disappear. It’s also a reason to leave the Hogwarts wards, so the Dark Lord can call Bellatrix to Apparate in and do the work …

This entire reasoning process is illegitimate and I refuse to participate, said Ravenclaw.

What lovely last words, said the last voice. Now shut up and think.

Rough stone tunnel went by underfoot, Harry’s shoes sometimes dipping into moisture or nearly slipping on a curved surface. The neurons in his brain, which kept on firing, imagined voices talking to each other, yelling at each other, even as the Listener stayed numb with horror and shame.

Gryffindor and Hufflepuff were conducting a debate about suicide by charging the Dark Lord’s gun, or by swallowing the little jewel on Harry’s steel ring. It seemed unclear whether the fate of the world was better or worse if the Dark Lord had Harry as a mind-slave; if the Dark Lord was going to win anyway, it might be better if he won faster.

And the last voice kept talking through it all; even in the depths of failure that last voice remained. What else did the Dark Lord always say in human speech and never in Parseltongue? Do we remember? Anything like that, anything at all?

It was all too distant in time, too distant in time even though it had all happened this very day. The Dark Lord had told him in Parseltongue just now that it was time to revive Hermione, and then he’d said other things all in English, Harry could hardly remember for all that they’d just been spoken. Before then … before then there’d been the Circle of Concealment, when Professor Quirrell had hissed that the barrier would explode if touched. And the Defence Professor had said in English for Harry not to take off his Cloak or try crossing the Circle, said in English that the resonance might strike Professor Quirrell afterwards but Harry would be dead. Said in English that if Harry touched the magic and Professor Quirrell didn’t remember how to halt the resonance, it would kill them both …

Suppose it doesn’t kill us both, said the last voice. On Halloween in Godric’s Hollow, the Dark Lord’s body was burned and we only ended up with a scar on our forehead. Suppose the resonance between us is deadlier to the Dark Lord than to us. What if this entire time we’ve been able to kill the Dark Lord at any time, just by dashing forward and touching our hands to any part of his exposed skin? And then it makes our scar bleed again, but that’s all. The sense of stop, don’t do that is inherited from the Dark Lord’s worst memory of his mistake in Godric’s Hollow, it may not actually apply to the Boy-Who-Lived.

A small note of hope rose.

Rose, and was quashed.

The Dark Lord can just throw away his wand, droned Ravenclaw. Professor Quirrell can turn into his Animagus form. Even if he dies the Dark Lord will possess someone else and return, and then torture our parents, to punish us.

We might be able to get to our parents in time, said the last voice. We might be able to hide them. We might be able to get the Philosopher’s Stone away from the Dark Lord if we killed his current body now, and that Stone could provide the nucleus of a counter-army.

The Dark Lord was moving on through the stony corridor. His hand still held the gun. He was at least four metres away from Harry.

If we dart forward, he will sense us approaching through the resonance, said Hufflepuff. He will fly forward rapidly, he can do that, he has the broomstick-enchantments that let him fly. He will fly forward, turn around, and fire the gun. He knows about the resonance, he’s thought of this already. This is not something the Dark Lord has failed to consider. He will be ready for it, and waiting.

Continuing the same line of argument, said the last voice. Suppose we can freely cast magic on Professor Quirrell but he can’t cast it on us.

Why would that be true? demanded Ravenclaw. In fact, we have evidence that it’s false. In Azkaban, when Professor Quirrell’s Avada Kedavra hit our Patronus Charm, it felt like our head was splitting apart –

Suppose that was all his magic going out of control. Suppose if we’d just cast, say, a Luminos targeting him, nothing bad would have happened.

But why? said Ravenclaw. Why suppose that?

Because, thought Harry, it explains why Professor Quirrell didn’t warn me not to cast any magic on him in Azkaban. Because Professor Quirrell never said in Parseltongue, that I can remember, that I’d hurt myself if I tried to cast magic on him. He could have given me that warning, but he didn’t, even though he gave me a lot of other warnings. Absence of evidence is weak evidence of absence.

There was a pause while Harry’s parts considered this.

We don’t actually have our wand, said Ravenclaw.

We might get it back at some point, thought the last voice.

But even then, Harry thought, and the grey hopelessness returned, the resonance is something the Dark Lord knows about. He’s already thought of everything I can do with that, he already has a response prepared. That was my mistake from the beginning. I didn’t respect the Dark Lord’s intelligence, I didn’t think that maybe he knew everything I knew and could see everything I saw and had already taken it into account.

Then, said the last voice, conditional on our winning, we must have hit him with something he doesn’t know about.

Dementors, offered Gryffindor.

The Dark Lord knows we can destroy, deflect, and possibly control Dementors, said Ravenclaw. He doesn’t know how, but he knows we have the capability, and where the heck would we get a Dementor anyway?

Maybe, ventured Hufflepuff, the Dark Lord’s whole horcrux system would short out via the resonance if we grabbed him and held him, sacrificing our own life to destroy him forever.

Balderdash, said Ravenclaw. But I guess it doesn’t hurt to engage in some pleasant fantasy before we die, no matter how stupid.

If Lord Voldemort had a strong enough fear of death, Hufflepuff argued, if he wanted strongly enough to just not need to think about death again, then the horcrux system could have design flaws like that. It never occurred to Voldemort to test his horcruxes on someone else, that could indicate he wasn’t able to think about the subject clearly –

So his fear of death is his fatal weakness? said Ravenclaw. Yeah, no. I’m thinking someone with over a hundred horcruxes might have a few fail-safe mechanisms in there.

And Harry’s brain went on thinking.

A genuine asymmetry in the magical resonance between them … seemed improbable, there was no reason for the magical effect to work like that. But the magical backlash could hit the stronger wizard harder, the more powerful magic resonating more dangerously. That could explain the observed event in Godric’s Hollow (Voldemort explodes, baby survives), and also explain the observed event in Azkaban (Voldemort severely impaired by backlash of his strong magic, first-year Boy-Who-Lived hit by lighter backlash of his weak magic). Or if it was only the caster’s magic that resonated, that could also explain both those two observations. That might even explain why Professor Quirrell had been in no rush to warn Harry against casting any magic on him. Though there was another obvious reason why Professor Quirrell would avoid raising the subject of the resonance; it was a gigantic hint about the mystery of Godric’s Hollow, if Harry had ever made the connection.

The part that was numb with grief and guilt took this opportunity to observe, speaking of obliviousness, that after events at Hogwarts had turned serious, they really really really REALLY should have reconsidered the decision made on First Thursday, at the behest of Professor McGonagall, not to tell Dumbledore about the sense of doom that Harry got around Professor Quirrell. It was true that Harry hadn’t been sure who to trust, there was a long stretch where it had seemed plausible that Dumbledore was the bad guy and Professor Quirrell the heroic opposition, but …

Dumbledore would have realised.

Dumbledore would have realised instantly.

The wise old wizard with the true phoenix on his shoulder would have known, and Harry hadn’t trusted him, Harry hadn’t told him all the relevant facts, and the reason for this had been sheer neglect to reconsider a cached decision made four days into the start of the school year. It had been marked something not to tell Dumbledore and even after Azkaban, even after Hermione died, even after everything, Harry had simply forgot to promote the question to deliberation and reconsider the trade-off.

Another wave of grief and shame washed over Harry, and for a time he walked on in the silence of the last voice, other voices being happy enough to fill the gap.

After what was at least several miles, and many grey thoughts, the stone tunnel ended.

The Dark Lord climbed up stone steps, and Harry followed after.

The two of them came into a dark, dank stone building. Dirty old stone doors swung open without being touched.

Before them lay marble slabs, rising up from bare ground, upon them names and dates. The tombstones were scattered in nothing like neat rows, and the rest of the graveyard ran wild.

The moon above was over three-quarters full, already seeming bright with night not fully fallen.

Harry had stopped walking upon seeing the graveyard. There was a blaring alarm in his brain saying to be anywhere other than here, but there weren’t any options for accomplishing that. So that alarm cried unanswered, even as behind Harry the stone doors of the mausoleum swung shut again and sealed themselves.

The Dark Lord came into the centre of the scattered graveyard. He stopped walking, and waved his wand above his head in a small circle.

There was a rumbling sound, and smoothly from the ground rose an altar, at least two metres wide and of black stone carved with grey sigils. And then surrounding the altar groaned up six dark-marble obelisks, regularly spaced, gleaming darkly beneath the fading twilight sky.

The unanswerable alarm in Harry’s brain grew louder.

‘This,’ said the Dark Lord in Professor Quirrell’s cadences, ‘is a workspace I made for myself, convenient to either Hogwarts or Hogsmeade.’ The Dark Lord flourished a hand at the altar. ‘That is where Miss Granger shall revive, and also where I shall be reborn into my true body. I shall remake myself first, of course. Magicss to revive girl-child eassier with true body.’ A strange snakish laughter accompanied these words. ‘Rest assured that though some aspects of girl-child’s resurrection shall be what others consider Dark, girl-child will not be harmed or made ugly by it. Shall still look like herself, mind shall be her own, nor shall I or mine harm her after.’

Harry’s tongue was dry and his mind was having trouble functioning. ‘Please, Professor, would you say in Parseltongue what is your real purpose in resurrecting Miss Granger?’

‘To restore to you girl-child friend’s counsel and restraint. To make sure she is part of the world for you to care about. That, boy, is truly the greater part of the reason I am doing this deed.’ Again snakish laughter accompanied these words, conveying sardonic awareness of some vast irony.

A small spark of hope kindled inside Harry, alongside the much greater note of confusion, and the fear that a perfect Occlumens could indeed lie in Parseltongue. Harry didn’t understand why the Dark Lord was doing this, if the next step was just to kill the Boy-Who-Lived or enslave him …

Maybe he’d just never understood Professor Quirrell at all, maybe somehow Harry’s model of Tom Riddle was just that wrong … maybe the Boy-Who-Lived would be Obliviated of the last day and dropped off somewhere with a confused Hermione Granger, while Lord Voldemort went on to conquer the world … ?

Hope flared up in Harry, but it was a confused hope that didn’t make any sense. It didn’t square with the Dark Lord who had mocked Dumbledore and laughed at his defeat. Harry couldn’t come up with any consistent account of Professor Quirrell’s motives that allowed for something like that.

I do not know what is meant to happen next.

The Dark Lord had moved forward to the altar. He knelt there, and seemed to reach deep into the stone of the altar itself, drawing forth a vial of liquid that looked black in the fading twilight.

When the Dark Lord spoke again his voice was clipped and precise. ‘Blood, blood, blood so wisely hidden,’ said the Dark Lord.

And the obelisks surrounding the altar began to speak, voices like a chanting chorus coming from the motionless stones, cadences older than Latin.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi.

The obelisks’ chant echoed after the end of each line, as if they were speaking out of synchrony with each other. The blood was poured from the vial, and it seemed to catch and hang over the altar, slowly expanding through the air, taking on a shape.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi (emoi).

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi (emoi).

A tall form rested upon the altar, and even in the dimming twilight it looked too pale.

The Defence Professor reached his hand into his robe, and drew forth a small irregular chunk of red glass.

He placed that upon the tall pale body.

The Stone stayed there for a time, minutes at least. The irregular chunk of red glass did not glow, or flash, or give any other indication of power.

Then the Stone moved, just a little, turning slightly upon the body.

The Defence Professor took back the Stone into his robes, and prodded the tall form that lay motionless upon the altar, touching the eyes with his fingers, poking the chest with his wand.

He threw back his head, then, and laughed.

‘Incredible,’ said the Dark Lord, in the voice of the Defence Professor that Harry had known. ‘Fixed, it is fixed in form! A mere construct sustained by magic, become the true substance at the Stone’s touch! And yet I sensed nothing! Nothing! I feared I had been deceived, that I had obtained a false Stone, but the substance proves true to my every test!’ The Defence Professor tucked the red glass back into his robes. ‘That is eldritch even by my standards, I admit.’

Then the Defence Professor walked around the altar, five times he walked around it, chanting something too low for Harry to hear.

The Dark Lord placed his wand in the hand of the figure lying on the altar.

He placed his hands, both of them, over the body’s forehead.

The Dark Lord spoke. ‘Fal. Tor. Pan.’

Without any warning there was a flash like lightning that lit up the entire graveyard, and Harry staggered back a step, his hands involuntarily going to his forehead. It felt as if he had been shot there, or a wasp stung him, upon his scar.

The Defence Professor collapsed.

And the too-tall figure sat up upon the altar.

It swung around smoothly, and stood tall upon the ground, at least a head higher than a normal man. The form’s limbs were lean and pale, little-muscled but giving an impression of terrible strength.

Harry took another staggering step back, his hands still clasped to his scar. Though the distance between them was wide, Harry felt a sense of terrifying apprehension in the air, as though the sense of doom had always been been out of focus and had now clarified, concentrated into a physical pain in the scar on Harry’s forehead.

Was that what Voldemort was supposed to look like? The nose looked like, it looked like it had malfunctioned during the resurrection process –

The too-tall figure threw back his head and laughed, raising his hands and wand to look at them. The left hand opened wide and it was like a pale half-spider with four over-long legs, fingers caressing the wand held in the other hand. Leaves stirred up from the graveyard, approaching to dance around the too-tall figure, surrounding him and clothing him, reforming into a high-necked shirt and flowing robes; and Lord Voldemort was laughing. Exactly the mirthless laughter that Harry remembered coming from his own throat inside the Dementor’s nightmare, precise in tone and timbre.

Red eyes gleamed beneath the fading twilight, their pupils slitted like a cat’s.

The form that Voldemort had abandoned raised itself, quivering, from the ground; and in a voice that Harry could barely hear, Quirinus Quirrell gasped, ‘Free – oh, free –’

‘Stupefy,’ said the high cold voice of Voldemort, and Quirinus Quirrell was blasted down into the ground; then, with a wave of Voldemort’s other hand, Quirinus Quirrell was picked up and flung away from the altar.

Voldemort walked away from the altar, then turned and looked at Harry; and the pain in Harry’s scar flared at it.

‘Frightened, child?’ Voldemort hissed, like there was an undercurrent of Parseltongue even to the Dark Lord’s human speech. ‘Good. Place the girl on the altar, and break your Transfiguration. Iss time for me to revive her.’

Is this really going to happen? Are we really going to do this?

Harry swallowed, mastering his fear through that note of impossible hope amid the confusion, and walked over to the altar. Then Harry took off his left shoe, and his left sock, and took off the toe-ring that was Hermione Granger, the Transfigured shape identical to the toe-ring that had been given Harry as an emergency portkey. There was a twinge of regret in Harry for not having the real portkey now, but only a twinge; an inner-circle Death Eater would routinely put up boundaries against portkeys, if Severus had been right. Behind Harry, Voldemort laughed again in what sounded like surprised appreciation.

‘I need my wand to Finite her,’ Harry said aloud.

‘You do not.’ High the voice and cruel. ‘You learned to sustain a Transfiguration by touch alone, without further use of the wand. You can likewise break your own Transfiguration wandlessly, by commanding your sustaining magic to drain away. Do so now.’

Harry swallowed, and touched the toe-ring. He had to try three times, and clear his mind, before he could push his magic out of the toe-ring, as before he had learned to make a tiny stream of magic flow in.

The breaking of the spell went much more slowly that way than a Finite Incantatem, almost like the sped-up reverse of watching something being Transfigured. The toe-ring distorted, flowing together, expanding. Colours changed, textures changed.

Two-thirds of a dead girl lay strewn across the altar, on her side with one arm falling off the altar’s edge, the position in which the reversion had chanced to place her. No blood flowed now from the chewed stumps of her thighs. The dead girl wore Hermione Granger’s face, but twisted and pale. It was as Harry had seen before in the hospital’s back room, the image burned into his brain during thirty long minutes of Transfiguration, the image he had reproduced during four even longer hours to Transfigure the decoy. The dead girl was naked, for her clothes were not part of her, and had not been Transfigured.

The sight brought back flashbacks, of the hours spent in the infirmary room, of the nightmares afterwards, all of which Harry suppressed.

‘Go back,’ said Voldemort’s high voice. ‘This is my work, now.’

Harry swallowed, and retreated from the altar, to the mouth of the long corridor where he’d stood before. ‘Her body is, should be, around five Celsius, I cooled her so, so there wouldn’t be brain damage –’ Harry’s own voice was wavering in pitch. Is he really going to do this? Really? There had to be a catch and Harry just couldn’t see it. Voldemort had said that neither he nor any of his would harm Hermione, that her body and mind would be her own – why?

Voldemort walked forth to the altar once more, orienting the body before him with a wave of his hand to lie straight across the altar. The Dark Lord spoke with high monotone precision, ‘Flesh, flesh, flesh so wisely hidden.’

The obelisks began chanting once more.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma hou emoi (emoi).

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma hou emoi (emoi).

New flesh flowed out of the stumps of the girl’s thighs, creeping forward like an ooze and solidifying.

The obelisks ceased chanting. A complete form lay naked upon the altar.

It didn’t look like Hermione. A Hermione Granger should be standing up and talking, she should have her Hogwarts uniform.

Voldemort raised a hand, then hissed, as though in annoyance. With a violent gesture, the robes around Quirinus Quirrell’s sleeping from were torn in half, his purple-and-green tie shredded, and his suit-jacket drawn from him to where Voldemort stood. Some part of Harry flinched, as if seeing the Dark Lord Voldemort attacking Professor Quirrell.

Voldemort plunged his hand deliberately into the suit jacket, which jerked as though something were being broken; then Voldemort shook out the suit jacket onto the ground beside him, emptying out the contents. Harry’s pouch fell from it, and his Time-Turner, and a broomstick, and Voldemort’s gun, and the Cloak, and a number of amulets and rings and stranger devices that Harry did not recognize.

And finally a chunk of red glass, which was laid upon Hermione Granger’s form, and allowed to stay there for a time.

Minutes passed. The Dark Lord donned an amulet from the heap of things beside the altar; also from the heap, Voldemort took four short wooden rods with straps upon them, and reached beneath his robes to attach them, it looked like they went on his upper arms and upper thighs. The Dark Lord rose into the air, moved left, right, up and down, seeming to wobble slightly at first; then his flight stabilized.

The chunk of red glass turned, slightly.

The Dark Lord Voldemort floated to the ground, and prodded Hermione Granger’s body with his wand.

‘There is an obstacle,’ hissed Voldemort.

In Harry’s mind the expectation of betrayal or other failure had already been so strong that the confirmation came only as a dull shock, not a sharp one. ‘What obstacle?’

‘Girl’s body is restored. Substance is repaired. But not magic, or life … this is body of dead Muggle.’ Voldemort turned from the altar, began to pace. ‘The full ritual would solve this. But that would require time … time and the blood of Granger’s enemy, and I do not think Draco Malfoy still qualifies, nor can I take my own blood unwillingly … foolish.’ Voldemort’s voice was a lower hiss. ‘Foolish, I should have foreseen this, and prepared. Her brain might awaken with an electrical shock, I know that much of Muggle medicine … but would her magic return to her? That I do not know, and I suspect if she awakens as a Muggle she will be a Muggle forever. Still, I can think of nothing better.’ The Dark Lord raised his wand –

‘Wait!’ Harry blurted, feeling hope return. She needs a spark of life and magic, just a spark to get her started …

Voldemort turned and looked at him. The snakelike face showed some slight degree of surprise.

‘Think I have something that might work,’ Harry hissed. ‘Needs wand. Have no intentions to use it against you.’ Harry said nothing about expecting his intentions wouldn’t change; he’d simply blurted out the idea fast enough that he hadn’t formed any specific intentions yet.

‘This,’ Voldemort hissed, ‘I desire to see.’ The Dark Lord reached into the heap of things by the altar, and picked up the wrapped form of Harry’s wand. It was thrown, gliding through the air and then dropping at Harry’s feet; and then the Dark Lord floated back, the heap of things moving smoothly backwards with him.

Harry unwrapped his wand, and moved forward.

We have our wand back, that’s step one, said the last voice, the voice of hope.

No part of Harry had any idea what step two might be, but it was still step one accomplished.

And Harry stood before the reformed body of Hermione Granger, who was still naked and dead, on a twilight-lit stone altar.

‘Lord Voldemort,’ Harry said, ‘I beg you, please give her some clothes. It might help me do this.’

‘Granted,’ hissed Voldemort. The pain in Harry’s scar flared as the naked girl’s body lifted into the air, then flared again as dead leaves danced around her and she was clothed in the seeming of a Hogwarts uniform, though the trim was red instead of blue. Hermione Granger’s hands folded over her chest, her legs straightened, and her body drifted back down.

Harry looked at her.

Focused on her, now that she looked human again.

She looks like she is sleeping, not dead. It took a conscious effort to look for breathing, fail to see it, and make the deduction. So far as naked perception was concerned … Hermione might as well be alive, right now.

That Hermione Granger would not approve of this situation, taken as a whole, seemed beyond question. But it didn’t mean that she would rather stay dead than be alive, other things being equal, though they might not be.

Because you wish to live, because my best guess is that you would wish to live …

Harry reached out his shaking left hand, and touched Hermione’s forehead. It was warm now, not the chill of five degrees Celsius; either Voldemort had increased her body temperature to normal, or the magic of the ritual had done it automatically. Which meant that Hermione’s brain was currently warm and without oxygen, come to think.

That did it, the sense of urgency rising in him.

Harry’s feet assumed the stance, his wand swung up to point at Hermione Granger’s dead body. The only thing wrong with Hermione’s body was that it was dead; everything else about that body was right, only one thing needed changing.

You don’t belong here, death.

‘Expecto,’ Harry shouted, feeling the magic and the life rise up into the Patronus Charm that was fuelled by both, ‘Patronum!’

The girl in the Hogwarts uniform was surrounded by a blazing aura of silver fire, as the Patronus was born inside her.

Harry staggered, as he felt a dip, a bite. Intuition or Tom Riddle’s memory told Harry that the life and magic that had just flowed into Hermione would never return to him, either one. It hadn’t been all his life or all his magic, not by a long shot, there hadn’t been time to expend that much, but whatever he’d just expended was gone forever.

And Hermione Granger was breathing, just like she was sleeping, rhythmic inhalations and exhalations. The twilight sky had dimmed further, and Harry could not see if colour was returning to her, but it should have been, it certainly should have been. She looked to be sleeping peacefully, and it wasn’t because being dead looked like sleeping, it was because she was asleep and her body was fine and nothing was hurting her while she slept.

Some part of Harry, that had somehow managed not to speak up earlier, quietly pointed out that they were still in a graveyard, the recently victorious Lord Voldemort was still in control of the situation, and that his guess about Hermione wanting to be alive was just a guess.

Harry was still smiling, as he slowly lowered his wand. The celebratory fireworks going off inside his mind were restrained, Harry wasn’t screaming and running around in little circles like Professor Flitwick, but that –

That –

That, Harry said aloud inside his mind, That is what I call Step Two.

‘Interesting,’ said the cold high voice. ‘Your Patronus draws upon your life as well as your magic … I guessed that much, for it was too powerful for a first-year to fuel with magic alone. And yet there must be more to the puzzle, since not just any life-fuelled spell would have done … was your happy thought the image of her returning to life? Was that all it took?’ Lord Voldemort was again toying with his wand, a dark interest in those red-slitted eyes. ‘I suspect I will feel quite stupid when I finally comprehend that spell, someday in my eternity. Now step away from the girl. There iss more work I intend to do, to give her besst chance of continued life.’

Harry stepped back, reluctantly, the sense of tension starting to return to him. He almost tripped over one haphazard grave marker, as the Dark Lord continued to walk forward.

Standing before the altar, the Dark Lord laid one finger upon Hermione Granger’s forehead.

Then the Dark Lord tapped his finger upon Hermione Granger’s forehead, and said, in a voice so low Harry almost did not hear, ‘Requiescus.’

Voldemort waved his hand at an obelisk, which began to rotate, turning itself to lay flat upon the ground, pointing outward. ‘Fascinating indeed,’ Voldemort hissed. ‘She is alive, and magical, and not another Tom Riddle as I feared you might have made her.’

The tension was rising again in Harry. He’d put his wand away into the back belt of his trousers, he did not want to remind Voldemort that he still had the wand on him. ‘What are you doing to her now?’

Another obelisk turned, lay flat upon the ground. ‘There is old, lost ritual to sacrifice magical creature, transfer magical nature to subject. Limitations are great. Transfer is temporary, only few hours. Subject sometimes dies when transfer wears off. But Stone will make permanent.’

Four obelisks lay flat upon the ground, evenly spaced; the other two obelisks had been floated away.

Voldemort began to reach into his own mouth, checked himself, hissed with annoyance again. He gestured at the sleeping mouth of Quirinus Quirrell, and from Quirrell’s mouth floated up two teeth, almost invisible in the falling night. One of these went to the pile of items, the other floated to before the altar.

Moments later, Harry cried out and took a step back.

Huge and misshapen, lumpy skin, legs thick as tree-trunks, a small head that looked like a coconut perched upon a boulder.

A mountain troll stood within the circle of obelisks, motionless as though asleep while standing.

‘What are you doing?’

Voldemort’s mouth was stretched in a wide smile; it looked horrible on him, like his face had too many teeth. ‘Shall sacrifice my fallback weapon, and girl-child shall gain troll’s power of regeneration. Transfiguration sickness is nothing before that, if perchance it was not fixed by previous ritual. And no knife shall slay girl-child, nor cutting curse, nor sickness take her.’

‘Why – why are you doing this?’ Harry’s voice shook.

‘Have not the tiniest intention of letting girl-child die again, after going to such lengths to resurrect her.’

Harry swallowed. ‘I’m very confused.’ Was Voldemort practising being nice? This hypothesis did not seem like a sufficient explanation.

‘Stay well back,’ Voldemort said coldly. ‘This ritual is Darker than the last.’ The Dark Lord began a new chant, softer syllables that seemed to seethe through the air like living things; and Harry, feeling a new surge of apprehension, stepped backwards.

Then Harry cried aloud, as pain flared again within his scar. The mountain troll crumbled in on itself, becoming ashes hanging in the air, then dust, and then the dust seemed to blow away without going anywhere; it was gone.

Hermione Granger slept on peacefully, whatever spell of repose Voldemort had cast on her being sufficient to the task.

‘Um,’ Harry said in a small voice. ‘Did it work?’

‘Diffindo.’

Harry stepped forward with a choked yell, and then halted, both as the stupidity of his motion caught up with him, and as the sudden cut that the Severing Charm had opened on Hermione’s leg closed almost as quickly as it had been made. In seconds there was only a light stain of blood on the surrounding flesh.

The Stone was laid again on Hermione, and after a time it turned. Voldemort laughed once more, as he passed his hand over her. ‘Marvellous.’

Then another tiny tooth was floating within the circle of obelisks; and an instant later, a unicorn stood where the troll had stood before, eyes dull and head lowered.

‘What?’ Harry said. ‘Why a unicorn?’

‘Power of unicorn’s blood to preserve life makes excellent combination with troll’s healing. Only Fiendfyre and Killing Curse shall girl-child fear, from this day.’ A flicker of snakish laughter. ‘Besides, had spare unicorn left over, might as well use.’

‘Unicorn’s blood has side effects-’

‘That is only when power of unicorn’s blood is stolen by another. This spell will make power of unicorn belong inside girl-child, as if she was always born that way.’

The grim chant and its seething words began again.

Harry watched, not understanding in the slightest.

Forget understanding, what am I seeing?

I’m seeing the Dark Lord Voldemort going to enormous lengths to resurrect Hermione Granger and keep her alive. It’s like he thinks that his own life depends on Hermione Granger being alive, somehow.

The confused parts of Harry looked around for a procedure to follow. Make a prediction based on your best current hypothesis was the first thought that came to mind, but it didn’t seem to lead anywhere. The plot of the story wasn’t going how it ought to, after the villain had won.

Again the blaze of pain in his scar, like a blow to Harry’s forehead. The unicorn swayed, and then disintegrated as the troll had done.

The Dark Lord laid the Stone upon Hermione’s form once more, clasping her hands around it.

Voldemort watched the unremarkable process for a time, then turned while the Stone still laid on her, making a high humming sound in his throat. ‘Ah, yes,’ hissed Voldemort. ‘That would be most appropriate. Do you still have the diary I gave you, boy? The diary of the famous scientist?’

Harry’s brain took a moment to place what Voldemort was talking about. It had been in Mary’s Room, in Mary’s Place, in October, that precious gift from a friend. The thought should have triggered a wave of awful sadness, for the Professor Quirrell that had been lost or never real; but there had been enough of that emotion already, and his brain had set it aside for now.

‘Yes,’ Harry said aloud. ‘I think it’s in my pouch, can I check?’ Harry knew it was in the pouch. He’d loaded it up with everything that he might possibly conceivably need, that he owned or had bought; everything that could have been a quest item.

From the heap of items by the altar, Harry’s mokeskin pouch was drawn out, tossed to Harry’s feet.

‘Roger Bacon’s diary,’ Harry said as he reached in a hand, and the diary appeared. Professor Quirrell had said that the diary would emerge unscathed from a fire, so Harry threw it toward Voldemort’s altar. Harry did not wince; there were more important things to worry about than polite treatment of books, even that one.

Voldemort picked up the diary, examining it, appearing quite absorbed.

Harry, as quietly and unobtrusively as he could, attached the pouch to his belt loop in back, where it wouldn’t be visible, near where Harry had put his wand.

Step three, the pouch.

‘Yes,’ Voldemort hissed as he flipped pages of the diary, ‘this will do quite well.’ The Stone moved slightly, and the Dark Lord’s other hand stored the Stone again within his robes.

‘What was your hidden purpose behind the diary?’ Harry said when the pouch was attached to his belt, and he’d put both of his empty hands where Voldemort could see them again. ‘I tried translating a little at the beginning, but it was going slowly –’ Actually, it had been excruciatingly slow and Harry had found other priorities.

‘Diary was exactly what it seemed, a gift meant to seduce you to my side.’ Voldemort made intricate gestures in the air with his wand, not even looking at what his hand was doing, as he held the diary in his other hand. For a moment Harry thought he could see a trail of darknes in the air, but the moonlight was too faint for certainty. ‘And now, my dear boy,’ Voldemort’s high voice was laced with grim amusement, as his wand briefly tapped Hermione Granger’s forehead with a casual gesture, ‘I make this diary into a far more precious gift, a sign of how much wisdom I have learned from you. For I would never want you to be deprived of Hermione Granger’s counsel and restraint, not ever while the stars yet live. Avadakedavra.’

The green bolt of the Killing Curse blazed out faster than Harry could possibly have cast the Patronus Charm, faster than he could possibly have moved, it was already over even as Harry cried out and went for his wand.

Quirinus Quirrell’s unconscious body did not even jerk, in death. The green light struck into it without other sign.

Darkness glowed in the air, anti-light in the trails that Voldemort had made before, and the Diary of Roger Bacon darkened as though corruption were creeping over it, even as a shiver appeared in the air around Hermione Granger’s form.

The pain in Harry’s scar flared overwhelmingly, like a brand driven into his forehead, it sent Harry dodging unthinkingly to one side as Tom Riddle’s reflexes took over.

And Voldemort was also screaming, shrieking as he dropped the diary to the ground, holding his own head and screaming.

Chance –

The last voice of hope said that, as Harry tried frantically to think, to understand. There wasn’t any point in trying to kill Voldemort now, it might only annoy him, weapons couldn’t kill him while any of his hundreds of horcruxes remained –

But it still seemed worth it to temporarily discarnate Voldemort, take the Stone and Hermione and run.

Harry’s right hand had already taken his wand. His left hand went around to his back, reached awkwardly into his pouch, began to make a silent sign, three English letters.

‘No!’ cried Voldemort. He’d dropped his hands from his head, was staring at Hermione’s body as though bewildered. ‘No, no!’

The item came up from Harry’s pouch into his hand, and Harry began to step forward as smoothly as he could, diminishing the range between them to what his brief trials had shown was doable.

‘My great creation –’ gasped Voldemort. His voice was high, sounding panicked. ‘Two different spirits cannot exist in the same world – it is gone, it is severed! A horcrux, I must make a horcrux at once –’ Voldemort’s gaze fell on Hermione Granger’s still-sleeping form, and he began to raise his wand in the air, executing the same gestures as before.

Harry raised his gun and pulled the trigger three times.

Even as Harry had raised the gun, he’d known he was making a mistake, his forebrain saw it and tried to stop his hand, but somehow the sick certainty didn’t propagate fast enough to prevent his finger from pulling the trigger –

The echo of the shots died away within the graveyard.

A fraction of a second before Harry had pulled the trigger, Voldemort had jabbed his wand downward, and a wide wall of dirt had shot up between them from the graveyard earth, intercepting all three bullets.

An instant after that, pain flared in Harry’s scar, a crawling feeling came close to his skin; and then Harry’s pouch, clothes, gun, everything except his wand disappeared, leaving him naked but for the wand still in his right hand, and the glasses he’d Charmed to stick to his nose. The steel ring upon his left pinky finger was yanked off hard enough to scrape skin, taking the Transfigured jewel with it.

‘That,’ said the voice of Voldemort from behind the dirt wall, ‘was absolutely predictable. Do you really think I would shout it aloud for you to hear, if my immortality were disrupted? Really, stupid child? Lower your wand, do not raise it up again at any time, or you die upon the spot.’

Harry swallowed, and pointed his wand downward. ‘You would have been disappointed in me,’ Harry said, his own voice now unusually high, ‘if I’d missed an opportunity like that, I mean.’ There was no time to think, and Harry’s mouth was operating on autopilot for trying to placate evil overlords that might have paternal feelings for you and whom you’d just failed to assassinate.

Voldemort stepped around from behind the dirt wall, smiling that horrible smile that seemed to contain too many teeth. ‘I promised not to raise my hand or wand against you, child, if you did not raise your hand or wand against me.’

‘I used bullets,’ Harry said, his voice still high. ‘That’s not a fist or a spell.’

‘My curse thinks differently. That is the puzzle piece that you missed. Did you think I would leave the peace between us to mere fortune? Before I created you, I invoked a curse upon myself and all other Tom Riddles who would descend from me. A curse to enforce that none of us would threaten the others’ immortality, so long as the other made no attempt upon our own. Typical of that ridiculous fiasco, the curse seems to have ended up binding me, but taking no hold upon the infant with his self so lost.’ A low, lethal chuckle. ‘But you tried to end my true life just then, stupid child. Now curse is lifted, and I may kill you any time I wish.’

‘I see,’ Harry said. He did see; that was why Voldemort had told him about his horcrux system in the first place, just to set up the moment when Harry knowingly tried to violate his immortality. Harry’s mind was frantically churning through options, none of which seemed helpful. His pouch, his clothes, Harry saw by the moonlight that they all now lay in another heap by the altar, out of reach. ‘And now you kill me?’ Harry still had his wand, presumably the Dark Lord couldn’t cast his own magic on that, or his glasses, because of the disharmony. Cast my own spell first? No, Voldemort just jabs his wand downward to make another shield, then shoots me – what else is there? What else?

‘Still a fool. If no further matters remained between us, I would already have killed you.’ The dirt wall crumbled at another gesture of the wand, and Voldemort moved smoothly back toward the heap of items by the altar. The Dark Lord stretched out a hand, and the diary of Roger Bacon flew to him. ‘This is, indeed, horcrux of girl-child, my superior version.’ In his other hand appeared a parchment. ‘This is ritual for resurrecting her, if it must be done again. Instructions are honest, no traps. Remember that girl-child’s spirit cannot float free like ghost, Resurrection Stone is my horcrux, not hers. Do not lose her horcrux, or her spirit may be trapped within it.’ Voldemort reached down, picked up Harry’s pouch, fed both the diary and the parchment into it. ‘Remember that, in case something goes wrong with next moves.’

‘I don’t understand what is happening,’ Harry said. There was nothing else left. ‘Please explain to me.’

The Dark Lord was now regarding Harry with a grim look. ‘When girl-child died, was in company of school’s Seer, heard prophecy spoken that you would become force of vast destruction. You would become threat beyond imagination, beyond apocalypse. That is why I went to such lengths to undo my killing of girl-child, keep it undone.’

‘Are,’ what ‘are you sure,’ what.

‘Dare not say specifics to you. Prophecy I heard of myself led me to fulfill it. Have not forgotten that disaster.’ Voldemort backed further away from Harry, red slitted eyes fixed upon the Boy-Who-Lived, gun unwavering in the left hand. ‘All this, all I have done, is to smash that destiny at every point of intervention. If some fate makes me fail in what comes next, idiot-child of foretold destruction, then you must kill yourself to save girl-child. Else all you claim to value dies by your own hand.’

‘I,’ Harry’s voice went up an octave, ‘I,’ another octave, ‘I really really wouldn’t do that, seriously!’

‘Silence, fool. Remain silent unless given leave by me to speak. Keep your wand pointed down and do not raise it unless told. Else you die upon the spot, and mark that I said that in Parseltongue.’ Voldemort reached into the altar again.

For a second Harry’s mind couldn’t process what he was seeing, and then he saw that Voldemort was holding a human arm, severed near the shoulder; it seemed too thin, that arm.

The Dark Lord pressed his wand to the flesh above the severed arm’s elbow, and the fingers twitched, twitched like they were alive; by dim moonlight Harry saw a darker mark appear on that flesh, just above the elbow.

Seconds later the first hooded figure appeared inside the graveyard with the popping sound of an Apparition. A moment after that came another pop, and then another.

The hooded figures wore silver skull masks, and moonlight fled from the robes beneath them.

‘Master!’ cried one of the black robes, the third to arrive. The voice was of peculiar timbre, from behind the silver skull mask. ‘Master – it has been so long – we had lost hope –’

‘Silence!’ shouted the high voice of the Dark Lord Voldemort. Every trace of Professor Quirrell was now gone from the too-tall figure. ‘Train your wand upon the Boy-Who-Lived, and watch him! Do not be distracted, not by anything! Stun him at once if he moves, if he begins to speak!’

More pops. Between graves, behind a tree, in all the shadowy spaces, more black robes were Apparating, all hooded and masked. Some of them voiced exclamations of joy, many of those sounding rather forced; others moved forwards as though to greet their Master. Voldemort gave them all the same instruction, except that some were commanded to Cruciate Harry Potter if he moved, others to restrain the Boy-Who-Lived if he moved, others told to fire hexes and curses, others told to cancel his magic.

Thirty-seven pops, Harry counted before the black robes and skull masks seemed to stop arriving.

All of them were now holding their wands pointed at Harry, aligned in a semicircle before him, where they wouldn’t get into each other’s lines of fire.

Harry continued pointing his wand downward, insofar as he had been told that, if he tried to raise it, he would die. He remained silent, insofar as he had been told that if he tried to speak, he would die. He tried not to shiver in the falling night temperatures, for he was naked, and it was getting colder.

You know, said the last voice within Harry, the voice of hope, I think this is getting pretty bad even by my standards.

Shut Up and Do The Impossible

The gibbous moon riding higher in the cloudless sky, the stars and wash of the Milky Way visible in all their majesty within the darkness, all these shone down upon the graveyard to bear witness from their unimaginable distances.

In the instant when Harry had realised there was no way at all left to save everyone, his mind’s voices had fallen away, become one, a single purpose taking up every fraction of his mind.

Fifty seconds.

Forty seconds.

Harry’s eyes tracked slowly across the air, until his gaze landed on the first Death Eater, the one closest to him.

Thirty seconds?

Twenty seconds?

‘Time’s almost up –’ hissed Voldemort.

‘I do know secrets you would like to know,’ Harry hissed. He didn’t look directly at the Dark Lord as he spoke. ‘But most valuable knowledge to you, I think, would be my ideas as to how world might be destroyed. Yet, to tell you such thoughts might lead to destruction of world. Do not know prophecy, but if there is prophecy, that makes it more than usually probable that any action I take might have that effect. Or to tell you such might prevent destruction of world, since you do seem motivated to avoid it. Not allowed to make such a decision myself. Would need to awaken and consult girl-child friend. Vow requires.’

There was a long pause. The Dark Lord, floating above and behind the curve of Death Eaters with levelled wands, began to laugh as Salazar Slytherin had thought a snake would laugh, cold amusement in the form of a hiss. ‘Do you know how to destroy world, then?’

‘Cannot deliberately try to imagine method. You might have way for servant to steal my thoughts. Vow prohibits. But suspect I could devise method, if girl-child said to try.’

Harry’s eyes drifted slowly to another Death Eater, and another.

More snakish laughter. ‘Clever. You have my compliments for thinking of such tactics. But no.’

‘Know it is annoying, but with world and your eternity at stake, would you not –’

‘Greater risk to world in introducing such complications, delaying your end. I will study Muggle sciences myself, think of all you might imagine. Now speak such secrets as you may tell me, or this ends.’

Slowly Harry’s vision tracked across the graveyard in careful arcs, ignoring the Dark Lord except as a floating blackness in his peripheral vision. His mouth went on speaking with only half his attention. ‘Have thought of idea you might not have considered, teacher. Your attempt to kill me might fail in certain specific way despite all your precautions, perhaps lead into my destroying world later. Would not ordinarily deem probable, but with prophecy at hand, may well be so.’

Voldemort went still, in the air. ‘How?’

‘Am not obligated to tell you.’

A cold anger began to seethe through the snakish reply. ‘Though I understand well your desperation and attempted cleverness, this begins to annoy me. I will not withhold from killing you, for that is still greater risk. To fail to tell me your thought risks destroying world. Speak!’

‘No. Vow does not obligate me to any positive action.’

The Dark Lord stared down at Harry Potter, who glanced up at the angry face only briefly before his eyes went back to the next Death Eater. Some of them were shifting their stances slightly, but they stood still, and said no words as they levelled their wands. The silver skull masks could not be read.

Then the Dark Lord began to chuckle again. ‘Survive your death, you think you might? No, child, my horcruxes are not linked to you also. I would know if they were. Or is there other reason you think you might survive beyond my ways of ensuring your death?’

Harry didn’t allow himself to be distracted. The repeated failures didn’t matter, they only led into the next action in the chain – but he still needed a next action –

‘Now speak a secret,’ the Dark Lord hissed, ‘or I –’

‘Life-eaters will pursue you always, hate you always, seek you out wherever you go, if what I have just done was successful, I have caused them to be set upon you! Guardian Charm secret will be beyond you for long time to come, perhaps forever! Best defense against life-eaters would die with me!’

‘This is starting to become sad …’ the Dark Lord’s voice trailed off. ‘Ah. I see. Life-eaters respond to expectations. You tell me I will be hunted, I expect to be hunted, they hunt me. Such is rare, but not unheard-of. Valuable secret, yes. Can see many uses.’ A cruel smile. ‘I shall allow you to select one person to be saved.’

‘Myself.’

‘Would tell you to die with dignity, but knowing myself, I know it for futility. You have wasted my kindly gift just then by annoying me, and I retract it. Any other secrets?’

‘Yes. Really interesting ones, too. Some you are unlikely to figure out on your own, not for very long time if ever. If I say I have told you all that do not risk world, will you not torment any of my friends or family? All of this speech started because you left me no way at all to save everyone.’

The Dark Lord stood still in the air for a long moment.

And Harry’s eyes went on tracking slowly across the graveyard, as his hand remained tight upon his wand.

In the instant when Harry had realized there was no way left to save everyone –

He couldn’t speak any incantation in English. But Transfiguration was wordless.

There was no material in contact with his wand’s end except air, which couldn’t be Transfigured. But Voldemort didn’t know about partial Transfiguration, which Harry could use to Transfigure a tiny bit of the material from his wand itself.

‘You’re stalling,’ the Dark Lord said. ‘Just to delay death? Or with other purpose?’

Harry said nothing, his other work slowing as his mind sought a continuation of the conversation that would work even against the Dark Lord’s will –

‘Speak and tell me purpose, or this ends now and your friends suffer for lifetimes!’

‘Lower Muggle weapon and do not point wand in my direction,’ Harry hissed, putting as much cold danger as he could into the snake’s voice. ‘Speak no commands to servants. I do possess capabilities of which you are ignorant. Can use one such capacity to cause huge explosion almost instantly, without speaking incantation. Slay your new body, all servants, Stone scattered to who knows where.’

At his current level of practise Harry could Transfigure one cubic millimetre as fast as he could apply his will and magic.

One cubic millimetre of antimatter.

It wasn’t a world-ending threat.

Voldemort could have been carved from stone. ‘You bluff, somehow.’

‘Not bluffing. Speaking in snaketalk, I tell you, I can do it almost instantly, before any spell can be cast at me, I think. You know very little of science as yet. Power I would command is stronger than process that fuels stars.’

‘Vow will stop you,’ hissed Voldemort. ‘You cannot risk world. Take no risks, none, with clever ideas!’

‘Would not risk world. I estimated size of explosion, nowhere near that large.’

‘You do NOT know, fool! Cannot be SURE!‘ Voldemort’s hiss was climbing higher.

‘I am reasonably certain. Vow will not stop me.’

There was an increasing fury in Voldemort’s expression, and yet his hiss carried a tinge of fear. ‘I shall wreak pain beyond imagining on all you care for –’

‘Shut up. I disregard all such threats now, as theory of games says I should. Only reason you make threats is that you expect me to respond.’ That, too, Harry had truly understood in the last extremity. ‘Offer me something I want, teacher. For your new body, for your continued holding of Stone, for lives of your servants.’

Harry’s mouth was running on automatic, his real attention elsewhere.

Beneath the moonlight glints a tiny fragment of silver, a fraction of a line …

From a tiny spot on the end of Harry’s wand, a cubic millimetre of anchor, stretched out a thin line of Transfigured spider-silk. It would have broken at once, if tested; it would have gone unremarked, if any had noticed its glint. Less than a tenth of a millimetre in cross-section, the tiny shape represented by the extended line of spider-silk was something Harry could Transfigure swiftly, ten centimetres of length to a cubic millimetre of total volume; and Harry could Transfigure a cubic millimetre in a fraction of a second. He was forcing the Transfiguration outward, extending it through the air as fast as he could without risking the transformation.

The tracing line of spider-silk looped around a Death Eater’s hood at neck level, returned to the pattern of threads.

Voldemort’s face was now impassive. ‘You must not leave here alive. Sensible people called good would also agree, this I tell you in snake’s speech. But all your friends I will treat kindly and protect under my reign, if you agree to die now as good person should.’

The last Death Eater was looped. The pattern of spider-silk was complete. The web had been drawn with loops around all the Death Eater’s necks. The ends of those loops had been anchored to a central circle; and that central circle in turn had three threads stretching across its centre. The entire pattern still touching the anchor-line stretching out of Harry’s wand.

Over the next seconds, those near-invisible threads of reflected moonlight turned black.

Filaments narrower, stronger, and sharper than steel wire; braided carbon nanotubes, each individual tube all a single molecule.

Harry hissed, ‘Want you to also promise to treat nations kindly under your rule. Will not accept less.’

Voldemort hovered still in the air, snake-face showing a dawning fury.

The last two threads stretched out from the dark pattern, black threads already in the form of nanotubes. They moved lightly through the air toward the Dark Lord himself, toward the sleeve just above Voldemort’s left hand that held the gun, toward the sleeve above the right hand that held the yew wand, threads placed high at first to give them time to drift slowly downward through the air. The threads looped around, went over themselves, tied slippable knots. Began to tighten, coming closer to the sleeve, as Harry Transfigured them shorter –

Harry felt the tickle of Voldemort’s power beginning to touch his own in the back of his mind; at the same time the Dark Lord’s eyes widened, his mouth opened.

And Harry Transfigured the black threads stretching across the black pattern’s centre to a quarter their previous size, shrinking the circle, yanking hard on everything attached, tightening loops.

(Black robes, falling.)

Harry wasn’t looking there, he didn’t see the falling masks, the blood, in the back of his mind he felt some explosions of magic like he’d felt when Hermione died but he ignored them, Harry’s eyes only saw the Dark Lord’s hands and wand and gun dropping downward, and then Harry’s wand was rising, pointing –

Harry screamed, ‘Stuporfy!’

The red bolt the colour of the Stunning Hex winged toward Voldemort, blazing across the graveyard almost faster than the eye could see.

Without any hesitation despite his wounds the Dark Lord jerked down and right through the air.

And the red bolt from Professor Flitwick’s secret Swerving Stunner turned in mid-air and slammed into Voldemort.

The pain that flashed through Harry’s scar was searing, it made him cry out and a red haze appear across his vision; despite everything, Harry dropped his wand in pain and sheer fatigue.

As Harry let go of his wand, the pain began to clear –

Something like a fugue state had come over Harry’s mind. The absolute state had partially worn off him, partially stayed with him. Elements of his mind were numb, maybe deliberately numbed by some part that was smart enough to predict what would happen otherwise. What he’d just done –

The thought was shut off, making space for an awareness of other things.

Harry was standing in the middle of a haphazard graveyard, tombstones scattered without order.

By moonlight and starlight, it could be seen that black robes littered the ground, surrounded by textures that didn’t match the surrounding graveyard earth, wetness tinged red in the moonlight. Some heads had come loose from the surrounding hoods of the robes, revealing hair that was long or short, dark or bright, which was all that could be seen beneath the moon. The silver masks stayed on, making all the hair originate in skulls instead of human faces –

The thought was shut off, making space for awareness of other things.

A girl in a red-trimmed Hogwarts uniform slept upon an altar. Near the altar, Harry’s things lay in a heap.

Upon the ground lay a too-tall pale man of inhuman face, blood pouring from the stumps of his wrists.

As soon as the Dark Lord Voldemort awakens, he will destroy everything you love. Dumbledore is no longer there to stop him.

He cannot be imprisoned, for he can abandon his body at any time.

He cannot be killed permanently, not without destroying more than a hundred horcruxes, one of which is the Pioneer plaque.

Materials: One wand, you are allowed to point it and speak this time.

You have five minutes.

Solve.

Harry stumbled toward the altar, knelt at its side, and picked up his pouch.

He walked toward where Voldemort lay.

The sense of apprehension had diminished, after Voldemort had been hexed unconscious. Now, as Harry approached, it rose to a terrifying height, flaring also into pain in his scar.

Harry ignored the inner shriek. That had been the last memory of Tom Riddle seared into Harry’s brain, the last cognitive pattern to be transferred over into the infant baby before Tom Riddle had exploded: a sense of mounting horror and dismay associated with the resonance that had spun out of control. Harry knew the meaning of it now, that sense of apprehension, and that made it easier to disregard. He’d guessed that the effect of the resonance mostly hit the caster, with power proportional to the caster’s power, and the bet had paid off.

Harry looked upon Voldemort’s body, and breathed deeply – through his mouth, because coppery smells Harry was not thinking about were coming in through his nose.

Harry knelt by Voldemort’s side, took out his medical kit from his pouch, and placed a self-tightening tourniquet around the body’s left wrist, then another tourniquet about the right.

It felt wrong, showing Voldemort that concern. Some part of Harry was aware, in the back of his mind, that some number of people had just had something extremely bad happen to them. What would have been balance, what would have been justice, was if Voldemort had suffered the same fate without an instant’s more hesitation. What Harry was doing now felt like Batman showing more concern for the Joker than for the Joker’s victims; it felt like a comic book where the writers wrung their hands endlessly about the morality of killing the Big Named Villains while innocents went on dying in the background. To show more solicitousness for the head villain than his minions, to pay more attention to his fate than the fates of his lower-status followers, was a flaw in human nature.

So it felt wrong when Harry rose up from beside the body, the tourniquets having tightened upon Voldemort’s wrists; it felt like Harry was doing something ethically monstrous.

Even though any sane strategic thinking said that Voldemort’s body must not die. The soul he’d created for himself had to be anchored in this brain, it mustn’t be allowed to float free.

Harry stepped back, back from Voldemort’s unconscious body, breathing deeply through his mouth. He went to the pile of his things, to put on his robes and other items, starting with placing the Time-Turner around his throat once more, readying his own escape and return if that was required …

More than a hundred horcruxes.

That had been insane, there wasn’t any other word for it, a sign of Voldemort’s damaged thinking about death. A Muggle security expert would have called it fence-post security, like building a fence-post over a hundred metres high in the middle of the desert. Only a very obliging attacker would try to climb the fence-post. Anyone sensible would just walk around the fence-post, and making the fence-post even higher wouldn’t stop that.

Once you forgot to be scared of how impossible the problem was supposed to be, it wasn’t even difficult, not by comparison to the last one.

Neville’s parents, for example, had been Crucioed into permanent insanity. Two hundred advanced horcruxes wouldn’t prevent that insanity, they would all just echo the same damaged mind.

It would be an ethically justified use of the Cruciatus Curse, if that were the only way to stop Voldemort permanently. It would be justice, balance, it would show that the Joker’s life wasn’t worth more than his meanest henchman …

All Harry needed to do was cast the Patronus Charm, send it to … Alastor Moody? … and tell him to come here. Well, no, it was a pretty good guess the Patronus Charm wouldn’t work if it was cast with that intent. Maybe just resolve to tell Moody that, and use his Time-Turner once he was out of range of Voldemort’s wards.

And then Voldemort could be Crucioed into permanent insanity.

It wasn’t even the least merciful fate. That would have been throwing Voldemort’s wand into the pit at Azkaban, if the wand stayed connected to Voldemort’s life and magic no matter where his ghost tried to flee.

Harry turned to face where Voldemort lay. He walked forward, and continued to control his breathing, ignoring the burning feeling in his throat. Some part of him knew that Voldemort was also Professor Quirrell, even though his body now was different. Even though the shift of personality had been perfect and that meant that Professor Quirrell had been just another mask …

Though Voldemort hadn’t planned to kill Harry painfully. Hadn’t thought to strike Harry with his followers’ Cruciatus, when Harry was being annoying before. That meant something, when your opponent was Voldemort. Maybe he’d had some remaining shred of fellow-feeling for the other Tom Riddle after all.

… it would be wrong to take that into account.

Wouldn’t it?

Harry looked back up at the stars. Here below the atmosphere the stars twinkled, they were embedded in the false dome of the night sky, stretched out across the wash of the Milky Way that glowed like a long ribbon, as if they were all close enough that you could fly up to them on a broomstick and touch them.

What would they want him to do now at this juncture, the children’s children’s children?

The answer to that also felt obvious, if it wasn’t just the part of Harry that still cared about Professor Quirrell doing the real talking.

Harry had needed to do the thing he’d done, it had prevented greater evils, Harry couldn’t have stopped Voldemort if the Death Eaters had fired first. But that thing Harry had done wasn’t something that could be balanced by a not-necessary tragedy happening to one more sentient being, even if that being was Voldemort. It would just be one more element of the sorrows of ancient Earth so long ago.

The past was past. You did what you had to do, and you didn’t do one scrap of harm more than that. Not even to balance things out, and make it all symmetrical.

The children’s children’s children wouldn’t want Voldemort to die, even if his minions had. They wouldn’t want Voldemort to hurt, if it didn’t accomplish anything compared to him not hurting.

Harry breathed deeply, and let go of – not his hate – not quite his hate – he hadn’t been able to hate his creator even at the very end – but even so, Harry let go of something. Of the sense that he ought to hate Voldemort, that it was a hate he was obliged to feel, for the endless list of crimes that Voldemort had committed for no good reason, not even his own happiness …

It’s all right, the stars whispered down at him. It’s all right not to hate him. It doesn’t make you a bad person.

In the end, there was only one option he would take, and since Harry already knew that, there was no point agonizing about it. Whether it was the best option, only time would tell.

Harry breathed deeply, building up the magic inside himself. The spell he was going to cast didn’t need to be precise, but it was still one of the most powerful spells he’d mastered.

Harry thought again of how unjust it was that Voldemort could not die with his followers, felt the slight trace of coldness in his blood that came with thoughts of ruthlessness. And then Harry let it go, let it all drain away beneath the starlight, because his dark side had never been anything except an inherited pattern of cognition, just one more bad habit of thinking to break.

Instead Harry looked at Hermione’s breathing form atop the altar, and let the tears finally start from his eyes. What would become of Hermione now, what path she would choose after this, Harry couldn’t guess; but she would be there to have a choice, their friendship wouldn’t have destroyed her existence. He hadn’t realised how shaky his hope had been, until he’d noticed how surprised he’d been after the hope had come true. Sometimes things did go better than expected.

And Harry took that thought, too, and put it into the magic he was building.

The power he was storing up was vibrating in him, like his whole body was part of his wand, either Harry’s eyes were blurring or there was a luminous white quiver running over the holly. And Harry thought the shape of the spell he would cast, he didn’t have much fine control but the pattern he needed was simple, it just needed to include –

Everything, forget everything, Tom Riddle, Professor Quirrell, forget your whole life, forget your entire episodic memory, forget the disappointment and the bitterness and the wrong decisions, forget Voldemort –

And at the last moment before Harry cast the spell, he had one final thought, a note of grace –

But if you ever had any truly happy memories, not hurting people or laughing at their pain, but the warm feeling of helping someone or being helped, there won’t be many, maybe just when you were a child, but if you had any truly happy memories then keep only those –

Something bright in him unfolded at the decision, knowing he’d made the right choice, and Harry pushed that too into his wand –

‘Obliviate!’

And it all poured out of Harry into the spell.

Harry fell over on his side, dropping his wand, strangled screams coming from his throat, his hands going helplessly to his scar, even as the sudden blast of pain in his head began to fade. Only dimly did his eyes see that the air was filled with glowing snowflakes, drifting motes of silver light like tiny specks of Patronus Charm.

Only a moment the silver light lasted, and then it was gone.

Professor Quirrell was gone.

Nothing left but a remnant.

And that spirit, what remained of it, wouldn’t be so different now from Harry’s own.

The Prophecy was complete.

They had each remade the other in their own image.

Harry started sobbing, then, from where he was curled up in the dirt.

He cried for a while.

And then eventually Harry staggered to his feet and picked up his wand again, because this day’s work wasn’t quite done.

Harry laid his wand directly on Voldemort’s wrist-stump; it made his scar throb with an ongoing pain, but neither of them exploded.

And Harry began a Transfiguration.

Slowly – though faster than Harry had been able to Transfigure Hermione’s body, last time – the stunned form of the snake-man changed, reshaped itself. As the Transfiguration progressed, especially as the snake-man’s head began to turn glassy and shrunken, the pain in Harry’s scar faded.

It would be a spell to maintain whether Harry was waking or sleeping; and later, when Harry was older and more powerful and maybe had some help, he would un-Transfigure the mind-wiped Tom Riddle and heal his body with the power of the Stone. After future-Harry had figured out what to do with an almost-completely-amnesiac wizard who still had some bad habits of thought and some highly negative emotional patterns – a dark side, as ’twere – plus a great deal of declarative and procedural knowledge about powerful magic. Harry had tried his best not to Obliviate that part, because he might need it, some day.

And meanwhile, just like magic hadn’t defined a Transfigured unicorn as dead for purposes of setting off wards, Voldemort’s horcruxes wouldn’t define a Transfigured Voldemort as dead and try to bring him back.

That was the hope, anyway.

Harry’s scar twinged one last time when the steel ring went on his pinky finger, holding the tiny green emerald in contact with his skin. Then his scar subsided, and did not hurt again.

An upthrust rock served Harry for a chair, when he staggered over it and sat down motionless, resting after a fashion, shoving back the exhaustion that threatened the corners of his mind. It was not done, there was more to do.

Harry took another deep breath, still inhaling through his mouth, said ‘Lumos’, and looked around the graveyard.

Black robes and severed skull masks, surrounded by pools of blood –

Hermione Granger, asleep on an altar.

Voldemort’s empty robes and bloody hands, lying where the Dark Lord had fallen.

Quirinus Quirrell with his shredded robes, fallen in a heap where the Killing Curse had stricken him.

Harry imagined someone else looking at this scene, trying to understand it, and shook his head, because that wouldn’t do, it wouldn’t do at all.

Then Harry shoved himself up from his rock, grimacing as his mind, if not body, protested. He hadn’t been bloodied or beaten much today, but somehow Harry’s body was managing to feel like all the stress had hit it directly.

Harry staggered over toward where Voldemort had fallen, and picked up Voldemort’s left hand from where it lay upon the ground.

Even in just the left hand, you could see the faint trace of snake’s scales; it was very distinctively Voldemort. That was good.

Harry went to the altar where the sleeping Hermione lay, and gently placed the detached hand around Hermione’s neck, carefully moving the fingers to clutch at her throat. It was hard to do, Hermione seemed so peaceful and innocent when she was sleeping, and Voldemort’s severed hand seemed so ugly; Harry bluntly overrode whatever part of his mind was thinking that, since it made no sense in context.

A few weak Severing Charms served to mess up the almost perfectly fine cut the nanofibre had made, which was critical; it would not do to have the hand-stump look like the neck-stumps. The multiple Diffindos scattered small bits of Voldemort-wrist all over Hermione’s shirt, which, Harry had to remind himself, was also part of the plan.

Harry repeated this with the right hand, arranging it symmetrically with the left.

Harry used Inflammare to singe Voldemort’s robes where they lay, and then arranged the singed clothing around Hermione.

Voldemort’s gun, and his wand, went into Harry’s pouch. Harry placed the Stone of Permanency in an ordinary pocket, he wasn’t sure what the Stone might do to his pouch.

The heap of things from inside Quirrell’s robe, also near the altar, yielded the wand that the Defence Professor had used when he was being Quirrell. Harry went to where Quirrell lay, and straightened out the body as best he could, and put Quirrell’s wand into his hand. Tears predictably came to Harry’s eyes, and Harry wiped them away on his sleeve.

Harry took another deep breath, still inhaling through his mouth, said ‘Lumos’ again, and once more looked around the graveyard.

Black robes, severed skull masks, and Hermione Granger lying on an altar with Voldemort’s severed hands clutched around her throat, and Voldemort’s singed clothing scattered around her. Quirinus Quirrell lay dead with his clothes torn and shredded, his wand in his right hand.

That would do.

There remained the problem of calling attention to it.

Harry was very nearly out of magic at this point. But he still had enough left to Transfigure a leaf into the deflated form of a three-metre weather balloon.

Harry’s pouch produced a bottle of oxyacetylene, and a stick of dynamite, and a spool of fuse-cord. Be prepared, that’s the Boy Scout’s marching song, be prepared for a life that includes mountain trolls and who knows what else …

Harry inflated the weather balloon with the oxyacetylene. That would produce a very sharp overpressure when it detonated, maybe as loud as a sonic boom.

He attached the stick of dynamite – it was overkill, for detonation, but it would do.

He attached a 60-second fuse to the stick of dynamite, but did not light it yet.

Harry put on his Cloak of Invisibility, that had been among the piles by the sacrificial altar.

He obtained his broomstick from his pouch, and mounted it.

Harry cast a Quieting Charm around Hermione Granger – it wouldn’t stop all the noise, not even close, and it wasn’t like she’d be permanently hurt if her eardrums burst, but it still seemed polite.

And then that was it. The Quieting Charm had done it. Harry was drained of magic for at least the next hour.

Harry mounted the broomstick, slowly rising into the air, lifting the weather balloon filled with oxyacetylene with him. The castle Hogwarts came into view, distantly gleaming in moonlight a few kilometres away, as Harry rose above the trees; and Harry did his best to figure the distance, and the angle as it would be seen from Hogwarts.

When he had risen high above the forest, Harry used a lighter to ignite the fuse on the dynamite attached to the weather balloon full of oxyacetylene. Then Harry spun the broomstick and darted away – though not directly toward the castle, that might take him too close to the route past-Harry and Professor Quirrell had traversed, it wouldn’t do to have the Professor sense another Harry –

Harry felt a leaden stab of sadness, and refused it.

Thirty-one one-thousand, thirty-two one-thousand, thirty-three one-thousand …

When Harry reached forty, not wanting to take chances with his own eardrums, he glanced at his wristwatch, noting the exact time, and spun his Time-Turner once.

Shut Up and Do The Impossible, Pt 2

Something like a fugue state had come over Harry’s mind. The absolute state had partially worn off him, partially stayed with him. Elements of his mind were numb, maybe deliberately numbed by some part that was smart enough to predict what would happen otherwise. What he’d just done –

The thought was shut off, making space for an awareness of other things.

Harry was standing in the middle of a haphazard graveyard, tombstones scattered without order.

By moonlight and starlight, it could be seen that black robes littered the ground, surrounded by textures that didn’t match the surrounding graveyard earth, wetness tinged red in the moonlight. Some heads had come loose from the surrounding hoods of the robes, revealing hair that was long or short, dark or bright, which was all that could be seen beneath the moon. The silver masks stayed on, making all the hair originate in skulls instead of human faces –

The thought was shut off, making space for awareness of other things.

A girl in a red-trimmed Hogwarts uniform slept upon an altar. Near the altar, Harry’s things lay in a heap.

Upon the ground lay a too-tall pale man of inhuman face, blood pouring from the stumps of his wrists.

As soon as the Dark Lord Voldemort awakens, he will destroy everything you love. Dumbledore is no longer there to stop him.

He cannot be imprisoned, for he can abandon his body at any time.

He cannot be killed permanently, not without destroying more than a hundred horcruxes, one of which is the Pioneer plaque.

Materials: One wand, you are allowed to point it and speak this time.

You have five minutes.

Solve.

Harry stumbled toward the altar, knelt at its side, and picked up his pouch.

He walked toward where Voldemort lay.

The sense of apprehension had diminished, after Voldemort had been hexed unconscious. Now, as Harry approached, it rose to a terrifying height, flaring also into pain in his scar.

Harry ignored the inner shriek. That had been the last memory of Tom Riddle seared into Harry’s brain, the last cognitive pattern to be transferred over into the infant baby before Tom Riddle had exploded: a sense of mounting horror and dismay associated with the resonance that had spun out of control. Harry knew the meaning of it now, that sense of apprehension, and that made it easier to disregard. He’d guessed that the effect of the resonance mostly hit the caster, with power proportional to the caster’s power, and the bet had paid off.

Harry looked upon Voldemort’s body, and breathed deeply – through his mouth, because coppery smells Harry was not thinking about were coming in through his nose.

Harry knelt by Voldemort’s side, took out his medical kit from his pouch, and placed a self-tightening tourniquet around the body’s left wrist, then another tourniquet about the right.

It felt wrong, showing Voldemort that concern. Some part of Harry was aware, in the back of his mind, that some number of people had just had something extremely bad happen to them. What would have been balance, what would have been justice, was if Voldemort had suffered the same fate without an instant’s more hesitation. What Harry was doing now felt like Batman showing more concern for the Joker than for the Joker’s victims; it felt like a comic book where the writers wrung their hands endlessly about the morality of killing the Big Named Villains while innocents went on dying in the background. To show more solicitousness for the head villain than his minions, to pay more attention to his fate than the fates of his lower-status followers, was a flaw in human nature.

So it felt wrong when Harry rose up from beside the body, the tourniquets having tightened upon Voldemort’s wrists; it felt like Harry was doing something ethically monstrous.

Even though any sane strategic thinking said that Voldemort’s body must not die. The soul he’d created for himself had to be anchored in this brain, it mustn’t be allowed to float free.

Harry stepped back, back from Voldemort’s unconscious body, breathing deeply through his mouth. He went to the pile of his things, to put on his robes and other items, starting with placing the Time-Turner around his throat once more, readying his own escape and return if that was required …

More than a hundred horcruxes.

That had been insane, there wasn’t any other word for it, a sign of Voldemort’s damaged thinking about death. A Muggle security expert would have called it fence-post security, like building a fence-post over a hundred metres high in the middle of the desert. Only a very obliging attacker would try to climb the fence-post. Anyone sensible would just walk around the fence-post, and making the fence-post even higher wouldn’t stop that.

Once you forgot to be scared of how impossible the problem was supposed to be, it wasn’t even difficult, not by comparison to the last one.

Neville’s parents, for example, had been Crucioed into permanent insanity. Two hundred advanced horcruxes wouldn’t prevent that insanity, they would all just echo the same damaged mind.

It would be an ethically justified use of the Cruciatus Curse, if that were the only way to stop Voldemort permanently. It would be justice, balance, it would show that the Joker’s life wasn’t worth more than his meanest henchman …

All Harry needed to do was cast the Patronus Charm, send it to … Alastor Moody? … and tell him to come here. Well, no, it was a pretty good guess the Patronus Charm wouldn’t work if it was cast with that intent. Maybe just resolve to tell Moody that, and use his Time-Turner once he was out of range of Voldemort’s wards.

And then Voldemort could be Crucioed into permanent insanity.

It wasn’t even the least merciful fate. That would have been throwing Voldemort’s wand into the pit at Azkaban, if the wand stayed connected to Voldemort’s life and magic no matter where his ghost tried to flee.

Harry turned to face where Voldemort lay. He walked forward, and continued to control his breathing, ignoring the burning feeling in his throat. Some part of him knew that Voldemort was also Professor Quirrell, even though his body now was different. Even though the shift of personality had been perfect and that meant that Professor Quirrell had been just another mask …

Though Voldemort hadn’t planned to kill Harry painfully. Hadn’t thought to strike Harry with his followers’ Cruciatus, when Harry was being annoying before. That meant something, when your opponent was Voldemort. Maybe he’d had some remaining shred of fellow-feeling for the other Tom Riddle after all.

… it would be wrong to take that into account.

Wouldn’t it?

Harry looked back up at the stars. Here below the atmosphere the stars twinkled, they were embedded in the false dome of the night sky, stretched out across the wash of the Milky Way that glowed like a long ribbon, as if they were all close enough that you could fly up to them on a broomstick and touch them.

What would they want him to do now at this juncture, the children’s children’s children?

The answer to that also felt obvious, if it wasn’t just the part of Harry that still cared about Professor Quirrell doing the real talking.

Harry had needed to do the thing he’d done, it had prevented greater evils, Harry couldn’t have stopped Voldemort if the Death Eaters had fired first. But that thing Harry had done wasn’t something that could be balanced by a not-necessary tragedy happening to one more sentient being, even if that being was Voldemort. It would just be one more element of the sorrows of ancient Earth so long ago.

The past was past. You did what you had to do, and you didn’t do one scrap of harm more than that. Not even to balance things out, and make it all symmetrical.

The children’s children’s children wouldn’t want Voldemort to die, even if his minions had. They wouldn’t want Voldemort to hurt, if it didn’t accomplish anything compared to him not hurting.

Harry breathed deeply, and let go of – not his hate – not quite his hate – he hadn’t been able to hate his creator even at the very end – but even so, Harry let go of something. Of the sense that he ought to hate Voldemort, that it was a hate he was obliged to feel, for the endless list of crimes that Voldemort had committed for no good reason, not even his own happiness …

It’s all right, the stars whispered down at him. It’s all right not to hate him. It doesn’t make you a bad person.

In the end, there was only one option he would take, and since Harry already knew that, there was no point agonizing about it. Whether it was the best option, only time would tell.

Harry breathed deeply, building up the magic inside himself. The spell he was going to cast didn’t need to be precise, but it was still one of the most powerful spells he’d mastered.

Harry thought again of how unjust it was that Voldemort could not die with his followers, felt the slight trace of coldness in his blood that came with thoughts of ruthlessness. And then Harry let it go, let it all drain away beneath the starlight, because his dark side had never been anything except an inherited pattern of cognition, just one more bad habit of thinking to break.

Instead Harry looked at Hermione’s breathing form atop the altar, and let the tears finally start from his eyes. What would become of Hermione now, what path she would choose after this, Harry couldn’t guess; but she would be there to have a choice, their friendship wouldn’t have destroyed her existence. He hadn’t realised how shaky his hope had been, until he’d noticed how surprised he’d been after the hope had come true. Sometimes things did go better than expected.

And Harry took that thought, too, and put it into the magic he was building.

The power he was storing up was vibrating in him, like his whole body was part of his wand, either Harry’s eyes were blurring or there was a luminous white quiver running over the holly. And Harry thought the shape of the spell he would cast, he didn’t have much fine control but the pattern he needed was simple, it just needed to include –

Everything, forget everything, Tom Riddle, Professor Quirrell, forget your whole life, forget your entire episodic memory, forget the disappointment and the bitterness and the wrong decisions, forget Voldemort –

And at the last moment before Harry cast the spell, he had one final thought, a note of grace –

But if you ever had any truly happy memories, not hurting people or laughing at their pain, but the warm feeling of helping someone or being helped, there won’t be many, maybe just when you were a child, but if you had any truly happy memories then keep only those –

Something bright in him unfolded at the decision, knowing he’d made the right choice, and Harry pushed that too into his wand –

‘OBLIVIATE!’

And it all poured out of Harry into the spell.

Harry fell over on his side, dropping his wand, strangled screams coming from his throat, his hands going helplessly to his scar, even as the sudden blast of pain in his head began to fade. Only dimly did his eyes see that the air was filled with glowing snowflakes, drifting motes of silver light like tiny specks of Patronus Charm.

Only a moment the silver light lasted, and then it was gone.

Professor Quirrell was gone.

Nothing left but a remnant.

And that spirit, what remained of it, wouldn’t be so different now from Harry’s own.

The Prophecy was complete.

They had each remade the other in their own image.

Harry started sobbing, then, from where he was curled up in the dirt.

He cried for a while.

And then eventually Harry staggered to his feet and picked up his wand again, because this day’s work wasn’t quite done.

Harry laid his wand directly on Voldemort’s wrist-stump; it made his scar throb with an ongoing pain, but neither of them exploded.

And Harry began a Transfiguration.

Slowly – though faster than Harry had been able to Transfigure Hermione’s body, last time – the stunned form of the snake-man changed, reshaped itself. As the Transfiguration progressed, especially as the snake-man’s head began to turn glassy and shrunken, the pain in Harry’s scar faded.

It would be a spell to maintain whether Harry was waking or sleeping; and later, when Harry was older and more powerful and maybe had some help, he would un-Transfigure the mind-wiped Tom Riddle and heal his body with the power of the Stone. After future-Harry had figured out what to do with an almost-completely-amnesiac wizard who still had some bad habits of thought and some highly negative emotional patterns – a dark side, as ’twere – plus a great deal of declarative and procedural knowledge about powerful magic. Harry had tried his best not to Obliviate that part, because he might need it, some day.

And meanwhile, just like magic hadn’t defined a Transfigured unicorn as dead for purposes of setting off wards, Voldemort’s horcruxes wouldn’t define a Transfigured Voldemort as dead and try to bring him back.

That was the hope, anyway.

Harry’s scar twinged one last time when the steel ring went on his pinky finger, holding the tiny green emerald in contact with his skin. Then his scar subsided, and did not hurt again.

An upthrust rock served Harry for a chair, when he staggered over it and sat down motionless, resting after a fashion, shoving back the exhaustion that threatened the corners of his mind. It was not done, there was more to do.

Harry took another deep breath, still inhaling through his mouth, said ‘Lumos’, and looked around the graveyard.

Black robes and severed skull masks, surrounded by pools of blood –

Hermione Granger, asleep on an altar.

Voldemort’s empty robes and bloody hands, lying where the Dark Lord had fallen.

Quirinus Quirrell with his shredded robes, fallen in a heap where the Killing Curse had stricken him.

Harry imagined someone else looking at this scene, trying to understand it, and shook his head, because that wouldn’t do, it wouldn’t do at all.

Then Harry shoved himself up from his rock, grimacing as his mind, if not body, protested. He hadn’t been bloodied or beaten much today, but somehow Harry’s body was managing to feel like all the stress had hit it directly.

Harry staggered over toward where Voldemort had fallen, and picked up Voldemort’s left hand from where it lay upon the ground.

Even in just the left hand, you could see the faint trace of snake’s scales; it was very distinctively Voldemort. That was good.

Harry went to the altar where the sleeping Hermione lay, and gently placed the detached hand around Hermione’s neck, carefully moving the fingers to clutch at her throat. It was hard to do, Hermione seemed so peaceful and innocent when she was sleeping, and Voldemort’s severed hand seemed so ugly; Harry bluntly overrode whatever part of his mind was thinking that, since it made no sense in context.

A few weak Severing Charms served to mess up the almost perfectly fine cut the nanofibre had made, which was critical; it would not do to have the hand-stump look like the neck-stumps. The multiple Diffindos scattered small bits of Voldemort-wrist all over Hermione’s shirt, which, Harry had to remind himself, was also part of the plan.

Harry repeated this with the right hand, arranging it symmetrically with the left.

Harry used Inflammare to singe Voldemort’s robes where they lay, and then arranged the singed clothing around Hermione.

Voldemort’s gun, and his wand, went into Harry’s pouch. Harry placed the Stone of Permanency in an ordinary pocket, he wasn’t sure what the Stone might do to his pouch.

The heap of things from inside Quirrell’s robe, also near the altar, yielded the wand that the Defence Professor had used when he was being Quirrell. Harry went to where Quirrell lay, and straightened out the body as best he could, and put Quirrell’s wand into his hand. Tears predictably came to Harry’s eyes, and Harry wiped them away on his sleeve.

Harry took another deep breath, still inhaling through his mouth, said ‘Lumos’ again, and once more looked around the graveyard.

Black robes, severed skull masks, and Hermione Granger lying on an altar with Voldemort’s severed hands clutched around her throat, and Voldemort’s singed clothing scattered around her. Quirinus Quirrell lay dead with his clothes torn and shredded, his wand in his right hand.

That would do.

There remained the problem of calling attention to it.

Harry was very nearly out of magic at this point. But he still had enough left to Transfigure a leaf into the deflated form of a three-metre weather balloon.

Harry’s pouch produced a bottle of oxyacetylene, and a stick of dynamite, and a spool of fuse-cord. Be prepared, that’s the Boy Scout’s marching song, be prepared for a life that includes mountain trolls and who knows what else …

Harry inflated the weather balloon with the oxyacetylene. That would produce a very sharp overpressure when it detonated, maybe as loud as a sonic boom.

He attached the stick of dynamite – it was overkill, for detonation, but it would do.

He attached a 60-second fuse to the stick of dynamite, but did not light it yet.

Harry put on his Cloak of Invisibility, that had been among the piles by the sacrificial altar.

He obtained his broomstick from his pouch, and mounted it.

Harry cast a Quieting Charm around Hermione Granger – it wouldn’t stop all the noise, not even close, and it wasn’t like she’d be permanently hurt if her eardrums burst, but it still seemed polite.

And then that was it. The Quieting Charm had done it. Harry was drained of magic for at least the next hour.

Harry mounted the broomstick, slowly rising into the air, lifting the weather balloon filled with oxyacetylene with him. The castle Hogwarts came into view, distantly gleaming in moonlight a few kilometres away, as Harry rose above the trees; and Harry did his best to figure the distance, and the angle as it would be seen from Hogwarts.

When he had risen high above the forest, Harry used a lighter to ignite the fuse on the dynamite attached to the weather balloon full of oxyacetylene. Then Harry spun the broomstick and darted away – though not directly toward the castle, that might take him too close to the route past-Harry and Professor Quirrell had traversed, it wouldn’t do to have the Professor sense another Harry –

Harry felt a leaden stab of sadness, and refused it.

Thirty-one one-thousand, thirty-two one-thousand, thirty-three one-thousand …

When Harry reached forty, not wanting to take chances with his own eardrums, he glanced at his wristwatch, noting the exact time, and spun his Time-Turner once.

Something to Protect: Albus Dumbledore

Harry stood now before the gargoyles that guarded the Headmaster’s – no, the Headmistress’s office. He had been summoned by Professor Sinistra, told that it was an emergency, but the gates were not opening for him.

Experiment had showed that the Stone made one Transfiguration permanent every three minutes and fifty-four seconds, irrespective of the size of object Transfigured. Just once, holding the Philosopher’s Stone up to the light of Harry’s most powerful torch in an otherwise darkened closet, Harry had thought he’d seen an array of tiny points inside the chunk of crimson glass; but Harry hadn’t been able to see it again, and now suspected himself of having imagined it. The Stone had no other powers that Harry could detect, nor did it respond to any attempted mental commands.

Harry had given himself until noon tomorrow to figure out how to begin using the Stone without it being grabbed by someone else, trying not to think about what was still happening, what had always been happening, in the meanwhile.

Ten minutes late, Minerva McGonagall approached, moving in a swift stride. Her arms were full of papers, she was once again wearing the Sorting Hat.

The gargoyles, with a brief sound of grinding stone, bowed low before her.

‘The new password is “Impermanence”,’ Minerva said to the gargoyles, and they stepped aside. ‘I’m sorry, Mr Potter, I was delayed –’

‘Understood.’

Minerva mounted the long spiral stairs, climbing instead of waiting to be carried, Harry following behind her.

‘We are meeting with Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement; with Alastor Moody, whom you have met; and with Bartemius Crouch, Director of the Department of International Magical Cooperation,’ Minerva said as she climbed. ‘They are Dumbledore’s heirs as much as you or I.’

‘How – how’s Hermione doing?’ Harry hadn’t had a chance to ask until now.

‘Filius said she seemed rather in shock, which I suppose is not surprising. She asked where you were, was told you were at a Quidditch game, asked where you really were, and refused to speak with anyone about what happened until she was allowed to talk with you. She was taken to St. Mungo’s, where,’ the Headmistress now sounded slightly perturbed, ‘a standard diagnostic Charm showed Miss Granger as a healthy unicorn in excellent physical condition except that her mane needs combing. Charms to detect active magic have each time detected her as being in the process of transforming into another shape. There was an Unspeakable who showed up before Filius, ah, removed him. He performed certain spells he probably ought not to have known, and declared that Hermione’s soul was in healthy condition but at least a mile away from her body. At that point the senior healers gave up. She’s currently alone in a cell with the rats and flies –’

‘She’s what?’

‘I’m sorry, Mr Potter, that’s Transfiguration jargon. Miss Granger is in an isolation chamber with a cage of tame rats, and a box of flies that will bear offspring in a single day. Logic suggests that whatever mystery underlies her resurrection, it left behind an emanation that is causing the healers’ Charms to produce gibberish. But if nothing happens to the rats or to the flies’ offspring, Miss Granger will be declared safe to return to Hogwarts after she wakes up again tomorrow morning.’

Harry still wasn’t sure … wasn’t sure at all, what Hermione would think of having been resurrected, at least under these particular circumstances. He didn’t actually think Hermione would yell at him for doing it wrong. That was just Harry’s brain trying to imagine her as a stereotype. Harry had been legitimately exhausted and not thinking very straight when he’d come up with that cover story, and Hermione would probably understand that part. But he couldn’t imagine what Hermione would think …

‘I wonder how Miss Granger will feel about having also vanquished You-Know-Who,’ Minerva said reflectively, climbing the moving stairs fast enough that Harry felt out of breath trying to keep up. ‘And people believing the most interesting things about her.’

‘You mean, because she’s always self-identified as a normal academic genius, and now a bunch of people think of her as the Girl-Who-Revived and everyone wants to shake her hand?’ Harry said. Even though she doesn’t remember doing anything to earn it. Even though it was all someone else’s work and other people’s sacrifices, and she’s getting the credit. Even though she doesn’t feel like she’s actually done anything worthy of the way other people treat her, and she’s not sure if she can ever live up to the person they imagine. ‘Gosh, I don’t know, I can’t imagine what that feels like.’

Maybe I shouldn’t have subjected her to it. But people had to be given something to believe or heaven knows what they’d have made up. Feeling guilty about this would be stupid. I think.

The two of them reached the top of the stairs, and came into the office filled with dozens of strange objects, all facing a great desk and a mighty throne behind it.

Minerva’s hand passed over one of those objects, the one with golden wibblers, her eyes closing briefly. Then Minerva took off the Sorting Hat and put it on a hatrack that held three slippers for left feet. She transformed the mighty throne into a simple cushioned chair and the great desk into a round table, around which four other chairs rose up.

Harry watched it all with a strange pang in his throat. He knew, without either of them saying anything, that there should have been more ceremony for the changing of the chairs, the changing of the table. Much more ceremony, for the first time the Headmistress sat down in her new office. But for whatever reason, there wasn’t time, and Minerva McGonagall was discarding all that for speed.

A wave of Minerva’s wand lit the Floo-fire in the fireplace, even as Minerva sat down into the chair that had been Dumbledore’s.

Harry quietly took one of the chairs around the table, sitting at Minerva’s left.

Almost at once, the Floo-fire burned emeraldine and whirled out Alastor Moody, who spun around with his wand raised, taking in the whole room at a seeming glance, and then pointed his wand directly at Harry and said ‘Avada Kedavra.’

It happened so fast, and took him so completely by surprise, that Harry’s wand wasn’t even half-raised by the time Alastor Moody finished the incantation.

‘Just checking,’ Alastor said to the Headmistress, whose own wand was now pointed at Alastor, her mouth open as if to say words she couldn’t find. ‘Voldie would’ve tried to dodge, if he’d taken over the boy’s body last night. I’ll still need to check the Granger girl, though.’ Alastor Moody went to Minerva’s right and sat down.

Harry had thought, in that split second, to try producing a wordless silver Patronus glow from his wand; but his wand hadn’t been in place to intercept in time, not even close.

Well, if I was feeling invincible before, that does for that. What a valuable life lesson, Mr Moody.

Then the Floo-fire burned green again, and spat out the oldest, grimmest, toughest-looking witch Harry had ever seen, like beef jerky given human shape. The old witch did not have her wand in her hand, but she projected an air of authority that was stronger and stricter than Dumbledore’s.

‘This is Director Amelia Bones, Mr Potter,’ said Headmistress McGonagall, who’d regained her poise. ‘We are still waiting on Director Crouch –’

‘The corpse of Bartemius Crouch Jr. was identified among the dead Death Eaters,’ the old witch said without preamble, even as she continued toward the chairs. ‘It took us entirely by surprise, and I’m afraid Bartemius is in considerable grief about it, on both counts. He will not be with us today.’

Harry kept the flinch inward.

Amelia Bones sat down in a chair, sitting to Moody’s own right.

‘Headmistress McGonagall,’ said the elder witch, still without hesitation or delay, ‘The Line of Merlin Unbroken, which Dumbledore left to me in regency, is not responding to my hand. The Wizengamot must have a Chief Warlock who is trustworthy, at once; matters are in great flux in Britain. I must know what Dumbledore has done, immediately!’

‘Crap,’ muttered Moody. His mad-eye was rolling wildly. ‘That’s not good, not good at all.’

‘Yes, well,’ said Minerva McGonagall, who looked rather apprehensive. ‘I cannot say that for certain. Albus – well, he clearly had an intimation that he might not survive this war. But I do not think he was expecting Miss Granger to come back from the dead and kill Voldemort only hours later. I do not think Albus was expecting that at all. I am not quite sure what his legacies will make of that –’

Amelia Bones rose half out of her chair. ‘You mean to imply that the Granger girl may have inherited the Line of Merlin Unbroken? This is a catastrophe! She is twelve years old, untested – surely Albus would not be so irresponsible as to leave the Line to whoever happened to defeat Voldemort, without knowing who!’

‘Well, putting it simply,’ Minerva said. Her fingers squared the paperwork she’d taken with her, now lying on the desk. ‘Albus did think he knew who would defeat Voldemort. There was a prophecy concerning it, a verified one, which now seems to be in abeyance, or – I don’t know, Madam Bones! I have one letter for Mr Potter that I am to give him in the event of Albus’s death or other departure, and then another letter that Albus said Mr Potter would be able to open only after he defeated Voldemort. I am not sure what will happen to it now. Perhaps Miss Granger will be able to open it, or perhaps it can never be opened –’

‘Hold up,’ Mad-Eye Moody said. He reached into his robes, drew out a long, grey-knobbed wand that Harry recognized; it was Dumbledore’s wand, of a form and style not like any other wand in Hogwarts. Moody laid the wand on the table. ‘Before we go any further, Albus left me an instruction or two of his own. Pick up this wand, boy.’

Harry hesitated, thinking.

Albus Dumbledore sacrificed himself for me. He trusted Moody. This probably isn’t a trap.

Then Harry began to reach for the wand.

It leaped up and flew across the table, into Harry’s hand. And the moment that Harry’s fingers grasped the handle it was like he heard a song, a paean of glory and battle that resonated in his mind. A wave of white fire ran up the handle and over the wood, magnifying as it moved, bursting from the end in a tremendous spray of sparks. Through the wood beneath his fingers ran a sense of strength and constrained danger, like a leashed wolf.

Harry was also receiving an impression of distinct skepticism, as if the wand had some level of awareness, and it was wondering how the hell it had ended up being held by a Hogwarts first-year.

‘Right,’ said Mad-Eye Moody into the puzzled stares. ‘So it wasn’t Miss Granger who defeated Voldie, then. Didn’t think so.’

‘What.’ Amelia Bones spoke the word flatly.

Mad-Eye Moody gave her a respectful nod. ‘Albus said this wand goes to whoever defeats its previous master. Took it off old Grindie, he did. Then Voldie defeated Albus, yesterday. Do I need to spell it out, Amelia?’

Amelia Bones was staring at Harry, her mouth wide open.

‘That might not be right,’ Harry said. He swallowed another pang of the awful guilt. ‘I mean, Voldemort used me as a hostage because I, I was stupid, and Dumbledore gave himself up to save me, maybe the wand thinks that counts as my defeating Dumbledore. Um, I did defeat Voldemort, though. Vanquished him. But I think it’s better if nobody has any idea I was there.’

Beep. Tick. Whirr. Ding. Poot.

‘That must have taken some doing,’ Mad-Eye said. The scarred man inclined his head slowly, a gesture of profound respect. ‘Don’t feel too guilty about losing Albus and David and Flamel, son, no matter how stupid you were. You won in the end. All of us put together never could. Just to check, son, you and David also destroyed Voldie’s horcrux? And you’re certain it was the real thing?’

Harry hesitated, weighing up the probable consequences of trust, the possible disasters of silence, and then shook his head to Moody in reply. He’d been planning to tell at least McGonagall about what was now inside her school, anyway. ‘Voldemort had … rather a lot of horcruxes, actually. So instead I Obliviated most of his memories, then Transfigured him into this.’ Harry raised his hand, and silently pointed to the emerald on his ring.

Splat. Boing. Splat. Splat.

‘Huh,’ Moody said, leaning back in his chair. ‘Minerva and I will be putting some alarms and enchantments on that ring of yours, son, if you don’t mind. Just in case you forget to sustain that Transfiguration one day. And don’t go hunting any other Dark wizards, ever, just live a quiet and peaceful life.’ The scarred man took a handkerchief and wiped at the beads of sweat that had now appeared on his forehead. ‘But well done, lad, you and David both, may he rest in peace. This was his idea, I’m guessing? Well done, I say.’

‘Indeed,’ said Amelia Bones, who had now regained her composure. ‘We all owe the both of you a tremendous debt of gratitude. But I say again that there is urgent business regarding the Line of Merlin Unbroken.’

‘I believe,’ Minerva McGonagall said slowly, ‘that I had best give Albus’s letters to Mr Potter, right now.’ At the top of her stack of papers now lay a parchment envelope, and a rolled-up parchment scroll sealed with a grey ribbon.

The Headmistress gave Harry the parchment envelope, first, and Harry opened it.

If you are reading this, Harry Potter, then I have fallen to Voldemort, and the quest now lies in your hands.

Though it may shock you to learn, this was the end that I wished in my heart would come to pass. For as I write this, it yet seems possible that Voldemort may fall by my own hand. And then, in time, I shall myself become the darkness you must overcome, to enter fully into your power. For it was said once that you might need to raise your hand against your mentor, the one who made you, who you loved; it was said that you might be my downfall. If you are reading this, then that shall never come to pass, and I am glad of it.

Even so, Harry, I would spare you this, the lonely fight against Voldemort. I write this, vowing to shelter you as long as I can, no matter the final cost to myself. But if I have failed, then know that I am glad of it, in my own selfish way.

With my passing, there is none left to oppose Voldemort as an equal save you. His shadow will fall long and terrible over magical Britain, and many will suffer and die for it. That shadow will not lift until you destroy its source, until you cleanse the heart of the darkness. How you are to do this, I do not know. If Voldemort knows not the power you bear, then neither do I. You must find that power within yourself, you must learn to wield it, you must become Voldemort’s final judge, and I beg you not to make the error of showing him mercy.

My wand, which I have left to you in Moody’s keeping, you must not dare to wield against Voldemort. For when that wand’s master is defeated, it passes to the victor in turn. When you have conquered my conqueror, then the wand will answer truly to your hand; but if you try to turn it against Voldemort before then, it will betray you for certain. Keep it out of Voldemort’s grasp at all costs. I should advise you not to wield that wand at all, yet it is a device of great power, which you might need in some desperate case. But if you pick it up you must fear its treachery at all times.

In my absence, the Wizengamot will inevitably fall to Malfoy. The Line of Merlin Unbroken I have passed to you, with Amelia Bones as your regent, until you come of age or come into your power. But she cannot oppose Malfoy for long, not with myself gone and Voldemort returned to advise him. Soon, I think, the Ministry will fall, and Hogwarts will become the last fortress. To Minerva I have left Hogwarts’s keys, but you alone are its prince, and she will help you however she can.

Alastor now leads the Order of the Phoenix. Heed his words well, both his advice and his confidences. It is one of my life’s greatest regrets that I did not heed Alastor more and sooner.

That you will in the end defeat Voldemort, I have no doubt.

For that will be only the beginning of your life’s destiny. Of that, too, I am certain.

When you have vanquished Voldemort, when you have saved this country, then, I hope, you may embark upon the true meaning of your days.

Hurry then to begin.

Yours in death (or in whatever),

Dumbledore.

P.S. The passwords are “phoenix’s price”, “phoenix’s fate”, and “phoenix’s egg”, spoken within my office. Minerva can move those rooms to where you can reach them more easily.

Harry folded up the parchment and put its back into the envelope, frowning thoughtfully, then took the grey-ribboned scroll from the Headmistress. When the long grey wand in Harry’s hand touched the ribbon, it fell away at once; and Harry unrolled the scroll, and read it.

Dear Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres:

If you are reading this, you have defeated Voldemort.

Congratulations on that.

I hope you had some time in which to celebrate before you opened this scroll, because the news in it is not cheerful.

During the First Wizarding War, there came a time when I realised that Voldemort was winning, that he would soon hold all within his hand.

In that extremity, I went into the Department of Mysteries and I invoked a password which had never been spoken in the history of the Line of Merlin Unbroken, did a thing forbidden and yet not utterly forbidden.

I listened to every prophecy that had ever been recorded.

And so I learned that my troubles were far worse than Voldemort.

From certain seers and diviners have come an increasing chorus of foretellings that this world is doomed to destruction.

And you, Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, are one of those foretold to destroy it.

By rights I should have ended your line of possibility, stopped you from ever being born, as I did my best to end all the other possibilities I discovered on that day of terrible awakening.

Yet in your case, Harry, and in your case alone, the prophecies of your apocalypse have loopholes, though those loopholes be ever so slight.

Always he will end the world, not he will end life.

Even when it was said that you would tear apart the very stars in heaven, it was not said that you would tear apart the people.

And so, it being clear that this world is not meant to last, I have gambled literally everything upon you, Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. There were no prophecies of how the world might be saved, so I found the prophecies that offered loopholes in the destruction; and I brought about the strange and complex conditions for those prophecies to come to pass. I ensured that Voldemort discovered a certain one of those prophecies, and so (even as I had feared) condemned your parents to death and made you what you are. I wrote a strange hint in your mother’s Potions textbook, having no idea why I must; and this proved to show Lily how to help her sister, and ensured you would gain Petunia Evans’s heartfelt love. I snuck invisibly into your bedroom in Oxford and administered the potion that is given to students with Time-Turners, to extend your day’s cycle by two hours. When you were six years old I smashed a rock that was on your windowsill, and to this day I cannot imagine why.

All in the desperate hope that you can pass us through the eye of the storm, somehow end this world and yet bring out its people alive.

Now that you have passed the preliminary test of defeating Voldemort, I place my all in your hands, all the tools I can possibly give you. The Line of Merlin Unbroken, the command of the Order of the Phoenix, all my wealth and all my treasures, the Elder Wand out of the Deathly Hallows, the loyalty of such of my friends as may heed me. I have left Hogwarts in Minerva’s care, for I do not think you will have time for it, but even that is yours if you demand it from her.

One thing I do not give you, and that is the prophecies. Upon the moment of my departure, they will be destroyed, and no future ones will be recorded, for it was said that you must not look upon them. If you think this frustrating, believe me when I say that even your wit cannot comprehend what frustration you have been spared. I will die, or be lost by you, or in some other way be taken from you – the prophecies are unclear, naturally – without ever once knowing what the future truly holds, or why I must do what I do. It is all cryptic madness and you are well rid of it.

There can only be one king upon the chessboard.

There can only be one piece whose value is beyond price.

That piece is not the world, it is the world’s peoples, wizard and Muggle alike, goblins and house-elves and all.

While survives any remnant of our kind, that piece is yet in play, though the stars should die in heaven.

And if that piece be lost, the game ends.

Know the value of all your other pieces, and play to win.

– Albus

Chapter 114. Shut Up and Do The Impossible

The gibbous moon riding higher in the cloudless sky, the stars and wash of the Milky Way visible in all their majesty within the darkness, all these shone down upon the graveyard to bear witness from their unimaginable distances.

In the instant when Harry had realised there was no way at all left to save everyone, his mind’s voices had fallen away, become one, a single purpose taking up every fraction of his mind.

Fifty seconds.

Forty seconds.

Harry’s eyes tracked slowly across the air, until his gaze landed on the first Death Eater, the one closest to him.

Thirty seconds?

Twenty seconds?

“Time’ss almosst up –” hissed Voldemort.

“I do know ssecretss you would like to know,” Harry hissed. He didn’t look directly at the Dark Lord as he spoke. ”But mosst valuable knowledge to you, I think, would be my ideass ass to how world might be desstroyed. Yet, to tell you ssuch thoughtss might lead to desstruction of world. Do not know prophecy, but if there iss prophecy, that makess it more than ussually probable that any action I take might have that effect. Or to tell you ssuch might prevent desstruction of world, ssince you do sseem motivated to avoid it. Not allowed to make ssuch a decission mysself. Would need to awaken and conssult girl-child friend. Vow requiress.”

There was a long pause. The Dark Lord, floating above and behind the curve of Death Eaters with leveled wands, began to laugh as Salazar Slytherin had thought a snake would laugh, cold amusement in the form of a hiss. “Do you know how to desstroy world, then?”

“Cannot deliberately try to imagine method. You might have way for sservant to ssteal my thoughtss. Vow prohibitss. But ssusspect I could devisse method, if girl-child ssaid to try.”

Harry’s eyes drifted slowly to another Death Eater, and another.

More snakish laughter. “Clever. You have my complimentss for thinking of ssuch tacticss. But no.”

“Know it iss annoying, but with world and your eternity at sstake, would you not –”

“Greater rissk to world in introducing ssuch complicationss, delaying your end. I will sstudy Muggle ssciencess mysself, think of all you might imagine. Now sspeak ssuch ssecretss as you may tell me, or thiss endss.”

Slowly Harry’s vision tracked across the graveyard in careful arcs, ignoring the Dark Lord except as a floating blackness in his peripheral vision. His mouth went on speaking with only half his attention. “Have thought of idea you might not have conssidered, teacher. Your attempt to kill me might fail in certain sspecific way desspite all your precautionss, perhapss lead into my desstroying world later. Would not ordinarily deem probable, but with prophecy at hand, may well be sso.”

Voldemort went still, in the air. “How?”

“Am not obligated to tell you.”

A cold anger began to seethe through the snakish reply. “Though I undersstand well your dessperation and attempted clevernesss, thiss beginss to annoy me. I will not withhold from killing you, for that iss sstill greater rissk. To fail to tell me your thought rissks desstroying world. Sspeak!”

“No. Vow doess not obligate me to any possitive action.”

The Dark Lord stared down at Harry Potter, who glanced up at the angry face only briefly before his eyes went back to the next Death Eater. Some of them were shifting their stances slightly, but they stood still, and said no words as they leveled their wands. The silver skull masks could not be read.

Then the Dark Lord began to chuckle again. “Ssurvive your death, you think you might? No, child, my horcruxess are not linked to you alsso. I would know if they were. Or iss there other reasson you think you might ssurvive beyond my ways of enssuring your death?”

Harry didn’t allow himself to be distracted. The repeated failures didn’t matter, they only led into the next action in the chain – but he still needed a next action –

“Now sspeak a ssecret,” the Dark Lord hissed, ”or I –”

“Life-eaterss will purssue you alwayss, hate you alwayss, sseek you out wherever you go, if what I have jusst done wass ssuccesssful, I have caused them to be set upon you! Guardian Charm ssecret will be beyond you for long time to come, perhapss forever! Besst defensse againsst life-eaterss would die with me!”

“Thiss iss sstarting to become ssad … ” the Dark Lord’s voice trailed off. “Ah. I ssee. Life-eaterss resspond to expectationss. You tell me I will be hunted, I expect to be hunted, they hunt me. Ssuch iss rare, but not unheard-of. Valuable ssecret, yess. Can ssee many ussess.” A cruel smile. “I sshall allow you to sselect one persson to be ssaved.”

“Mysself.”

“Would tell you to die with dignity, but knowing mysself, I know it for futility. You have wassted my kindly gift jusst then by annoying me, and I retract it. Any other ssecretss?”

“Yess. Really interessting oness, too. Ssome you are unlikely to figure out on your own, not for very long time if ever. If I ssay I have told you all that do not rissk world, will you not torment any of my friendss or family? All of thiss sspeech sstarted becausse you left me no way at all to ssave everyone.”

The Dark Lord stood still in the air for a long moment.

And Harry’s eyes went on tracking slowly across the graveyard, as his hand remained tight upon his wand.

In the instant when Harry had realized there was no way left to save everyone –

He couldn’t speak any incantation in English. But Transfiguration was wordless.

There was no material in contact with his wand’s end except air, which couldn’t be Transfigured. But Voldemort didn’t know about partial Transfiguration, which Harry could use to Transfigure a tiny bit of the material from his wand itself.

“You’re sstalling,” the Dark Lord said. “Jusst to delay death? Or with other purposse?”

Harry said nothing, his other work slowing as his mind sought a continuation of the conversation that would work even against the Dark Lord’s will –

“Sspeak and tell me purposse, or thiss endss now and your friendss suffer for lifetimess!”

“Lower Muggle weapon and do not point wand in my direction,” Harry hissed, putting as much cold danger as he could into the snake’s voice. “Sspeak no commandss to sservantss. I do posssesss capabilitiess of which you are ignorant. Can usse one ssuch capacity to causse huge explossion almosst insstantly, without sspeaking incantation. Sslay your new body, all sservantss, Sstone sscattered to who knowss where.”

At his current level of practice Harry could Transfigure one cubic millimeter as fast as he could apply his will and magic.

One cubic millimeter of antimatter.

It wasn’t a world-ending threat.

Voldemort could have been carved from stone. “You bluff, ssomehow.”

“Not bluffing. Sspeaking in ssnaketalk, I tell you, I can do it almosst insstantly, before any sspell can be casst at me, I think. You know very little of sscience ass yet. Power I would command iss sstronger than processs that fuelss sstarss.”

“Vow will sstop you,” hissed Voldemort. “You cannot rissk world. Take no risskss, none, with clever ideass!”

“Would not rissk world. I esstimated ssize of explossion, nowhere near that large.”

“You do NOT know, fool! Cannot be SURE!“Voldemort’s hiss was climbing higher.

“I am reassonably certain. Vow will not sstop me.”

There was an increasing fury in Voldemort’s expression, and yet his hiss carried a tinge of fear. “I sshall wreak pain beyond imagining on all you care for –”

“Sshut up. I dissregard all ssuch threatss now, as theory of gamess ssayss I sshould. Only reasson you make threatss iss that you expect me to resspond.” That, too, Harry had truly understood in the last extremity. “Offer me ssomething I want, teacher. For your new body, for your continued holding of Sstone, for livess of your sservantss.”

Harry’s mouth was running on automatic, his real attention elsewhere.

Beneath the moonlight glints a tiny fragment of silver, a fraction of a line …

From a tiny spot on the end of Harry’s wand, a cubic millimeter of anchor, stretched out a thin line of Transfigured spider-silk. It would have broken at once, if tested; it would have gone unremarked, if any had noticed its glint. Less than a tenth of a millimeter in cross-section, the tiny shape represented by the extended line of spider-silk was something Harry could Transfigure swiftly, ten centimeters of length to a cubic millimeter of total volume; and Harry could Transfigure a cubic millimeter in a fraction of a second. He was forcing the Transfiguration outward, extending it through the air as fast as he could without risking the transformation.

The tracing line of spider-silk looped around a Death Eater’s hood at neck level, returned to the pattern of threads.

Voldemort’s face was now impassive. “You musst not leave here alive. Ssenssible people called good would alsso agree, thiss I tell you in ssnake’ss sspeech. But all your friendss I will treat kindly and protect under my reign, if you agree to die now ass good persson sshould.”

The last Death Eater was looped. The pattern of spider-silk was complete. The web had been drawn with loops around all the Death Eater’s necks. The ends of those loops had been anchored to a central circle; and that central circle in turn had three threads stretching across its center. The entire pattern still touching the anchor-line stretching out of Harry’s wand.

Over the next seconds, those near-invisible threads of reflected moonlight turned black.

Filaments narrower, stronger, and sharper than steel wire; braided carbon nanotubes, each individual tube all a single molecule.

Harry hissed, “Want you to alsso promisse to treat nationss kindly under your rule. Will not accept lesss.”

Voldemort hovered still in the air, snake-face showing a dawning fury.

The last two threads stretched out from the dark pattern, black theads already in the form of nanotubes. They moved lightly through the air toward the Dark Lord himself, toward the sleeve just above Voldemort’s left hand that held the gun, toward the sleeve above the right hand that held the yew wand, threads placed high at first to give them time to drift slowly downward through the air. The threads looped around, went over themselves, tied slippable knots. Began to tighten, coming closer to the sleeve, as Harry Transfigured them shorter –

Harry felt the tickle of Voldmort’s power beginning to touch his own in the back of his mind; at the same time the Dark Lord’s eyes widened, his mouth opened.

And Harry Transfigured the black threads stretching across the black pattern’s center to a quarter their previous size, shrinking the circle, yanking hard on everything attached, tightening loops.

(Black robes, falling.)

Harry wasn’t looking there, he didn’t see the falling masks, the blood, in the back of his mind he felt some explosions of magic like he’d felt when Hermione died but he ignored them, Harry’s eyes only saw the Dark Lord’s hands and wand and gun dropping downward, and then Harry’s wand was rising, pointing –

Harry screamed, “STUPORFY!”

The red bolt the colour of the Stunning Hex winged toward Voldemort, blazing across the graveyard almost faster than the eye could see.

Without any hesitation despite his wounds the Dark Lord jerked down and right through the air.

And the red bolt from Professor Flitwick’s secret Swerving Stunner turned in midair and slammed into Voldemort.

The pain that flashed through Harry’s scar was searing, it made him cry out and a red haze appear across his vision, despite everything Harry dropped his wand in pain and sheer fatigue.

As Harry let go of his wand, the pain began to clear –

The next chapter will post in 10 minutes.

Chapter 120. Something to Protect: Draco Malfoy

A/N: Farewell, Terry Pratchett, 1948-2015. Your characters were an inspiration to me, and now I can see how much they taught me about Level 1 and Level 3 Character Intelligence: that self-awareness often manifests as humor or as genre-savviness; that an inner spark of optimization can shine just as brightly through characters who are told (but not shown) to be lowly and stupid; that intelligent characters can go along with a spark of goodness and light running through a story, rather than cynicism. I wish I could have met you, and spoken with you about your methods. You were loved by so many, and surely at least one person who would tear apart the foundations of reality to bring you back; but your brain is dead and warm now, and so your story ends.

Even if the stars should die in heaven,
Our sins can never be undone.
No single death will be forgiven
When fades at last the last lit sun.
Then in the cold and silent black
As light and matter end,
We’ll have ourselves a last look back
And toast an absent friend.

The boy sat in an office near to where the once-Deputy Headmistress had held court. His tears had run dry hours ago. Now there was only the waiting to see what would become of him, the orphan ward of Hogwarts, whose life and happiness lay in the hands of his family’s enemies. The boy had been called to this room, and he had come because there was nothing else to do and nowhere else to go. Vincent and Gregory had left his side, called back by their mothers for their fathers’ hurried funerals. Perhaps the boy should have gone with them, but he could not bring himself to do so. He would not have been able to act the part of a Malfoy. The feeling of emptiness that filled him up was so profound that it left no room even for pretended courtesy.

Everyone was dead.

His father was dead, and his godfather Mr MacNair, and his fallback godfather Mr Avery. Even Sirius Black, his mother’s cousin, had somehow managed to die, and the last remnant of House Black was no friend to any Malfoy.

Everyone was dead.

There came a knock upon the office’s door; and then, when the boy made no reply, the door opened, revealing –

“Go away,” Draco Malfoy said to the Boy-Who-Lived. He couldn’t muster any force in the words.

“I will soon,” Harry Potter said, as he stepped into the room. “But there’s a decision to be made, and only you can make it.”

Draco turned his head toward the wall, because just looking at Harry Potter took more energy than he had left in him.

“You have to decide,” Harry said, “what happens to Draco Malfoy after this. I don’t mean that in any ominous way. No matter what, you’re still going to grow up to be the rich heir of a Noble and Most Ancient House. The thing is,” Harry’s voice was wavering now, “the thing is, there’s a horrible truth you don’t know, and I keep thinking that if you knew, you’d tell me not to be your friend anymore. And I don’t want to stop being your friend. But to just – never tell you – and always maintain that lie so I can go on being your friend – I can’t do that. It’s also wrong. I don’t … don’t want this anymore, I don’t want to be manipulating you. I’ve hurt you too much already.”

Then stop trying to be my friend, you’re no good at it anyway. The words rose up into Draco’s consciousness, and were rejected from his lips. He felt like he’d mostly lost Harry already, from the games Harry had played with their friendship, the lies and manipulations; and yet the thought of going back to Slytherin alone, maybe without Vincent and Gregory if their mothers terminated the arrangement … Draco didn’t want to do that, he didn’t want to go back to Slytherin and live out his life among only people who’d agreed to be Sorted into Slytherin House. Draco was barely sensible enough to remember how many of his real friends were also friends with Harry, that Padma was a Ravenclaw and even Theodore was a Chaotic Lieutenant. All that remained of Malfoy House was a tradition, now; and that tradition said it wasn’t clever to tell the war’s victor to go away and stop trying to be friends with you.

“All right,” Draco said emptily. “Tell me.”

“That’s what I’m going to do,” Harry said. “And then the Headmistress will come in after I leave, and seal away your last half-hour of memory. But before then, knowing the whole truth, you’ll get to decide whether you still want to be involved with me.” Harry’s voice was shaking. “Um. According to the records I was reading through before I came here, the story really began in 1926 with the birth of a half-blood wizard named Tom Morfin Riddle. His mother died in childbirth, and he grew up in a Muggle orphanage, until his Hogwarts letter was brought to him by Professor Dumbledore …”

The Boy-Who-Lived continued speaking, words that slammed into what was left of Draco’s mind like falling houses.

The Dark Lord had been a half-blood. He’d never believed in blood purity for a fraction of a second.

Tom Riddle had come up with the idea of Lord Voldemort as a bad joke.

The Death Eaters had been meant to lose to David Monroe, so Monroe could take over.

After giving up on that, Tom Riddle had gone on playing Voldemort instead of actually trying to win, because he’d liked bossing the Death Eaters around.

Voldemort used me to try to frame Father for my attempted murder, then used me again to go after the Philosopher’s Stone. Draco couldn’t remember that part, but he’d already been told that he’d been used as a pawn alongside Professor Sprout, and that no charges would be filed.

And then the last horror.

“You –” whispered Draco Malfoy. “You –”

“I’m the one who killed your father and all the other Death Eaters last night. They’d been told to open fire on me the moment I did anything, so I had to kill them in order to have a chance at dealing with Voldemort, who was a danger to the entire world.” Harry Potter’s voice was strained. “I didn’t think about you and Theodore and Vincent and Gregory, but if I had, I’d have done it anyway. My mind managed not to realise until afterwards that Mr White was Lucius, but if I’d realised, I still wouldn’t have risked leaving him alive, in case he knew wandless magic. The thought occurred to me long before that it would be pretty convenient, in terms of the political landscape, for all the Death Eaters to suddenly die. I always thought that the Death Eaters were horrible people, much more strongly than I ever let on to you, since the first day we met. But if your father hadn’t been there, and I’d had a button that could kill him remotely, I wouldn’t have pressed the button just for political reasons. The way I feel about what I’ve done, and whether there’s remorse … well, there’s a part of me that’s screaming in generic horror about having killed anyone. And another part that says that from a moral standpoint, the Death Eaters signed away their lives on the day they signed up with Voldemort. They pointed their wands at me first, blah blah and so on. But right now I just feel sick about what I’ve done to you. Again. I feel like,” Harry Potter’s voice wobbled a bit, “everything I do only hurts you, for all my good intentions, that you’ve only ever lost things from being around me, so if you tell me to stay away entirely from Draco Malfoy after this, then I will. And if you want me to try to be your friend for real this time, without ever trying to manipulate you again, without ever using you again or risking hurting you again, then I will, I swear I will.”

The next Lord Malfoy was crying, openly in front of his enemy, decorum and composure abandoned, because he didn’t have anyone left for whose sake he could keep it.

A lie.

A lie.

Everything had been a lie, it was all lies piled on top of lies, lies lies lies –

“You should die,” Draco forced out. “You should die for having killed Father.” The words only filled him with more emptiness, but they had to be said.

Harry Potter just shook his head. “And if that’s not an option?”

“You should hurt.”

Harry only shook his head again.

The Boy-Who-Lived pressed the Lord Malfoy for his decision.

The Lord Malfoy refused to give it. He couldn’t say it, couldn’t bring himself to say it, either way. He didn’t want the war’s victor and their mutual friends to abandon him, and he wasn’t going to give Harry the absolution he wanted, either.

So Draco Malfoy refused to answer, and then the time of that self’s memory ended.

The boy sat in an office near to where the once-Deputy Headmistress had held court. His tears had run dry hours ago. Now there was only the waiting to see what would become of him, the orphan ward of Hogwarts, whose life and happiness lay in the hands of his family’s enemies. The boy had been called to this room, and he had come, because there was nothing else to do, and nowhere else to go. Vincent and Gregory had left his side, called back by their mothers for their fathers’ hurried funerals. Perhaps the boy should have gone with them, but he could not bring himself to do so. He would not have been able to act the part of a Malfoy. The feeling of emptiness that filled him up was so profound that it left no room even for lies.

Everyone was dead.

Everyone was dead, and it had all been futile from the beginning.

There was a knock upon the office door, and then, after a polite pause, it opened to reveal Headmistress McGonagall, dressed much as she had dressed when she was a Professor. “Mr Malfoy?” his family’s victorious enemy said. “Please come with me.”

Listlessly, Draco rose up, and followed her out of the office. Seeing Harry Potter waiting beside her gave him some pause, but then his mind simply shut it out.

“Here’s the last thing,” Harry Potter said. “I found it in a folded parchment whose outside said that it was the last weapon to be used against House Malfoy, telling me not to read any further until the whole war hung in the balance. I didn’t want to tell it to you before because I thought it might prejudice your decision unfairly. If you were a good person who never killed or lied, but you had to do one or the other, which would be worse?”

Draco ignored him and continued in Headmistress McGonagall’s company, leaving Harry behind looking sadly after.

They came to the Headmistress’s old office, where she lit her Floo-fire with a wave of her wand, said to the green flame “Gringotts travel office” and stepped through after a firm glance in his direction.

For lack of any other option, Draco Malfoy followed.

She lay in bed, feeling more listless than usual that morning, awoken too early with the Sun just beginning to rise – though the direct sunlight was blocked by the skyscrapers that shadowed her house. A faint tinge of hangover gnawed at her temples, dried her mouth; she tried to be sparing with the drink (though she didn’t know why she bothered) but yesterday she’d felt … even more depressed than usual, like she’d lost something, somehow. Not for the first time, not for the hundredth time, she thought about moving – to Adelaide, to Perth, maybe to Perth Amboy if that was what it took. She always had the sense there was somewhere else she ought to be; but while she could live a comfortable life on the payments the insurance company made to her, she couldn’t afford luxuries. She couldn’t pay to go gallivanting around the world looking for someplace that fit her unsatisfied sense of belonging. She’d watched the TV for long enough, she’d rented enough travelogues, to know that nowhere the VCR showed her gave her any more sense of rightness than Sydney.

She’d felt frozen, stopped in time, ever since the traffic accident that had stolen her memories – not just of a dead family that meant nothing to her now, but memories like how a stove worked. She suspected, no, she knew, that whatever her heart was waiting for, whatever key needed to turn inside her to make her life begin moving again, it was one more thing she’d lost to that runaway minivan. She thought about that almost every morning, trying to guess what she was missing, missing, missing from her life and mind.

Somebody rang her doorbell.

She groaned, turning her head far enough to look at the LED alarm clock at the side of her bed. 6:31, it said, with the AM dot lit. Seriously? Well, that idiot could wait while she staggered out of bed at her own pace, then.

Stagger out of bed she did, ignoring the doorbell as it rang again, as she ducked into the bathroom and dressed herself.

She clambered down the stairs, ignoring the ever-nagging sense that someone else ought to be answering her door for her. “Who’s there?” she called to the closed door; the door had a peephole, but it was fogged over.

“Are you Nancy Manson?” came a woman’s voice, speaking in a precise Scottish accent.

“Yes,” she said cautiously.

“Eunoe,” spoke the Scottish voice, and Nancy leapt back in shock as a flash of light came from the door and hit her and …

Nancy swayed, putting a hand to her forehead. Flashes of light just going through doors and hitting people, that was … that was … that wasn’t particularly surprising …

“Would you please open the door?” said the Scottish woman’s voice. “The war is over and your memories should be returning shortly. There’s someone here who ought to see you.”

My memories –

Nancy’s head was already feeling clogged, like she was about to start hacking something out of her brain, but she managed to reach out and yank the door open.

There in front of her was a woman dressed as a (perfectly normal) witch, from black robes to tall pointed hat –

- and standing beside her a boy, with short white-blonde hair and wearing (perfectly normal) dark robes trimmed in green, staring at her with his jaw dropped and eyes wide and beginning to fill with tears.

Green-trimmed robes and white-blonde hair …

Something warm stirred in her memory. She felt her heart rising into her throat as she realized that the thing that she’d been looking for these past ten years might be right in front of her this very instant. Somewhere deep inside her, ice was cracking around her heart, the piece of her that had been stopped for so long preparing to move once more.

The boy was staring at her, his mouth working soundlessly.

A mysterious name came into her mind, rose to her lips.

“Lucius?” she whispered.

The next update will be on March 13th, 2015 at 12PM Pacific (7PM UTC).

A good place to start reading Pratchett is with the book Mort.

Chapter 121. Something to Protect: Severus Snape

A somber mood pervaded the Headmistress’s office. Minerva had returned after dropping off Draco and Narcissa/Nancy at St. Mungo’s, where the Lady Malfoy was being examined to see if a decade living as a Muggle had done any damage to her health; and Harry had come up to the Headmistress’s office again and then … not been able to think of priorities. There was so much to do, so many things, that even Headmistress McGonagall didn’t seem to know where to start, and certainly not Harry. Right now Minerva was repeatedly writing words on parchment and then erasing them with a handwave, and Harry had closed his eyes for clarity. Was there any next first thing that needed to happen …

There came a knock upon the great oaken door that had been Dumbledore’s, and the Headmistress opened it with a word.

The man who entered the Headmistress’s office appeared worn, he had discarded his wheelchair but still walked with a limp. He wore black robes that were simple, yet clean and unstained. Over his left shoulder was slung a knapsack, of sturdy gray leather set with silver filigree that held four green pearl-like stones. It looked like a thoroughly enchanted knapsack, one that could contain the contents of a Muggle house.

One look at him, and Harry knew.

Headmistress McGonagall sat frozen behind her new desk.

Severus Snape inclined his head to her.

“What is the meaning of this?” said the Headmistress, sounding … heart-sick, like she’d known, upon a glance, just like Harry had.

“I resign my position as the Potions Master of Hogwarts,” the man said simply. “I will not stay to draw my last month’s salary. If there are students who have been particularly harmed by me, you may use the money for their benefit.”

He knows. The thought came to Harry, and he couldn’t have said in words just what the Potions Master now knew; except that it was clear that Severus knew it.

“Severus …” Headmistress McGonagall began. Her voice sounded hollow. “Professor Severus Snape, you may not realize how difficult it is to find Potions Masters who can safely teach Muggleborns, or Professors sharp enough to keep Slytherin House in any semblance of order …”

Again the man inclined his head. “I think it need not be said to you, Headmistress, but I recommend in the strongest possible terms that the next Head of Slytherin be nothing like me.”

“Severus, you only did as Albus told you to do! You could stay on and act differently!”

“Headmistress,” Harry said. His own voice seemed also hollow, and Harry wondered at it, for he hadn’t known Severus Snape that well. “If he wants to go, I think you should let him go.”

Dumbledore was using him. Maybe not exactly the way Professor Quirrell thought, maybe it was prophecy rather than sabotaging Slytherin, but Dumbledore was still using him. There were things that could have been said long ago to Severus, to free him. It’s clear why Dumbledore didn’t risk that, but still, Severus wasn’t being used kindly. Even his blindness and grief were being used, the way he didn’t grasp the consequences of his actions as Potions Master …

“It is well to find you here, Mr Potter,” Severus said. “There is unfinished business between us.”

Harry didn’t know what to say, so he just nodded.

Severus seemed to be having some difficulty speaking, as he stood before the two of them with the grey knapsack on his shoulder. Finally he seemed to find the words he’d come to speak. “Your mother. Lily. She was –”

“I know,” Harry said, through the thickness of his throat. “You don’t have to say it.”

“Lily was a fine upstanding witch, Mr Potter. I would not have you think otherwise from any words I said to you.”

“Severus?” said Minerva McGonagall, looking as shocked as if she’d been bitten by her own shoes.

The former Potions Master kept his eyes on Harry. “More than one bar lay between myself and Lily, most notably my ill-advised attempts to curry favor with the purebloods of my house. If I made it sound like one mistake upon a muddy field ended it all, if I pretended that she had no reason but shallowness not to love me, I hope your books have also told you why fools may say such things.”

“They did,” Harry said. He was looking at the fine gray knapsack on Severus Snape’s left shoulder, unable to meet the Potions Master’s eyes. “They did.”

“However,” the former Potions Master continued, “I’m afraid I have nothing more to say about your father than what I’ve already told you.”

“Severus!”

The former Potions Master seemed to have eyes only for Harry. “The Dark Mark upon my arm is not dead, nor is the prophecy fulfilled by that story you recounted before the crowd. How did you destroy all but a remnant of the Dark Lord?”

Harry hesitated. “I Obliviated most of his memories and … sealed him, I guess is how wizards say it. Even if the seal breaks, he won’t come back as himself.”

Severus frowned briefly and then shrugged. “I suppose that is acceptable.”

“Professor Snape,” Harry said, because this too was now his responsibility, “the Order of the Phoenix owes you for services rendered. I’m in an excellent position to repay it, both financially and magically. Just in case you want to start your next life in a position of wealth, or with better hair, or something.”

“Strange words to say to such as me,” the former Potions Master said in a soft drawl. “I went to the Dark Lord intending to sell him the prophecy in exchange for Lily’s love becoming mine, by whatever darkness was required to achieve it. That is hardly something to be forgiven lightly. And then, in the years after when I was a Potions Master … that you experienced yourself. Do you think my service to the Order of the Phoenix has repaid all my sins?”

“People are always broken,” Harry said, though the words stuck in his throat. “They always make mistakes. At least you tried to repay them.”

“Perhaps,” said the former Potions Master. “My final duty was to fail in guarding the Stone, to be struck down. This I have done, and I survived it, which I never expected to do.” Severus was leaning against the door through which he’d entered, taking his weight off his left leg. “I would not have thought to ask for your forgiveness, but since you offer it so freely, I will accept with thanks. From this day on I wish to take less unkindly ways, and I think that is best done by starting over.”

Tears glistened on Minerva McGonagall’s nose and cheeks, when she spoke her voice was without hope. “Surely you could start over inside Hogwarts.”

Severus shook his head. “Too many students would remember me as the evil Potions Master. No, Minerva. I will go someplace new, and take a new name, and find someone new to love.”

“Severus Snape,” Harry said, because it was his responsibility to say it, “has all your will been done?”

“Lily’s killer is vanquished,” the man said. “I am content.”

The Headmistress lowered her head. “Be well, Severus,” she whispered.

“I do have one last piece of advice,” Harry said. “If you want it.”

“What is it?” said Severus Snape.

“Ruminating about the past can contribute to depression. You have my blanket permisson to just never think about your past, ever. You shouldn’t think that it’s your responsibility to Lily to bear your guilt for her, or anything like that. Just keep your mind on your future and whatever new people you meet.”

“I shall take your wisdom into consideration,” Severus said neutrally.

“Also, try a different brand of hair shampoo.”

A wry grin crossed Severus’s face, and Harry thought it might have been, for the first time, that man’s true smile. “Drop dead, Potter.”

Harry laughed.

Severus laughed.

Minerva was sobbing.

Without saying anything else, the free man took a pinch of Floo powder, and cast it into the office’s fireplace, and strode into the green flame whispering something that nobody caught; and that was the last that anyone ever heard of Severus Snape.

The last chapter will post on March 14th, 2015, at 9AM Pacific (4PM UTC).
Thank you all for reading.

Omake Files 1, 2, 3

Hail the Dark Lord Rowling.

‘Omake’ is a non-canonical extra.

OMAKE FILES #1: 72 Hours to Victory

(A.k.a. ‘What Happens If You Change Harry But Leave All Other Characters Constant’)

Dumbledore peered over his desk at young Harry, twinkling in a kindly sort of way. The boy had come to him with a terribly intense look on his childish face – Dumbledore hoped that whatever this matter was, it wasn’t too serious. Harry was far too young for his life trials to be starting already. ‘What was it you wished to speak to me about, Harry?’

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres leaned forward in his chair, smiling grimly. ‘Headmaster, I got a sharp pain in my scar during the Sorting Feast. Considering how and where I got this scar, it didn’t seem like the sort of thing I should just ignore. I thought at first it was because of Professor Snape, but I followed the Baconian experimental method which is to find the conditions for both the presence and the absence of the phenomenon, and I’ve determined that my scar hurts if and only if I’m facing the back of Professor Quirrell’s head, whatever’s under his turban. While it could be something more innocuous, I think we should provisionally assume the worst, that it’s You-Know-Who – wait, don’t look so horrified, this is actually a priceless opportunity –’

OMAKE FILES #2: I Ain’t Afraid of Dark Lords

This was the original version of Chapter 9. It was replaced because – while many readers did enjoy it – many other readers had massive allergies to songs in fanfics, for reasons that should not much need belaboring. I didn’t want to drive readers away before they got to Ch. 10.

Lee Jordan is the fellow prankster of Fred and George (in canon). ‘Lee Jordan’ had sounded like a Muggleborn name to me, implying that he would be capable of instructing Fred and George on a tune that Harry would know. This was not as obvious to some readers as it was to your author.

Draco went to Slytherin, and Harry breathed a small sigh of relief. It had seemed like a sure thing, but you never did know what tiny event might upset the course of your master plan.

They were approaching the Ps now …

And over at the Gryffindor table, there was a whispered conversation.

‘What if he doesn’t like it?’

‘He’s got no right to not like it –’

‘– not after the prank he played on –’

‘– Neville Longbottom, his name was –’

‘– he’s as fair a fair target now as fair can be.’

‘All right. Just make sure you don’t forget your parts.’

‘We’ve rehearsed it often enough –’

‘- over the last three hours.’

And Minerva McGonagall, from where she stood at the speaker’s podium of the Head Table, looked down at the next name on her list. Please don’t let him be a Gryffindor please don’t let him be a Gryffindor OH PLEASE don’t let him be a Gryffindor … She took a deep breath, and called:

‘Potter, Harry!’

There was a sudden silence in the hall as all whispered conversation stopped.

A silence broken by a horrible buzzing noise that modulated and changed in hideous mockery of musical melody.

Minerva’s head jerked around, shocked, and identified the buzzing noise as coming from the Gryffindor direction, where They were standing on top of the table blowing into some kind of tiny devices held against Their lips. Her hand started to drop to her wand, to Silencio the lot of Them, but another sound stopped her.

Dumbledore was chuckling.

Minerva’s eyes went back to Harry Potter, who had only just started to step out of line before he’d stumbled and halted.

Then the young boy began to walk again, moving his legs in odd sweeping motions, and waving his arms back and forth and snapping his fingers, in synchrony with Their music.

To the tune of ‘Ghostbusters’

(As performed on the kazoo by Fred and George Weasley,
and sung by Lee Jordan.)

.

There’s a Dark Lord near?
Got no need to fear
Who you gonna call?

‘HARRY POTTER!’ shouted Lee Jordan, and the Weasley twins performed a triumphant chorus.

With a Killing Curse?
Well it could be worse.
Who you gonna call?

‘HARRY POTTER!’ There were a lot more voices shouting it this time.

The Weasley Horrors went off into an extended wailing, now accompanied by some of the older Muggleborns, who had produced their own tiny devices, Transfigured out of the school silverware no doubt. As their music reached its anticlimax, Harry Potter shouted:

I ain’t afraid of Dark Lords!

There was cheering then, especially from the Gryffindor table, and more students produced their own antimusical instruments. The hideous buzzings redoubled in volume and built to another awful crescendo:

I ain’t afraid of Dark Lords!

Minerva glanced to both sides of the Head Table, afraid to look but with all too good a notion of what she would see.

Trelawney frantically fanning herself, Flitwick looking on with curiosity, Hagrid clapping along to the music, Sprout looking severe, and Quirrell gazing at the boy with sardonic amusement. Directly to her left, Dumbledore humming along; and directly to her right, Snape gripping his empty wine goblet, white-knuckled, so hard that the thick silver was slowly deforming.

Dark robes and a mask?
Impossible task?
Who you gonna call?
HARRY POTTER!

Giant Fire-Ape?
Old bat in a cape?
Who you gonna call?
HARRY POTTER!

Minerva’s lips set in a white line. She would have words with Them about that last verse, if They thought she was powerless because it was the first day of school and Gryffindor had no points to take away. If They didn’t care about detentions then she would find something else.

Then, with a sudden gasp of horror, she looked in Snape’s direction, surely he realised the Potter boy must have no idea who that was talking about –

Snape’s face had gone beyond rage into a kind of pleasant indifference. A faint smile played about his lips. He was looking in the direction of Harry Potter, not the Gryffindor table, and his hands held the crumpled remains of a former wine goblet …

And Harry walked forwards, sweeping his arms and legs through the motions of the Ghostbusters dance, keeping a smile on his face. It was a great setup, had caught him completely by surprise. The least he could do was play along and not ruin it all.

Everyone was cheering him. It made him feel all warm inside and sort of awful at the same time.

They were cheering him for a job he’d done when he was one year old. A job he hadn’t really finished. Somewhere, somehow, the Dark Lord was still alive. Would they have been cheering quite so hard, if they knew that?

But the Dark Lord’s power had been broken once.

And Harry would protect them again. If there was in fact a prophecy and that was what it said. Well, actually regardless of what any darn prophecy said.

All those people believing in him and cheering him – Harry couldn’t stand to let that be false. To flash and fade like so many other child prodigies. To be a disappointment. To fail to live up to his reputation as a symbol of the Light, never mind how he’d gotten it. He would absolutely, positively, no matter how long it took and even if it killed him, fulfill their expectations. And then go on to exceed those expectations, so that people wondered, looking back, that they had once asked so little of him.

And he shouted out the lie that he’d invented because it scanned well and the song called for it:

I ain’t afraid of Dark Lords!
I ain’t afraid of Dark Lords!

Harry took his last steps toward the Sorting Hat as the music ended. He swept a bow to the Order of Chaos at the Gryffindor table, and then turned and swept another bow to the other side of the hall, and waited for the applause and giggling to die away …

omake files #3: Alternate Endings of Self-Awareness

The offer to tell the whole plot to anyone who guessed what has never happened before spurred a lot of interesting attempts. The first omake below is taken directly from my personal favourite answer, by Meteoricshipyards. The second is based on Kazuma’s suggestion for what ‘has never happened before’, the third on a combination of yoyoente and dougal74, the fourth on wolf550e’s review of chapter 10. The one that starts with K, and the one just above that, are from DarkHeart81. The others are my own. Anyone who wants to pick up one of my own ideas and run with them, particularly the last one, is welcome to do so. And before I get 100 indignant complaints, yes, I am well aware that the legislative body of the UK is the House of Commons in Parliament.

… In the back of his mind, he wondered if the Sorting Hat was genuinely conscious in the sense of being aware of its own awareness, and if so, whether it was satisfied with only getting to talk to eleven-year-olds once per year. Its song had implied so: Oh, I’m the Sorting Hat and I’m okay, I sleep all year and I work one day …

When there was once more silence in the room, Harry sat on the stool and carefully placed onto his head the 800-year-old telepathic artefact of forgotten magic.

Thinking, just as hard as he could: Don’t Sort me yet! I have questions I need to ask you! Have I ever been Obliviated? Did you Sort the Dark Lord when he was a child and can you tell me about his weaknesses? Can you tell me why I got the brother wand to the Dark Lord’s? Is the Dark Lord’s ghost bound to my scar and is that why I get so angry sometimes? Those are the most important questions, but if you’ve got another moment can you tell me anything about how to rediscover the lost magics that created you?

And the Sorting Hat answered, ‘No. Yes. No. No. Yes and no, next time don’t ask double questions. No.’ and out loud, ‘Ravenclaw!’

‘Oh, dear. This has never happened before …’

What?

‘I’m allergic to your hair shampoo –’

And then the Sorting Hat sneezed, with a mighty ‘A-CHOO!’ that echoed around the Great Hall.

‘Well!’ Dumbledore cried jovially. ‘It seems Harry Potter has been sorted into the new House of Achoo! McGonagall, you can serve as the Head of House Achoo. You’d better hurry up on making arrangements for Achoo’s curriculum and classes, tomorrow is the first day!’

‘But, but, but,’ stammered McGonagall, her mind in nearly complete disarray, ‘who will be Head of House Gryffindor?’ It was all she could think of, she had to stop this somehow …

Dumbledore put a finger to his cheek, looking thoughtful. ‘Snape.’

Snape’s screech of protest nearly drowned out McGonagall’s, ‘Then who will be Head of Slytherin?’

‘Hagrid.’

Don’t Sort me yet! I have questions I need to ask you! Have I ever been Obliviated? Did you Sort the Dark Lord when he was a child and can you tell me about his weaknesses? Can you tell me why I got the brother wand to the Dark Lord’s? Is the Dark Lord’s ghost bound to my scar and is that why I get so angry sometimes? Those are the most important questions, but if you’ve got another moment can you tell me anything about how to rediscover the lost magics that created you?

There was a brief pause.

Hello? Do I need to repeat the questions?

The Sorting Hat screamed, an awful high-pitched sound that echoed through the Great Hall and caused most of the students to clap their hands over their ears. With a desperate yowl, it leapt off Harry Potter’s head and bounded across the floor, pushing itself along with its brim, and made it halfway to the Head Table before it exploded.

‘Slytherin!’

Seeing the look of horror on Harry Potter’s face, Fred Weasley thought faster than he ever had in his life. In a single motion he whipped out his wand, whispered ‘Silencio!’ and then ‘Changemyvoiceio!’ and finally ‘Ventriliquo!’

‘Just kidding!’ said Fred Weasley. ‘Gryffindor!’

‘Oh, dear. This has never happened before …’

What?

‘Ordinarily I would refer such questions to the Headmaster, who could ask me in turn, if he wished. But some of the information you’ve asked for is not only beyond your own user level, but beyond the Headmaster’s.’

How can I raise my user level?

‘I’m afraid I am not allowed to answer that question at your current user level.’

What options are available at my user level?

After that it didn’t take long –

‘Root!’

‘Oh, dear. This has never happened before …’

What?

‘I’ve had to tell students before that they were mothers – it would break your heart to know what I saw in their minds – but this is the first time I’ve ever had to tell someone they were a father.’

WHAT?

‘Draco Malfoy is carrying your baby.’

WHAAAAAAAT?

‘To repeat: Draco Malfoy is carrying your baby.’

But we’re only eleven –

‘Actually, Draco is secretly thirteen years old.’

B-b-but men can’t get pregnant –

‘And a girl under those clothes.’

But we’ve never had sex, you idiot!

‘She obliviated you after the rape, moron!’

Harry Potter fainted. His unconscious body fell off the stool with a dull thud.

‘Ravenclaw!’ called out the Hat from where it lay on top of his head. That had been even funnier than its first idea.

‘Elf!’

Huh? Harry remembered Draco mentioning a House Elf, but what was that exactly?

Judging by the appalled looks dawning on the faces around him, it wasn’t anything good –

‘Pancakes!’

‘Representatives!’

‘Oh, dear. This has never happened before …’

What?

‘I’ve never Sorted someone who was a reincarnation of Godric Gryffindor AND Salazar Slytherin AND Naruto.’

‘Atreides!’

‘Fooled you again! Hufflepuff! Slytherin! Hufflepuff!’

‘Pickled stewberries!’

‘Khaaannnn!’

At the Head Table, Dumbledore went on smiling benignly; small metallic sounds occasionally came from Snape’s direction as he idly compacted the twisted remains of what had once been a heavy silver wine goblet; and Minerva McGonagall clenched the podium in a white-knuckled grip, knowing that Harry Potter’s contagious chaos had infected the Sorting Hat itself.

Scenario after scenario played out through Minerva’s head, each worse than the last. The Hat would say that Harry was too evenly balanced between Houses to Sort, and decide that he belonged to all of them. The Hat would proclaim that Harry’s mind was too strange to be Sorted. The Hat would demand that Harry be expelled from Hogwarts. The Hat had gone into a coma. The Hat would insist that a whole new House of Doom be created just to accomodate Harry Potter, and Dumbledore would make her do it …

Minerva remembered what Harry had told her in that disastrous trip to Diagon Alley, about the … planning fallacy, she thought it had been … and how people were usually too optimistic, even when they thought they were being pessimistic. It was the sort of information that preyed on your mind, dwelling in it and spinning off nightmares …

But what was the worst that could happen?

Well … in the worst-case scenario, the Hat would assign Harry to a whole new House. Dumbledore would insist that she do it – create a whole new House just for him – and she’d have to rearrange all the class schedules on the first day of term. And Dumbledore would remove her as Head of House Gryffindor, and give her beloved House over to … Professor Binns, the History ghost; and she would be assigned as Head of Harry’s House of Doom; and she would futilely try to give the child orders, deducting point after point without effect, while disaster after disaster was blamed on her.

Was that the worst-case scenario?

Minerva honestly didn’t see how it could be any worse than that.

And even in the very worst case – no matter what happened with Harry – it would all be over in seven years.

Minerva felt her knuckles slowly relax their white-knuckled grip on the podium. Harry had been right, there was a kind of comfort in staring directly into the furthest depths of the darkness, knowing that you had confronted your worst fears and were now prepared.

The frightened silence was broken by a single word.

‘Headmaster!’ called the Sorting Hat.

At the Head Table, Dumbledore rose, his face puzzled. ‘Yes?’ he addressed the Hat. ‘What is it?’

‘I wasn’t talking to you,’ said the Hat. ‘I was Sorting Harry Potter into the place in Hogwarts where he most belongs, namely the Headmaster’s office –’

The trunk shop was more richly appointed than any other shop Harry had visited; the curtains were lush and delicately patterned, the floor and walls of stained and polished wood, and the trunks occupied places of honour on polished ivory platforms. The salesman was dressed in robes of finery only a cut below those of Lucius Malfoy, and spoke with exquisite, oily politeness to both Harry and Professor McGonagall.

Harry had asked his questions, and had gravitated to a trunk of heavy-looking wood, not polished but warm and solid, carved with the pattern of a guardian dragon whose eyes shifted to look at anyone nearing it. A trunk charmed to be light, to shrink on command, to sprout small clawed tentacles from its bottom and squirm after its owner. A trunk with two drawers on each of four sides that each slid out to reveal compartments as deep as the whole trunk. A lid with four locks each of which would reveal a different space inside. And – this was the important part – a handle on the bottom which slid out a frame containing a staircase leading down into a small, lighted room that would hold, Harry estimated, around twelve bookcases.

If they made luggage like this, Harry didn’t know why anyone bothered owning a house.

One hundred and eight golden Galleons. That was the price of a good trunk, lightly used. At around fifty British pounds to the Galleon, that was enough to buy a second-hand car. It would be more expensive than everything else Harry had ever bought in his whole life all put together.

Ninety-seven Galleons. That was how much was left in the bag of gold Harry had been allowed to take out of Gringotts.

Professor McGonagall wore a look of chagrin upon her face. After a long day’s shopping she hadn’t needed to ask Harry how much gold was left in the bag, after the salesman quoted his price, which meant the Professor could do good mental arithmetic without pen and paper. Once again, Harry reminded himself that scientifically illiterate was not at all the same thing as stupid.

‘I’m sorry, young man,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘This is entirely my fault. I would offer to take you back to Gringotts, but the bank will be closed for all but emergency services now.’

Harry looked at her, wondering …

‘Well,’ sighed Professor McGonagall, as she swung on one heel, ‘we may as well go, I suppose.’

… she hadn’t lost it completely when a child had dared defy her. She hadn’t been happy, but she had thought instead of exploding in fury. It might have just been that there was an immortal Dark Lord to fight – that she had needed Harry’s goodwill. But most adults wouldn’t have been capable of thinking even that much; wouldn’t consider future consequences at all, if someone lower in status had refused to obey them …

‘Professor?’ Harry said.

The witch turned back and looked at him.

Harry took a deep breath. He needed to be a little angry for what he wanted to try now, there was no way he’d have the courage to do it otherwise. She didn’t listen to me, he thought to himself, I would have taken more gold but she didn’t want to listen … Focusing his entire world on McGonagall and the need to bend this conversation to his will, he spoke.

‘Professor, you thought one hundred Galleons would be more than enough for a trunk. That’s why you didn’t bother warning me before it went down to ninety-seven. Which is just the sort of thing the research studies show – that’s what happens when people think they’re leaving themselves a little error margin. They’re not pessimistic enough. If it’d been up to me, I’d have taken two hundred Galleons just to be sure. There was plenty of money in that vault, and I could have put back any extra later. But I thought you wouldn’t let me do it. I thought you’d be angry at me just for asking. Was I wrong?’

‘I suppose I must confess that you are right,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘But, young man –’

‘That sort of thing is the reason why I have trouble trusting adults.’ Somehow Harry kept his voice steady. ‘Because they get angry if you even try to reason with them. To them it’s defiance and insolence and a challenge to their higher tribal status. If you try to talk to them they get angry. So if I had anything really important to do, I wouldn’t be able to trust you. Even if you listened with deep concern to whatever I said – because that’s also part of the role of someone playing a concerned adult – you’d never change your actions, you wouldn’t actually behave differently, because of anything I said.’

The salesman was watching them both with unabashed fascination.

‘I can understand your point of view,’ Professor McGonagall said eventually. ‘If I sometimes seem too strict, please remember that I have served as Head of Gryffindor House for what feels like several thousand years.’

Harry nodded and continued. ‘So – suppose I had a way to get more Galleons from my vault without us going back to Gringotts, but it involved me violating the role of an obedient child. Would I be able to trust you with that, even though you’d have to step outside your own role as Professor McGonagall to take advantage of it?’

‘What?’ said Professor McGonagall.

‘To put it another way, if I could make today have happened differently, so that we didn’t take too little money with us, would that be all right even though it would involve a child being insolent to an adult in retrospect?’

‘I … suppose …’ the witch said, looking quite puzzled.

Harry took out the mokeskin pouch, and said, ‘Eleven Galleons originally from my family vault.’

And there was gold in Harry’s hand.

For a moment Professor McGonagall’s mouth gaped wide, then her jaw snapped shut and her eyes narrowed and the witch bit out, ‘Where did you get that –’

‘From my family vault, like I said.’

‘How?’

‘Magic.’

‘That’s hardly an answer!’ snapped Professor McGonagall, and then stopped, blinking.

‘No, it isn’t, is it? I ought to claim that it’s because I experimentally discovered the true secrets of how the pouch works and that it can actually retrieve objects from anywhere, not just its own inside, if you phrase the request correctly. But actually it’s from when I fell into that pile of gold before and I shoved some Galleons into my pocket. Anyone who understands pessimism knows that money is something you might need quickly and without much warning. So now are you angry at me for defying your authority? Or glad that we succeeded in our important mission?’

The salesman’s eyes were wide like saucers.

And the tall witch stood there, silent.

‘Discipline at Hogwarts must be enforced,’ she said after almost a full minute. ‘For the sake of all the students. And that must include courtesy and obedience from you to all professors.’

‘I understand, Professor McGonagall.’

‘Good. Now let us buy that trunk and go home.’

Harry felt like throwing up, or cheering, or fainting, or something. That was the first time his careful reasoning had ever worked on anyone. Maybe because it was also the first time he had something really serious that an adult needed from him, but still –

Minerva McGonagall, +1 point.

Harry bowed, and gave the bag of gold and the extra eleven Galleons into McGonagall’s hands. ‘Thank you very much, Professor. Can you finish up the purchase for me? I’ve got to visit the lavatory.’

The salesman, unctuous once more, pointed toward a door set into the wall with a gold-handled knob. As Harry started to walk away, he heard the salesman ask in his oily voice, ‘May I inquire as to who that was, Madam McGonagall? I take it he is Slytherin – third-year, perhaps? – and from a prominent family, but I did not recognise –’

The slam of the lavatory door cut off his words, and after Harry had identified the lock and pressed it into place, he grabbed the magical self-cleaning towel and, with shaky hands, wiped moisture off his forehead. Harry’s entire body was sheathed in sweat which had soaked clear through his Muggle clothing, though at least it didn’t show through the robes.

The Sun was setting and it was very late indeed, by the time they stood again in the courtyard of the Leaky Cauldron, the silent leaf-dusted interface between magical Britain’s Diagon Alley and the entire Muggle world. (That was one awfully decoupled economy … ) Harry was to go to a phone box and call his father, once he was on the other side. He didn’t need to worry about his luggage being stolen, apparently. His trunk had the status of a major magical item, something that most Muggles wouldn’t notice; that was part of what you could get in the wizarding world, if you were willing to pay the price of a second-hand car.

‘So here we part ways, for a time,’ Professor McGonagall said. She shook her head in wonderment. ‘This has been the strangest day of my life for … many a year. Since the day I learned that a child had defeated You-Know-Who. I wonder now, looking back, if that was the last reasonable day of the world.’

Oh, like she had anything to complain about. You think your day was surreal? Try mine.

‘I was very impressed with you today,’ Harry said to her. ‘I should have remembered to compliment you out loud, I was awarding you points in my head and everything.’

‘Thank you, Mr Potter,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘If you had already been sorted into a House I would have deducted so many points that your grandchildren would still be losing the House Cup.’

‘Thank you, Professor.’ It was probably too early to call her Minnie.

This woman might well be the sanest adult Harry had ever met, despite her lack of scientific background. Harry was even considering offering her the number-two position in whatever group he formed to fight the Dark Lord, though he wasn’t silly enough to say that out loud. Now what would be a good name for that … ? The Death Eater Eaters?

‘I’ll see you again soon, when school starts,’ Professor McGonagall said. ‘And, Mr Potter, about your wand –’

‘I know what you’re going to ask,’ Harry said. He took out his precious wand and, with a deep twinge of inner pain, flipped it over in his hand, presenting her with the handle. ‘Take it. I hadn’t planned to do anything, not a single thing, but I don’t want you to have nightmares about me blowing up my house.’

Professor McGonagall shook her head rapidly. ‘Oh no, Mr Potter! That isn’t done. I only meant to warn you not to use your wand at home, since the Ministry can detect under-age magic and it is prohibited without supervision.’

‘Ah,’ Harry said. ‘That sounds like a very sensible rule. I’m glad to see the wizarding world takes that sort of thing seriously.’

Professor McGonagall peered hard at him. ‘You really mean that.’

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘I get it. Magic is dangerous and the rules are there for good reasons. Certain other matters are also dangerous. I get that too. Remember that I am not stupid.’

‘I am unlikely ever to forget it. Thank you, Harry, that does make me feel better about entrusting you with certain things. Goodbye for now.’

Harry turned to go, into the Leaky Cauldron and out towards the Muggle world.

As his hand touched the back door’s handle, he heard a last whisper from behind him.

‘Hermione Granger.’

‘What?’ Harry said, his hand still on the door.

‘Look for a first-year girl named Hermione Granger on the train to Hogwarts.’

‘Who is she?’

There was no answer, and when Harry turned around, Professor McGonagall was gone.

Headmaster Albus Dumbledore leaned forward over his desk. His twinkling eyes peered out at Minerva. ‘So, my dear, how did you find Harry?’

Minerva opened her mouth. Then she closed her mouth. Then she opened her mouth again. No words came out.

‘I see,’ Albus said gravely. ‘Thank you for your report, Minerva. You may go.’

It was later in the day, the Sun lowering in the summer sky and shoppers beginning to peter out from the streets. Some shops had already closed; Harry and Professor McGonagall had bought his textbooks from Flourish and Blotts just under the deadline. With only a slight explosion when Harry had made a beeline for the keyword ‘Arithmancy’ and discovered that the seventh-year textbooks invoked nothing more mathematically advanced than trigonometry.

At this moment, though, dreams of low-hanging research fruit were far from Harry’s mind.

At this moment, the two of them were walking out of Ollivander’s, and Harry was staring at his wand. He’d waved it, and produced multicoloured sparks, which really shouldn’t have come as such an extra shock after everything else he’d seen, but somehow –

I can do magic.

Me. As in, me personally. I am magical; I am a wizard.

He had felt the magic pouring up his arm, and in that instant, realised that he had always had that sense, that he had possessed it his whole life, the sense that was not sight or sound or smell or taste or touch but only magic. Like having eyes but keeping them always closed, so that you didn’t even realise that you were seeing darkness; and then one day the eye opened, and saw the world. The shock of it had poured through him, touching pieces of himself, awakening them, and then died away in seconds; leaving only the certain knowledge that he was now a wizard, and always had been, and had even, in some strange way, always known it.

And –

‘It is very curious indeed that you should be destined for this wand when its brother why, its brother gave you that scar.’

That could not possibly be coincidence. There had been thousands of wands in that shop. Well, okay, actually it could be coincidence, there were six billion people in the world and thousand-to-one coincidences happened every day. But Bayes’s Theorem said that any reasonable hypothesis which made it more likely than a thousand-to-one that he’d end up with the brother to the Dark Lord’s wand, was going to have an advantage.

Professor McGonagall had simply said how peculiar and left it at that, which had put Harry into a state of shock at the sheer, overwhelming incuriosity of wizards and witches. In no imaginable world would Harry have just gone ‘Hm’ and walked out of the shop without even trying to come up with a hypothesis for what was going on.

His left hand rose and touched his scar.

What … exactly …

‘You’re a full wizard now,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Congratulations.’

Harry nodded.

‘And what do you think of the wizarding world?’ said she.

‘It’s strange,’ Harry said. ‘I ought to be thinking about everything I’ve seen of magic … everything that I now know is possible, and everything I now know to be a lie, and all the work left before me to understand it. And yet I find myself distracted by relative trivialities like,’ Harry lowered his voice, ‘the whole Boy-Who-Lived thing.’ There didn’t seem to be anyone nearby, but no point tempting fate.

Professor McGonagall ahemmed. ‘Really? You don’t say.’

Harry nodded. ‘Yes. It’s just … odd. To find out that you were part of this grand story, the quest to defeat the great and terrible Dark Lord, and it’s already done. Finished. Completely over with. Like you’re Frodo Baggins and you find out that your parents took you to Mount Doom and had you toss in the Ring when you were one year old and you don’t even remember it.’

Professor McGonagall’s smile had grown somewhat fixed.

‘You know, if I were anyone else, anyone else at all, I’d probably be pretty worried about living up to that start. Gosh, Harry, what have you done since you defeated the Dark Lord? Your own bookshop? That’s great! Say, did you know I named my child after you? But I have hopes that this will not prove to be a problem.’ Harry sighed. ‘Still … it’s almost enough to make me wish that there were some loose ends from the quest, just so I could say that I really, you know, participated somehow.’

‘Oh?’ said Professor McGonagall in an odd tone. ‘What did you have in mind?’

‘Well, for example, you mentioned that my parents were betrayed. Who betrayed them?’

‘Sirius Black,’ the witch said, almost hissing the name. ‘He’s in Azkaban. Wizarding prison.’

‘How probable is it that Sirius Black will break out of prison and I’ll have to track him down and defeat him in some sort of spectacular duel, or better yet put a large bounty on his head and hide out in Australia while I wait for the results?’

Professor McGonagall blinked. Twice. ‘Not likely. No one has ever escaped from Azkaban, and I doubt that he will be the first.’

Harry was a bit sceptical of that ‘no one has ever escaped from Azkaban’ line. Still, maybe with magic you could actually get close to a 100% perfect prison, especially if you had a wand and they did not. The best way to get out would be to not go there in the first place.

‘All right then,’ Harry said. ‘Sounds like it’s been nicely wrapped up.’ He sighed, scrubbing his palm over his head. ‘Or maybe the Dark Lord didn’t really die that night. Not completely. His spirit lingers, whispering to people in nightmares that bleed over into the waking world, searching for a way back into the living lands he swore to destroy, and now, in accordance with the ancient prophecy, he and I are locked in a deadly duel where the winner shall lose and the loser shall win –’

Professor McGonagall’s head swivelled, and her eyes darted around, as though to search the street for listeners.

‘I’m joking, Professor,’ Harry said with some annoyance. Sheesh, why did she always take everything so seriously –

A slow sinking sensation began to dawn in the pit of Harry’s stomach.

Professor McGonagall looked at Harry with a calm expression. A very, very calm expression. Then a smile was put on. ‘Of course you are, Mr Potter.’

Aw crap.

If Harry had needed to formalise the wordless inference that had just flashed into his mind, it would have come out something like, If I estimate the probability of Professor McGonagall doing what I just saw as the result of carefully controlling herself, versus the probability distribution for all the things she would do naturally if I made a bad joke, then this behaviour is significant evidence for her hiding something.

But what Harry actually thought was, Aw crap.

Harry turned his own head to scan the street. Nope, no one nearby. ‘He’s not dead, is he,’ Harry sighed.

‘Mr Potter –’

‘The Dark Lord is alive. Of course he’s alive. It was an act of utter optimism for me to have even dreamed otherwise. I must have taken leave of my senses, I can’t imagine what I was thinking. Just because someone said that his body was found burned to a crisp, I can’t imagine why I would have thought he was dead. Clearly I have much left to learn about the art of proper pessimism.’

‘Mr Potter –’

‘At least tell me there’s not really a prophecy …’ Professor McGonagall was still giving him that bright, fixed smile. ‘Oh, you have got to be kidding me.’

‘Mr Potter, you shouldn’t go inventing things to worry about –’

‘Are you actually going to tell me that? Imagine my reaction later, when I find out that there was something to worry about after all.’

Her fixed smile faltered.

Harry’s shoulders slumped. ‘I have a whole world of magic to analyse. I do not have time for this.’

Then both of them shut up, as a man in flowing orange robes appeared on the street and slowly passed them by; Professor McGonagall’s eyes tracked him, unobtrusively. Harry’s mouth was moving as he chewed hard on his lip, and someone watching closely would have noticed a tiny spot of blood appear.

When the orange-robed man had passed into the distance, Harry spoke again, in a low murmur. ‘Are you going to tell me the truth now, Professor McGonagall? And don’t bother trying to wave it off, I’m not stupid.’

‘You’re eleven years old, Mr Potter!’ she said in a harsh whisper.

‘And therefore subhuman. Sorry … for a moment there, I forgot.’

‘These are dreadful and important matters! They are secret, Mr Potter! It is a catastrophe that you, still a child, know even this much! You must not tell anyone, do you understand? Absolutely no one!’

As sometimes happened when Harry got sufficiently angry, his blood went cold, instead of hot, and a terrible dark clarity descended over his mind, mapping out possible tactics and assessing their consequences with iron realism.

Point out that you have a right to know: failure. Eleven-year-old children do not have rights to know anything, in McGonagall’s eyes.

Say that you will not be friends any more: failure. She does not value your friendship sufficiently.

Point out that you will be in danger if you do not know: failure. Plans have already been made based on your ignorance. The certain inconvenience of rethinking will seem far more unpalatable than the mere uncertain prospect of your coming to harm.

Justice and reason will both fail. You must either find something you have that she wants, or find something you can do which she fears …

Ah.

‘Well then, Professor,’ Harry said in a low, icy tone, ‘it sounds like I have something you want. You can, if you like, tell me the truth, the whole truth, and in return I will keep your secrets. Or you can try to keep me ignorant so you can use me as a pawn, in which case I will owe you nothing.’

McGonagall stopped short in the street. Her eyes blazed and her voice descended into an outright hiss. ‘How dare you!’

‘How dare you!’ he whispered back at her.

‘You would blackmail me?’

Harry’s lips twisted. ‘I am offering you a favour. I am giving you a chance to protect your precious secret. If you refuse I will have every natural motive to make inquiries elsewhere, not to spite you, but because I have to know! Get past your pointless anger at a child who you think ought to obey you, and you’ll realise that any sane adult would do the same! Look at it from my perspective! How would you feel if it was you?’

Harry watched McGonagall, observed her harsh breathing. It occurred to him that it was time to ease off the pressure, let her simmer for a while. ‘You don’t have to decide right away,’ Harry said in a more normal tone. ‘I’ll understand if you want time to think about my offer … but I’ll warn you of one thing,’ Harry said, his voice going colder. ‘Don’t try that Obliviation spell on me. Some time ago I worked out a signal, and I have already sent that signal to myself. If I find that signal and I don’t remember sending it …’ Harry let his voice trail off significantly.

McGonagall’s face was working as her expressions shifted. ‘I … wasn’t thinking of Obliviating you, Mr Potter … but why would you have invented such a signal if you didn’t know about –’

‘I thought of it while reading a Muggle science-fiction book, and said to myself, well, just in case … And no, I won’t tell you the signal, I’m not dumb.’

‘I hadn’t planned to ask,’ McGonagall said. She seemed to fold in on herself, and suddenly looked very old, and very tired. ‘This has been an exhausting day, Mr Potter. Can we get your trunk, and send you home? I will trust you not to speak upon this matter until I have had time to think. Keep in mind that there are only two other people in the whole world who know about this matter, and they are Headmaster Albus Dumbledore and Professor Severus Snape.’

So. New information; that was a peace offering. Harry nodded in acceptance, and turned his head to look forward, and started walking again, as his blood slowly began to warm over once more.

‘So now I’ve got to find some way to kill an immortal Dark Wizard,’ Harry said, and sighed in frustration. ‘I really wish you had told me that before I started shopping.’

Thursday.

If you wanted to be specific, 3:32pm on Thursday afternoon.

Harry and all the other boys in the first year were outside on a grassy field with Madam Hooch, standing next to the Hogwarts supply of broomsticks. The girls would be learning to fly separately. Apparently, for some reason, girls didn’t want to learn how to fly on broomsticks in the presence of boys.

Harry had been a little wobbly all day long. He just couldn’t seem to stop wondering how that particular stable time loop had been selected out of what was, in retrospect, a rather large space of possibilities.

Also: seriously, broomsticks? He was going to fly on, basically, a line segment? Wasn’t that pretty much the single most unstable shape you could possibly find, short of attempting to hold on to a point marble? Who’d selected that design for a flying device, out of all the possibilities? Harry had been hoping that it was just a figure of speech, but no, they were standing in front of what looked for all the world like ordinary wooden kitchen broomsticks. Had someone just got stuck on the idea of broomsticks and failed to consider anything else? It had to be. There was no way that the optimal designs for cleaning kitchens and flying would happen to coincide if you worked them out from scratch.

It was a clear day with a bright blue sky and a brilliant sun that was just begging to get in your eyes and make it impossible to see, if you were trying to fly around the sky. The ground was nice and dry, smelling positively baked, and somehow felt very, very hard under Harry’s shoes.

Harry kept reminding himself that the lowest common denominator of eleven-year-olds was expected to learn this and it couldn’t be that hard.

‘Stick out your right hand over the broom, or left hand if you’re left-handed,’ called Madam Hooch. ‘And say, Up!’

‘Up!’ everyone shouted.

The broomstick leapt eagerly into Harry’s hand.

Which put him at the head of the class, for once. Apparently saying ‘Up!’ was a lot more difficult than it looked, and most of the broomsticks were rolling around on the ground or trying to inch away from their would-be riders.

(Of course Harry would have bet money that Hermione had done at least as well when it came her own turn to try, earlier in the day. There couldn’t possibly be anything he could master on the first try which would baffle Hermione, and if there was and it turned out to be broomstick riding instead of anything intellectual, Harry would just die.)

It took a while for everyone to get a broomstick in front of them. Madam Hooch showed them how to mount and then walked around the field, correcting grips and stances. Apparently even among the few children who’d been allowed to fly at home, they hadn’t been taught to do it correctly.

Madam Hooch surveyed the field of boys, and nodded. ‘Now, when I blow my whistle, you kick off from the ground, hard.’

Harry swallowed hard, trying to quell the queasy feeling in his stomach.

‘Keep your brooms steady, rise a few feet, and then come straight back down by leaning forwards slightly. On my whistle – three – two –’

One of the brooms shot skyward, accompanied by a young boy’s screams – of horror, not delight. The boy was spinning at an awful rate as he ascended, they only got glimpses of his white face –

As though in slow motion, Harry was leaping back off his own broomstick and scrabbling for his wand, though he didn’t really know what he planned to do with it, he’d had exactly two sessions of Charms and the last one had been the Hover Charm but Harry had only been able to cast the spell successfully one time out of three and he certainly couldn’t levitate whole people –

If there is any hidden power in me, let it reveal itself now!

‘Come back, boy!’ shouted Madam Hooch (which had to be the most unhelpful instruction imaginable for dealing with an out-of-control broomstick, from a flying instructor, and a fully automatic section of Harry’s brain added Madam Hooch to his tally of fools).

And the boy was thrown off the broomstick.

He seemed to move very slowly through the air, at first.

‘Wingardium Leviosa!’ screamed Harry.

The spell failed. He could feel it fail.

There was a thud and a distant cracking sound, and the boy lay face down on the grass in a heap.

Harry sheathed his wand and raced forwards at full speed. He arrived at the boy’s side at the same time as Madam Hooch, and Harry reached into his pouch and tried to recall oh god what was the name never mind he’d just try ‘Healer’s Pack!’ and it popped up into his hand and –

‘Broken wrist,’ Madam Hooch said. ‘Calm down, boy, he just has a broken wrist!’

There was a sort of mental lurch as Harry’s mind snapped out of Panic Mode.

The Emergency Healing Pack Plus lay open in front of him, and there was a syringe of liquid fire in Harry’s hand, which would have kept the boy’s brain oxygenated if he’d managed to snap his neck.

‘Ah …’ Harry said in a rather wavering sort of voice. His heart was pounding so loudly that he almost couldn’t hear himself panting for breath. ‘Broken bone … right … Setting String?’

‘That’s for emergencies only,’ snapped Madam Hooch. ‘Put it away, he’s fine.’ She leaned over the boy, offering him a hand. ‘Come on, boy, it’s all right, up you get!’

‘You’re not seriously going to make him ride the broomstick again?’ Harry said in horror.

Madam Hooch sent Harry a glare. ‘Of course not!’ She pulled the boy to his feet using his good arm – Harry saw with a shock that it was Neville Longbottom again, what was with him? – and she turned to all the watching children. ‘None of you is to move while I take this boy to the hospital wing! You leave those brooms where they are or you’ll be out of Hogwarts before you can say “Quidditch.” Come on, dear.’

And Madam Hooch walked off with Neville, who was clutching his wrist and trying to control his sniffles.

When they were out of earshot, one of the Slytherins started giggling.

That set off the others.

Harry turned and looked at them. It seemed like a good time to memorise some faces.

And Harry saw that Draco was strolling towards him, accompanied by Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle. Mr Crabbe wasn’t smiling. Mr Goyle decidedly was. Draco himself was wearing a very controlled face that twitched occasionally, from which Harry inferred that Draco thought it was hilarious but saw no political advantage to be gained by laughing about it now instead of in the Slytherin dungeons afterwards.

‘Well, Potter,’ Draco said in a low voice that didn’t carry, still with that very controlled face that was twitching occasionally, ‘Just wanted to say, when you take advantage of emergencies to demonstrate leadership, you want to look like you’re in total control of the situation, rather than, say, going into a complete panic.’ Mr Goyle giggled, and Draco shot him a quelling look. ‘But you probably scored a few points anyway. You need any help stowing that healer’s kit?’

Harry turned to look at the Healing Pack, which got his own face turned away from Draco. ‘I think I’m fine,’ Harry said. He put the syringe back in its place, redid the latches, and stood up.

Ernie Macmillan arrived just as Harry was feeding the pack back into his mokeskin pouch.

‘Thank you, Harry Potter, on behalf of Hufflepuff,’ Ernie Macmillan said formally. ‘It was a good try and a good thought.’

‘A good thought indeed,’ drawled Draco. ‘Why didn’t anyone in Hufflepuff have their wands out? Maybe if you’d all helped instead of just Potter, you could’ve caught him. I thought Hufflepuffs were supposed to stick together?’

Ernie looked like he was torn between getting angry and wanting to die of shame. ‘We didn’t think of it in time –’

‘Ah,’ said Draco, ‘didn’t think of it, I guess that’s why it’s better to have one Ravenclaw as a friend than all of Hufflepuff.’

Oh, hell, how was Harry supposed to juggle this one … ‘You’re not helping,’ Harry said in a mild tone. Hoping Draco would interpret that as you’re interfering with my plans, please shut up.

‘Hey, what’s this?’ said Mr Goyle. He stooped to the grass and picked up something around the size of a large marble, a glass ball that seemed to be filled with a swirling white mist.

Ernie blinked. ‘Neville’s Remembrall!’

‘What’s a Remembrall?’ asked Harry.

‘It turns red if you’ve forgotten something,’ Ernie said. ‘It doesn’t tell you what you forgot, though. Give it here, please, and I’ll hand it back to Neville later.’ Ernie held out his hand.

A sudden grin flashed across Mr Goyle’s face and he spun around and raced away.

Ernie stood still for a moment in surprise, and then shouted ‘Hey!’ and ran after Mr Goyle.

And Mr Goyle grabbed a broomstick, hopped on with one smooth motion and took to the air.

Harry’s jaw dropped. Hadn’t Madam Hooch said that would get him expelled?

‘That idiot!’ Draco hissed. He opened his mouth to shout –

‘Hey!’ shouted Ernie. ‘That’s Neville’s! Give it back!’

The Slytherins started cheering and hooting.

Draco’s mouth snapped shut. Harry caught the sudden look of indecision on his face.

‘Draco,’ Harry said in a low tone, ‘if you don’t order that idiot back on the ground, the teacher’s going to get back and –’

‘Come and get it, Hufflepuffle!’ shouted Mr Goyle, and a great cheer went up from the Slytherins.

‘I can’t!’ whispered Draco. ‘Everyone in Slytherin would think I’m weak!’

‘And if Mr Goyle gets expelled,’ hissed Harry, ‘your father is going to think you’re a moron!’

Draco’s face twisted in agony.

At that moment –

‘Hey, Slytherslime,’ shouted Ernie, ‘didn’t anyone ever tell you that Hufflepuffs stick together? Wands out, Hufflepuff!’

And there were suddenly a whole lot of wands pointed in Mr Goyle’s direction.

Three seconds later –

‘Wands out, Slytherin!’ said around five different Slytherins.

And there were a whole lot of wands pointed in Hufflepuff’s direction.

Two seconds later –

‘Wands out, Gryffindor!’

‘Do something, Potter!’ whispered Draco. ‘I can’t be the one to stop this it has to be you! I’ll owe you a favour just think of something aren’t you supposed to be brilliant?’

In around five and a half seconds, realised Harry, someone was going to cast the Sumerian Simple Strike Hex and by the time it was over and the teachers were done expelling people the only boys left in his year would be Ravenclaws.

‘Wands out, Ravenclaw!’ shouted Michael Corner who was apparently feeling left out of the disaster.

‘Gregory Goyle!’ screamed Harry. ‘I challenge you to a contest for possession of Neville’s Remembrall!’

There was a sudden pause.

‘Oh, really?’ said Draco in the loudest drawl Harry had ever heard. ‘That sounds interesting. What sort of contest, Potter?’

Er …

‘Contest’ had been as far as Harry’s inspiration had got. What sort of contest, he couldn’t say ‘chess’ because Draco wouldn’t be able to accept without it looking strange, he couldn’t say ‘arm-wrestling’ because Mr Goyle would crush him –

‘How about this?’ Harry said loudly. ‘Gregory Goyle and I stand apart from each other, and no one else is allowed to come near either of us. We don’t use our wands and neither does anyone else. I don’t move from where I’m standing, and neither does he. And if I can get my hands on Neville’s Remembrall, then Gregory Goyle relinquishes all claim to that Remembrall he’s holding and gives it to me.’

There was another pause as people’s looks of relief transmuted to confusion.

‘Hah, Potter!’ said Draco loudly. ‘I’d like to see you do that! Mr Goyle accepts!’

‘It’s on!’ said Harry.

‘Potter, what?’ whispered Draco, which he somehow did without moving his lips.

Harry didn’t know how to answer without moving his.

People were putting their wands away, and Mr Goyle swooped gracefully to the ground, looking rather confused. Some Hufflepuffs started over towards Mr Goyle, but Harry shot them a desperately pleading look and they backed off.

Harry walked toward Mr Goyle and stopped when he was a few paces away, far enough apart that they couldn’t reach each other.

Slowly, deliberately, Harry sheathed his wand.

Everyone else backed away.

Harry swallowed. He knew in broad outline what he wanted to do, but it had to be done in such a way that no one understood what he’d done –

‘All right,’ Harry said loudly. ‘And now …’ He took a deep breath and raised one hand, fingers ready to snap. There were gasps from anyone who’d heard about the pies, which was practically everyone. ‘I call upon the insanity of Hogwarts! Happy happy boom boom swamp swamp swamp!’ And Harry snapped his fingers.

A lot of people flinched.

And nothing happened.

Harry let the silence stretch on for a while, developing, until …

‘Um,’ someone said. ‘Is that it?’

Harry looked at the boy who’d spoken. ‘Look in front of you. You see that patch of ground that looks barren, without any grass on it?’

‘Um, yeah,’ said the boy, a Gryffindor (Dean something?).

‘Dig it up.’

Now Harry was getting a lot of strange looks.

‘Er, why?’ said Dean something.

‘Just do it,’ said Terry Boot in a weary voice. ‘No point asking why, trust me on this one.’

Dean something knelt down and began to scoop away dirt.

After a minute or so, Dean stood up again. ‘There’s nothing there,’ Dean said.

Huh. Harry had been planning to go back in time and bury a treasure map that would lead to another treasure map that would lead to Neville’s Remembrall which he would put there after getting it back from Mr Goyle …

Then Harry realised there was a much simpler way which didn’t threaten the secret of Time-Turners quite as much.

‘Thanks, Dean!’ Harry said loudly. ‘Ernie, would you look around on the ground where Neville fell and see if you can find Neville’s Remembrall?’

People looked even more confused.

‘Just do it,’ said Terry Boot. ‘He’ll keep trying until something works, and the scary thing is that –’

‘Merlin!’ gasped Ernie. He was holding up Neville’s Remembrall. ‘It’s here! Right where he fell!’

‘What?’ cried Mr Goyle. He looked down and saw …

… that he was still holding Neville’s Remembrall.

There was a rather long pause.

‘Er,’ said Dean something, ‘that’s not possible, is it?’

‘It’s a plot hole,’ said Harry. ‘I made myself weird enough to distract the universe for a moment and it forgot that Goyle had already picked up the Remembrall.’

‘No, wait, I mean, that’s totally not possible –’

‘Excuse me, are we all standing around here waiting to go flying on broomsticks? Yes we are. So shut up. Anyway, once I get my hands on Neville’s Remembrall, the contest is over and Gregory Goyle has to relinquish all claim to the Remembrall he’s holding and give it to me. Those were the terms, remember?’ Harry stretched out a hand and beckoned Ernie. ‘Just roll it over here, since no one’s supposed to get close to me, okay?’

‘Hold on!’ shouted a Slytherin – Blaise Zabini, Harry wasn’t likely to forget that name. ‘How do we know that’s Neville’s Remembrall? You could’ve just dropped another Remembrall there –’

‘The Slytherin is strong with this one,’ Harry said, smiling. ‘But you have my word that the one Ernie’s holding is Neville’s. No comment about the one Gregory Goyle’s holding.’

Zabini spun to Draco. ‘Malfoy! You’re not just going to let him get away with that –’

‘Shut up, you,’ rumbled Mr Crabbe, standing behind Draco. ‘Mr Malfoy doesn’t need you to tell him what to do!’

Good minion.

‘My bet was with Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy,’ Harry said. ‘Not with you, Zabini. I have done what Mr Malfoy said he’d like to see me do, and as for the judgement of the bet, I leave that up to Mr Malfoy.’ Harry inclined his head towards Draco and raised his eyebrows slightly. That ought to allow Draco to save enough face.

There was a pause.

‘You promise that actually is Neville’s Remembrall?’ Draco said.

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘That’s the one that’ll go back to Neville and it was his originally. And the one Gregory Goyle’s holding goes to me.’

Draco nodded, looking decisive. ‘I won’t question the word of the Noble House of Potter, then, no matter how strange that all was. And the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy keeps its word as well. Mr Goyle, give that to Mr Potter –’

‘Hey!’ Zabini said. ‘He hasn’t won yet, he hasn’t got his hands on –’

‘Catch, Harry!’ said Ernie, and he tossed the Remembrall.

Harry easily snapped the Remembrall out of the air, he’d always had good reflexes that way. ‘There,’ said Harry, ‘I win …’

Harry trailed off. All conversation stopped.

The Remembrall was glowing bright red in his hand, blazing like a miniature sun that cast shadows on the ground in broad daylight.

Thursday.

If you wanted to be specific, 5:09pm on Thursday afternoon, in Professor McGonagall’s office, after flying classes. (With an extra hour for Harry slipped in between.)

Professor McGonagall sitting on her stool. Harry in the hot seat in front of her desk.

‘Professor,’ Harry said tightly, ‘Slytherin was pointing their wands at Hufflepuff, Gryffindor was pointing their wands at Slytherin, some idiot called wands out in Ravenclaw, and I had maybe five seconds to keep the whole thing from blowing sky-high! It was all I could think of!’

Professor McGonagall’s face was pinched and angry. ‘You are not to use the Time-Turner in that fashion, Mr Potter! Is the concept of secrecy not something that you understand?’

‘They don’t know how I did it! They just think I can do really weird things by snapping my fingers! I’ve done other weird stuff that can’t be done with Time-Turners even, and I’ll do more stuff like that, and this case won’t even stand out! I had to do it, Professor!’

‘You did not have to do it!’ snapped Professor McGonagall. ‘All you needed to do was get this anonymous Slytherin back on the ground and the wands put away! You could have challenged him to a game of Exploding Snap but no, you had to use the Time-Turner in a flagrant and unnecessary manner!’

‘It was all I could think of! I don’t even know what Exploding Snap is, they wouldn’t have accepted a game of chess and if I’d picked arm-wresting I would have lost!’

‘Then you should have picked wrestling!’

Harry blinked. ‘But then I’d have lost –’

Harry stopped.

Professor McGonagall was looking very angry.

‘I’m sorry, Professor McGonagall,’ Harry said in a small voice. ‘I honestly didn’t think of that, and you’re right, I should have, it would have been brilliant if I had, but I just didn’t think of that at all …’

Harry’s voice trailed off. It was suddenly apparent to him that he’d had a lot of other options. He could have asked Draco to suggest something, he could have asked the crowd … his use of the Time-Turner had been flagrant and unnecessary. There had been a giant space of possibilities, why had he picked that one?

Because he’d seen a way to win. Win possession of an unimportant trinket that the teachers would’ve taken back from Mr Goyle anyway.

Intent to win. That was what had got him.

‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said again. ‘For my pride and my stupidity.’

Professor McGonagall wiped a hand across her forehead. Some of her anger seemed to dissipate. But her voice still came out very hard. ‘One more display like that, Mr Potter, and you will be returning that Time-Turner. Do I make myself very clear?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘I understand and I’m sorry.’

‘Then, Mr Potter, you will be allowed to retain the Time-Turner for now. And considering the size of the debacle you did, in fact, avert, I will not deduct any points from Ravenclaw.’

Plus you couldn’t explain why you’d deducted the points. But Harry wasn’t dumb enough to say that out loud.

‘More importantly, why did the Remembrall go off like that?’ Harry said. ‘Does it mean I’ve been Obliviated?’

‘That puzzles me as well,’ Professor McGonagall said slowly. ‘If it were that simple, I would think that the courts would use Remembralls, and they do not. I shall look into it, Mr Potter.’ She sighed. ‘You can go now.’

Harry started to get up from his chair, then halted. ‘Um, sorry, I did have something else I wanted to tell you –’

You could hardly see the flinch. ‘What is it, Mr Potter?’

‘It’s about Professor Quirrell –’

‘I’m sure, Mr Potter, that it is nothing of importance.’ Professor McGonagall spoke the words in a great rush. ‘Surely you heard the Headmaster tell the students that you were not to bother us with any unimportant complaints about the Defence Professor?’

Harry was rather confused. ‘But this could be important, yesterday I got this sudden sense of doom when –’

‘Mr Potter! I have a sense of doom as well! And my sense of doom is suggesting that you must not finish that sentence!’

Harry’s mouth gaped open. Professor McGonagall had succeeded; Harry was speechless.

‘Mr Potter,’ said Professor McGonagall, ‘if you have discovered anything that seems interesting about Professor Quirrell, please feel free not to share it with me or anyone else. Now I think you’ve taken up enough of my valuable time –’

‘This isn’t like you!’ Harry burst out. ‘I’m sorry but that just seems unbelievably irresponsible! From what I’ve heard there’s some kind of jinx on the Defence position, and if you already know something’s going to go wrong, I’d think you’d all be on your toes –’

‘Go wrong, Mr Potter? I certainly hope not.’ Professor McGonagall’s face was expressionless. ‘After Professor Blake was caught in a closet with no fewer than three fifth-year Slytherins last February, and a year before that, Professor Summers failed so completely as an educator that her students thought a boggart was a kind of furniture, it would be catastrophic if some problem with the extraordinarily competent Professor Quirrell came to my attention now, and I dare say most of our students would fail their Defence O.W.L.s and N.E.W.T.s.’

‘I see,’ Harry said slowly, taking it all in. ‘So in other words, whatever’s wrong with Professor Quirrell, you desperately don’t want to know about it until the end of the school year. And since it’s currently September, he could assassinate the Prime Minister on live television and get away with it so far as you’re concerned.’

Professor McGonagall gazed at him unblinkingly. ‘I am certain that I could never be heard endorsing such a statement, Mr Potter. At Hogwarts we strive to be proactive with respect to anything that threatens the educational attainment of our students.’

Such as first-year Ravenclaws who can’t keep their mouths shut. ‘I believe I understand you completely, Professor McGonagall.’

‘Oh, I doubt that, Mr Potter. I doubt that very much.’ Professor McGonagall leaned forward, her face tightening again. ‘Since you and I have already discussed matters far more sensitive than these, I shall speak frankly. You, and you alone, have reported this mysterious sense of doom. You, and you alone, are a chaos magnet the likes of which I have never seen. After our little shopping trip to Diagon Alley, and then the Sorting Hat, and then today’s little episode, I can well foresee that I am fated to sit in the Headmaster’s office and hear some hilarious tale about Professor Quirrell in which you and you alone play a starring role, after which there will be no choice but to fire him. I am already resigned to it, Mr Potter. And if this sad event takes place any earlier than the Ides of May, I will string you up by the gates of Hogwarts with your own intestines and pour fire beetles into your nose. Now do you understand me completely?’

Harry nodded, his eyes very wide. Then, after a second, ‘What do I get if I can make it happen on the last day of the school year?’

‘Get out of my office!’

Thursday.

There must have been something about Thursdays in Hogwarts.

It was 5:32pm on Thursday afternoon, and Harry was standing next to Professor Flitwick, in front of the great stone gargoyle that guarded the entrance to the Headmaster’s office.

No sooner had he made it back from Professor McGonagall’s office to the Ravenclaw study rooms than one of the students told him to report to Professor Flitwick’s office, and there Harry had learned that Dumbledore wanted to speak to him.

Harry, feeling rather apprehensive, had asked Professor Flitwick if the Headmaster had said what this was about.

Professor Flitwick had shrugged in a helpless sort of way.

Apparently Dumbledore had said that Harry was far too young to invoke the words of power and madness.

Happy happy boom boom swamp swamp swamp? Harry had thought but not said aloud.

‘Please don’t worry too much, Mr Potter,’ squeaked Professor Flitwick from somewhere around Harry’s shoulder level. (Harry was grateful for Professor Flitwick’s gigantic puffy beard, it was hard getting used to a Professor who was not only shorter than him but spoke in a higher-pitched voice.) ‘Headmaster Dumbledore may seem a little odd, or a lot odd, or even extremely odd, but he has never hurt a student in the slightest, and I don’t believe he ever will.’ Professor Flitwick gave Harry an encouraging smile. ‘Just keep that in mind at all times and you’ll be sure not to panic!’

This was not helping.

‘Good luck!’ squeaked Professor Flitwick, and leaned over to the gargoyle and said something that Harry somehow failed to hear at all. (Of course, the password wouldn’t be much good if you could hear someone saying it.) And the stone gargoyle walked aside with a very natural and ordinary movement that Harry found rather shocking, since the gargoyle still looked like solid, immovable stone the whole time.

Behind the gargoyle was a set of slowly revolving spiral stairs. There was something disturbingly hypnotic about it, and even more disturbing was that revolving the spiral ought not to take you anywhere.

‘Up you go!’ squeaked Flitwick.

Harry rather nervously stepped onto the spiral, and found himself, for some reason that his brain couldn’t seem to visualise at all, moving upwards.

The gargoyle thudded back into place behind him, and the spiral stairs kept turning and Harry kept being higher up, and after a rather dizzying time, Harry found himself in front of an oak door with a brass griffin knocker.

Harry reached out and turned the doorknob.

The door swung open.

And Harry saw the most interesting room he’d ever seen in his life.

There were tiny metal mechanisms that whirred or ticked or slowly changed shape or emitted little puffs of smoke. There were dozens of mysterious fluids in dozens of oddly shaped containers, all bubbling, boiling, oozing, changing colour, or forming into interesting shapes that vanished half a second after you saw them. There were things that looked like clocks with many hands, inscribed with numbers or in unrecognisable languages. There was a bracelet bearing a lenticular crystal that sparkled with a thousand colours, and a bird perched atop a golden platform, and a wooden cup filled with what looked like blood, and a statue of a falcon encrusted in black enamel. The wall was all hung with pictures of people sleeping, and the Sorting Hat was casually poised on a hat rack that was also holding two umbrellas and three red slippers for left feet.

In the midst of all the chaos was a clean black oaken desk. Before the desk was an oaken stool. And behind the desk was a well-cushioned throne containing Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore, who was adorned with a long silver beard, a hat like a squashed giant mushroom, and what looked to Muggle eyes like three layers of bright pink pyjamas.

Dumbledore was smiling, and his bright eyes twinkled with a mad intensity.

With some trepidation, Harry seated himself in front of the desk. The door swung shut behind him with a loud thunk.

‘Hello, Harry,’ said Dumbledore.

‘Hello, Headmaster,’ Harry replied. So they were on a first-name basis? Would Dumbledore now say to call him –

‘Please, Harry!’ said Dumbledore. ‘Headmaster sounds so formal. Just call me Heh for short.’

‘I’ll be sure to, Heh,’ said Harry.

There was a slight pause.

‘Do you know,’ said Dumbledore, ‘you’re the first person who’s ever taken me up on that?’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. He tried to control his voice despite the sudden sinking feeling in his stomach. ‘I’m sorry, I, ah, Headmaster, you told me to do it so I did –’

‘Heh, please!’ said Dumbledore cheerfully. ‘And there’s no call to be so worried, I won’t launch you out a window just because you make one mistake. I’ll give you plenty of warnings first, if you’re doing something wrong! Besides, what matters isn’t how people talk to you, it’s what they think of you.’

He’s never hurt a student, just keep remembering that and you’ll be sure not to panic.

Dumbledore drew forth a small metal case and flipped it open, showing some small yellow lumps. ‘Sherbet lemon?’ said the Headmaster.

‘Er, no thank you, Heh,’ said Harry. Does slipping a student LSD count as hurting them, or does that fall into the category of harmless fun? ‘You, um, said something about my being too young to invoke the words of power and madness?’

‘That you most certainly are!’ Dumbledore said. ‘Thankfully the Words of Power and Madness were lost seven centuries ago and no one has the slightest idea what they are any more. It was just a little remark.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. He was aware that his mouth was hanging open. ‘Why did you call me here, then?’

‘Why?’ Dumbledore repeated. ‘Ah, Harry, if I went around all day asking why I do things, I’d never have time to get a single thing done! I’m quite a busy person, you know.’

Harry nodded, smiling. ‘Yes, it was a very impressive list. Headmaster of Hogwarts, Chief Warlock of the Wizengamot, and Supreme Mugwump of the International Confederation of Wizards. Sorry to ask but I was wondering, is it possible to get more than six hours if you use more than one Time-Turner? Because it’s pretty impressive if you’re doing all that on just thirty hours a day.’

There was another slight pause, during which Harry went on smiling. He was a little apprehensive, actually a lot apprehensive, but once it had become clear that Dumbledore was deliberately messing with him, something within him absolutely refused to sit and take it like a defenceless lump.

‘I’m afraid Time doesn’t like being stretched out too much,’ said Dumbledore after the slight pause, ‘and yet we ourselves seem to be a little too large for it, and so it’s a constant struggle to fit our lives into Time.’

‘Indeed,’ Harry said with grave solemnity. ‘That’s why it’s best to come to our points quickly.’

For a moment Harry wondered if he’d gone too far.

Then Dumbledore chuckled. ‘Straight to the point it shall be.’ The Headmaster leaned forwards, tilting his squashed mushroom hat and brushing his beard against his desk. ‘Harry, this Monday you did something that should have been impossible even with a Time-Turner. Or rather, impossible with only a Time-Turner. Where did those two pies come from, I wonder?’

A jolt of adrenaline shot through Harry. He’d done that using the Cloak of Invisibility, the one that had been given him in a Christmas box along with a note, and that note had said: If Dumbledore saw a chance to possess one of the Deathly Hallows he would never let it escape his grasp … .

‘A natural thought,’ Dumbledore went on, ‘is that since none of the first-years present were able to cast such a spell, someone else was present, and yet unseen. And if no one could see them, why, it would be easy enough for them to throw the pies. One might further suspect that since you had a Time-Turner, you were the invisible one; and that since the spell of Disillusionment is far beyond your current abilities, you had an invisibility cloak.’ Dumbledore smiled conspiratorially. ‘Am I on the right track so far, Harry?’

Harry was frozen. He had the feeling that an outright lie would not at all be wise, and possibly not the least bit helpful, and he couldn’t think of anything else to say.

Dumbledore waved a friendly hand. ‘Don’t worry, Harry, you haven’t done anything wrong. Invisibility cloaks aren’t against the rules – I suppose they’re rare enough that no one ever got around to putting them on the list. But really I was wondering something else entirely.’

‘Oh?’ Harry said in the most normal voice he could manage.

Dumbledore’s eyes shone with enthusiasm. ‘You see, Harry, after you’ve been through a few adventures you tend to catch the hang of these things. You start to see the pattern, hear the rhythm of the world. You begin to harbour suspicions before the moment of revelation. You are the Boy-Who-Lived, and somehow an invisibility cloak made its way into your hands only four days after you discovered our magical Britain. Such cloaks are not for sale in Diagon Alley, but there is one which might find its own way to a destined wearer. And so I cannot help but wonder if by some strange chance you have found not just an invisibility cloak, but the Cloak of Invisibility, one of the three Deathly Hallows and reputed to hide the wearer from the gaze of Death himself.’ Dumbledore’s gaze was bright and eager. ‘May I see it, Harry?’

Harry swallowed. There was a full flood of adrenaline in his system now and it was entirely useless, this was the most powerful wizard in the world and there was no way he could make it out the door and there was nowhere in Hogwarts for him to hide if he did, he was about to lose the Cloak that had been passed down through the Potters for who knew how long –

Slowly Dumbledore leaned back into his high chair. The bright light had gone out of his eyes, and he looked puzzled and a little sorrowful. ‘Harry,’ said Dumbledore, ‘if you don’t want to, you can just say no.’

‘I can?’ Harry croaked.

‘Yes, Harry,’ said Dumbledore. His voice sounded sad now, and worried. ‘It seems that you’re afraid of me, Harry. May I ask what I’ve done to earn your distrust?’

Harry swallowed. ‘Is there some way you can swear a binding magical oath that you won’t take my cloak?’

Dumbledore shook his head slowly. ‘Unbreakable Vows are not to be used so lightly. And besides, Harry, if you did not already know the spell, you would have only my word that the spell was binding. Yet surely you realise that I do not need your permission to see the Cloak. I am powerful enough to draw it forth myself, mokeskin pouch or no.’ Dumbledore’s face was very grave. ‘But this I will not do. The Cloak is yours, Harry. I will not seize it from you. Not even to look at for just a moment, unless you decide to show it to me. That is a promise and an oath. Should I need to prohibit you from using it on the school grounds, I will require you to go to your vault at Gringotts and store it there.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. He swallowed hard, trying to calm the flood of adrenaline and think reasonably. He took the mokeskin pouch off his belt. ‘If you really don’t need my permission … then you have it.’ Harry held out the pouch to Dumbledore, and bit down hard on his lip, sending that signal to himself in case he was Obliviated afterwards.

The old wizard reached into the pouch, and without saying any word of retrieval, drew forth the Cloak of Invisibility.

‘Ah,’ breathed Dumbledore. ‘I was right …’ He poured the shimmering black velvet mesh through his hand. ‘Centuries old, and still as perfect as the day it was made. We have lost much of our art over the years, and now I cannot make such a thing myself, no one can. I can feel the power of it like an echo in my mind, like a song forever being sung without anyone to hear it …’ The wizard looked up from the Cloak. ‘Do not sell it,’ he said, ‘do not give it to anyone as a possession. Think twice before you show it to anyone, and ponder three times again before you reveal it is a Deathly Hallow. Treat it with respect, for this is indeed a Thing of Power.’

For a moment Dumbledore’s face grew wistful …

… and then he handed the Cloak back to Harry.

Harry put it back in his pouch.

Dumbledore’s face was grave once more. ‘May I ask again, Harry, how you came to distrust me so?’

Suddenly Harry felt rather ashamed.

‘There was a note with the Cloak,’ Harry said in a small voice. ‘It said that you would try to take the Cloak from me, if you knew. I don’t know who left the note, though, I really don’t.’

‘I … see,’ Dumbledore said slowly. ‘Well, Harry, I won’t impugn the motives of whoever left you that note. Who knows but that they themselves may have had the best of good intentions? They did give you the Cloak, after all.’

Harry nodded, impressed by Dumbledore’s charity, and abashed at the sharp contrast with his own attitude.

The old wizard went on. ‘But you and I are both game pieces of the same colour, I think. The boy who finally defeated Voldemort, and the old man who held him off long enough for you to save the day. I will not hold your caution against you, Harry, we must all do our best to be wise. I will only ask that you think twice and ponder three times again, the next time someone tells you to distrust me.’

‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said. He felt wretched at this point, he’d just told off Gandalf essentially, and Dumbledore’s kindness was only making him feel worse. ‘I shouldn’t have distrusted you.’

‘Alas, Harry, in this world …’ The old wizard shook his head. ‘I cannot even say you were unwise. You did not know me. And in truth there are some at Hogwarts who you would do well not to trust. Perhaps even some you call friends.’

Harry swallowed. That sounded rather ominous. ‘Like who?’

Dumbledore stood up from his chair, and began examining one of his instruments, a dial with eight hands of varying length.

After a few moments, the old wizard spoke again. ‘He probably seems to you quite charming,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Polite – to you at least. Well-spoken, maybe even admiring. Always ready with a helping hand, a favour, a word of advice –’

‘Oh, Draco Malfoy!’ Harry said, feeling rather relieved that it wasn’t Hermione or something. ‘Oh no, no no no, you’ve got it all wrong, he’s not turning me, I’m turning him.’

Dumbledore froze where he was peering at the dial. ‘You’re what?’

‘I’m going to turn Draco Malfoy from the Dark Side,’ Harry said. ‘You know, make him a good guy.’

Dumbledore straightened and turned to Harry. He was wearing one of the most astonished expressions Harry had ever seen on anyone, let alone someone with a long silver beard. ‘Are you certain,’ said the old wizard after a moment, ‘that he is ready to be redeemed? I fear that whatever goodness you think you see within him is only wishful thinking – or worse, a lure, a bait –’

‘Er, not likely,’ Harry said. ‘I mean if he’s trying to disguise himself as a good guy he’s incredibly bad at it. This isn’t a question of Draco coming up to me and being all charming and me deciding that he must have a hidden core of goodness deep down. I selected him for redemption specifically because he’s the heir to House Malfoy and if you had to pick one person to redeem, it would obviously be him.’

Dumbledore’s left eye twitched. ‘You intend to sow seeds of love and kindness in Draco Malfoy’s heart because you expect Malfoy’s heir to prove valuable to you?’

‘Not just to me!’ Harry said indignantly. ‘To all of magical Britain, if this works out! And he’ll have a happier and mentally healthier life himself! Look, I don’t have enough time to turn everyone away from the Dark Side and I’ve got to ask where the Light can gain the most advantage the fastest –’

Dumbledore started laughing. Laughing a lot harder than Harry would expect, almost howling. It seemed positively undignified. An ancient and powerful wizard ought to chuckle in deep booming tones, not laugh so hard he was gasping for breath. Harry had once literally fallen out of his chair while watching the Marx Brothers film Duck Soup, and that was how hard Dumbledore was laughing now.

‘It’s not that funny,’ Harry said after a while. He was starting to worry about Dumbledore’s sanity again.

Dumbledore got himself under control again with a visible effort. ‘Ah, Harry, one symptom of the disease called wisdom is that you begin laughing at things that no one else thinks is funny, because when you’re wise, Harry, you start getting the jokes!’ The old wizard wiped tears away from his eyes. ‘Ah, me. Ah, me. Oft evil will shall evil mar indeed, in very deed.’

Harry’s brain took a moment to place the familiar words … ‘Hey, that’s a Tolkien quote! Gandalf says that!’

‘Théoden, actually,’ said Dumbledore.

‘You’re Muggleborn?’ Harry said in shock.

‘I’m afraid not,’ said Dumbledore, smiling again. ‘I was born seventy years before that book was published, dear child. But it seems that my Muggleborn students tend to think alike in certain ways. I have accumulated no fewer than twenty copies of The Lord of the Rings and three sets of Tolkien’s entire collected works, and I treasure every one of them.’ Dumbledore drew his wand and held it up and struck a pose. ‘You cannot pass! How does that look?’

‘Ah,’ Harry said in something approaching complete brain shutdown, ‘I think you’re missing a Balrog.’ And the pink pyjamas and squashed mushroom hat were not helping in the slightest.

‘I see.’ Dumbledore sighed and glumly sheathed the wand in his belt. ‘I fear there have been precious few Balrogs in my life of late. Nowadays it’s all meetings of the Wizengamot where I must try desperately to prevent any work from getting done, and formal dinners where foreign politicians compete to see who can be the most obstinate fool. And being mysterious at people, knowing things I have no way of knowing, making cryptic statements which can only be understood in hindsight, and all the other small ways in which powerful wizards amuse themselves after they have left the part of the pattern that allows them to be heroes. Speaking of which, Harry, I have a certain something to give you, something which belonged to your father.’

‘You do?’ said Harry. ‘Gosh, who would have figured.’

‘Yes indeed,’ said Dumbledore. ‘I suppose it is a little predictable, isn’t it?’ His face turned solemn. ‘Nonetheless …’

Dumbledore went back to his desk and sat down, pulling out one of the drawers as he did so. He reached in using both arms, and, straining slightly, pulled a rather large and heavy-looking object out of the drawer, which he then deposited on his oaken desk with a huge thunk.

‘This,’ Dumbledore said, ‘was your father’s rock.’

Harry stared at it. It was light grey, discoloured, irregularly shaped, sharp-edged, and very much a plain old ordinary large rock. Dumbledore had deposited it so that it rested on the widest available cross-section, but it still wobbled unstably on his desk.

Harry looked up. ‘This is a joke, right?’

‘It is not,’ said Dumbledore, shaking his head and looking very serious. ‘I took this from the ruins of James and Lily’s home in Godric’s Hollow, where also I found you; and I have kept it from then until now, against the day when I could give it to you.’

In the mixture of hypotheses that served as Harry’s model of the world, Dumbledore’s insanity was rapidly rising in probability. But there was still a substantial amount of probability allocated to other alternatives … ‘Um, is it a magical rock?’

‘Not so far as I know,’ said Dumbledore. ‘But I advise you with the greatest possible stringency to keep it close about your person at all times.’

All right. Dumbledore was probably insane but if he wasn’t … well, it would be just too embarrassing to get in trouble from ignoring the advice of the inscrutable old wizard. That had to be like #4 on the list of the Top 100 Obvious Failure Modes.

Harry stepped forward and put his hands on the rock, trying to find some angle from which to lift it without cutting himself. ‘I’ll put it in my pouch, then.’

Dumbledore frowned. ‘That may not be close enough to your person. And what if your mokeskin pouch is lost, or stolen?’

‘You think I should just carry a big rock everywhere I go?’

Dumbledore gave Harry a serious look. ‘That might prove wise.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. It looked rather heavy. ‘I’d think the other students would tend to ask me questions about that.’

‘Tell them I ordered you to do it,’ said Dumbledore. ‘No one will question that, since they all think I’m insane.’ His face was still perfectly serious.

‘Er, to be honest if you go around ordering your students to carry large rocks I can kind of see why people would think that.’

‘Ah, Harry,’ said Dumbledore. The old wizard gestured, a sweep of one hand that seemed to take in all the mysterious instruments around the room. ‘When we are young we believe that we know everything, and so we believe that if we see no explanation for something, then no explanation exists. When we are older we realise that the whole universe works by a rhythm and a reason, even if we ourselves do not know it. It is only our own ignorance which appears to us as insanity.’

‘Reality is always lawful,’ said Harry, ‘even if we don’t know the law.’

‘Precisely, Harry,’ said Dumbledore. ‘To understand this – and I see that you do understand it – is the essence of wisdom.’

‘So … why do I have to carry this rock exactly?’

‘I can’t think of a reason, actually,’ said Dumbledore.

‘… you can’t.’

Dumbledore nodded. ‘But just because I can’t think of a reason doesn’t mean there is no reason.’

The instruments ticked on.

‘Okay,’ said Harry, ‘I’m not even sure if I should be saying this, but that is simply not the correct way to deal with our admitted ignorance of how the universe works.’

‘It isn’t?’ said the old wizard, looking surprised and disappointed.

Harry had the feeling this conversation was not going to work out in his favour, but he carried on regardless. ‘No. I don’t even know if that fallacy has an official name, but if I had to make one up myself, it would be “privileging the hypothesis” or something like that. How can I put this formally … um … suppose you had a million boxes, and only one of the boxes contained a diamond. And you had a box full of diamond-detectors, and each diamond-detector always went off in the presence of a diamond, and went off half the time on boxes that didn’t have a diamond. If you ran twenty detectors over all the boxes, you’d have, on average, one false candidate and one true candidate left. And then it would just take one or two more detectors before you were left with the one true candidate. The point being that when there are lots of possible answers, most of the evidence you need goes into just locating the true hypothesis out of millions of possibilities – bringing it to your attention in the first place. The amount of evidence you need to judge between two or three plausible candidates is much smaller by comparison. So if you just jump ahead without evidence and promote one particular possibility to the focus of your attention, you’re skipping over most of the work. Like, you live in a city where there are a million people, and there’s a murder, and a detective says, well, we’ve got no evidence at all, so have we considered the possibility that Mortimer Snodgrass did it?’

‘Did he?’ said Dumbledore.

‘No,’ said Harry. ‘But later it turns out that the murderer had black hair, and Mortimer has black hair, so everyone’s like, ah, looks like Mortimer did it after all. So it’s unfair to Mortimer for the police to promote him to their attention without having good reasons already in hand to suspect him. When there are lots of possibilities, most of the work goes into just locating the true answer – starting to pay attention to it. You don’t need proof, or the sort of official evidence that scientists or courts demand, but you need some sort of hint, and that hint has to discriminate that particular possibility from the millions of others. Otherwise you can’t just pluck the right answer out of thin air. You can’t even pluck a possibility worth thinking about out of thin air. And there’s got to be a million other things I could do besides carrying around my father’s rock. Just because I’m ignorant about the universe doesn’t mean that I’m unsure about how I should reason in the presence of my uncertainty. The laws for thinking with probabilities are no less iron than the laws that govern old-fashioned logic, and what you just did is not allowed.’ Harry paused. ‘Unless, of course, you have some hint you’re not mentioning.’

‘Ah,’ said Dumbledore. He tapped his cheek, looking thoughtful. ‘An interesting argument, certainly, but doesn’t it break down at the point where you make an analogy between a million potential murderers only one of whom committed the murder, and taking one out of many possible courses of action, when many possible courses of action may all be wise? I do not say that carrying your father’s rock is the one best possible course of action, only that it is wiser to do than not.’

Dumbledore once again reached into the same desk drawer he had accessed earlier, this time seeming to root around inside – at least his arm seemed to be moving. ‘I will remark,’ Dumbledore said while Harry was still trying to sort out how to reply to this completely unexpected rejoinder, ‘that it is a common misconception of Ravenclaws that all the smart children are Sorted there, leaving none for other Houses. This is not so; being Sorted to Ravenclaw indicates that you are driven by your desire to know things, which is not at all the same quality as being intelligent.’ The wizard was smiling as he bent over the drawer. ‘Nonetheless, you do seem rather intelligent. Less like an ordinary young hero and more like a young mysterious ancient wizard. I think I may have been taking the wrong approach with you, Harry, and that you may be able to understand things that few others could grasp. So I shall be daring, and offer you a certain other heirloom.’

‘You don’t mean …’ gasped Harry. ‘My father … owned another rock?’

‘Excuse me,’ said Dumbledore, ‘I am still older and more mysterious than you and if there are any revelations to be made then I will do the revealing, thank you … oh, where is that thing!’ Dumbledore reached down further into the desk drawer, and still further. His head and shoulders and whole torso disappeared inside until only his hips and legs were sticking out, as though the desk drawer was eating him.

Harry couldn’t help but wonder just how much stuff was in there and what the complete inventory would look like.

Finally Dumbledore rose back up out of the drawer, holding the objective of his search, which he set down on the desk alongside the rock.

It was a used, ragged-edged, textbook with a worn spine: Intermediate Potion Making by Libatius Borage. There was a picture of a smoking vial on the cover.

‘This,’ Dumbledore intoned, ‘was your mother’s fifth-year Potions textbook.’

‘Which I am to carry with me at all times,’ said Harry.

‘Which holds a terrible secret. A secret whose revelation could prove so disastrous that I must ask you to swear – and I do require you to swear it seriously, Harry, whatever you may think of all this – never to tell anyone or anything else.’

Harry considered his mother’s fifth-year Potions textbook, which, apparently, held a terrible secret.

The problem was that Harry did take that oaths like that very seriously. Any vow was an Unbreakable Vow if made by the right sort of person.

And …

‘I’m feeling thirsty,’ Harry said, ‘and that is not at all a good sign.’

Dumbledore entirely failed to ask any questions about this cryptic statement. ‘Do you swear, Harry?’ said Dumbledore. His eyes gazed intently into Harry’s. ‘Otherwise I cannot tell you.’

‘Yes,’ said Harry. ‘I swear.’ That was the trouble with being a Ravenclaw. You couldn’t refuse an offer like that or your curiosity would eat you alive, and everyone else knew it.

‘And I swear in turn,’ said Dumbledore, ‘that what I am about to tell you is the truth.’

Dumbledore opened the book, seemingly at random, and Harry leaned in to see.

‘Do you see these notes,’ Dumbledore said in a voice so low it was almost a whisper, ‘written in the margins of the book?’

Harry squinted slightly. The yellowing pages seemed to be describing something called a potion of eagle’s splendour, many of the ingredients being items that Harry didn’t recognise at all and whose names didn’t appear to derive from English. Scrawled in the margin was a handwritten annotation saying, I wonder what would happen if you used Thestral blood here instead of blueberries? and immediately beneath was a reply in different handwriting, You’d get sick for weeks and maybe die.

‘I see them,’ said Harry. ‘What about them?’

Dumbledore pointed to the second scrawl. ‘The ones in this handwriting,’ he said, still in that low voice, ‘were written by your mother. And the ones in this handwriting,’ moving his finger to indicate the first scrawl, ‘were written by me. I would turn myself invisible and sneak into her dorm while she was sleeping. Lily thought one of her friends was writing them and they had the most amazing fights.’

That was the exact point at which Harry realised that the Headmaster of Hogwarts was, in fact, crazy.

Dumbledore was looking at him with a serious expression. ‘Do you understand the implications of what I have just told you, Harry?’

‘Ehhh …’ Harry said. His voice seemed to be stuck. ‘Sorry … I … not really …’

‘Ah well,’ said Dumbledore, and sighed. ‘I suppose your cleverness has limits after all, then. Shall we all just pretend I didn’t say anything?’

Harry rose from his chair, wearing a fixed smile. ‘Of course,’ Harry said. ‘You know it’s actually getting rather late in the day and I’m a bit hungry, so I should be going down to dinner, really’ and Harry made a beeline for the door.

The doorknob entirely failed to turn.

‘You wound me, Harry,’ said Dumbledore’s voice in quiet tones that were coming from right behind him. ‘Do you not at least realise that what I have told you is a sign of trust?’

Harry slowly turned around.

In front of him was a very powerful and very insane wizard with a long silver beard, a hat like a squashed giant mushroom, and wearing what looked to Muggle eyes like three layers of bright pink pyjamas.

Behind him was a door that didn’t seem to be working at the moment.

Dumbledore was looking rather saddened and weary, like he wanted to lean on a wizard’s staff he didn’t have. ‘Really,’ said Dumbledore, ‘you try anything new instead of following the same pattern every time for a hundred and ten years, and people all start running away.’ The old wizard shook his head in sorrow. ‘I’d hoped for better from you, Harry Potter. I’d heard that your own friends also think you mad. I know they are mistaken. Will you not believe the same of me?’

‘Please open the door,’ Harry said, his voice trembling. ‘If you ever want me to trust you again, open the door.’

There was the sound behind him of a door opening.

‘There were more things I planned to say to you,’ Dumbledore said, ‘and if you leave now, you will not know what they were.’

Sometimes Harry absolutely hated being a Ravenclaw.

He’s never hurt a student, said Harry’s Gryffindor side. Just keep remembering that and you’ll be sure not to panic. You’re not going to run away just because things are getting interesting, are you?

You can’t just walk out on the Headmaster! said the Hufflepuff part. What if he starts deducting House points? He could make your school life very difficult if he decides he doesn’t like you!

And a piece of himself which Harry didn’t much like but couldn’t quite manage to silence was pondering the potential advantages of being one of the few friends of this mad old wizard who also happened to be Headmaster, Chief Warlock, and Supreme Mugwump. And unfortunately his inner Slytherin seemed to be much better than Draco at turning people to the Dark Side, because it was saying things like poor fellow, he looks like he needs someone to talk to, doesn’t he? and you wouldn’t want such a powerful man to end up trusting someone less virtuous, would you? and I wonder what sort of incredible secrets Dumbledore could tell you if, you know, you became friends with him and even I bet he’s got a reaallly interesting book collection.

You’re all a bunch of lunatics, Harry thought at the entire assemblage, but he’d been unanimously outvoted by every component part of himself.

Harry turned, took a step towards the open door, reached out, and deliberately closed it again. It was a costless sacrifice given that he was staying anyway, Dumbledore could control his movements regardless, but maybe it would impress Dumbledore.

When Harry turned back around he saw that the powerful insane wizard was once more smiling and looking friendly. That was good, maybe.

‘Please don’t do that again,’ Harry said. ‘I don’t like being trapped.’

‘I am sorry about that, Harry,’ said Dumbledore in what sounded like tones of sincere apology. ‘But it would have been terribly unwise to let you leave without your father’s rock.’

‘Of course,’ Harry said. ‘It wasn’t reasonable of me to expect the door to open before I put the quest items in my inventory.’

Dumbledore smiled and nodded.

Harry went over to the desk, twisted his mokeskin pouch around to the front of his belt, and, with some effort, managed to heave up the rock in his eleven-year-old arms and feed it in.

He could actually feel the weight slowly diminishing as the Widening Lip charm ate the rock, and the burp which followed was rather noisy and had a distinctly complaining sound to it.

His mother’s fifth-year Potions textbook (which held a secret that was in fact pretty terrible) followed shortly after.

And then Harry’s inner Slytherin made a sly suggestion for ingratiating himself with the Headmaster, which, unfortunately, had been perfectly pitched in such a way as to gain the support of the majority Ravenclaw faction.

‘So,’ Harry said. ‘Um. As long as I’m hanging around, I don’t suppose you would like to give me a bit of a tour of your office? I’m a bit curious as to what some of these things are,’ and that was his understatement for the month of September.

Dumbledore gazed at him, and then nodded with a slight grin. ‘I’m flattered by your interest,’ said Dumbledore, ‘but I’m afraid there isn’t much to say.’ Dumbledore took a step closer to the wall and pointed to a painting of a sleeping man. ‘These are portraits of past Headmasters of Hogwarts.’ He turned and pointed to his desk. ‘This is my desk.’ He pointed to his chair. ‘This is my chair –’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said, ‘actually I was wondering about those.’ Harry pointed to a small cube that was softly whispering ‘blorple … blorple … blorple’.

‘Oh, the little fiddly things?’ said Dumbledore. ‘They came with the Headmaster’s office and I have absolutely no idea what most of them do. Although this dial with the eight hands counts the number of, let’s call them sneezes, by left-handed witches within the borders of France, you would not believe how much work it took to nail that down. And this one with the golden wibblers is my own invention and Minerva is never, ever going to figure out what it’s doing.’

Dumbledore took a step over to the hat rack while Harry was still processing this. ‘Here of course we have the Sorting Hat, I believe the two of you have met. It told me that it was never again to be placed on your head under any circumstances. You’re only the fourteenth student in history it’s said that about, Baba Yaga was another one and I’ll tell you about the other twelve when you’re older. This is an umbrella. This is another umbrella.’ Dumbledore took another few steps and turned around, now smiling quite broadly. ‘And of course, most people who come to my office want to see Fawkes.’

Dumbledore was standing next to the bird on the golden platform.

Harry came over, rather puzzled. ‘This is Fawkes?’

‘Fawkes is a phoenix,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Very rare, very powerful magical creatures.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. He lowered his head and stared into the tiny, beady black eyes, which showed not the slightest sign of power or intelligence.

‘Ahhh …’ Harry said again.

He was pretty sure he recognised the shape of the bird. It was pretty hard to miss.

‘Umm …’

Say something intelligent! Harry’s mind roared at itself. Don’t just stand there sounding like a gibbering moron!

Well what the heck am I supposed to say? Harry’s mind fired back.

Anything!

You mean, anything besides ‘Fawkes is a chicken’ –

Yes! Anything but that!

‘So, ah, what sort of magic do phoenixes do, then?’

‘Their tears have the power to heal,’ Dumbledore said. ‘They are creatures of fire, and move between all places as easily as fire may extinguish itself in one place and be kindled in another. The tremendous strain of their innate magic ages their bodies quickly, and yet they are as close to undying as any creature that exists in this world, for whenever their bodies fail them they immolate themselves in a burst of fire and leave behind a hatchling, or sometimes an egg.’ Dumbledore came closer and inspected the chicken, frowning. ‘Hm … looking a little peaky there, I’d say.’

By the time this statement registered fully in Harry’s mind, the chicken was already on fire.

The chicken’s beak opened, but it didn’t have time for so much as a single caw before it began to wither and char. The blaze was brief, intense, and entirely self-contained; there was no smell of burning.

And then the fire died down only seconds after it had begun, leaving behind a tiny, pathetic heap of ashes on the golden platform.

‘Don’t look so horrified, Harry!’ said Dumbledore. ‘Fawkes hasn’t been hurt.’ Dumbledore’s hand dipped into a pocket, and then the same hand sifted through the ashes and turned up a small yellowish egg. ‘Look, here’s an egg!’

‘Oh … wow … amazing …’

‘But now we really should get on with things,’ Dumbledore said. Leaving the egg behind in the ashes of the chicken, he returned to his throne and seated himself. ‘It’s almost time for dinner, after all, and we wouldn’t want to have to use our Time-Turners.’

There was a violent power struggle going on in the Government of Harry. Slytherin and Hufflepuff had switched sides after seeing the Headmaster of Hogwarts set fire to a chicken.

‘Yes, things,’ said Harry’s lips. ‘And then dinner.’

You’re sounding like a gibbering moron again observed Harry’s Internal Critic.

‘Well,’ Dumbledore said. ‘I fear I have a confession to make, Harry. A confession and an apology.’

‘Apologies are good’ that doesn’t even make sense! What am I talking about?

The old wizard sighed deeply. ‘You may not still think so after understanding what I have to say. I’m afraid, Harry, that I’ve been manipulating you your entire life. It was I who consigned you to the care of your wicked step-parents –’

‘My step-parents aren’t wicked!’ blurted Harry. ‘My parents, I mean!’

‘They aren’t?’ Dumbledore said, looking surprised and disappointed. ‘Not even a little wicked? That doesn’t fit the pattern …’

Harry’s inner Slytherin screamed at the top of its mental lungs, Shut up you idiot he’ll take you away from them!

‘No, no,’ said Harry, lips frozen in a ghastly grimace, ‘I was just trying to spare your feelings, they’re actually very wicked …’

‘They are?’ Dumbledore leaned forward, gazing at him intently. ‘What do they do?’

Talk fast ‘they, ah, I have to do dishes and wash problems and they don’t let me read a lot of books and –’

‘Ah, good, that’s good to hear,’ said Dumbledore, leaning back again. He smiled in a sad sort of way. ‘I apologise for that, then. Now where was I? Ah, yes. I’m sorry to say, Harry, that I am responsible for virtually everything bad that has ever happened to you. I know that this will probably make you very angry.’

‘Yes, I’m very angry!’ said Harry. ‘Grrr!’

Harry’s Internal Critic promptly awarded him the All-Time Award for the Worst Acting in the History of Ever.

‘And I just wanted you to know,’ Dumbledore said, ‘I wanted to tell you as early as possible, in case something happens to one of us later, that I am truly, truly sorry. For everything that has already happened, and everything that will.’

Moisture glistened in the old wizard’s eyes.

‘And I’m very angry!’ said Harry. ‘So angry that I want to leave right now unless you’ve got anything else to say!’

Just go before he sets you on fire! shrieked Slytherin, Hufflepuff, and Gryffindor.

‘I understand,’ said Dumbledore. ‘One last thing then, Harry. You are not to attempt the forbidden door on the third-floor corridor. There’s no possible way you could get through all the traps, and I wouldn’t want to hear that you’d been hurt trying. Why, I doubt that you could so much as open the first door, since it’s locked and you don’t know the spell Alohomora –’

Harry spun around and bolted for the exit at top speed, the doorknob turned agreeably in his hand and then he was racing down the spiral stairs even as they turned, his feet almost stumbling over themselves, in just a moment he was at the bottom and the gargoyle was walking aside and Harry fired out of the stairwell like a cannonball.

Harry Potter.

There must have been something about Harry Potter.

It was Thursday for everyone, after all, and yet this sort of thing didn’t seem to happen to anyone else.

It was 6:21pm on Thursday afternoon when Harry Potter, firing out of the stairwell like a cannonball and accelerating at top speed, ran directly into Minerva McGonagall as she was turning a corner on her way to the Headmaster’s office.

Thankfully neither of them were much hurt. As had been explained to Harry a little earlier in the day – back when he was refusing to go anywhere near a broomstick again – Quidditch needed solid iron Bludgers just to stand a decent chance of injuring the players, since wizards tended to be a lot more resistant than Muggles to impacts.

Harry and Professor McGonagall did both end up on the floor, and the parchments she had been carrying went all over the corridor.

There was a terrible, terrible pause.

‘Harry Potter,’ breathed Professor McGonagall from where she was lying on the floor right next to Harry. Her voice rose to nearly a shriek. ‘What were you doing in the Headmaster’s office?’

‘Nothing!’ squeaked Harry.

‘Were you talking about the Defence Professor?’

‘No! Dumbledore called me up there and he gave me this big rock and said it was my father’s and I should carry it everywhere!’

There was another terrible pause.

‘I see,’ said Professor McGonagall, her voice a little calmer. She stood up, brushed herself off, and glared at the scattered parchments, which jumped into a neat stack and scurried back against the corridor wall as though to hide from her gaze. ‘My sympathies, Mr Potter, and I apologise for doubting you.’

‘Professor McGonagall,’ Harry said. His voice was wavering. He pushed himself off the floor, stood, and looked up at her trustworthy, sane face. ‘Professor McGonagall …’

‘Yes, Mr Potter?’

‘Do you think I should?’ Harry said in a small voice. ‘Carry my father’s rock everywhere?’

Professor McGonagall sighed. ‘That is between you and the Headmaster, I’m afraid.’ She hesitated. ‘I will say that ignoring the Headmaster completely is almost never wise. I am sorry to hear of your dilemma, Mr Potter, and if there’s any way I can help you with whatever you decide to do –’

‘Um,’ Harry said. ‘Actually I was thinking that once I know how, I could Transfigure the rock into a ring and wear it on my finger. If you could teach me how to sustain a Transfiguration –’

‘It is good that you asked me first,’ Professor McGonagall said, her face growing a bit stern. ‘If you lost control of the Transfiguration the reversal would cut off your finger and probably rip your hand in half. And at your age, even a ring is too large a target for you to sustain indefinitely without it being a serious drain on your magic. But I can have a ring forged for you with a setting for a jewel, a small jewel, in contact with your skin, and you can practise sustaining a safe subject, like a marshmallow. When you have kept it up successfully, even in your sleep, for a full month, I will allow you to Transfigure, ah, your father’s rock …’ Professor McGonagall’s voice trailed off. ‘Did the Headmaster really –’

‘Yes. Ah … um …’

Professor McGonagall sighed. ‘That’s a bit strange even for him.’ She stooped and picked up the stack of parchments. ‘I’m sorry about this, Mr Potter. I apologise again for mistrusting you. But now it’s my own turn to see the Headmaster.’

‘Ah … good luck, I guess. Er …’

‘Thank you, Mr Potter.’

‘Um …’

Professor McGonagall walked over to the gargoyle, inaudibly spoke the password, and stepped through into the revolving spiral stairs. She began to rise out of sight, and the gargoyle started back –

‘Professor McGonagall the Headmaster set fire to a chicken!’

‘He wha–’

‘I’m sorry,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘but we’re about to have company.’

‘It’s fine,’ Harry whispered. ‘It was enough.’ He would never forget this day, and not because of the unimportant things that had happened earlier. He would learn how to cast that spell if it was the last thing he ever learned.

Then the heavy oaken doors of the classroom blasted off their hinges and skittered across the marble floor with a high-pitched shriek.

‘Quirinus! How dare you!’

Like a vast thundercloud, an ancient and powerful wizard blew into the room, a look of such incandescent rage upon his face that the stern look he had earlier turned upon Harry seemed like nothing.

There was a wrench of disorientation in Harry’s mind as the part that wanted to run away screaming from the scariest thing it had ever seen ran away, rotating into place a part of him which could take the shock.

None of Harry’s facets were happy about having their star-gazing interrupted. ‘Headmaster Albus Percival –’ Harry started to say in icy tones.

Wham. Professor Quirrell’s hand came down hard upon his desk. ‘Mr Potter!’ barked Professor Quirrell. ‘This is the Headmaster of Hogwarts and you are a mere student! You will address him appropriately!’

Harry looked at Professor Quirrell.

Professor Quirrell was giving Harry a stern glare.

Neither of them smiled.

Dumbledore’s long strides had come to a halt before where Harry stood in front of the dais and Professor Quirrell stood by his desk. The Headmaster stared in shock at both of them.

‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said in meekly polite tones. ‘Headmaster, thank you for wanting to protect me, but Professor Quirrell did the right thing.’

Slowly, Dumbledore’s expression changed from something that would vaporize steel into something merely angry. ‘I heard students saying that this man had you abused by older Slytherins! That he forbade you to defend yourself!’

Harry nodded. ‘He knew exactly what was wrong with me and he showed me how to fix it.’

‘Harry, what are you talking about?’

‘I was teaching him how to lose,’ Professor Quirrell said dryly. ‘It’s an important life skill.’

It was apparent that Dumbledore still didn’t understand, but his voice had lowered in register. ‘Harry …’ he said slowly. ‘If there’s any threat the Defence Professor has offered you to prevent you from complaining –’

You lunatic, after today of all days do you really think I –

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said, trying to look abashed, ‘what’s wrong with me isn’t that I keep quiet about abusive professors.’

Professor Quirrell chuckled. ‘Not perfect, Mr Potter, but good enough for your first day. Headmaster, did you stay long enough to hear about the fifty-one points for Ravenclaw, or did you storm out as soon as you heard the first part?’

A brief look of disconcertion crossed Dumbledore’s face, followed by surprise. ‘Fifty-one points for Ravenclaw?’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘He wasn’t expecting them, but it seemed appropriate. Tell Professor McGonagall that I think the story of what Mr Potter went through to earn back the lost points will do just as well to make her point. No, Headmaster, Mr Potter didn’t tell me anything. It’s easy to see which part of today’s events are her work, just as I know that the final compromise was your own suggestion. Though I wonder how on Earth Mr Potter was able to gain the upper hand over both Snape and you and then Professor McGonagall was able to gain the upper hand over him.’

Somehow Harry managed to control his face. Was it that obvious to a real Slytherin?

Dumbledore came closer to Harry, scrutinizing. ‘Your colour looks a little off, Harry,’ the old wizard said. He peered closely at Harry’s face. ‘What did you have for lunch today?’

‘What?’ Harry said, his mind wobbling in sudden confusion. Why would Dumbledore be asking about deep-fried lamb and thin-sliced broccoli when that was just about the last probable cause of –

The old wizard straightened up. ‘Never mind, then. I think you’re fine.’

Professor Quirrell coughed, loudly and deliberately. Harry looked at the professor, and saw that Professor Quirrell was staring sharply at Dumbledore.

‘Ah-hem!’ Professor Quirrell said again.

Dumbledore and Professor Quirrell locked eyes, and something seemed to pass between them.

‘If you don’t tell him,’ Professor Quirrell said then, ‘I will, even if you fire me for it.’

Dumbledore sighed and turned back to Harry. ‘I apologize for invading your mental privacy, Mr Potter,’ the Headmaster said formally. ‘I had no purpose except to determine if Professor Quirrell had done the same.’

What?

The confusion lasted just exactly as long as it took Harry to understand what had just happened.

‘You – !’

‘Gently, Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell. His face was hard, however, as he stared at Dumbledore.

‘Legilimency is sometimes mistaken for common sense,’ said the Headmaster. ‘But it leaves traces which another skilful Legilimens can detect. That was all I looked for, Mr Potter, and I asked you an irrelevant question to ensure you wouldn’t think about anything important while I looked.’

‘You should have asked first!’

Professor Quirrell shook his head. ‘No, Mr Potter, the Headmaster had some justification for his concerns, and had he asked for permission you would have thought of exactly those things you did not wish him to see.’ Professor Quirrell’s voice grew sharper. ‘I am rather more concerned, Headmaster, that you saw no need to tell him afterwards!’

‘You have now made it more difficult to confirm his mental privacy on future occasions,’ Dumbledore said. He favoured Professor Quirrell with a cold look. ‘Was that your intention, I wonder?’

Professor Quirrell’s expression was implacable. ‘There are too many Legilimens in this school. I insist that Mr Potter receive instruction in Occlumency. Will you permit me to be his tutor?’

‘Absolutely not,’ Dumbledore said at once.

‘I did not think so. Then since you have deprived him of my free services, you will pay for Mr Potter’s tutoring by a licensed Occlumency instructor.’

‘Such services do not come cheaply,’ Dumbledore said, looking at Professor Quirrell in some surprise. ‘Although I do have certain connections –’

Professor Quirrell shook his head firmly. ‘No. Mr Potter will ask his account manager at Gringotts to recommend a neutral instructor. With respect, Headmaster Dumbledore, after the events of this morning I must protest you or your friends having access to Mr Potter’s mind. I must also insist that the instructor have taken an Unbreakable Vow to reveal nothing, and that he agree to be Obliviated of each session immediately afterwards.’

Dumbledore was frowning. ‘Such services are extremely expensive, as you well know, and I cannot help but wonder why you deem them necessary.’

‘If it’s money that’s the problem,’ Harry spoke up, ‘I have some ideas for making large amounts of money quickly –’

‘Thank you Quirinus, your wisdom is now quite evident and I am sorry for disputing it. Your concern for Harry Potter does you credit, as well.’

‘You’re welcome,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I hope you will not object if I go on making him a particular focus of my attentions.’ Professor Quirrell’s face was now very serious, and very still.

Dumbledore looked at Harry.

‘It is my own wish also,’ Harry said.

‘So that’s how it is to be …’ the old wizard said slowly. Something strange passed across his face. ‘Harry … you must realize that if you choose this man as your teacher and your friend, your first mentor, then one way or another you will lose him, and the manner in which you lose him may or may not allow you to ever get him back.’

That hadn’t occurred to Harry. But there was that jinx on the Defence position … one which had apparently worked with perfect regularity for decades …

‘Probably,’ said Professor Quirrell quietly, ‘but he will have the full use of me while I last.’

Dumbledore sighed. ‘I suppose it is economical, at least, since as the Defence Professor you’re already doomed in some unknown fashion.’

Harry had to work hard to suppress his expression as he realized what Dumbledore had actually been implying.

‘I will inform Madam Pince that Mr Potter is allowed to obtain books on Occlumency,’ said Dumbledore.

‘There is preliminary training which you must do on your own,’ said Professor Quirrell to Harry. ‘And I do suggest that you hurry up on it.’

Harry nodded.

‘I’ll take my leave of you then,’ said Dumbledore. He nodded to both Harry and Professor Quirrell, and departed, walking a bit slowly.

‘Can you cast the spell again?’ Harry said the moment Dumbledore was gone.

‘Not today,’ said Professor Quirrell quietly, ‘and not tomorrow either, I’m afraid. It takes a lot out of me to cast, though less to keep going, and so I usually prefer to maintain it as long as possible. This time I cast it on impulse. Had I thought, and realized we might be interrupted –’

Dumbledore was now Harry’s least favourite person in the entire world.

They both sighed.

‘Even if I only ever see it once,’ Harry said, ‘I will never stop being grateful to you.’

Professor Quirrell nodded.

‘Have you heard of the Pioneer programme?’ Harry said. ‘They were probes that would fly by different planets and take pictures. Two of the probes would end up on trajectories that took them out of the Solar System and into interstellar space. So they put a golden plaque on the probes, with a picture of a man, and a woman, and showing where to find our Sun in the galaxy.’

Professor Quirrell was silent for a moment, then smiled. ‘Tell me, Mr Potter, can you guess what thought went through my mind when I finished assembling the thirty-seven items on the list of things I would never do as a Dark Lord? Put yourself in my shoes – imagine yourself in my place – and guess.’

Harry imagined himself looking over a list of thirty-seven things not to do once he became a Dark Lord.

‘You decided that if you had to follow the whole list all the time, there wouldn’t be much point in becoming a Dark Lord in the first place,’ Harry said.

‘Precisely,’ said Professor Quirrell. He was grinning. ‘So I am going to violate rule two – which was simply “don’t brag” – and tell you about something I have done. I don’t see how the knowledge could do any harm. And I strongly suspect you would have figured it out anyway, once we knew each other well enough. Nonetheless … I shall have your oath never to speak of what I am about to tell.’

‘You have it!’ Harry had a feeling this was going to be really good.

‘I subscribe to a Muggle bulletin which keeps me informed of progress on space travel. I didn’t hear about Pioneer 10 until they reported its launch. But when I discovered that Pioneer 11 would also be leaving the Solar System forever,’ Professor Quirrell said, his grin the widest that Harry had yet seen from him, ‘I sneaked into NASA, I did, and I cast a lovely little spell on that lovely golden plaque which will make it last a lot longer than it otherwise would.’

…

…

…

‘Yes,’ Professor Quirrell said, who now seemed to be standing around fifty feet taller, ‘I thought that was how you might react.’

…

…

…

‘Mr Potter?’

‘… I can’t think of anything to say.’

‘“You win” seems appropriate,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘You win,’ Harry said immediately.

‘See?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘We can only imagine what giant heap of trouble you would have landed in if you had been unable to say that.’

They both laughed.

A further thought occurred to Harry. ‘You didn’t add any extra information to the plaque, did you?’

‘Extra information?’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding as if the idea had never occurred to him before and he was quite intrigued.

Which made Harry rather suspicious, considering that it’d taken less than a minute for Harry to think of it.

‘Maybe you included a holographic message like in Star Wars?’ said Harry. ‘Or … hm. A portrait seems to store a whole human brain’s worth of information … you couldn’t have added any extra mass to the probe, but maybe you could’ve turned an existing part into a portrait of yourself? Or you found a volunteer dying of a terminal illness, sneaked them into NASA, and cast a spell to make sure their ghost ended up in the plaque –’

‘Mr Potter,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice suddenly sharp, ‘a spell requiring a human death would certainly be classified by the Ministry as Dark Arts, regardless of circumstances. Students should not be heard talking about such things.’

And the amazing thing about the way Professor Quirrell said it was how perfectly it maintained plausible deniability. It had been said in exactly the appropriate tone for someone who wasn’t willing to discuss such things and thought students should steer away from them. Harry honestly didn’t know whether Professor Quirrell was just waiting to talk about it until after Harry had learned to protect his mind.

‘Got it,’ Harry said. ‘I won’t talk with anyone else about that idea.’

‘Please be discreet about the whole matter, Mr Potter,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I prefer to go through my life without attracting public notice. You will find nothing in the newspapers about Quirinus Quirrell until I decided it was time for me to teach Defence at Hogwarts.’

That seemed a little sad, but Harry understood. Then Harry realized the implications. ‘So just how much awesome stuff have you done that no one else knows about –’

‘Oh, some,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘But I think that’s quite enough for today, Mr Potter, I confess I am feeling a bit tired –’

‘I understand. And thank you. For everything.’

Professor Quirrell nodded, but he was leaning harder on his desk.

Harry quickly took his leave.

In the dungeons of Slytherin.

An unused classroom lit with eerie green light, much brighter this time and coming from a small crystal globe with a temporary enchantment, but eerie green light nonetheless, casting strange shadows from the dusty desks.

Two boy-sized figures in cowled grey cloaks (no masks) had entered in silence, and sat down in two chairs opposite the same desk.

It was the second meeting of the Bayesian Conspiracy.

Draco Malfoy hadn’t been sure if he should look forward to it or not.

Harry Potter, judging by the expression on his face, didn’t seem to have any doubts on the appropriate mood.

Harry Potter looked like he was ready to kill someone.

‘Hermione Granger,’ said Harry Potter, just as Draco was opening his mouth. ‘Don’t ask.’

He couldn’t have gone on another date, could he? thought Draco, but that didn’t make any sense.

‘Harry,’ said Draco, ‘I’m sorry but I have to ask this anyway, did you really order the mudblood girl an expensive mokeskin pouch for her birthday?’

‘Yes, I did. You’ve already worked out why, of course.’

Draco reached up and raked fingers through his hair in frustration, his cowl brushing the back of his hand. He hadn’t been quite sure why, but now he couldn’t say so. And Slytherin knew he was courting Harry Potter, he’d made it obvious enough in Defence class. ‘Harry,’ said Draco, ‘people know I’m friends with you, they don’t know about the Conspiracy of course, but they know we’re friends, and it makes me look bad when you do that sort of thing.’

Harry Potter’s face tightened. ‘Anyone in Slytherin who can’t understand the concept of acting nice toward people you don’t actually like should be ground up and fed to pet snakes.’

‘There are a lot of people in Slytherin who don’t,’ Draco said, his voice serious. ‘Most people are stupid, and you have to look good in front of them anyway.’ Harry Potter had to understand that if he ever wanted to get anywhere in life.

‘What do you care what other people think? Are you really going to live your life needing to explain everything you do to the dumbest idiots in Slytherin, letting them judge you? I’m sorry, Draco, but I’m not lowering my cunning plots to the level of what the dumbest Slytherins can understand, just because it might make you look bad otherwise. Not even your friendship is worth that. It would take all the fun out of life. Tell me you haven’t ever thought the same thing when someone in Slytherin is being too stupid to breathe, that it’s beneath the dignity of a Malfoy to have to pander to them.’

Draco genuinely hadn’t. Ever. Pandering to idiots was like breathing, you did it without thinking about it.

‘Harry,’ Draco said at last. ‘Just doing whatever you want, without worrying about how it looks, isn’t smart. The Dark Lord worried about how he looked! He was feared and hated, and he knew exactly what sort of fear and hate he wanted to create. Everyone has to worry about what other people think.’

The cowled figure shrugged. ‘Perhaps. Remind me sometime to tell you about something called Asch’s Conformity Experiment, you might find it quite amusing. For now I’ll just note that it’s dangerous to worry about what other people think on instinct, because you actually care, not as a matter of cold-blooded calculation. Remember, I was beaten and bullied by older Slytherins for fifteen minutes, and afterwards I stood up and graciously forgave them. Just like the good and virtuous Boy-Who-Lived ought to do. But my cold-blooded calculations, Draco, tell me that I have no use for the dumbest idiots in Slytherin, since I don’t own a pet snake. So I have no reason to care what they think about how I conduct my duel with Hermione Granger.’

Draco did not clench his fists in frustration. ‘She’s just some mudblood,’ Draco said, keeping his voice calm, rather than shouting. ‘If you don’t like her, push her down the stairs.’

‘Ravenclaw would know –’

‘Have Pansy Parkinson push her down the stairs! You wouldn’t even have to manipulate her, offer her a Sickle and she’d do it!’

‘I would know! Hermione beat me in a book-reading contest, she’s getting better grades than me, I have to defeat her with my brain or it doesn’t count!’

‘She’s just a mudblood! Why do you respect her that much?’

‘She’s a power among Ravenclaws! Why do you care what some powerless idiot in Slytherin thinks?’

‘It’s called politics! And if you can’t play it you can’t have power!’

‘Walking on the moon is power! Being a great wizard is power! There are kinds of power that don’t require me to spend the rest of my life pandering to morons!’

Both of them stopped, and, in almost perfect unison, began taking deep breaths to calm themselves.

‘Sorry,’ Harry Potter said after a few moments, wiping sweat from his forehead. ‘Sorry, Draco. You’ve got a lot of political power and it makes sense for you to keep it. You should be calculating what Slytherin thinks. It’s an important game and I shouldn’t have insulted it. But you can’t ask me to lower the level of my game in Ravenclaw, just so that you don’t look bad by associating with me. Tell Slytherin you’re gritting your teeth while you pretend to be my friend.’

That was exactly what Draco had told Slytherin, and he still wasn’t sure whether it was true.

‘Anyway,’ Draco said. ‘Speaking of your image. I’m afraid I’ve got some bad news. Rita Skeeter heard some of the stories about you and she’s been asking questions.’

Harry Potter raised his eyebrows. ‘Who?’

‘She writes for the Daily Prophet,’ Draco said. He tried to keep the worry out of his voice. The Daily Prophet was one of Father’s primary tools, he used it like a wizard’s wand. ‘That’s the newspaper people actually pay attention to. Rita Skeeter writes about celebrities, and as she puts it, uses her quill to puncture their over-inflated reputations. If she can’t find any rumours about you, she’ll just make up her own.’

‘I see,’ said Harry Potter. His green-lit face looked very thoughtful beneath the cowl.

Draco hesitated before saying what he had to say next. By now someone had certainly reported to Father that he was courting Harry Potter, and Father would also know that Draco hadn’t written home about it, and Father would understand that Draco didn’t think he could actually keep it a secret, which sent a clear message that Draco was practising his own game now but still on Father’s side, since if Draco had been tempted away, he would have been sending false reports.

It followed that Father had probably anticipated what Draco was about to say next.

Playing the game with Father for real was a rather unnerving sensation. Even if they were on the same side. It was, on the one hand, exhilarating, but Draco also knew that in the end it would turn out that Father had played the game better. There was no other way it could possibly go.

‘Harry,’ Draco finally said. ‘This isn’t a suggestion. This isn’t my advice. Just the way it is. My father could almost certainly quash that article. But it would cost you.’

That Father had been expecting Draco to tell Harry Potter exactly that was not something Draco said out loud. Harry Potter would work it out on his own, or not.

But instead Harry Potter shook his head, smiling beneath the cowl. ‘I have no intention of trying to quash Rita Skeeter.’

Draco didn’t even try to keep the incredulity out of his voice. ‘You can’t tell me you don’t care what the newspaper says about you!’

‘I care less than you might think,’ said Harry Potter. ‘But I have my own ways of dealing with the likes of Skeeter. I don’t need Lucius’s help.’

A worried look came over Draco’s face before he could stop it. Whatever Harry Potter was about to do next, it would be something Father wasn’t expecting, and Draco was feeling very nervous about where that might lead.

Draco also realized that his hair was getting sweaty underneath the cowl. He’d never actually worn one of those before, and hadn’t realized that the Death Eaters’ cloaks probably had things like Cooling Charms.

Harry Potter wiped some sweat from his forehead again, grimaced, took out his wand, pointed it upward, took a deep breath, and said ‘Frigideiro!’

Moments later Draco felt the cold draft.

‘Frigideiro! Frigideiro! Frigideiro! Frigideiro! Frigideiro!’

Then Harry Potter lowered the wand, though his hand seemed a bit shaky, and put it back into his robes.

The whole room seemed perceptibly cooler. Draco could have done that too, but still, not bad.

‘So,’ Draco said. ‘Science. You’re going to tell me about blood.’

‘We’re going to find out about blood,’ Harry Potter said. ‘By doing experiments.’

‘All right,’ Draco said. ‘What sort of experiments?’

Harry Potter smiled evilly beneath his cowl, and said, ‘You tell me.’

‘Aaahhhhh! Finite Incantatem! Aaaahhh!’

Harry’s left hand had been put into a pot of boiling cooking oil and left there. He’d put everything he had into the Finite Incantatem and it still wasn’t working.

Some hexes required specific counters or you couldn’t undo them, or maybe it was just that Draco was that much stronger.

‘Aaaaahhhh!’

Harry’s hand was really starting to hurt, now, and that was interfering with his attempts to think creatively.

But a few screams later, Harry realized what he had to do.

His pouch, unfortunately, was on the wrong side of his body, and it took some twisting to reach into it, especially with his other arm flailing around in a reflex, unstoppable attempt to fling off the source of pain. By the time he managed it his other arm had chucked his wand away again.

‘Medical ahhhhh kit! Medical kit!’

On the floor, the green light was too dim to see by.

Harry couldn’t stand. He couldn’t crawl. He rolled across the floor to where he thought his wand was, and it wasn’t there, and with one hand he managed to raise himself high enough to see his wand, and he rolled there, and got the wand, and rolled back to where the medical kit was opened. There was also a good deal of screaming, and a bit of throwing up.

It took eight tries before Harry could cast Lumos.

And then, well, the package wasn’t designed to be opened one-handed, because all wizards were idiots, that was why. Harry had to use his teeth and so it took a while before Harry finally managed to wrap the Numbcloth over his left hand.

When all feeling in his left hand was finally gone, Harry let his mind come apart, and lay motionless on the floor, and cried for a while.

Well, Harry’s mind said silently into itself, when it had recovered enough to think in words again. Was it worth it?

Slowly, Harry’s functional hand reached up to a desk.

Harry pulled himself to his feet.

Took a deep breath.

Exhaled.

Smiled.

It wasn’t much of a smile, but it was a smile nonetheless.

Thank you, Professor Quirrell, I couldn’t have lost without you.

He hadn’t redeemed Draco yet, not even close. Contrary to what Draco himself might now believe, Draco was still the child of a Death Eater, through and through. Still a boy who’d grown up thinking ‘rape’ was something the cool older kids did. But it was one heck of a start.

Harry couldn’t claim it had all gone just as planned. It had all gone just as completely made up on the spot. The plan hadn’t called for this to happen until December or thereabouts, after Harry had taught Draco the techniques not to deny the evidence when he saw it.

But he’d seen the look of fear on Draco’s face, realized that Draco was already taking an alternative hypothesis seriously, and seized the moment. One case of true curiosity had the same sort of redeeming power in rationality that one case of true love had in films.

In retrospect, Harry had given himself hours to make the most important discovery in the history of magic, and months to break through the undeveloped mental barriers of an eleven-year-old boy. This could indicate that Harry had some sort of major cognitive deficit with respect to estimating task completion times.

Was Harry going to Science Hell for what he’d done? Harry wasn’t sure. He’d contrived to keep Draco’s mind on the possibility that magic was fading, made sure Draco would carry out the part of the experiment that would seem at first to point in that direction. He’d waited until after explaining genetics to prompt Draco into realizing about magical creatures (though Harry had thought in terms of ancient artifacts like the Sorting Hat, which no one could duplicate any more, but which continued to function). But Harry hadn’t actually exaggerated any evidence, hadn’t distorted the meaning of any results. When the Interdict of Merlin had invalidated the test that should have been definitive, he’d told Draco up front.

And then there was the part after that …

But he hadn’t actually lied to Draco. Draco had believed it, and that would make it true.

The end, admittedly, had not been fun.

Harry turned, and staggered toward the door.

Time to test Draco’s locking spell.

The first step was simply trying to turn the doorknob. Draco could have been bluffing.

Draco hadn’t been bluffing.

‘Finite Incantatem.’ Harry’s voice came out rather hoarse, and he could feel that the spell hadn’t taken.

So Harry tried it again, and that time it felt true. But another twist at the doorknob showed it hadn’t worked. No surprise there.

Time to bring out the big guns. Harry drew a deep breath. This spell was one of the most powerful he’d learned so far.

‘Alohomora!’

Harry staggered a little after saying it.

And the classroom door still didn’t open.

That shocked Harry. Harry hadn’t been planning to go anywhere near Dumbledore’s forbidden corridor, of course. But a spell to open magical locks had seemed like a useful sort of spell anyway, and so Harry had learned it. Was Dumbledore’s forbidden corridor meant to lure people so stupid that they didn’t notice the security was worse than what Draco Malfoy could put on it?

Fear was creeping back into Harry’s system. The placard in the medical kit had said the Numbcloth could only safely be used for up to thirty minutes. After that it would come off automatically, and not be reusable for 24 hours. Right now it was 6:51pm. He’d put on the Numbcloth about five minutes ago.

So Harry took a step back, and considered the door. It was a solid panel of dark oaken wood, interrupted only by the brass metal doorknob.

Harry didn’t know any explosive or cutting or smashing spells, and Transfiguring explosive would have violated the rule against Transfiguring things to be burned. Acid was a liquid and would have made fumes …

But that was no obstacle to a creative thinker.

Harry laid his wand against one of the door’s brass hinges, and concentrated on the form of cotton as a pure abstraction apart from any material cotton, and also on the pure material apart from the pattern that made it a brass hinge, and brought the two concepts together, imposing shape on substance. An hour of Transfiguration practise every day for a month had got Harry to the point where he could Transfigure a subject of five cubic centimetres in just under a minute.

After two minutes the hinge hadn’t changed at all.

Whoever had designed Draco’s locking spell, they’d thought of that, too. Or the door was part of Hogwarts and the castle was immune.

A glance showed the walls to be solid stone. So was the floor. So was the ceiling. You couldn’t separately Transfigure a part of something that was a solid whole; Harry would have needed to try Transfiguring the whole wall, which would have taken hours or maybe days of continuous effort, if he could have done it at all, and if the wall wasn’t contiguous with the rest of the whole castle …

Harry’s Time-Turner wouldn’t open until 9pm. After that he could go back to 6pm, before the door was locked.

How long would the torture spell last?

Harry swallowed hard. Tears were coming into his eyes again.

His brilliantly creative mind had just offered the ingenious suggestion that Harry could cut his hand off using the hacksaw in the tool-set stored in his pouch, which would hurt, obviously, but might hurt a lot less than Draco’s pain spell, since the nerves would be gone; and he had tourniquets in the healer’s kit.

And that was obviously a hideously stupid idea that Harry would regret the rest of his entire life.

But Harry didn’t know if he could hold out for two hours under torture.

He wanted out of this classroom, he wanted out of this classroom now, he didn’t want to wait in here screaming for two hours until he could use the Time-Turner, he needed to get out and find someone to get the torture spell off his hand …

Think! Harry screamed at his brain. Think! Think!

The Slytherin dorm was mostly empty. People were at dinner. For some reason Draco himself wasn’t feeling very hungry.

Draco closed the door to his private room, locked it, Charmed it shut, Quieted it, sat down on his bed, and started to cry.

It wasn’t fair.

It wasn’t fair.

It was the first time Draco had ever really lost, Father had warned him that losing for real would hurt the first time it happened, but he’d lost so much, it wasn’t fair, it wasn’t fair for him to lose everything the very first time he lost.

Somewhere in the dungeons, a boy Draco had actually liked was screaming in pain. Draco had never hurt anyone he’d liked before. Punishing people who deserved it was supposed to be fun, but this just felt sick inside. Father hadn’t warned him about that, and Draco wondered if it was a hard lesson everyone had to learn when they grew up, or if Draco was just weak.

Draco wished it were Pansy screaming. That would have felt better.

And the worst part was knowing that it might have been a mistake to hurt Harry Potter.

Who else was there for Draco now? Dumbledore? After what he’d done? Draco would sooner have been burned alive.

Draco would have to go back to Harry Potter because there was nowhere else for him to go. And if Harry Potter said he didn’t want him, then Draco would be nothing, just a pathetic little boy who could never be a Death Eater, never join Dumbledore’s faction, never learn science.

The trap had been perfectly set, perfectly executed. Father had warned Draco over and over that what you sacrificed to Dark rituals couldn’t be regained. But Father hadn’t known that the accursed Muggles had invented rituals that didn’t need wands, rituals you could be tricked into doing without knowing it, and that was only one of the terrible secrets which scientists knew and which Harry Potter had brought with him.

Draco started crying harder, then.

He didn’t want this, he didn’t want this but there was no turning back. It was too late. He was already a scientist.

Draco knew he should go back and free Harry Potter and apologize. It would have been the smart thing to do.

Instead Draco stayed in his bed and sobbed.

He’d already hurt Harry Potter. It might be the only time Draco ever got to hurt him, and he would have to hold to that one memory for the rest of his life.

Let him keep screaming.

Harry dropped the remnants of his hacksaw to the ground. The brass hinges had proved impervious, not even scratched, and Harry was beginning to suspect that even the desperation act of trying to Transfigure acid or explosives would have failed to open this door. On the plus side, the attempt had destroyed the hacksaw.

His watch said it was 7:02pm, with less than fifteen minutes left, and Harry tried to remember if there were any other sharp things in his pouch that needed destroying, and felt another fit of tears welling up. If only, when his Time-Turner opened, he could go back and prevent –

And that was when Harry realized he was being silly.

It wasn’t the first time he’d been locked in a room.

Professor McGonagall had already told him the correct way to do this.

… she’d also told him not to use the Time-Turner for this sort of thing.

Would Professor McGonagall realize that this occasion really did warrant a special exception? Or just take away the Time-Turner entirely?

Harry gathered up all his things, all the evidence, into his pouch. A Scourgify took care of the vomit on the floor, though not the sweat that had soaked his robes. He left the overturned desks overturned, it wasn’t important enough to be worth doing with one hand.

When he was done, Harry glanced down at his watch. 7:04pm.

And then Harry waited. Seconds passed, feeling like years.

At 7:07pm, the door opened.

Professor Flitwick’s puff-bearded face looked rather concerned. ‘Are you all right, Harry?’ said the squeaky voice of Ravenclaw’s Head of House. ‘I got a note saying you’d been locked in here –’

The time was just before noon, and Harry and Professor Quirrell were seated at the foot and head of a wide, long, flat table, in a sumptuously appointed private room with thoroughly cushioned couches and chairs along the walls, and soft curtains hanging everywhere.

They were about to eat lunch in Mary’s Place, which Professor Quirrell had said was known to him as one of the best restaurants in Diagon Alley, especially for – his voice had dropped meaningfully – certain purposes.

It was the nicest restaurant that Harry had ever been in, and it was really eating away at Harry that Professor Quirrell was treating him to the meal.

The first part of the mission, to find an Occlumency instructor, had been a success. Professor Quirrell, smiling evilly, had told Griphook to recommend the best he knew, and not worry about the expense, since Dumbledore was paying it; and the goblin had smiled in return. There might have been a certain amount of smiling on Harry’s part as well.

The second part of the plan had been a complete failure.

Harry was not allowed to take money out of his vault without Headmaster Dumbledore or some other school official present, and Professor Quirrell had not been given the vault key. Harry’s Muggle parents could not authorize it because they were Muggles, and Muggles had around the same legal standing as children or kittens: they were cute, so if you tortured them in public you could get arrested, but they weren’t people. Some reluctant provision had been made for recognizing the parents of Muggleborns as human in a limited sense, but Harry’s adoptive parents did not fall into that legal category.

It seemed that Harry was effectively an orphan in the eyes of the wizarding world. As such, the Headmaster of Hogwarts, or his deputies within the school system, were Harry’s guardians until he graduated. Harry could breathe without Dumbledore’s permission, but only so long as the Headmaster did not specifically prohibit it.

Harry had then asked if he could simply tell Griphook how to diversify his investments beyond stacks of gold coins sitting in his vault.

Griphook had stared blankly and asked what diversify meant.

Banks, it seemed, did not make investments. Banks stored your gold coins in secure vaults for an annual fee.

The wizarding world did not have a concept of stock. Or equity. Or corporations. Businesses were run by families out of their personal vaults.

Loans were made by rich people, not banks. Though Gringotts would witness the contract, for a fee, and enforce its collection, for a much larger fee.

Good rich people let their friends borrow money and pay it back whenever. Bad rich people charged you interest.

There was no secondary market in loans.

Evil rich people charged you annual interest rates of at least 20%.

Harry had stood up, turned away, and rested his head against the wall.

Harry had asked if he needed the Headmaster’s permission before he could start a bank.

Professor Quirrell had interrupted at this point, saying that it was time for lunch, and swiftly conducted a fuming Harry out of the bronze doors of Gringotts, through Diagon Alley, and to a fine restaurant called Mary’s Place, where a room had been reserved for them. The owner had looked shocked at seeing Professor Quirrell accompanied by Harry Potter, but had conducted them to the room without complaint.

And Professor Quirrell had quite deliberately announced that he would pay the bill, seeming to rather enjoy the look on Harry’s face.

‘No,’ said Professor Quirrell to the waitress, ‘we will not require menus. I will have the daily special accompanied by a bottle of Chianti, and Mr Potter will have the Diracawl soup to start, followed by a plate of Roopo balls, and treacle pudding for dessert.’

The waitress, clad in robes that still looked severe and formal while being rather shorter than usual, bowed respectfully and departed, shutting the door behind her.

Professor Quirrell waved a hand in the direction of the door, and a bolt slid shut. ‘Note the bolt on the inside. This room, Mr Potter, is known as Mary’s Room. It happens to be proof against all scrying, and I do mean all; Dumbledore himself could detect nothing of what happens here. Mary’s Room is used by two kinds of people. The first sort are engaged in illicit dalliances. And the second sort lead interesting lives.’

‘Really,’ said Harry.

Professor Quirrell nodded.

Harry’s lips were parted in anticipation. ‘It would be a waste to just sit here and eat lunch, then, without doing anything special.’

Professor Quirrell grinned, then took out his wand and flicked it in the direction of the door. ‘Of course,’ he said, ‘people who lead interesting lives take precautions more thorough than the dalliers. I have just sealed us in. Nothing will now pass in or out of this room – through the crack under the door, for example. And …’

Professor Quirrell then spoke no fewer than four different Charms, none of which Harry recognized.

‘Even that does not really suffice,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘If we were doing anything of truly great import, it would be necessary to perform another twenty-three checks besides those. If, say, Rita Skeeter knew or guessed that we would come here, it is possible that she could be in this room wearing the true Cloak of Invisibility. Or she could be an Animagus with a tiny form, perhaps. There are tests to rule out such rare possibilities, but to perform all of them would be arduous. Still, I wonder if I should do them anyway, just so as not to teach you bad habits?’ And Professor Quirrell tapped a finger on his cheek, looking abstracted.

‘It’s fine,’ Harry said, ‘I understand, and I’ll remember.’ Though he was a little disappointed that they weren’t doing anything of truly great import.

‘Very well,’ Professor Quirrell said. He leaned back in his chair, smiling broadly. ‘You wrought quite well today, Mr Potter. The basic notion was yours, I’m sure, even if you delegated the execution. I don’t think we’ll be hearing much more from Rita Skeeter after this. Lucius Malfoy will not be pleased with her failure. If she’s smart, she’ll flee the country the instant she realizes she’s been fooled.’

A sinking sensation began to dawn in Harry’s stomach. ‘Lucius was behind Rita Skeeter … ?’

‘Oh, you didn’t realize that?’ said Professor Quirrell.

Harry hadn’t thought about what would happen to Rita Skeeter afterwards.

At all.

Not in the slightest.

But she would get fired from her job, of course she would be fired, she might have children going through Hogwarts for all Harry knew, and now it was worse, much worse –

‘Is Lucius going to have her killed?’ Harry said in a barely audible voice. Somewhere in his head, the Sorting Hat was screaming at him.

Professor Quirrell smiled dryly. ‘If you have not dealt with journalists before, take it from me that the world gets a little brighter every time one dies.’

Harry jumped out of his chair with a convulsive movement, he had to find Rita Skeeter and warn her before it was too late –

‘Sit down,’ Professor Quirrell said sharply. ‘No, Lucius won’t kill her. But Lucius makes life extremely unpleasant for those who serve him ill. Miss Skeeter will flee and start her life over with a new name. Sit down, Mr Potter; there is nothing you can do at this point, and you have a lesson to learn.’

Harry sat down, slowly. There was a disappointed, annoyed look on Professor Quirrell’s face that was doing more to stop him than the words.

‘There are times,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice cutting, ‘when I worry that your brilliant Slytherin mind is simply wasted on you. Repeat after me. Rita Skeeter was a vile, disgusting woman.’

‘Rita Skeeter was a vile, disgusting woman,’ Harry said. He wasn’t comfortable saying it, but there didn’t seem to be any other possible actions, none at all.

‘Rita Skeeter tried to destroy my reputation, but I executed an ingenious plan and destroyed her reputation first.’

‘Rita Skeeter challenged me. She lost the game, and I won.’

‘Rita Skeeter was an obstacle to my future plans. I had no choice but to deal with her if I wanted those plans to succeed.’

‘Rita Skeeter was my enemy.’

‘I cannot possibly get anything done in life if I am not willing to defeat my enemies.’

‘I have defeated one of my enemies today.’

‘I am a good boy.’

‘I deserve a special reward.’

‘Ah,’ said Professor Quirrell, who had been grinning a benevolent smile for the last few lines, ‘I see I have succeeded in catching your attention.’

That was true. And while Harry felt like he was being railroaded into something – no, that wasn’t just a feeling, he had been railroaded – he couldn’t deny that saying those things, and seeing Professor Quirrell’s smile, did make him feel better.

Professor Quirrell reached into his robes, the gesture slow and deliberately significant, and drew forth …

… a book.

It was different from any book Harry had ever seen, the edges and corners visibly misshapen; rough-hewn was the phrase that came to mind, like it had been hacked out of a book mine.

‘What is it?’ breathed Harry.

‘A diary,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘Whose?’

‘That of a famous person.’ Professor Quirrell was smiling broadly.

‘Okay …’

Professor Quirrell’s expression became more serious. ‘Mr Potter, one of the requisites for becoming a powerful wizard is an excellent memory. The key to a puzzle is often something you read twenty years ago in an old scroll, or a peculiar ring you saw on the finger of a man you met only once. I mention this to explain how I managed to remember this item, and the label attached to it, after meeting you a good deal later. You see, Mr Potter, over the course of my life, I have viewed a number of private collections held by individuals who are, perhaps, not quite deserving of all that they have –’

‘You stole it?’ Harry said incredulously.

‘That is correct,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Very recently, in fact. I think you will appreciate this particular item much more than the vile little man who held it for no other purpose than impressing his equally vile friends with its rarity.’

Harry was simply gaping now.

‘But if you feel that my actions were incorrect, Mr Potter, I suppose you needn’t accept your special present. Though of course I shan’t go to the trouble of putting it back. So which is it to be?’

Professor Quirrell tossed the book from one hand to another, causing Harry to reach out involuntarily with a look of dismay.

‘Oh,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘don’t worry about a little rough handling. You could toss this diary in a fireplace and it would emerge unscathed. In any case, I await your decision.’

Professor Quirrell casually threw the book up into the air and caught it again, grinning.

No, said Gryffindor and Hufflepuff.

Yes, said Ravenclaw. What part of the word book did you two not understand?

The theft part, said Hufflepuff.

Oh, come on, said Ravenclaw, you can’t seriously ask us to say no and spend the rest of our life wondering what it was.

It sounds like a net positive from a utilitarian standpoint, said Slytherin. Think of it as an economic transaction which generates gains from trade, only without the trade part. Plus, we didn’t steal it and it won’t help anyone to have Professor Quirrell keep it.

He’s trying to turn you Dark! shrieked Gryffindor, and Hufflepuff nodded firmly.

Don’t be a naive little boy, said Slytherin, he’s trying to teach you Slytherin.

Yeah, said Ravenclaw. Whoever owned the book originally was probably a Death Eater or something. It belongs with us.

Harry’s mouth opened, then halted that way, an agonized look on his face.

Professor Quirrell seemed to be quite enjoying himself. He had balanced the book on its corner, on one finger, and was keeping it upright while humming a little tune.

There came a knock at the door.

The book vanished back into Professor Quirrell’s robes, and he rose up from his chair. Professor Quirrell started to walk over to the door –

– and staggered, suddenly lurching into the wall.

‘It’s all right,’ said Professor Quirrell’s voice, which suddenly sounded a lot weaker than usual. ‘Sit down, Mr Potter, it’s just a dizzy spell. Sit down.’

Harry’s fingers gripped the edge of his chair, uncertain as to what he should do, what he could do. Harry couldn’t even get too close to Professor Quirrell, not unless he wanted to defy that sense of Doom –

Professor Quirrell straightened, then, his breathing seeming a bit heavy, and opened the door.

The waitress came in, bearing a platter of food; and as she distributed the plates, Professor Quirrell walked slowly back to the table.

But by the time the waitress had bowed her way out, Professor Quirrell was sitting upright and smiling again.

Still, the brief episode of whatever-it-was had decided Harry. He couldn’t say no, not after Professor Quirrell had gone to that much trouble.

‘Yes,’ Harry said.

Professor Quirrell held up a cautioning finger, then took out his wand again, locked the door again, and repeated three of the same Charms from earlier.

Then Professor Quirrell took the book back out of his robes and tossed it to Harry, who almost dropped it into his soup.

Harry shot Professor Quirrell a look of helpless indignation. You weren’t supposed to do that with books, enchanted or not.

Harry opened the book with ingrained, instinctive care. The pages seemed too thick, with a texture unlike either Muggle paper or wizarding parchment. And the contents were …

… blank?

‘Am I supposed to be seeing –’

‘Look nearer the beginning,’ said Professor Quirrell, and Harry (again with that helpless, ingrained care) turned a block of pages back.

The lettering was obviously handwritten, and very hard to read, but Harry thought the words might be Latin.

‘What is this?’ said Harry.

‘That,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘is a record of the magical researches of a Muggleborn who never came to Hogwarts. He refused his letter, and conducted his own small investigations, which never did get very far without a wand. From the description on the placard, I expect that his name bears rather more significance to you than to me. That, Harry Potter, is the diary of Roger Bacon.’

Harry almost fainted.

Nestled up against the wall, where Professor Quirrell had stumbled, glistened the crushed remains of a beautiful blue beetle.

There is a main hallway running through the middle of Hogwarts’s second floor on the north-south axis, and near the centre of this hallway there is an opening into a short corridor which goes a dozen paces back before turning at a right angle, making an L-shape, and then goes a dozen paces more before it ends at a bright, wide window, looking out from three stories above upon the light drizzle falling over the east grounds of Hogwarts. Standing by the window you can hear nothing of the main hallway, and no one in the hallway would hear what went on by the window. If you think there is anything odd about this, you haven’t been in Hogwarts very long.

Four boys in red-trimmed robes are laughing, and a boy in green-trimmed robes is screaming and grabbing frantically onto the edges of the opened window with his hands, as the four boys make as though to push him out. It’s just a joke, of course, and besides, a fall from that height wouldn’t kill a wizard. All good fun. If you think there is anything odd about this –

‘What are you doing?’ says a sixth boy’s voice.

The four boys in red-trimmed robes spin around with sudden starts, and the boy in green-trimmed robes frantically pushes himself away from the window and falls to the floor, face streaked with tears.

‘Oh,’ says the most handsome of the boys in red-trimmed robes, sounding relieved, ‘it’s you. Hey, Lessy, you know who this is?’

There isn’t any answer from the boy on the floor, who’s trying to get his sniffling under control, and the boy in the red-trimmed robes draws back his leg for a kick –

‘Stop it!’ shouts the sixth boy.

The boy in the red-trimmed robes wobbles as he aborts the kick. ‘Um,’ he says, ‘do you know who this is?’

The sixth boy’s breathing sounds strange. ‘Lesath Lestrange,’ he says, his breath coming in short pants, ‘and he didn’t do anything to my parents, he was five years old.’

Neville Longbottom stared at the four huge fifth-year bullies in front of him, trying very hard to control his trembling.

He should have just told Harry Potter no.

‘Why are you defending him?’ said the handsome one, slowly, sounding puzzled with the first hints of offense. ‘He’s a Slytherin. And a Lestrange.’

‘He’s a boy who lost his parents,’ said Neville Longbottom. ‘I know how that is.’ He didn’t know where the words had come from. It sounded too cool, like something Harry Potter would say.

The trembling went on, though.

‘Who do you think you are?’ said the handsome one, starting to sound angry.

I am Neville, the last scion of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Longbottom –

Neville couldn’t say it.

‘I think he’s a traitor,’ said one of the other Gryffindors, and there was a sudden sinking sensation in Neville’s stomach.

He’d known it, he’d just known it. Harry Potter had been wrong after all. Bullies wouldn’t stop only because Neville Longbottom told them to stop.

The handsome one took a step forward, and the three others followed.

‘So that’s how it is for you,’ Neville said, amazed at how steady his voice was. ‘It doesn’t matter to you if it’s Lesath Lestrange or Neville Longbottom.’

Lesath Lestrange let out a sudden gasp, from where he was lying on the floor.

‘Evil is evil,’ snarled the same boy who’d spoken before, ‘and if you’re friends with evil, you’re evil too.’

The four took another step forward.

Lesath rose, wobbling, to his feet. His face was grey, and he took a few steps forward, and leaned against the wall, and didn’t say anything. His eyes were fixed on the turn in the hallway, the way out.

‘Friends,’ Neville said. Now his voice was going up a bit in pitch. ‘Yes, I have friends. One of them is the Boy-Who-Lived.’

A couple of the Gryffindors looked suddenly worried. The handsome one didn’t flinch. ‘Harry Potter isn’t here,’ he said, his voice hard, ‘and if he was, I don’t think he’d like to see a Longbottom defending a Lestrange.’

And the Gryffindors took another long step forward, and behind them, Lesath crept along the wall, waiting for his chance.

Neville swallowed, and raised his right hand with his thumb and forefinger pressed together.

He shut his eyes, because Harry Potter had made him promise not to peek.

If this didn’t work, he was never trusting anyone again.

His voice came out surprisingly clear, considering.

‘Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. By the debt that you owe me and the power of your true name I summon you, I open the way for you, I call upon you to manifest yourself before me.’

Neville snapped his fingers.

And then Neville opened his eyes.

Lesath Lestrange was staring at him.

The four Gryffindors were staring at him.

The handsome one started to chuckle, and that set off the other three.

‘Was Harry Potter supposed to step around the corner or something?’ said the handsome one. ‘Aw. Looks like you’ve been stood up.’

The handsome one took a menacing step forward toward Neville.

The other three followed in lock-step.

‘Ahem,’ said Harry Potter from behind them, leaning against the wall by the window, in the dead end of the hallway, which nobody could possibly have reached without being seen.

If watching people scream always felt this good, Neville could sort of understand why people became bullies.

Harry Potter stalked forward, placing himself between Lesath Lestrange and the others. He swept his icy gaze across the boys in red-trimmed robes, and then his eyes came to rest on the handsome one, the ringleader. ‘Mr Carl Sloper,’ said Harry Potter. ‘I believe I have comprehended this situation fully. If Lesath Lestrange has ever committed a single evil himself, rather than being born to the wrong parents, the fact is not known to you. If I am mistaken in this, Mr Sloper, I suggest you inform me at once.’

Neville saw the fear and awe on the other boys’ faces. He was feeling it himself. Harry had claimed it would all be a trick, but how could it be?

‘But he’s a Lestrange,’ said the ringleader.

‘He’s a boy who lost his parents,’ Harry Potter said, his voice growing even colder.

This time all three of the other Gryffindors flinched.

‘So,’ said Harry Potter. ‘You saw that Neville didn’t want you tormenting an innocent boy on behalf of the Longbottoms. This failed to move you. If I tell you that the Boy-Who-Lived also thinks you are in the wrong, that what you did today was a terrible mistake, does that make a difference?’

The ringleader took a step toward Harry.

The others did not follow him.

‘Carl,’ one of them said, swallowing. ‘Maybe we should go.’

‘They say you’re going to be the next Dark Lord,’ the ringleader said, staring at Harry.

A grin crossed Harry Potter’s face. ‘They also say I’m secretly betrothed to Ginevra Weasley and there’s a prophecy about us conquering France.’ The smile faded. ‘Since you’re determined to force the issue, Mr Carl Sloper, let me make things clear. Leave Lesath alone. I will know if you don’t.’

‘So Lessy sneaked to you,’ said the ringleader coldly.

‘Sure,’ said Harry Potter dryly, ‘and he also told me what you did today after you left Charms class, in a private secluded place where no one could see you, with a certain Hufflepuff girl wearing a white ribbon in her hair –’

The ringleader’s jaw dropped in shock.

‘Eep,’ said one of the other Gryffindors in a high-pitched voice, and spun on his heels and ran around the corner. His footsteps rapidly pattered away and faded.

And then there were six.

‘Ah,’ said Harry Potter, ‘there goes a slightly intelligent young man. The rest of you could stand to learn from Bertram Kirke’s example, before you get into, shall we say, trouble.’

‘Are you threatening to sneak on us?’ said the handsome Gryffindor, his voice trying to be angry, and rather wavering. ‘Bad things happen to sneaks.’

The other two Gryffindors started slowly moving back.

Harry Potter started laughing. ‘Oh, you did not just say that. Are you really trying to intimidate me? Me? Now honestly, do you think you’re scarier than Peregrine Derrick, Severus Snape or for that matter You-Know-Who?’

Even the ringleader flinched at that.

Harry Potter raised his hand, fingers poised, and all three of the Gryffindors leaped backward, and one of them blurted ‘Don’t – !’

‘See,’ said Harry Potter, ‘this is where I snap my fingers and you become part of a hilariously amusing story that will be told with much nervous laughter at dinner tonight. But the thing is, people I trust keep telling me not to do that. Professor McGonagall told me I was taking the easy way out of everything and Professor Quirrell says I need to learn how to lose. So you remember that story where I let myself get beaten up by some older Slytherins? We could do that. You could bully me for a while and I could let you. Only you remember that part at the end where I tell my many, many friends inside this school not to do anything about it? This time we’ll skip that part. So go ahead. Bully me.’

Harry Potter stepped forward, his arms opened wide in invitation.

The three Gryffindors broke and ran, and Neville had to sidestep quickly to avoid getting run over.

There was silence, as their footsteps faded, and then more silence after that.

And then there were three.

Harry Potter drew a deep breath, then exhaled. ‘Whew,’ he said. ‘How are you doing, Neville?’

Neville’s voice came out in a high-pitched squeak. ‘Okay, that was really cool.’

A grin flashed across Harry Potter’s face. ‘You were pretty cool too, you know.’

Neville knew that Harry Potter was just saying that, trying to make him feel good, and it still started a warm glow inside his chest.

Harry turned toward Lesath Lestrange –

‘Are you okay, Lestrange?’ said Neville before Harry could open his mouth.

Now there was something you didn’t expect to find yourself saying, ever.

Lesath Lestrange turned slowly, and stared at Neville, his face tight, no longer crying, tears glistening as they dried.

‘You think you know how it is?’ said Lesath, his voice high and shaking. ‘You think you know? My parents are in Azkaban, I try not to think about it and they always remind me, they think it’s great that Mother is there in the cold and the dark with the Dementors sucking away her life, I wish I was like Harry Potter, at least his parents aren’t hurting, my parents are always hurting, every second of every day, I wish I was like you, at least you can see your parents sometimes, at least you know they loved you, if Mother ever loved me the Dementors will have eaten that thought by now –’

Neville’s eyes were wide with shock. He hadn’t expected this.

Lesath turned to Harry Potter, whose eyes were full of horror.

Lesath flung himself on the floor in front of Harry Potter, touched his forehead to the ground, and whispered, ‘Help me, Lord.’

There was an awful silence. Neville couldn’t think of a single thing to say, and from the naked shock on Harry’s face, he couldn’t think of anything either.

‘They say you can do anything, please, please my Lord, get my parents out of Azkaban, I’ll be your loyal servant forever, my life will be yours and my death as well, only please –’

‘Lesath,’ Harry said, his voice breaking, ‘Lesath, I can’t, I can’t really do things like that, it’s all just stupid tricks.’

‘It’s not!’ said Lesath, his voice high and desperate. ‘I saw it, the stories are true, you can!’

Harry swallowed. ‘Lesath, I set the whole thing up with Neville, we planned it all out in advance, ask him!’

They had, though Harry hadn’t said how he was going to do any of it …

When Lesath looked up from the floor his face was ghastly, and his voice came out in a shriek that hurt Neville’s ears. ‘You son of a mudblood! You could get her out, you just won’t! I got down on my knees and begged you and you still won’t help! I should have known, you’re the Boy-Who-Lived, you think she belongs there!’

‘I can’t!’ Harry said, his voice as desperate as Lesath’s. ‘It’s not a question of what I want, I don’t have the power!’

Lesath rose to his feet, and spat on the floor in front of Harry, and then turned and walked away. When he was around the corner the sound of his feet sped up, and as they faded Neville thought he heard a single sob.

And then there were two.

Neville looked at Harry.

Harry looked at Neville.

‘Wow,’ Neville said quietly. ‘He didn’t seem very grateful for being rescued.’

‘He thought I could help him,’ Harry said, his voice hoarse. ‘He had hope for the first time in years.’

Neville swallowed, and said it. ‘I’m sorry.’

‘Wha?’ said Harry, sounding totally confused.

‘I wasn’t grateful when you helped me –’

‘Every single thing you said before was completely right,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived.

‘No,’ Neville said, ‘it wasn’t.’

They simultaneously gave brief sad smiles, each condescending to the other.

‘I know this wasn’t real,’ said Neville, ‘I know I couldn’t have done anything if you hadn’t been here, but thanks for letting me pretend.’

‘Give me a break,’ said Harry.

Harry had turned from Neville, and was staring out the window at the gloomy clouds.

A completely ridiculous thought came to Neville. ‘Are you feeling guilty because you can’t get Lesath’s parents out of Azkaban?’

‘No,’ said Harry.

A few seconds went by.

‘Yes,’ said Harry.

‘You’re silly,’ said Neville.

‘I am aware of this,’ said Harry.

‘Do you have to do literally anything anyone asks you?’

The Boy-Who-Lived turned back and looked at Neville again. ‘Do? No. Feel guilty about not doing? Yes.’

Neville was having trouble finding words. ‘Once the Dark Lord died, Bellatrix Black was literally the most evil person in the entire world and that was before she went to Azkaban. She tortured my mother and father into insanity because she wanted to find out what happened to the Dark Lord –’

‘I know,’ Harry said quietly. ‘I get that, but –’

‘No! You don’t! She had a reason for doing that, and my parents were both Aurors! It’s not even close to the worst thing she’s ever done!’ Neville’s voice was shaking.

‘Even so,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived, his eyes distant as they stared off into somewhere else, some other place that Neville couldn’t imagine. ‘There might be some incredibly clever solution that makes it possible to save everyone and let them all live happily ever after, and if only I was smart enough I would have thought of it by now –’

‘You have problems,’ said Neville. ‘You think you ought to be what Lesath Lestrange thinks you are.’

‘Yeah,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived, ‘that pretty much nails it. Every time someone cries out in prayer and I can’t answer, I feel guilty about not being God.’

Neville didn’t quite understand that, but … ‘That doesn’t sound good.’

Harry sighed. ‘I understand that I have a problem, and I know what I need to do to solve it, all right? I’m working on it.’

Harry watched Neville leave.

Of course Harry hadn’t said what the solution was.

The solution, obviously, was to hurry up and become God.

Neville’s footsteps moved off, and soon could no longer be heard.

And then there was one.

‘Ahem,’ said Severus Snape’s voice from directly behind him.

Harry let out a small scream and instantly hated himself.

Slowly, Harry turned around.

The tall greasy man in the spotted robes was leaning against the wall in the same position Harry had occupied.

‘A fine invisibility cloak, Potter,’ drawled the Potions Master. ‘Much is explained.’

Oh, bloody crap.

‘And perhaps I have been in Dumbledore’s company too long,’ said Severus, ‘but I cannot help but wonder if that is the Cloak of Invisibility.’

Harry immediately turned into someone who’d never heard of the Cloak of Invisibility and who was exactly as smart as Harry thought Severus thought Harry was.

‘Oh, possibly,’ said Harry. ‘I trust you realize the implications, if it is?’

Severus’s voice was condescending. ‘You have no idea what I’m talking about, do you, Potter? A rather clumsy try at fishing.’

(Professor Quirrell had remarked over their lunch that Harry really needed to conceal his state of mind better than putting on a blank face when someone discussed a dangerous topic, and had explained about one-level deceptions, two-level deceptions, and so on. So either Severus was in fact modelling Harry as a one-level player, which made Severus himself two-level, and Harry’s three-level move had been successful; or Severus was a four-level player and wanted Harry to think the deception had been successful. Harry, smiling, had asked Professor Quirrell what level he played at, and Professor Quirrell, also smiling, had responded, One level higher than you.)

‘So you were watching this whole time,’ said Harry. ‘Disillusionment, I think it’s called.’

A thin smile. ‘It would have been foolish of me to take the slightest risk that you came to harm.’

‘And you wanted to see the results of your test first hand,’ said Harry. ‘So. Am I like my father?’

A strange sad expression came over the man, one that looked foreign to his face. ‘I should sooner say, Harry Potter, that you resemble –’

Severus stopped short.

He stared at Harry.

‘Lestrange called you a son of a mudblood,’ Severus said slowly. ‘It didn’t seem to bother you much.’

Harry furrowed his eyebrows. ‘Not under those circumstances, no.’

‘You’d just helped him,’ Severus said. His eyes were intent on Harry. ‘And he threw it back in your face. Surely that isn’t something you’d just forgive?’

‘He’d just been through a pretty harrowing experience,’ Harry said. ‘And I don’t think being rescued by first-years helped his pride much, either.’

‘I suppose it was easy enough to forgive,’ Severus said, and his voice was odd, ‘since Lestrange means nothing to you. Just some strange Slytherin. If it was a friend, perhaps, you would have felt far more injured by what he said.’

‘If he were a friend,’ Harry said, ‘all the more reason to forgive him.’

There was a long silence. Harry felt, and he couldn’t have said why or from where, that the air was filling up with a dreadful tension, like water rising, and rising, and rising.

Then Severus smiled, looking suddenly relaxed once more, and all the tension vanished.

‘You are a very forgiving person,’ Severus said, still smiling. ‘I suppose your stepfather, Michael Verres-Evans, was the one who taught it to you.’

‘More like Dad’s science fiction and fantasy collection,’ said Harry. ‘Sort of my fifth parent, really. I’ve lived the lives of all the characters in all my books, and all their mighty wisdom thunders in my head. Somewhere in there was someone like Lesath, I expect, though I couldn’t say who. It wasn’t hard to put myself in his shoes. And it was my books that told me what to do about it, too. The good guys forgive.’

Severus gave a light, amused laugh. ‘I’m afraid I wouldn’t know much about what good people do.’

Harry looked at him. That was kind of sad, actually. ‘I’ll lend you some novels with good people in them, if you like.’

‘I should like to ask your advice about something,’ Severus said, his voice casual. ‘I know of another fifth-year Slytherin who was being bullied by Gryffindors. He was wooing a beautiful Muggleborn girl, who came across him being bullied, and tried to rescue him. And he called her a mudblood, and that was the end for them. He apologized, many times, but she never forgave him. Have you any thoughts for what he could have said or done, to win from her the forgiveness you gave Lestrange?’

‘Erm,’ Harry said, ‘based on only that information, I’m not sure he was the main one who had a problem. I’d have told him not to date someone that incapable of forgiveness. Suppose they’d married, can you imagine life in that household?’

There was a pause.

‘Oh, but she could forgive,’ Severus said with amusement in his voice. ‘Why, afterwards, she went off and became the girlfriend of the bully. Tell me, why would she forgive the bully, and not the bullied?’

Harry shrugged. ‘At a wild guess, because the bully had hurt someone else very badly, and the bullied had hurt her just a little, and to her that just felt far more unforgivable somehow. Or, not to put too fine a point on it, was the bully handsome? Or for that matter, rich?’

There was another pause.

‘Yes to both,’ said Severus.

‘And there you have it,’ said Harry. ‘Not that I’ve ever been through high school myself, but my books give me to understand that there’s a certain kind of teenage girl who’ll be outraged by a single insult if the boy is plain or poor, yet who can somehow find room in her heart to forgive a rich and handsome boy his bullying. She was shallow, in other words. Tell whoever it was that she wasn’t worthy of him and he needs to get over it and move on and next time date girls who are deep instead of pretty.’

Severus stared at Harry in silence, his eyes glittering. The smile had faded, and though Severus’s face twitched, it did not return.

Harry was starting to feel a bit nervous. ‘Um, not that I’ve got any experience in the area myself, obviously, but I think that’s what a wise adviser from my books would say.’

There was more silence and more glittering.

It was probably a good time to change the subject.

‘So,’ Harry said. ‘Did I pass your test, whatever it was?’

‘I think,’ Severus said, ‘that there should be no more conversations between us, Potter, and you would be exceedingly wise never to speak of this one.’

Harry blinked. ‘Would you mind telling me what I did wrong?’

‘You offended me,’ said Severus. ‘And I no longer trust your cunning.’

Harry stared at Severus, taken rather aback.

‘But you have given me well-meant advice,’ said Severus Snape, ‘and so I will give you true advice in return.’ His voice was almost perfectly steady. Like a string stretched almost perfectly horizontal, despite the massive weight hanging from its middle, by a million tons of tension pulling at either end. ‘You almost died today, Potter. In the future, never share your wisdom with anyone unless you know exactly what you are both talking about.’

Harry’s mind finally made the connection.

‘You were that –’

Harry’s mouth snapped shut as the almost died part sank in, two seconds too late.

‘Yes,’ said Severus, ‘I was.’

And the terrible tension flooded back into the room like water pressurized at the bottom of the ocean.

Harry couldn’t breathe.

Lose. Now.

‘I didn’t know,’ Harry whispered. ‘I’m s–’

‘No,’ said Severus. Just that one word.

Harry stood there in silence, his mind frantically searching for options. Severus stood between him and the window, which was a real pity, because a fall from that height wouldn’t kill a wizard.

‘Your books betrayed you, Potter,’ said Severus, still in that voice stretched tight by a million tons of pull. ‘They did not tell you the one thing you needed to know. You cannot learn from stories what it is like to lose the one you love. That is something you could never understand without feeling it yourself.’

‘My father,’ Harry whispered. It was his best guess, the one thing that might save him. ‘My father tried to protect you from the bullies.’

A ghastly smile stretched across Severus’s face, and the man moved toward Harry.

And past him.

‘Goodbye, Potter,’ said Severus, not looking back on his way out. ‘We shall have little to say to each other from today on.’

And at the corner, the man stopped, and without turning, spoke one final time.

‘Your father was the bully,’ said Severus Snape, ‘and what your mother saw in him was something I never did understand until this day.’

He left.

Harry turned and walked toward the window. His shaking hands went onto the ledge.

Never give anyone wise advice unless you know exactly what you’re both talking about. Got it.

Harry stared out at the clouds and the light drizzle for a while. The window looked out on the east grounds, and it was afternoon, so if the Sun was visible through the clouds at all, Harry couldn’t see it.

His hands had stopped shaking, but there was a tight feeling in Harry’s chest, like it was being compressed by metal bands.

So his father had been a bully.

And his mother had been shallow.

Maybe they’d grown up later. Good people like Professor McGonagall did seem to think the world of them, and it might not be only because they were heroic martyrs.

Of course, that was scant consolation when you were eleven and about to turn into a teenager, and wondering what sort of teenager you might become.

So very terrible.

So very sad.

Such an awful life Harry led.

Learning that his genetic parents hadn’t been perfect, why, he ought to spend awhile moping about that, feeling sorry for himself.

Maybe he could complain to Lesath Lestrange.

Harry had read about Dementors. Cold and darkness surrounded them, and fear, they sucked away all your happy thoughts and in that absence all your worst memories rose to the surface.

He could imagine himself in Lesath’s shoes, knowing that his parents were in Azkaban for life, that place from which no one had ever escaped.

And Lesath would be imagining himself in his mother’s place, in the cold and the darkness and the fear, alone with all of her worst memories, even in her dreams, every second of every day.

For an instant Harry imagined his own Mum and Dad in Azkaban with the Dementors sucking out their life, draining away the happy memories of their love for him. Just for an instant, before his imagination blew a fuse and called an emergency shutdown and told him never to imagine that again.

Was it right to do that to anyone, even the second most evil person in the world?

No, said the wisdom of Harry’s books, not if there’s any other way, any other way at all.

And unless the wizarding justice system was as perfect as their prisons – and that sounded rather improbable, all things considered – somewhere in Azkaban was a person who was entirely innocent, and probably more than one.

There was a burning sensation in Harry’s throat, and moisture gathering in his eyes, and he wanted to teleport all of Azkaban’s prisoners to safety and call down fire from the sky and blast that terrible place down to bedrock. But he couldn’t, because he wasn’t God.

And Harry remembered what Professor Quirrell had said beneath the starlight: Sometimes, when this flawed world seems unusually hateful, I wonder whether there might be some other place, far away, where I should have been … But the stars are so very, very far away … And I wonder what I would dream about, if I slept for a long, long time.

Right now this flawed world seemed unusually hateful.

And Harry couldn’t understand Professor Quirrell’s words, it might have been an alien that had spoken, or an Artificial Intelligence, something built along such different lines from Harry that his brain couldn’t be forced to operate in that mode.

You couldn’t leave your home planet while it still contained a place like Azkaban.

You had to stay and fight.

Saturday dawned bright and clear and with the students speaking in hushed voices, as though the first to shout might set off the explosion.

Draco had hoped that they would be fighting in the upper levels of Hogwarts again. Professor Quirrell had said that real fights were more likely to take place in cities than forests, and fighting inside schoolrooms and corridors was supposed to simulate that, with ribbons to mark the allowed areas. Dragon Army had done well in those fights.

Instead, just as Draco had feared, Professor Quirrell had come up with something special for this battle.

The battleground was the Hogwarts Lake.

And not in boats, either.

They were fighting underwater.

The Giant Squid had been temporarily paralysed; spells had been set in place to keep away the grindylows; Professor Quirrell had gone and talked to the merfolk; and all the soldiers had been issued potions of underwater action that allowed them to breathe, see clearly, talk to each other, and swim not quite as fast as a fast walk by kicking their legs.

A huge silver sphere hung in the centre of the battleground, shining like a small underwater moon. It would help to provide a sense of direction – at first. The moon would slowly go into eclipse as the battle went on, and when it had gone entirely dark, the battle would end if it hadn’t already.

War in water. You couldn’t defend a perimeter, attackers could come at you from any direction, and even with the potion you couldn’t see very far in the darkness of the lake.

And if you swam too far away from the action, you would start to glow after a while, and be easy to hunt down – ordinarily if an army scattered and ran instead of fighting, Professor Quirrell would just declare them defeated; but today they were working on a points system. Of course you still had some time before you started to glow, if you wanted to play assassin.

Dragon Army had been set low in the water at the start of the game; above and far away, the distant underwater moon shone. The murky water was mostly lit by Lumos Charms, though his soldiers would extinguish the lights as soon as they began manoeuvres. There was no point in letting the enemy see you before you saw them.

Draco kicked his legs a few times, propelling him to a higher position from which he could gaze down at where his soldiers hovered in the water.

The conversations died down almost at once under Draco’s icy glare, his soldiers looking up at him with gratifying expressions of fear and worry.

‘Listen to me very carefully,’ said General Malfoy. His voice came out a little lower, a little burbly with bubbles, libsten to me vebwy carebfully, but the sound travelled clearly. ‘There’s only one way we can win this. We’ve got to march on Sunshine together with Chaos, and beat Sunshine. Then we fight it out with Potter and win. That’s got to happen, understand? No matter what else goes on, that part has to happen that way –’

And Draco explained the plan he and Harry had come up with.

Astonished looks were exchanged among the soldiers.

‘– and if any of your plots get in the way of that,’ finished Draco, ‘after we are out of the water, I will set you on fire.’

There was a nervous chorus of yessirs.

‘And everyone with secret orders, make sure you carry them out to the letter,’ said Draco.

Around half his soldiers openly nodded, and Draco marked them for death after he rose to power.

Of course all the private orders were fake, like one Dragon being told to offer a false traitor’s commission to another Dragon, and the second Dragon being told in hushed confidence to report anything said by the first Dragon. Draco had told each Dragon that the whole war could depend on that one thing, and that he hoped they understood it was more important than the plans they’d previously made. With luck that would keep all the idiots happy, and maybe flush out a few spies to boot, if the reports didn’t match the instructions.

Draco’s real plan for winning against Chaos … well, it was simpler than the one he’d burned, but Father still wouldn’t have liked it. Despite trying, though, Draco hadn’t been able to think of anything better. It was a plot that couldn’t possibly have worked against anyone except Harry Potter. In fact it had been Harry’s plan originally, according to the traitor, though Draco had guessed that without being told. Draco and the traitor had just modified it a little …

Harry took a deep breath, feeling the water gurgle harmlessly in his lungs.

They’d fought in the forest, and he hadn’t had a chance to say it.

They’d fought in the corridors of Hogwarts, and he hadn’t had a chance to say it.

They’d fought in the air, broomsticks issued to every soldier, and it still hadn’t made sense to say it.

Harry had thought he wouldn’t ever get to say those words, not while he was still young enough for them to be real …

The Chaos Legionnaires were looking at Harry in puzzlement, as their general swam with his feet pointing up toward the distant light of the surface, and his head pointed down toward the murky depths.

‘Why are you upside down?’ the young commander shouted at his army, and began to explain how to fight after you abandoned the privileged orientation of gravity.

A hollow, booming bell echoed through the water, and on the instant, Zabini and Anthony and five other soldiers struck out downward, into the murky depths of the lake. Parvati Patil, the only Gryffindor in the group, turned her head back for a moment and gave them all a cheery wave as she dived; and after a moment, Scott and Matt did the same. The rest just sank and vanished.

General Granger swallowed a lump in her throat as she watched them go. She was risking everything on this, dividing her army instead of just trying to take as many enemy soldiers with them as possible.

The thing to realize, Zabini had told her, was that no army would move until they had a plan that let them expect victory. Sunshine couldn’t just plan to win themselves, they had to make both other armies think they would win until it was too late.

Ernie and Ron still looked like they were in shock. Susan was gazing after the disappearing soldiers with a calculating look. Her army, what was left of it, just looked bewildered, traceries of light dappling on their uniforms as they all drifted just below the sunlit surface of the lake.

‘Now what?’ said Ron.

‘Now we wait,’ said Hermione, loudly enough for all the soldiers to hear. It felt odd to talk with her mouth full of water, she kept feeling like she was committing some sort of horrible impoliteness at the dinner table and was about to drool all over herself. ‘All of us left here are going to get zapped, but that was going to happen anyway with Dragon and Chaos ganging up on us. We’ve just got to take as many of them with us as we can.’

‘I’ve got a plan,’ said one of her Sunshine Soldiers … Hannah, her voice had been a little hard to recognize at first. ‘It’s like all complicated, but I know how we can get Dragon and Chaos to start fighting each other –’

‘Me too!’ said Fay. ‘I’ve got a plan too! See, Neville Longbottom is secretly on our side –’

‘You were talking to Neville?’ said Ernie. ‘That’s not right, I was the one who –’

Daphne Greengrass and a couple of other Slytherins who hadn’t gone with Zabini were giggling helplessly as the cries of ‘No, wait, I was the one who got Longbottom’ erupted from one soldier after another.

Hermione just looked at them all wearily.

‘Okay,’ said Hermione when it had all died down, ‘does everyone get it? All your plots were faked by the Chaos Legion, or maybe some by Dragon. Anyone who really wanted to betray Harry or Malfoy went straight to me or Zabini, not you. Just go ahead and compare notes on all your secret plots and you’ll see it for yourselves.’ She might not be as good at plotting as Zabini, but she could always understand what all her officers told her, that was why Professor Quirrell had made her the general. ‘So don’t bother trying to do any plots when the other armies get here. Just fight, okay? Please?’

‘But,’ said Ernie with shock on his face, ‘Neville is in Hufflepuff! You’re saying he lied to us?’

Daphne was laughing so hard and so helplessly that the exhalations had turned her upside down in the water.

‘I’m not sure what Longbottom is,’ said Ron darkly, ‘but I don’t think he’s a Hufflepuff any more. Not now that Harry Potter’s got to him.’

‘Do you know,’ said Susan, ‘I asked him that, and Neville told me he had become a Chaos Hufflepuff?’

‘Anyway,’ said Hermione in a loud voice. ‘Zabini took everyone who we thought was a spy with him, so in our army we can stop watching each other quite so hard now, I hope.’

‘Anthony was a spy?’ yelled Ron.

‘Parvati was a spy?’ gasped Hannah.

‘Parvati was totally a spy,’ said Daphne. ‘She shopped at the spy shoe store and wore spy lipstick, and some day she’s going to marry a nice spy husband and have a lot of little spies.’

And then a gong sound echoed through the water, indicating that Sunshine had just scored two points.

This was shortly followed by the triple gong of Dragon losing a single point.

Traitors weren’t allowed to kill generals, not after the disaster of the first battle in December when all three generals had been shot in the first minute. But with any luck …

‘Aw,’ said Hermione. ‘It sounds like Mr Crabbe is taking a little nap.’

Like two shoals of fish, the armies swam along.

Neville Longbottom kicked his feet in slow, measured motions. Diving, always diving in whatever direction you happened to be moving. You wanted to show the enemy the smallest profile, present them with your head or your feet. So you were always diving, downward and head-first, and the enemy was always down.

Like every Chaos Legionnaire in the army, Neville’s head was constantly rotating as he swam, looking up, down, around, to every side. Not just watching for Sunshine Soldiers, but watching for any sign that a Chaos Legionnaire had drawn their wand and was about to betray them. Usually traitors waited until the confusion of battle to make their move, but that early gong had put them all on guard.

… the truth was, Neville was feeling sad about that. In November he’d been a soldier in a united army, all of them pulling together and helping each other, and now they were all watching each other constantly for the first signs of betrayal. It might have been more fun for General Chaos, but it wasn’t nearly as much fun for Neville.

The direction formerly known as up was getting steadily brighter, as they came closer to the surface and Sunshine.

‘Wands out,’ said General Chaos.

Neville’s squad drew their wands, pointing them straight ahead toward the enemy, as their heads scanned around more rapidly. If there were Sunny traitors, the time was approaching for them to strike.

The other shoal of fish, Dragon Army, was doing the same thing.

‘Now!’ shouted the distant voice of the Dragon General.

‘Now!’ shouted General Chaos.

‘For Sunshine!’ shouted all the soldiers in both armies, and charged downward.

‘What?’ said Minerva involuntarily as she watched the screens from next to the lake, a cry echoed in many other places; all of Hogwarts was watching this battle as they had watched the first.

Professor Quirrell was laughing dryly. ‘I warned you, Headmaster. It is impossible to have rules without Mr Potter exploiting them.’

For long precious seconds, as the forty-seven soldiers charged her own seventeen, Hermione’s mind went blank.

Why …

Then it all snapped into place.

Every time a soldier originally from Sunshine got shot by someone crying the name of Sunshine, she would lose a Quirrell point. When two Sunshine Soldiers were shot by either army, both enemy armies would be two points closer to overtaking her, it was the same gain only shared. And if anyone shot another soldier not in the name of Sunshine, that gong wouldn’t get lost in the confusion …

Hermione was suddenly very glad that Zabini hadn’t gone with the obvious plan of starting trouble between the other two armies while they attacked Sunshine.

It was still disheartening, though, that sense of your chances closing down, of hope being taken away.

Most of Hermione’s soldiers were still looking confused, but some had expressions of dawning horror as they got it.

‘It’s all right,’ Susan Bones said firmly. Heads turned to look at the Sunshine Captain. ‘Our job is the same, to take as many of them with us as we can. And remember, Zabini took away all the spies! We don’t have to stay on the lookout like they do!’ The girl was smiling defiantly, provoking answering smiles from many of the other soldiers, even from Hermione herself. ‘It can be like it was in November. We just have to keep our heads high, fight our best, and trust each other –’

Daphne shot her.

‘Blood for the blood god!’ shrieked Neville of Chaos, though since he was underwater it came out more like Blubbled for the blubbled glub!

Captain Weasley spun and raised his wand toward Neville and fired. But Neville was swimming downward toward him, wand pointed straight ahead, and that meant the Simple Shield could shelter Neville’s entire profile; if anyone shot him now, it wasn’t going to be Sunny Ron.

A grimly determined look came over Captain Weasley’s face, and he arrowed straight up toward Neville, mouthing the word Contego, though the shield wasn’t visible in the water.

The two enemy champions shot toward each other like arrows released from bows, each aimed to split the other down the middle. They had duelled many times before, but this time would pay for all.

(Far away by the lakeside, a hundred breaths were held.)

‘Rainbows and unicorns!’ roared the Sunshine Captain.

‘The Black Goat with a thousand young!’

‘Do your homework!’

Closer and yet closer, the two champions charged, neither willing to swerve, the first person to turn would present a vulnerable broadside and get shot, though if neither lost their nerve they would crash right into each other …

Falling straight down as the enemy rose straight up to meet him, hammer descending to meet anvil in a path neither was willing to leave …

‘Special attack, Chaotic Twist!’

Neville saw the look of horror on Captain Weasley’s face as the Hover Charm caught him. They’d tested it before the battle had started; and just as Harry had suspected, Wingardium Leviosa became a whole new sort of weapon once everyone was swimming underwater.

‘Curse you, Longbottom!’ shrieked Ron Weasley, ‘Can’t you ever fight without your dumb special attacks –’

and by that time the Sunshine Captain had been spun around sideways and Neville shot him in the leg.

‘I don’t fight fair,’ said Neville to the sleeping form, ‘I fight like Harry Potter.’

Granger: 237 / Malfoy: 217 / Potter: 220

It still hurt every time he had to shoot Hermione. Harry could hardly stand to look at the expression of peace that had come over her sleeping face, arms now drifting aimlessly as the curves of sunlight moved over her camouflage uniform and the cloud of her chestnut hair.

And if Harry had tried to duck out of being the one to shoot her … not only would Draco have known what it meant, Hermione would have been offended.

She’s not dead, Harry said to his brain as his kicking feet pushed him away, she’s just resting. Idiot.

Are you sure? said his brain. What if she’s an ex-Hermione? Could we go back and check?

Harry glanced back briefly.

See, she’s fine, there are bubbles coming out of her mouth.

Could’ve been her last breath escaping.

Oh be quiet. Why are you being so paranoid-protective, anyway?

Er, first real friend we’ve ever had in our whole life? Hey, remember what happened to our pet rock?

Would you shut up about that worthless lump of rubble, it wasn’t even alive let alone sentient, that is like the most pathetic childhood trauma ever –

The two armies swiftly separated, becoming two shoals of fish once more.

General Granger had gone down seventeen points, and taken three Chaotics and two Dragons with her; and one Chaotic and two Dragons had been shot as traitors. So she’d lost net seven points, Harry had lost one, Draco had lost two; that put Sunshine twenty points up on Dragon, and seventeen points up on Chaos. Chaos could still win easily if they exterminated all twenty remaining Dragons. The wild card, of course, being those seven remaining Sunshine Soldiers …

… if you could call them that.

The two shoals swam uneasily next to each other, the soldiers in each army awaiting an order to call out their true allegiances, and attack …

‘Everyone who got them,’ Harry said loudly, ‘remember Special Orders One through Three. And don’t forget it’s Merlin Says on Three. Do not acknowledge.’

The trustworthy two-thirds of the army did not nod, and the other third just looked puzzled.

Special Order One: Don’t bother trying to call out any codewords in this battle, don’t expend effort on any plot not specially approved by the commander; just swim, shield, and fire.

Hermione and Draco had both been fighting their soldiers, trying to get them to stop plotting on their own all through December. Harry had egged his soldiers on and supported their plotting through the last two battles … while also telling them that at some future point he might ask them to put a plot or two on hold, to which they’d all readily agreed. So now, in this critical battle, they were happy to obey.

Neither Hermione or Draco could have given that order successfully, Harry was certain. It was the difference between your soldiers seeing you as an ally in their plotting, and seeing you as a spoilsport old fuddy-duddy who didn’t want them to have any fun. Imposition of order equalled escalation of chaos, and it also worked in reverse …

‘There they are!’ shouted someone, and pointed.

From the depths of the lake arose the forgotten ones, the ones who’d forsaken the last battle, the seven missing Sunshine Soldiers, glowing with the bright aura of cowards, now fading as they returned to battle.

The two shoals of fish wavered, pointing wands uneasily.

‘Hold your fire!’ shouted Harry, and a similar cry came from General Malfoy.

There was a moment of held breath.

Then the seven Sunshine Soldiers swam up to join Dragon Army.

There was a triumphant cheer from Dragon Army.

There were cries of dismay from a third of the Chaos Legion.

Some of the other two-thirds smiled, though they shouldn’t have.

Harry wasn’t smiling.

Oh, this is so completely not going to work …

But Harry hadn’t been able to think of anything better.

‘Special Orders Two and Three still apply!’ shouted Harry. ‘Fight!’

‘For the Chaos Legion!’ roared twenty Chaotic Legionnaires.

‘For Dragon Army!’ roared twenty Dragon Warriors and seven Sunshine Soldiers.

And the Chaotics dived straight downward, as all the traitors got ready to strike.

Granger: 237 / Malfoy: 220 / Potter: 226

Draco’s head darted around frantically, trying to weigh up what was happening; somehow, despite his greater forces, he’d lost the initiative. Four small Chaotic forces were being pursued by four larger Dragon forces, but because Draco’s forces were the ones trying to force an engagement, it meant that they had to follow where Chaos ran, and somehow that was producing concentrations of Chaotic force that would fire into the exposed sides of Dragon –

It was happening again!

‘Prismatis!’ shouted Draco, raising his wand, and that shield you could see even through the water, a sparkling multicoloured flat wall wide enough to shield Draco and the five other Dragons with him from the Chaotic force that had just started firing on them as they swam past, and that let the other five Dragons turn their attentions back to the Chaotic force they’d been chasing –

There was a tense moment as sleep spell after sleep spell crashed into Draco’s Prismatic Wall, and Draco was hoping to Merlin that none of those four Chaotics had learned the Breaking Drill Hex –

Then there was the bell of a Dragon victory, and the Chaotic force spun head-for-foot and began swimming away; and Draco, his hands now shaking slightly, dropped the Prismatic Wall and lowered his wand.

Fighting in water was more exhausting even than fighting on broomsticks.

‘Do not pursue!’ Draco cried to his soldiers as they started to follow, then, ‘Sonorus! Reform on me!’

The Dragon forces started converging on Draco, and the Chaotic forces spun around and began pursuing the Dragons on the instant – Draco swore out loud as he heard the bell of a Chaotic victory, someone hadn’t oriented their Simple Shield right – and then the Dragon forces were in supporting range of each other and the Chaotics were moving back into the murky distance.

Somehow, despite their numerical superiority, the Dragons had scored three times against the Chaotics and the Chaotics had scored four times back, and he’d heard one Dragon spy get executed. Either Harry Potter had thought of a lot of very good ideas very fast, or for some unimaginable reason he’d already spent a lot of time working out how to fight underwater. This wasn’t working, and Draco needed to rethink things.

It looked like everyone was having trouble aiming while swimming, too, the battle might last long enough that time would be called … the distant underwater moon was only half full now, that wasn’t good … he had to rethink things fast …

‘What is it?’ said Padma Patil, as she and her force swam over toward Draco.

Padma was his second-in-command; she was clever and powerful, and better yet, she hated Granger and saw Harry as a rival, which made her trustworthy. Working with Padma was making him realize the truth of the old adage that Ravenclaw was sister to Slytherin; Draco had been surprised when his father had told him it was an acceptable House for his future wife, but now he saw the sense of it.

‘Wait until we’re all here,’ Draco said. The truth was, he needed to catch his breath. That was the trouble with being the general and the most powerful wizard, you had to keep using magic.

Zabini came in next, commanding a force of two Sunnies and four Dragons, one of whom was Gregory keeping an eye on Zabini. Draco didn’t trust Zabini. And neither Draco nor Zabini trusted the Sunnies enough to make them a majority of any unit; they were supposed to be loyal either to Draco directly, or to Granger who’d been fooled by the promise that the Dragons would be betrayed in the end after both forces had been depleted, just as Harry’s more trusted Chaotics should’ve been fooled into not shooting at the Sunnies by the promise of their firing fake Sleep Hexes and switching to support Chaos later; but it was possible some of the Sunnies were loyal to Chaos and weren’t firing real Sleep Hexes and that was why Dragon wasn’t winning the way their numerical advantage should’ve let them win …

The next unit that approached was depleted, three soldiers holding wands on two other soldiers, who were swimming with empty hands.

Draco gritted his teeth. More traitor problems. He needed to talk to Professor Quirrell about having some way to punish traitors at least, conditions like these were unrealistic, in real life you tortured your traitors to death.

‘General Malfoy!’ shouted the commander of the problem unit as it swam up, a Ravenclaw boy named Terry. ‘We don’t know what to do – Cesi shot Bogdan, but Cesi says Kellah told him that Bogdan shot Specter –’

‘I didn’t!’ said Kellah.

‘Yes you did!’ shrieked Cesi. ‘General Malfoy, she’s the spy, I should’ve rea–’

‘Somnium,’ said Draco.

There was the triple bell of a one-point loss from Dragon, and then Kellah’s limp body began to float away in the water.

Draco had heard the word recursion by this point, and he knew a Harry Potter plot when he saw one.

(Unfortunately Draco had not heard of autoimmune disorders, and the thought did not readily occur to him that a clever virus would begin its attack by creating symptoms of an autoimmune disorder so as to get the body to distrust its own immune system … )

‘General order!’ said Draco, raising his voice. ‘Nobody gets to shoot spies except myself, Gregory, Padma, and Terry. If anyone sees anything suspicious they come to one of us.’

And then –

There was the bell of Sunshine scoring two points.

‘What?’ said Draco and Zabini around the same time; their heads swivelled around. No one seemed to have been hit, and all the Sunshine soldiers were present and accounted for. (Except Parvati, who had been shot by some still-unknown traitor in Padma’s squad; and of course Padma had shot Parvati again in case she was faking, so it wasn’t her … )

‘A Sunny traitor in Chaos?’ said Zabini, sounding puzzled. ‘But all the ones I knew about were supposed to strike during Chaos’s attack on Sunshine –’

‘No!’ said Padma in a tone of sudden realization. ‘That was Chaos executing a spy!’

‘What?’ said Zabini. ‘But why –’

And Draco got it. Damn it! ‘Because Potter thinks he’s safe for how much he beats Sunshine, but not for how much he beats us! So he doesn’t want to lose a single point when he executes a traitor! General order! If you have to execute a traitor, call Sunshine first! And don’t forget to switch back to Dragon afterwards –’

Granger: 253 / Malfoy: 252 / Potter: 252

Longbottom’s body drifted chaotically through the water, arms and legs disarrayed. After Draco had finally got a hit in they’d all shot him again just to be sure.

Nearby was Harry Potter, now protected by a Prismatic Sphere, looking at them all grimly as the last sliver of crescent moon slowly diminished, somewhere far away. If Longbottom had managed to shoot one more soldier (Draco knew Harry was thinking), if the two Chaotics had managed to hold out just a little longer, they might have won …

After Draco had reformed his forces and struck out again, the ensuing battle and execution of spies in Sunshine’s name had left Sunshine exactly one point ahead of Dragon and Chaos both. Once Harry had started doing it, Draco had been left with no choice but to follow suit.

But now they had General Chaos outnumbered three to one, the survivors of Dragon Army and the last remaining Sunny traitor: Draco, and Padma, and Zabini.

And Draco, who was no fool, had ordered Padma to take Zabini’s wand after Longbottom had shot Gregory and fallen in turn to Draco. The boy had given him an insulted look, told Draco that he owed him for this, and handed it over.

That left Draco and Padma to take down General Chaos.

‘I don’t suppose you’d like to surrender?’ said Draco, smiling as evilly as any smile he’d ever directed at Harry Potter.

‘Sleep before surrender!’ shouted General Chaos.

‘Just so you know,’ said Draco, ‘Zabini doesn’t actually have an older sister for you to rescue from Gryffindor bullies. But Zabini does have a mother who doesn’t approve of Muggleborns like Granger, and I wrote her a few notes, and offered Zabini a few favours – nothing involving my father, just things I can do in school. And by the way, Zabini’s mother doesn’t approve of the Boy-Who-Lived, either. Just in case you still thought Zabini was really on your side.’

Harry’s face grew even grimmer.

Draco raised his wand, and began breathing rhythmically, building up strength for a Breaking Drill Hex. Granger’s Prismatic Sphere was almost as strong as Draco’s now, and Harry’s wasn’t much weaker, where did those two find time?

‘Lagann!’ spoke Draco, putting everything he had into it, and the green spiral blazed out and Harry’s shield shattered, and at almost the same moment –

‘Somnium!’ said Padma.

Granger: 253 / Malfoy: 252 / Potter: 254

Harry let out a long breath of relief, and not just because he didn’t have to hold the Prismatic Sphere any more. His hand was shaking as he lowered his wand.

‘You know,’ said Harry, ‘I was pretty worried there for a moment.’

Special Order Two: If a Sunny traitor doesn’t seem to be really shooting at you, fake being hit occasionally. Prefer targeting Dragons to Sunnies but go ahead and shoot Sunnies if you can’t shoot Dragons.

Special Order Three: Merlin says do not shoot at Blaise Zabini or either Patil twin.

With a wide grin, Parvati Patil stripped the Transfigured patch off her uniform’s insignia, and let it float away in the water.

‘Gryffindors for Chaos,’ she said, and handed Zabini his wand back.

‘Thank you very much,’ Harry said, and bowed sweepingly to the Gryffindor girl. ‘And thank you as well,’ bowing to Zabini. ‘You know, when you came to me with that plan, I wondered if you were brilliant or crazy, and I’ve decided that you’re both. And by the way,’ Harry said, now turning as though to address Draco’s body, ‘Zabini does have a cousin –’

‘Somnium,’ said Zabini’s voice.

Granger: 255 / Malfoy: 252 / Potter: 254

And Harry Potter’s body floated away, his expression of shock and horror quickly relaxing into sleep.

‘On second thought,’ Parvati said cheerfully, ‘make that Gryffindors for Sunshine.’

She started to laugh, more exhilarated than she’d ever been in her life, she’d finally got to assassinate and replace her twin sister and she’d wanted to do that since forever, and this had been perfect, it had all been perfect –

– and then her wand spun around in a lightning motion just as Zabini’s wand turned to point at her.

‘Wait!’ said Zabini. ‘Do not shoot, do not resist. That’s an order.’

‘What?’ said Parvati.

‘Sorry,’ said Zabini, looking not-quite-sincerely apologetic, ‘but I can’t be totally sure you’re for Sunshine. So I order you to let me shoot you.’

‘Hold on!’ said Parvati. ‘We’re only ahead of Chaos by one point! If you shoot me now –’

‘I’ll shoot you in the name of Dragon, obviously,’ said Zabini, now sounding a little superior. ‘Just because we tricked them into doing it, doesn’t mean it won’t work for us.’

Parvati stared at him, her eyes narrowing. ‘General Malfoy said your mother doesn’t like Hermione.’

‘I suppose,’ said Zabini, still with that superior smirk. ‘But some of us are more willing than Draco Malfoy to annoy a parent.’

‘And Harry Potter said you have a cousin –’

‘Nope,’ said Zabini.

Parvati stared at him, trying to think, but she wasn’t really good at plotting; Zabini’d said the plan was to secretly keep the scores of Chaos and Dragon as even as possible so they’d use Sunshine’s name to execute their traitors instead of losing even a single point, and that had worked … but … she had the feeling she was missing something, she wasn’t a Slytherin …

‘Why don’t I shoot you in the name of Dragon?’ said Parvati.

‘Because I outrank you,’ said Zabini.

Parvati had a bad feeling about this.

She stared at him for a long moment.

And then –

‘Somni–’ she started to say, and then realized she hadn’t said for Dragon, and frantically cut herself off –

Granger: 255 / Malfoy: 254 / Potter: 254

‘Hey, everyone,’ said Blaise Zabini’s face on the screens, looking quite amused, ‘guess it’s all down to me.’

All by the lakeside, people were holding their breath.

Sunshine was ahead of Dragon and Chaos by exactly one point.

Blaise Zabini could shoot himself in the name of either Dragon or Chaos, or just leave things the way they were.

A series of chimes indicated that the last minute of time was running out.

And the Slytherin was smiling a strange, twisted smile, and casually toying with his wand, the dark wood barely visible in the dark water.

‘You know,’ said Blaise Zabini’s voice, in the tones of someone who’d been rehearsing the words for a while, ‘it’s just a game, really. And games are supposed to be fun. So how about if I just do whatever I feel like?’

The Slytherin common room could be accurately and precisely described as a re-militarized zone; the moment you stepped through the portrait hole you would see that the left half of the room was Definitely Not Talking to the right half and vice versa. It was very clear, it did not need to be explained to anyone, that you did not have the option of not taking sides.

At a table in the exact middle of the room, Blaise Zabini sat by himself, smirking as he did his homework. He had a reputation now, and meant to keep it.

‘You doing anything interesting today?’ said Tracey.

‘Nope,’ said Daphne.

If you went high enough in Hogwarts, you didn’t see many other people around, just corridors and windows and staircases and the occasional portrait, and now and then some interesting sight, such as a bronze statue of a furry creature like a small child, holding a peculiar flat spear …

If you went high enough in Hogwarts, you didn’t see many other people around, which suited Harry.

There were much worse places to be trapped, Harry supposed. In fact you probably couldn’t think of anywhere better to be trapped than an ancient castle with a fractal ever-changing structure that meant you couldn’t ever run out of places to explore, full of interesting people and interesting books and incredibly important knowledge unknown to Muggle science.

If Harry hadn’t been told that he couldn’t leave, he probably would’ve jumped at the chance to spend more time in Hogwarts, he would’ve plotted and connived to get it. Hogwarts was literally optimal, not in all the realms of possibility maybe, but certainly on the real planet Earth, it was the Maximum Fun Location.

How could the castle and its grounds seem so much smaller, so much more confining, how could the rest of the world become so much more interesting and important, the instant Harry had been told that he wasn’t allowed to leave? He’d spent months here and hadn’t felt claustrophobic then.

You know the research on this, observed some part of himself, it’s just standard scarcity effects, like that time where as soon as a county outlawed phosphate detergents, people who’d never cared before drove to the next county in order to buy huge loads of phosphate detergent, and surveys showed that they rated phosphate detergents as gentler and more effective and even easier-pouring … and if you give two-year-olds a choice between a toy in the open and one protected by a barrier they can go around, they’ll ignore the toy in the open and go for the one behind the barrier … salespeople know that they can sell things just by telling the customer it might not be available … it was all in Cialdini’s book Influence, everything you’re feeling right now, the grass is always greener on the side that’s not allowed.

If Harry hadn’t been told that he couldn’t leave, he probably would’ve jumped at the chance to stay at Hogwarts over the summer …

… but not the rest of his life.

That was sort of the problem, really.

Who knew whether there was still a Dark Lord Voldemort for him to defeat?

Who knew whether He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named still existed outside of the imagination of a possibly-not-just-pretending-to-be-crazy old wizard?

Lord Voldemort’s body had been found burned to a crisp, there couldn’t really be such things as souls. How could Lord Voldemort still be alive? How did Dumbledore know that he was alive?

And if there wasn’t a Dark Lord, Harry couldn’t defeat him, and he would be trapped in Hogwarts forever.

… maybe he would be legally allowed to escape after he graduated his seventh year, six years and four months and three weeks from now. It wasn’t that long as lengths of time went, it only seemed like long enough for protons to decay.

Only it wasn’t just that.

It wasn’t just Harry’s freedom that was at stake.

The Headmaster of Hogwarts, the Chief Warlock of the Wizengamot, the Supreme Mugwump of the International Confederation of Wizards, was quietly sounding the alarm.

A false alarm.

A false alarm which Harry had triggered.

You know, said the part of him that refined his skills, didn’t you sort of ponder, once, how every different profession has a different way to be excellent, how an excellent teacher isn’t like an excellent plumber; but they all have in common certain methods of not being stupid; and that one of the most important such techniques is to face up to your little mistakes before they turn into big mistakes?

… although this already seemed to qualify as a big mistake, actually …

The point being, said his inner monitor, it’s getting worse literally by the minute. The way spies turn people is, they get them to commit a little sin, and then they use the little sin to blackmail them into a bigger sin, and then they use that sin to make them do even bigger things and then the blackmailer owns their soul.

Didn’t you once think about how the person being blackmailed, if they could foresee the whole path, would just decide to take the punch on the first step, take the hit of exposing that first sin? Didn’t you decide that you would do that, if anyone ever tried to blackmail you into doing something major in order to conceal something little? Do you see the similarity here, Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres?

Only it wasn’t little, it already wasn’t little, there would be a lot of very powerful people extremely angry at Harry, not just for the false alarm but for freeing Bellatrix from Azkaban, if the Dark Lord did exist and did come after him later, that war might already be lost –

You don’t think they’ll be impressed by your honesty and rationality and foresight in stopping this before it snowballs even further?

Harry did not, in fact, think this; and after a moment’s reflection, whichever part of himself he was talking to, had to agree that this was absurdly optimistic.

His wandering feet took him near an open window, and Harry went over, and leaned his arms on the ledge, and stared down at the grounds of Hogwarts from high above.

Brown that was barren trees, yellow that was dead grass, ice-coloured ice that was frozen creeks and frozen streams … whichever school official had dubbed it The Forbidden Forest really hadn’t understood marketing, the name just made you want to go there even more. The Sun was sinking in the sky, for Harry had been thinking for some hours now, thinking mostly the same thoughts over and over, but with key differences each time, like his thoughts were not going in circles, but climbing a spiral, or descending it.

He still couldn’t believe that he’d gone through the entire thing with Azkaban – he’d switched off his Patronus before it took all his life, he’d stunned an Auror, he’d figured out how to hide Bella from the Dementors, he’d faced down twelve Dementors and scared them away, he’d invented the rocket-assisted broomstick, and ridden it – he’d gone through the entire thing without ever once rallying himself by thinking, I have to do this … because … I promised Hermione I’d come back from lunch! It felt like an irrevocably missed opportunity; like, having done it wrong that time, he would never be able to get it right no matter what sort of challenge he faced next time, or what promise he made. Because then he would just be doing it awkwardly and deliberately to make up for having missed it the first time around, instead of making the heroic declarations he could’ve made if he’d remembered his promise to Hermione. Like that one wrong turn was irrevocable, you only got one chance, had to do it right on the first try …

He should’ve remembered that promise to Hermione before going to Azkaban.

Why had he decided to do that, again?

My working hypothesis is that you’re stupid, said Hufflepuff.

That is not a useful fault analysis, thought Harry.

If you want a little more detail, said Hufflepuff, the Defence Professor of Hogwarts was all like Let’s get Bellatrix Black out of Azkaban! and you were like Okay!

Hold on, that’s not fair –

Hey, said Hufflepuff, notice how, once you’re all the way up here, and the individual trees sort of blur together, you can actually see the shape of the forest?

Why had he done it … ?

Not because of any cost-benefit calculation, that was for sure. He’d been too embarrassed to pull out a sheet of paper and start calculating expected utilities, he’d worried that Professor Quirrell would stop respecting him if he said no or even hesitated too much to help a maiden in distress.

He’d thought, somewhere deep inside him, that if your mysterious teacher offered you the first mission, the first chance, the call to adventure, and you said no, then your mysterious teacher walked away from you in disgust, and you never got another chance to be a hero …

… yeah, that had been it. In retrospect, that had been it. He’d gone and started thinking his life had a plot and here was a plot twist, as opposed to, oh, say, here was a proposal to break Bellatrix Black out of Azkaban. That had been the true and original reason for the decision in the split second where it had been made, his brain perceptually recognizing the narrative where he said no as dissonant. And when you thought about it, that wasn’t a rational way to make decisions. Professor Quirrell’s ulterior motive to obtain the last remains of Slytherin’s lost lore, before Bellatrix died and it was irrevocably forgotten, seemed impressively sane by comparison; a benefit commensurate with what had appeared at the time as a small risk.

It didn’t seem fair, it didn’t seem fair, that this was what happened if he lost his grip on his rationality for just a tiny fraction of a second, the tiny fraction of a second required for his brain to decide to be more comfortable with yes arguments than no arguments during the discussion that had followed.

From high above, far enough above that the individual trees blurred together, Harry stared out at the forest.

Harry didn’t want to confess and ruin his reputation forever and get everyone angry at him and maybe end up killed by the Dark Lord later. He’d rather be trapped in Hogwarts for six years than face that. That was how he felt. And so it was in fact helpful, a relief, to be able to cling to a single decisive factor, which was that if Harry confessed, Professor Quirrell would go to Azkaban and die there.

(A catch, a break, a stutter in Harry’s breathing.)

If you phrased it that way … why, you could even pretend to be a hero, instead of a coward.

Harry lifted his eyes from the Forbidden Forest, looked up at the clear blue forbidden sky.

Stared out the glass panes at the big bright burning thing, the fluffy things, the mysterious endless blue in which they were embedded, that strange new unknown place.

It … actually did help, it helped quite a lot, to think that his own troubles were nothing compared to being in Azkaban. That there were people in the world who were really in trouble and Harry Potter was not one of them.

What was he going to do about Azkaban?

What was he going to do about magical Britain?

… which side was he on, now?

In the bright light of day, everything that Albus Dumbledore had said certainly sounded a lot wiser than Professor Quirrell. Better and brighter, more moral, more convenient, wouldn’t it be nice if it were true. And the thing to remember was that Dumbledore believed things because they sounded nice, but Professor Quirrell was the one who was sane.

(Again the catch in his breathing, it happened each time he thought of Professor Quirrell.)

But just because something sounded nice, didn’t make it wrong, either.

And if the Defence Professor did have a flaw in his sanity, it was that his outlook on life was too negative.

Really? inquired the part of Harry that had read eighteen million experimental results about people being too optimistic and overconfident. Professor Quirrell is too pessimistic? So pessimistic that his expectations routinely undershoot reality? Stuff him and put him in a museum, he’s unique. Which one of you two planned the perfect crime, and then put in all the error margin and fallbacks that ended up saving your butt, just in case the perfect crime went wrong? Hint hint, his name wasn’t Harry Potter.

But ‘pessimistic’ wasn’t the correct word to describe Professor Quirrell’s problem – if a problem it truly was, and not the superior wisdom of experience. But to Harry it looked like Professor Quirrell was constantly interpreting everything in the worst possible light. If you handed Professor Quirrell a glass that was 90% full, he’d tell you that the 10% empty part proved that no one really cared about water.

That was a very good analogy, now that Harry thought about it. Not all of magical Britain was like Azkaban, that glass was well over half full …

Harry stared up at the bright blue sky.

… although, following the analogy, if Azkaban existed, then maybe it did prove that the 90% good part was there for other reasons, people trying to make a show of kindness as Professor Quirrell had put it. For if they were truly kind they would not have made Azkaban, they would storm the fortress to tear it down … wouldn’t they?

Harry stared up at the bright blue sky. If you wanted to be a rationalist you had to read an awful lot of papers on flaws in human nature, and some of those flaws were innocent logical failures, and some of them looked a lot darker.

Harry stared up at the bright blue sky, and thought of the Milgram experiment.

Stanley Milgram had done it to investigate the causes of World War II, to try to understand why the citizens of Germany had obeyed Hitler.

So he had designed an experiment to investigate obedience, to see if Germans were, for some reason, more liable to obey harmful orders from authority figures.

First he’d run a pilot version of his experiment on American subjects, as a control.

And afterwards he hadn’t bothered trying it in Germany.

Experimental apparatus: A series of 30 switches set in a horizontal line, with labels starting at 15 volts and going up to 450 volts, with labels for each group of four switches. The first group of four labelled Slight Shock, the sixth group labelled Extreme Intensity Shock, the seventh group labelled Danger: Severe Shock, and the two last switches left over labelled just XXX.

And an actor, a confederate of the experimenter, who had appeared to the true subjects to be someone just like them: someone who had answered the same ad for participants in an experiment on learning, and who had lost a (rigged) lottery and been strapped into a chair, along with the electrodes. The true experimental subjects had been given a slight shock from the electrodes, just so that they could see that it worked.

The true subject had been told that the experiment was on the effects of punishment on learning and memory, and that part of the test was to see if it made a difference what sort of person administered the punishment; and that the person strapped to the chair would try to memorize sets of word pairs, and that each time the learner got one wrong, the teacher was to administer a successively stronger shock.

At the 300-volt level, the actor would stop trying to call out answers and begin kicking at the wall, after which the experimenter would instruct the subjects to treat non-answers as wrong answers and continue.

At the 315-volt level the pounding on the wall would be repeated.

After that nothing would be heard.

If the subject objected or refused to press a switch, the experimenter, maintaining an impassive demeanour and dressed in a grey lab coat, would say Please continue, then The experiment requires that you continue, then It is absolutely essential that you continue, then You have no other choice, you must go on. If the fourth prod still didn’t work, the experiment halted there.

Before running the experiment, Milgram had described the experimental setup, and then asked fourteen psychology seniors what percentage of subjects they thought would go all the way up to the 450-volt level, what percentage of subjects would press the last of the two switches marked XXX, after the victim had stopped responding.

The most pessimistic answer had been 3%.

The actual number had been 26 out of 40.

The subjects had sweated, groaned, stuttered, laughed nervously, bitten their lips, dug their fingernails into their flesh. But at the experimenter’s prompting, they had, most of them, gone on administering what they believed to be painful, dangerous, possibly lethal electrical shocks. All the way to the end.

Harry could hear Professor Quirrell laughing, in his mind; the Defence Professor’s voice saying something along the lines of: Why, Mr Potter, even I had not been so cynical; I knew men would betray their most cherished principles for money and power, but I did not realize that a stern look also sufficed.

It was dangerous, to try and guess at evolutionary psychology if you weren’t a professional evolutionary psychologist; but when Harry had read about the Milgram experiment, the thought had occurred to him that situations like this had probably arisen many times in the ancestral environment, and that most potential ancestors who’d tried to disobey Authority were dead. Or that they had, at least, done less well for themselves than the obedient. People thought themselves good and moral, but when push came to shove, some switch flipped in their brain, and it was suddenly a lot harder to heroically defy Authority than they thought. Even if you could do it, it wouldn’t be easy, it wouldn’t be some effortless display of heroism. You would tremble, your voice would break, you would be afraid; would you be able to defy Authority even then?

Harry blinked, then; because his brain had just made the connection between Milgram’s experiment and what Hermione had done on her first day of Defence class, she’d refused to shoot a fellow student, even when Authority had told her that she must, she had trembled and been afraid but she had still refused. Harry had seen that happen right in front of his own eyes and he still hadn’t made the connection until now …

Harry stared down at the reddening horizon, the Sun was sinking lower, the sky fading, darkening, even if most of it was still blue, soon it would turn to night. The gold and red colours of Sun and sunset reminded him of Fawkes; and Harry wondered, for a moment, if it must be a sad thing to be a phoenix, and call and cry and scream without being heeded.

But Fawkes would never give up, as many times as he died he would always be reborn, for Fawkes was a being of light and fire, and despairing over Azkaban belonged to the darkness just as much as did Azkaban itself.

If you were given a glass half-empty and half-full, then that was the way reality was, that was the truth and it was so; but you still had a choice of how to feel about it, whether you would despair over the empty half or rejoice in the water that was there.

Milgram had tried certain other variations on his test.

In the eighteenth experiment, the experimental subject had only needed to call out the test words to the victim strapped into the chair, and record the answers, while someone else pressed the switches. It was the same apparent suffering, the same frantic pounding followed by silence; but it wasn’t you pressing the switch. You just watched it happen, and read the questions to the person being tortured.

37 of 40 subjects had continued their participation in that experiment to the end, the 450-volt end marked XXX.

And if you were Professor Quirrell, you might have decided to feel cynical about that.

But 3 out of 40 subjects had refused to participate all the way to the end.

The Hermiones.

They did exist, in the world, the people who wouldn’t fire a Simple Strike Hex at a fellow student even if the Defence Professor ordered them to do it. The ones who had sheltered Gypsies and Jews and homosexuals in their attics during the Holocaust, and sometimes lost their lives for it.

And were those people from some other species than humanity? Did they have some extra gear in their heads, some additional chunk of neural circuitry, which lesser mortals did not possess? But that was not likely, given the logic of sexual reproduction which said that the genes for complex machinery would be scrambled beyond repair, if they were not universal.

Whatever parts Hermione was made from, everyone had those same parts inside them somewhere …

… well, that was a nice thought but it wasn’t strictly true, there was such a thing as literal brain damage, people could lose genes and the complex machine could stop working, there were sociopaths and psychopaths, people who lacked the gear to care. Maybe Lord Voldemort had been born like that, or maybe he had known good and yet still chosen evil; at this point it didn’t matter in the slightest. But a supermajority of the population ought to be capable of learning to do what Hermione and Holocaust resisters did.

The people who had been run through the Milgram experiment, who had trembled and sweated and nervously laughed as they went all the way to pressing the switches marked XXX, many of them had written to thank Milgram, afterwards, for what they had learned about themselves. That, too, was part of the story, the legend of that legendary experiment.

The Sun had almost sunk below the horizon now, a last golden tip peeking above the faraway tops of trees.

Harry looked at it, that tip of Sun, his glasses were supposed to be proof against UV so he ought to be able to look directly at it without damaging his eyes.

Harry stared directly at it, that tiny fraction of the Light that was not obscured and blocked and hidden, even if it was only 3 parts out of 40, the other 37 parts were there somewhere. The 7.5% of the glass that was full, which proved that people really did care about water, even if that force of caring within themselves was too often defeated. If people truly didn’t care, the glass would have been truly empty. If everyone had been like You-Know-Who inside, secretly cleverly selfish, there would have been no resisters to the Holocaust at all.

Harry looked at the sunset, on the second day of the rest of his life, and knew that he had switched sides.

Because he couldn’t believe in it any more, he couldn’t really, not after going to Azkaban. He couldn’t do what 37 out of 40 people would vote for him to do. Everyone might have inside them what it took to be Hermione, and someday they might learn; but someday wasn’t now, not here, not today, not in the real world. If you were on the side of 3 out of 40 people then you weren’t a political majority, and Professor Quirrell had been right, Harry would not bow his head in submission when that happened.

There was a sort of awful appropriateness to it. You shouldn’t go to Azkaban and come back having not changed your mind about anything important.

So is Professor Quirrell right, then? asked Slytherin. Leaving out whether he’s good or evil, is he right? Are you, to them, whether they know it or not, their next Lord? We’ll just leave out the Dark part, that’s him being cynical again. But is it your intention now to rule? I’ve got to say, that makes even me nervous.

Do you think you can be trusted with power? said Gryffindor. Isn’t there some sort of rule that people who want power shouldn’t have it? Maybe we should make Hermione the ruler instead.

Do you think you’re fit to run a society and not have it collapse into total chaos inside of three weeks flat? said Hufflepuff. Imagine how loudly Mum would scream if she’d heard you’d been elected Prime Minister, now ask yourself, are you sure she’s wrong about that?

Actually, said Ravenclaw, I have to point out that all this political stuff sounds overwhelmingly boring. How about if we leave all the electioneering to Draco and stick to science? It’s what we’re actually good at, and that’s been known to improve the human condition too, y’know.

Slow down, thought Harry at his components, we don’t have to decide everything right now. We’re allowed to ponder the problem as fully as possible before coming to a solution.

The last part of the Sun sank below the horizon.

It was strange, this feeling of not quite knowing who you were, which side you were on, of having not already made up your mind about something as major as that, there was an unfamiliar sensation of freedom in it …

And that reminded him of what Professor Quirrell had said to his last question, which reminded him of Professor Quirrell, which made it hard once more to breathe, started that burning sensation in Harry’s throat, sent his thoughts around that loop of the climbing spiral once again.

Why was he so sad, now, whenever he thought of Professor Quirrell? Harry was used to knowing himself, and he didn’t know why he felt so sad …

It felt like he’d lost Professor Quirrell forever, lost him in Azkaban, that was how it felt. As surely as if the Defence Professor had been eaten by Dementors, consumed in the empty voids.

Lost him! Why did I lose him? Because he said Avada Kedavra and there was in fact a perfectly good reason even though I didn’t see it for a couple of hours? Why can’t things go back to the way they were?

But then it hadn’t been the Avada Kedavra. That might have played a part in irreversibly collapsing a structure of rationalizations and flinches and carefully not thinking about certain things. But it hadn’t been the Avada Kedavra, that hadn’t been the disturbing thing that Harry had seen.

What did I see … ?

Harry looked at the fading sky.

He’d seen Professor Quirrell turn into a hardened criminal while facing the Auror, and the apparent change of personalities had been effortless, and complete.

Another woman had known the Defence Professor as Jeremy Jaffe.

How many different people are you, anyway?

I cannot say that I bothered keeping count.

You couldn’t help but wonder …

… whether Professor Quirrell was just one more name on the list, just one more person that had been turned into, made up in the service of some unguessable goal.

Harry would always be wondering now, every time he talked to Professor Quirrell, if it was a mask, and what motive was behind that mask. With every dry smile, Harry would be trying to see what was pulling the levers on the lips.

Is that how other people will start thinking of me, if I get too Slytherin? If I pull off too many plots, will I never be able to smile at anyone again, without them wondering what I really mean by it?

Maybe there was some way to restore a trust in surface appearances and make a normal human relationship possible again, but Harry couldn’t think of what it might be.

That was how Harry had lost Professor Quirrell, not the person, but the … connection …

Why did that hurt so much?

Why did it feel so lonely, now?

Surely there were other people, maybe better people, to trust and befriend? Professor McGonagall, Professor Flitwick, Hermione, Draco, not to mention Mum and Dad, it wasn’t like Harry was alone …

Only …

A choking sensation grew in Harry’s throat as he understood.

Only Professor McGonagall, Professor Flitwick, Hermione, Draco, they all of them sometimes knew things that Harry didn’t, but …

They did not excel above Harry within his own sphere of power; such genius as they possessed was not like his genius, and his genius was not like theirs; he might look upon them as peers, but not look up to them as his superiors.

None of them had been, none of them could ever be …

Harry’s mentor …

That was who Professor Quirrell had been.

That was who Harry had lost.

And the manner in which he had lost his first mentor might or might not allow Harry to ever get him back. Maybe someday he would know all Professor Quirrell’s hidden purposes and the doubts between them would go away; but even if that seemed possible, it didn’t seem very probable.

There was a gust of wind, outside Hogwarts, it bent the empty trees, rippled the lake whose heart was still unfrozen, made a whispering sound as it slid past the window that looked upon the half-twilit world, and Harry’s thoughts wandered outward for a time.

Then returned inward again, to the next step of the spiral.

Why am I different from the other children my age?

If Professor Quirrell’s answer to that had been an evasion, then it was a very well-calculated one. Deep enough and complex enough, sufficiently full of suggestions of hidden meaning, to serve as a trap for a Ravenclaw who couldn’t be diverted by less. Or maybe Professor Quirrell had meant his answer honestly. Who knew what motive might have pulled that lever on those lips?

I will say this much, Mr Potter: you are already an Occlumens, and I think you will become a perfect Occlumens before long. Identity does not mean, to such as us, what it means to other people. Anyone we can imagine, we can be; and the true difference about you, Mr Potter, is that you have an unusually good imagination. A playwright must contain his characters, he must be larger than them in order to enact them within his mind. To an actor or spy or politician, the limit of his own diameter is the limit of who he can pretend to be, the limit of which face he may wear as a mask. But for such as you and I, anyone we can imagine, we can be, in reality and not pretence. While you imagined yourself a child, Mr Potter, you were a child. Yet there are other existences you could support, larger existences, if you wished. Why are you so free, and so great in your circumference, when other children your age are small and constrained? Why can you imagine and become selves more adult than a mere child of a playwright should be able to compose? That I do not know, and I must not say what I guess. But what you have, Mr Potter, is freedom.

If that was a snow job it was one heck of a distracting one.

And the still more worrisome thought was that Professor Quirrell hadn’t realized how disturbed Harry would be, how wrong that speech would sound to him, how much damage it would do to his trust in Professor Quirrell.

There ought to always be one real person who you truly were, at the centre of everything …

Harry stared out at the falling night, the gathering darkness.

… right?

It was almost bedtime when Hermione heard the scattered intakes of breath and looked up from her copy of Beauxbatons: A History to see the missing boy, the boy who had been misplaced at lunch that Sunday, whose dinner non-appearance had been accompanied by rumours – and she hadn’t believed them because they were completely ridiculous, but she’d felt a little queasiness inside – that he’d withdrawn from Hogwarts in order to hunt down Bellatrix Black.

‘Harry!’ she shrieked, she didn’t even realize that she was talking directly to him for the first time in a week, or notice how some other students started at the sound of her yelling all the way across the Ravenclaw common room.

Harry’s eyes had already lifted to her, he was already walking toward her, so she stopped halfway out of her chair –

A few moments later, Harry was seated across from her, and he was putting away his wand after casting a Quieting barrier around them.

(And an awful lot of Ravenclaws were trying not to look like they were watching.)

‘Hey,’ Harry said. His voice wavered. ‘I missed you. You’re … going to talk to me again, now?’

Hermione nodded, she just nodded, she couldn’t think of what to say. She’d missed Harry too, but she was realizing, with a guilty sort of feeling, that it might’ve been a lot worse for him. She had other friends, Harry … it didn’t feel fair, sometimes, that Harry talked to only her like that, so that she had to talk to him; but Harry had a look about him like unfair things had been happening to him, too.

‘What’s been going on?’ she said. ‘There’s all sorts of rumours. There were people saying you’d run off to fight Bellatrix Black, there were people saying you’d run off to join Bellatrix Black –’ and those rumours had said that Hermione had just made up the thing about the phoenix, and she’d yelled that the whole Ravenclaw common room had seen it, so then the next rumour had claimed she’d made up that part too, which was stupidity of such an inconceivable level that it left her completely flabbergasted.

‘I can’t talk about it,’ Harry said in a bare whisper. ‘Can’t talk about a lot of it. I wish I could tell you everything,’ his voice wavered, ‘but I can’t … I guess, if it helps or anything, I’m not going to lunch with Professor Quirrell any more …’

Harry put his hands over his face, then, covering his eyes.

Hermione felt the queasy feeling all through her stomach.

‘Are you crying?’ said Hermione.

‘Yeah,’ said Harry, his voice sounding a little breathy. ‘I don’t want anyone else to see.’

There was a little silence. Hermione wanted to help but she didn’t know what to do about a boy crying, and she didn’t know what was happening; she felt like huge things were happening around her – no, around Harry – and if she knew what they were she would probably be scared, or alarmed, or something, but she didn’t know anything.

‘Did Professor Quirrell do something wrong?’ she said at last.

‘That’s not why I can’t go to lunch with him any more,’ Harry said, still in that bare whisper with his hands pressed over his eyes. ‘That was the Headmaster’s decision. But yeah, Professor Quirrell said some things to me that made me trust him less, I guess …’ Harry’s voice sounded very shaky. ‘I’m feeling kind of alone right now.’

Hermione put her hand on her cheek where Fawkes had touched her yesterday. She’d kept thinking about that touch, over and over, maybe because she wanted it to be important, to mean something to her …

‘Is there any way I can help?’ she said.

‘I want to do something normal,’ Harry said from behind his hands. ‘Something very normal for first-year Hogwarts students. Something eleven-year-olds and twelve-year-olds like us are supposed to do. Like play a game of Exploding Snap or something … I don’t suppose you have the cards or know the rules or anything like that?’

‘Um … I don’t know the rules, actually …’ said Hermione. ‘I know they explode.’

‘I don’t suppose Gobstones?’ said Harry.

‘Don’t know the rules and they spit at you. Those are boy games, Harry!’

There was a pause. Harry ground his hands against his face to wipe it, and then took his hands away; and then he was looking at her, looking a little helpless. ‘Well,’ Harry said, ‘what do wizards and witches our age do, when they play, you know, the kind of pointless silly games we’re supposed to play at this age?’

‘Hopscotch?’ said Hermione. ‘Jump-rope? Unicorn attack? I don’t know, I read books!’

Harry started laughing, and Hermione started giggling along with him even though she didn’t know quite why, but it was funny.

‘I guess that helped a little,’ said Harry. ‘Actually I think it helped more than playing Gobstones for an hour could’ve possibly helped, so thanks for being you. And no matter what, I’m not having anyone Obliviate everything I know about calculus. I’d sooner die.’

‘What?’ said Hermione. ‘Why – why would you ever want to do that?’

Harry stood up from the table, and there was a rush of restored background noise as his rise broke the Quieting Charm. ‘I’m a tad sleepy so I’m going off to bed,’ Harry said, now his voice was ordinary and wry, ‘I’ve got some lost time to make up for, but I’ll see you at breakfast, and then at Herbology, if that’s all right. Not to mention it wouldn’t be fair to dump all my depression on you. G’night, Hermione.’

‘Good night, Harry,’ she said, feeling very confused and alarmed. ‘Pleasant dreams.’

Harry stumbled a little as she said that, and then he continued on toward the stairs that led to the first-year-boys’ dorms.

Harry turned the Quieting Charm all the way up, on his bed’s headboard, so that he wouldn’t wake anyone else up if he screamed.

Set his alarm to wake him up for breakfast (if he wasn’t up already by that hour, if indeed he slept at all).

Got into bed, laid down –

– felt the lump beneath his pillow.

Harry stared up at the canopy above his bed.

Hissed under his breath, ‘Oh, you’ve got to be kidding me …’

It took a few seconds before Harry could muster the heart to sit up in bed, pull the blanket over himself and his pillow to obscure the deed from the other boys, cast a low-intensity Lumos and see what was under his pillow.

There was a parchment, and a deck of playing cards.

The parchment read,

A little bird told me that Dumbledore has shut the door of your cage.

I must admit, on this occasion, that Dumbledore may have a point. Bellatrix Black is loosed upon the world once more, and that is not good news for any good person. If I stood in Dumbledore’s place, I might well do the same.

But just in case … The Salem Witches’ Institute in America accepts boys as well, despite the name. They are good people and would protect you even from Dumbledore, if you needed it. Britain holds that you need Dumbledore’s permission to emigrate to magical America, but magical America disagrees. So in the final extremity, get outside the wards of Hogwarts and tear in half the King of Hearts from this deck of cards.

That you should resort to it only in the final extremity goes without saying.

Be well, Harry Potter.

– Santa Claus

Harry stared down at the pack of cards.

It couldn’t take him anywhere else, not right now, portkeys didn’t work here.

But he still felt unnerved about the prospect of picking it up, even to hide it inside his trunk …

Well, he’d already picked up the parchment, which could just as easily have been enchanted with a trap, if a trap was involved.

But still.

‘Wingardium Leviosa,’ Harry whispered, and Hovered the packet of cards to lie next to where his alarm clock rested in a pocket of the headboard. He’d deal with it tomorrow.

And then Harry lay back in bed, and closed his eyes, to dream without any phoenix to protect him, and pay his reckoning.

He came awake with a gasp of horror, not a scream, he’d yet to scream this night, but his blanket was all tangled around him from where his sleeping form had jerked as he dreamed of running, trying to get away from the gaps in space that were pursuing him through a corridor of metal lit by dim gaslight, an endlessly long corridor of metal lit by dim gaslight, and he hadn’t known, in the dream, that touching those voids meant he would die horribly and leave his still-breathing body empty behind him, all he’d known was that he had to run and run and run from the wounds in the world sliding after him –

Harry started to cry again, it wasn’t for the horror of the chase, it was that he’d run away while someone behind him was screaming for help, screaming for him to come back and save her, help her, she was being eaten, she was going to die, and in the dream Harry had run away instead of helping her.

‘Don’t go!’ The voice came in a scream from behind the metal door. ‘No, no, no, don’t go, don’t take it away, don’t don’t don’t – ’

Why had Fawkes ever rested on his shoulder? He’d walked away. Fawkes should hate him.

Fawkes should hate Dumbledore. He’d walked away.

Fawkes should hate everyone –

The boy wasn’t awake, wasn’t dreaming, his thoughts were jumbled and confused in the shadowlands that bordered sleep and waking, unprotected by the safety rails that his aware mind imposed on itself, the careful rules and censors. In that shadowland his brain had woken up enough to think, but something else was too sleepy to act; his thoughts ran free and wild, unconstrained by his self-concept, his waking self’s ideals of what he shouldn’t think. That was the freedom of his brain’s dreams, as his self-concept slept. Free to repeat, over and over, Harry’s new worst nightmare:

‘No, I didn’t mean it, please don’t die!’

‘No, I didn’t mean it, please don’t die!’

‘No, I didn’t mean it, please don’t die!’

A rage grew in him alongside the self-loathing, a terrible hot wrath / icy cold hatred, for the world which had done that to her / for himself, and in his half-awake state Harry fantasized escapes, fantasized ways out of the moral dilemma, he imagined himself hovering above the vast triangular horror of Azkaban, and whispering an incantation unlike any syllables that had ever been heard before on Earth, whispers that echoed all the way across the sky and were heard on the other side of the world, and there was a blast of silver Patronus fire like a nuclear explosion that tore apart all the Dementors in an instant and ripped apart the metal walls of Azkaban, shattered the long corridors and all the dim orange lights, and then a moment later his brain remembered that there were people in there, and rewrote the half-dream fantasy to show all the prisoners laughing as they flew away in flocks from the burning wreck of Azkaban, the silver light restoring the flesh to their limbs as they flew, and Harry started crying harder into his pillow, because he couldn’t do it, because he wasn’t God –

He’d sworn upon his life and magic and his art as a rationalist, he’d sworn by all he held sacred and all his happy memories, he’d given his oath so now he had to do something, had to do something, had to do something –

Maybe it was pointless.

Maybe trying to follow rules was pointless.

Maybe you just burned down Azkaban however.

And in fact he’d sworn he’d do it, so now that was what he had to do.

He’d just do whatever it took to get rid of Azkaban, that was all. If that meant ruling Britain, fine, if that meant finding a spell to whisper that would echo all across the sky, whatever, the important thing was to destroy Azkaban.

That was the side he was on, that was who he was, so there, it was done.

His waking mind would have demanded a lot more details before accepting that as an answer, but in his half-dreaming state it felt like enough of a resolution to let his tired mind fall truly asleep again, and dream the next nightmare.

She came awake with a gasp of horror, a disruption of her breathing that left her feeling deprived of air and yet her lungs didn’t move, she woke up with an unvoiced scream on her lips and no words, no words came forth, for she could not understand what she had seen, she could not understand what she had seen, it was too large for her to encompass and still taking shape, she could not put words to that formless shape and so she could not discharge it, could not discharge it and become innocent and unknowing once more.

‘What time is it?’ she whispered.

Her golden jewelled alarm clock, the beautiful and magical and expensive alarm clock that the Headmaster had given her as a gift upon her employment at Hogwarts, whispered back, ‘Around two in the morning. Go back to sleep.’

Her sheets were soaked in sweat, her nightclothes soaked in sweat, she took her wand from beside the pillow and cleaned herself up before she tried to go back to sleep, she tried to go back to sleep and eventually succeeded.

Sybill Trelawney went back to sleep.